Genesis 1

1 In the beginning, God created heaven and earth.

2 But the earth was empty and unoccupied, and darknesses were over the face of the abyss; and so the Spirit of God was brought over the waters.

3 And God said, "Let there be light." And light became.

4 And God saw the light, that it was good; and so he divided the light from the darknesses.

5 And he called the light, 'Day,' and the darknesses, 'Night.' And it became evening and morning, one day.

6 God also said, "Let there be a firmament in the midst of the waters, and let it divide waters from waters."

7 And God made a firmament, and he divided the waters that were under the firmament, from those that were above the firmament. And so it became.

8 And God called the firmament 'Heaven.' And it became evening and morning, the second day.

9 Truly God said: "Let the waters that are under heaven be gathered together into one place; and let the dry land appear." And so it became.

10 And God called the dry land, 'Earth,' and he called the gathering of the waters, 'Seas.' And God saw that it was good.

11 And he said, "Let the land spring forth green plants, both those producing seed, and fruit-bearing trees, producing fruit according to their kind, whose seed is within itself, over all the earth." And so it became.

12 And the land brought forth green plants, both those producing seed, according to their kind, and trees producing fruit, with each having its own way of sowing, according to its species. And God saw that it was good.

13 And it became evening and the morning, the third day.

14 Then God said: "Let there be lights in the firmament of heaven. And let them divide day from night, and let them become signs, both of the seasons, and of the days and years.

15 Let them shine in the firmament of heaven and illuminate the earth." And so it became.

16 And God made two great lights: a greater light, to rule over the day, and a lesser light, to rule over the night, along with the stars.

17 And he set them in the firmament of heaven, to give light over all the earth,

18 and to rule over the day as well as the night, and to divide light from darkness. And God saw that it was good.

19 And it became evening and morning, the fourth day.

20 And then God said, "Let the waters produce animals with a living soul, and flying creatures above the earth, under the firmament of heaven."

21 And God created the great sea creatures, and everything with a living soul and the ability to move that the waters produced, according to their species, and all the flying creatures, according to their kind. And God saw that it was good.

22 And he blessed them, saying: "Increase and multiply, and fill the waters of the sea. And let the birds be multiplied above the land."

23 And it became evening and morning, the fifth day.

24 God also said, "Let the land produce living souls in their kind: cattle, and animals, and wild beasts of the earth, according to their species." And so it became.

25 And God made the wild beasts of the earth according to their species, and the cattle, and every animal on the land, according to its kind. And God saw that it was good.

26 And he said: "Let us make Man to our image and likeness. And let him rule over the fish of the sea, and the flying creatures of the air, and the wild beasts, and the entire earth, and every animal that moves on the earth."

27 And God created man to his own image; to the image of God he created him; male and female, he created them.

28 And God blessed them, and he said, "Increase and multiply, and fill the earth, and subdue it, and have dominion over the fish of the sea, and the flying creatures of the air, and over every living thing that moves upon the earth."

29 And God said: "Behold, I have given you every seed-bearing plant upon the earth, and all the trees that have in themselves the ability to sow their own kind, to be food for you,

30 and for all the animals of the land, and for all the flying things of the air, and for everything that moves upon the earth and in which there is a living soul, so that they may have these on which to feed." And so it became.

31 And God saw everything that he had made. And they were very good. And it became evening and morning, the sixth day.

Genesis 2

1 And so the heavens and the earth were completed, with all their adornment.

2 And on the seventh day, God fulfilled his work, which he had made. And on the seventh day he rested from all his work, which he had accomplished.

3 And he blessed the seventh day and sanctified it. For in it, he had ceased from all his work: the work whereby God created whatever he should make.

4 These are the generations of heaven and earth, when they were created, in the day when the Lord God made heaven and earth,

5 and every sapling of the field, before it would rise up in the land, and every wild plant, before it would germinate. For the Lord God had not brought rain upon the earth, and there was no man to work the land.

6 But a fountain ascended from the earth, irrigating the entire surface of the land.

7 And then the Lord God formed man from the clay of the earth, and he breathed into his face the breath of life, and man became a living soul.

8 Now the Lord God had planted a Paradise of enjoyment from the beginning. In it, he placed the man whom he had formed.

9 And from the soil the Lord God produced every tree that was beautiful to behold and pleasant to eat. And even the tree of life was in the midst of Paradise, and the tree of the knowledge of good and evil.

10 And a river went forth from the place of enjoyment so as to irrigate Paradise, which is divided from there into four heads.

11 The name of one is the Phison; it is that which runs through all the land of Hevilath, where gold is born;

12 and the gold of that land is the finest. In that place is found bdellium and the onyx stone.

13 And the name of the second river is the Gehon; it is that which runs through all the land of Ethiopia.

14 Truly, the name of the third river is the Tigris; it advances opposite the Assyrians. But the fourth river, it is the Euphrates.

15 Thus, the Lord God brought the man, and put him into the Paradise of enjoyment, so that it would be attended and preserved by him.

16 And he instructed him, saying: "From every tree of Paradise, you shall eat.

17 But from the tree of the knowledge of good and evil, you shall not eat. For in whatever day you will eat from it, you will die a death."

18 The Lord God also said: "It is not good for the man to be alone. Let us make a helper for him similar to himself."

19 Therefore, the Lord God, having formed from the soil all the animals of the earth and all the flying creatures of the air, brought them to Adam, in order to see what he would call them. For whatever Adam would call any living creature, that would be its name.

20 And Adam called each of the living things by their names: all the flying creatures of the air, and all the wild beasts of the land. Yet truly, for Adam, there was not found a helper similar to himself.

21 And so the Lord God sent a deep sleep upon Adam. And when he was fast asleep, he took one of his ribs, and he completed it with flesh for it.

22 And the Lord God built up the rib, which he took from Adam, into a woman. And he led her to Adam.

23 And Adam said: "Now this is bone from my bones, and flesh from my flesh. This one shall be called woman, because she was taken from man."

24 For this reason, a man shall leave behind his father and mother, and he shall cling to his wife; and the two shall be as one flesh.

25 Now they were both naked: Adam, of course, and his wife. And they were not ashamed.

Genesis 3

1 However, the serpent was more crafty than any of the creatures of the earth that the Lord God had made. And he said to the woman, "Why has God instructed you, that you should not eat from every tree of Paradise?"

2 The woman responded to him: "From the fruit of the trees which are in Paradise, we eat.

3 Yet truly, from the fruit of the tree which is in the middle of Paradise, God has instructed us that we should not eat, and that we should not touch it, lest perhaps we may die."

4 Then the serpent said to the woman: "By no means will you die a death.

5 For God knows that, on whatever day you will eat from it, your eyes will be opened; and you will be like gods, knowing good and evil."

6 And so the woman saw that the tree was good to eat, and beautiful to the eyes, and delightful to consider. And she took from its fruit, and she ate. And she gave to her husband, who ate.

7 And the eyes of them both were opened. And when they realized themselves to be naked, they joined together fig leaves and made coverings for themselves.

8 And when they had heard the voice of the Lord God taking a walk in Paradise in the afternoon breeze, Adam and his wife hid themselves from the face of the Lord God in the midst of the trees of Paradise.

9 And the Lord God called Adam and said to him: "Where are you?"

10 And he said, "I heard your voice in Paradise, and I was afraid, because I was naked, and so I hid myself."

11 He said to him, "Then who told you that you were naked, if you have not eaten of the tree from which I instructed you that you should not eat?"

12 And Adam said, "The woman, whom you gave to me as a companion, gave to me from the tree, and I ate."

13 And the Lord God said to the woman, "Why have you done this?" And she responded, "The serpent deceived me, and I ate."

14 And the Lord God said to the serpent: "Because you have done this, you are cursed among all living things, even the wild beasts of the earth. Upon your breast shall you travel, and the ground shall you eat, all the days of your life.

15 I will put enmities between you and the woman, between your offspring and her offspring. She will crush your head, and you will lie in wait for her heel."

16 To the woman, he also said: "I will multiply your labors and your conceptions. In pain shall you give birth to sons, and you shall be under your husband's power, and he shall have dominion over you."

17 Yet truly, to Adam, he said: "Because you have listened to the voice of your wife, and have eaten of the tree, from which I instructed you that you should not eat, cursed is the land that you work. In hardship shall you eat from it, all the days of your life.

18 Thorns and thistles shall it produce for you, and you shall eat the plants of the earth.

19 By the sweat of your face shall you eat bread, until you return to the earth from which you were taken. For dust you are, and unto dust you shall return."

20 And Adam called the name of his wife, 'Eve,' because she was the mother of all the living.

21 The Lord God also made for Adam and his wife garments from skins, and he clothed them.

22 And he said: "Behold, Adam has become like one of us, knowing good and evil. Therefore, now perhaps he may put forth his hand and also take from the tree of life, and eat, and live in eternity."

23 And so the Lord God sent him away from the Paradise of enjoyment, in order to work the earth from which he was taken.

24 And he cast out Adam. And in front of the Paradise of enjoyment, he placed the Cherubim with a flaming sword, turning together, to guard the way to the tree of life.

Genesis 4

1 Truly, Adam knew his wife Eve, who conceived and gave birth to Cain, saying, "I have obtained a man through God."

2 And again she gave birth to his brother Abel. But Abel was a pastor of sheep, and Cain was a farmer.

3 Then it happened, after many days, that Cain offered gifts to the Lord, from the fruits of the earth.

4 Abel likewise offered from the firstborn of his flock, and from their fat. And the Lord looked with favor on Abel and his gifts.

5 Yet in truth, he did not look with favor on Cain and his gifts. And Cain was vehemently angry, and his countenance fell.

6 And the Lord said to him: "Why are you angry? And why is your face fallen?

7 If you behave well, will you not receive? But if you behave badly, will not sin at once be present at the door? And so its desire will be within you, and you will be dominated by it."

8 And Cain said to his brother Abel, "Let us go outside." And when they were in the field, Cain rose up against his brother Abel, and he put him to death.

9 And the Lord said to Cain, "Where is your brother Abel?" And he responded: "I do not know. Am I my brother's keeper?"

10 And he said to him: "What have you done? The voice of your brother's blood cries out to me from the land.

11 Now, therefore, you will be cursed upon the land, which opened its mouth and received the blood of your brother at your hand.

12 When you work it, it will not give you its fruit; a vagrant and a fugitive shall you be upon the land."

13 And Cain said to the Lord: "My iniquity is too great to deserve kindness.

14 Behold, you have cast me out this day before the face of the earth, and from your face I will be hidden; and I will be a vagrant and a fugitive on the earth. Therefore, anyone who finds me will kill me."

15 And the Lord said to him: "By no means will it be so; rather, whoever would kill Cain, will be punished sevenfold." And the Lord placed a seal upon Cain, so that anyone who found him would not put him to death.

16 And so Cain, departing from the face of the Lord, lived as a fugitive on the earth, toward the eastern region of Eden.

17 Then Cain knew his wife, and she conceived and gave birth to Enoch. And he built a city, and he called its name by the name of his son, Enoch.

18 Thereafter, Enoch conceived Irad, and Irad conceived Mahujael, and Mahujael conceived Mathusael, and Mathusael conceived Lamech.

19 Lamech took two wives: the name of one was Adah, and the name of the other was Zillah.

20 And Adah conceived Jabel, who was the father of those who live in tents and are shepherds.

21 And the name of his brother was Jubal; he was the father of those who sing to the harp and the organ.

22 Zillah also conceived Tubalcain, who was a hammerer and artisan in every work of brass and iron. In fact, the sister of Tubalcain was Noema.

23 And Lamech said to his wives Adah and Zillah: "Listen to my voice, you wives of Lamech, pay attention to my speech. For I have killed a man to my own harm, and an adolescent to my own bruising.

24 Sevenfold vengeance will be given for Cain, but for Lamech, seventy-seven times."

25 Adam also knew his wife again, and she gave birth to a son, and she called his name Seth, saying, "God has given me another offspring, in place of Abel, whom Cain killed."

26 But to Seth also was born a son, whom he called Enos. This one began to invoke the name of the Lord.

Genesis 5

1 This is the book of the lineage of Adam. In the day that God created man, he made him to the likeness of God.

2 He created them, male and female; and he blessed them. And he called their name Adam, in the day when they were created.

3 Then Adam lived for one hundred and thirty years. And then he conceived a son in his own image and likeness, and he called his name Seth.

4 And after he conceived Seth, the days of Adam that passed were eight hundred years. And he conceived sons and daughters.

5 And all the time that passed while Adam lived was nine hundred and thirty years, and then he died.

6 Seth likewise lived for one hundred and five years, and then he conceived Enos.

7 And after he conceived Enos, Seth lived for eight hundred and seven years, and he conceived sons and daughters.

8 And all the days of Seth that passed were nine hundred and twelve years, and then he died.

9 In truth, Enos lived ninety years, and then he conceived Cainan.

10 After his birth, he lived eight hundred and fifteen years, and he conceived sons and daughters.

11 And all the days of Enos that passed were nine hundred and five years, and then he died.

12 Likewise, Cainan lived seventy years, and then he conceived Mahalalel.

13 And after he conceived Mahalalel, Cainan lived for eight hundred and forty years, and he conceived sons and daughters.

14 And all the days of Cainan that passed were nine hundred and ten years, and then he died.

15 And Mahalalel lived sixty-five years, and then he conceived Jared.

16 And after he conceived Jared, Mahalalel lived for eight hundred and thirty years, and he conceived sons and daughters.

17 And all the days of Mahalalel that passed were eight hundred and ninety-five years, and then he died.

18 And Jared lived for one hundred and sixty-two years, and then he conceived Enoch.

19 And after he conceived Enoch, Jared lived for eight hundred years, and he conceived sons and daughters.

20 And all the days of Jared that passed were nine hundred and sixty-two years, and then he died.

21 Now Enoch lived for sixty-five years, and then he conceived Methuselah.

22 And Enoch walked with God. And after he conceived Methuselah, he lived for three hundred years, and he conceived sons and daughters.

23 And all the days of Enoch that passed were three hundred and sixty-five years.

24 And he walked with God, and then he was seen no more, because God took him.

25 Likewise, Methuselah lived for one hundred and eighty-seven years, and then he conceived Lamech.

26 And after he conceived Lamech, Methuselah lived for seven hundred and eighty-two years, and he conceived sons and daughters.

27 And all the days of Methuselah that passed were nine hundred and sixty-nine years, and then he died.

28 Then Lamech lived for one hundred and eighty-two years, and he conceived a son.

29 And he called his name Noah, saying, "This one will console us from the works and hardships of our hands, in the land that the Lord has cursed."

30 And after he conceived Noah, Lamech lived for five hundred and ninety-five years, and he conceived sons and daughters.

31 And all the days of Lamech that passed were seven hundred and seventy-seven years, and then he died. In truth, when Noah was five hundred years old, he conceived Shem, Ham, and Japheth.

Genesis 6

1 And when men began to be multiplied upon the earth, and daughters were born to them,

2 the sons of God, seeing that the daughters of men were beautiful, took to themselves wives from all whom they chose.

3 And God said: "My spirit shall not remain in man forever, because he is flesh. And so his days shall be one hundred and twenty years."

4 Now giants were upon the earth in those days. For after the sons of God went in to the daughters of men, and they conceived, these became the powerful ones of ancient times, men of renown.

5 Then God, seeing that the wickedness of men was great upon the earth and that every thought of their heart was intent upon evil at all times,

6 repented that he had made man on the earth. And being touched inwardly with a sorrow of heart,

7 he said, "I will eliminate man, whom I have created, from the face of the earth, from man to other living things, from animals even to the flying things of the air. For it grieves me that I have made them."

8 Yet truly, Noah found grace before the Lord.

9 These are the generations of Noah. Noah was a just man, and yet he was predominate among his generations, for he walked with God.

10 And he conceived three sons: Shem, Ham, and Japheth.

11 Yet the earth was corrupted before the eyes of God, and it was filled with iniquity.

12 And when God had seen that the earth had been corrupted, (indeed, all flesh had corrupted its way upon the earth)

13 he said to Noah: "The end of all flesh has arrived in my sight. The earth has been filled with iniquity by their presence, and I will destroy them, along with the earth.

14 Make yourself an ark from smoothed wood. You shall make little dwelling places in the ark, and you shall smear pitch on the interior and exterior.

15 And thus shall you make it: The length of the ark shall be three hundred cubits, its width fifty cubits, and its height thirty cubits.

16 You shall make a window in the ark, and you shall complete it within a cubit of the top. Then you shall set the door of the ark at its side. You shall make in it: a lower part, upper rooms, and a third level.

17 Behold, I shall bring the waters of a great flood upon the earth, so as to put to death all flesh in which there is the breath of life under heaven. All things that are on the earth shall be consumed.

18 And I shall establish my covenant with you, and you shall enter the ark, you and your sons, your wife and the wives of your sons with you.

19 And from every living thing of all that is flesh, you shall lead pairs into the ark, so that they may survive with you: from the male sex and the female,

20 from birds, according to their kind, and from beasts, in their kind, and from among all animals on earth, according to their kind; pairs from each shall enter with you, so that they may be able to live.

21 Therefore, you shall take with you from all the foods that are able to be eaten, and you shall carry these with you. And these shall be used as food, some for you, and the rest for them."

22 And so Noah did all things just as God had instructed him.

Genesis 7

1 And the Lord said to him: "Enter the ark, you and all your house. For I have seen you to be just in my sight, within this generation.

2 From all the clean animals, take seven and seven, the male and the female. Yet truly, from animals that are unclean, take two and two, the male and the female.

3 But also from the birds of the air, take seven and seven, the male and the female, so that offspring may be saved upon the face of the whole earth.

4 For from that point, and after seven days, I will rain upon the earth for forty days and forty nights. And I will wipe away every substance that I have made, from the surface of the earth."

5 Therefore, Noah did all things just as the Lord had commanded him.

6 And he was six hundred years old when the waters of the great flood inundated the earth.

7 And Noah entered into the ark, and his sons, his wife, and the wives of his sons with him, because of the waters of the great flood.

8 And from the animals both clean and unclean, and from the birds, and from everything that moves upon the earth,

9 two by two they were brought into the ark to Noah, male and female, just as the Lord had instructed Noah.

10 And when seven days had passed, the waters of the great flood inundated the earth.

11 In the six hundredth year of the life of Noah, in the second month, in the seventeenth day of the month, all the fountains of the great abyss were released, and the floodgates of heaven were opened.

12 And rain came upon the earth for forty days and forty nights.

13 On the very same day, Noah and his sons, Shem, Ham, and Japheth, and his wife and the three wives of his sons with them, entered the ark.

14 They and every animal according to its kind, and all the cattle in their kind, and everything that moves upon the earth in their kind, and every flying thing according to its kind, all the birds and all that can fly,

15 entered the ark to Noah, two by two out of all that is flesh, in which there was the breath of life.

16 And those that entered went in male and female, from all that is flesh, just as God had instructed him. And then the Lord closed him in from the outside.

17 And the great flood occurred for forty days upon the earth. And the waters were increased, and they lifted the ark high above the land.

18 For they overflowed greatly, and they filled everything on the surface of the earth. And then the ark was carried across the waters.

19 And the waters prevailed beyond measure across the earth. And all the lofty mountains under the whole heaven were covered.

20 The water was fifteen cubits higher than the mountains which it covered.

21 And all flesh was consumed which moved upon the earth: flying things, animals, wild beasts, and all moving things that crawl upon the ground. And all men,

22 and everything in which there is the breath of life on earth, died.

23 And he wiped away all substance that was upon the earth, from man to animal, the crawling things just as much as the flying things of the air. And they were wiped away from the earth. But only Noah remained, and those who were with him in the ark.

24 And the waters possessed the earth for one hundred and fifty days.

Genesis 8

1 Then God remembered Noah, and all living things, and all the cattle, which were with him in the ark, and he brought a wind across the earth, and the waters were diminished.

2 And the fountains of the abyss and the floodgates of heaven were closed. And the rain from heaven was restrained.

3 And the waters were restored to their coming and going from the earth. And they began to diminish after one hundred and fifty days.

4 And the ark rested in the seventh month, on the twenty-seventh day of the month, upon the mountains of Armenia.

5 Yet in truth, the waters were departing and decreasing until the tenth month. For in the tenth month, on the first day of the month, the tips of the mountains appeared.

6 And when forty days had passed, Noah, opening the window that he had made in the ark, sent forth a raven,

7 which went forth and did not return, until the waters were dried up across the earth.

8 Likewise, he sent forth a dove after him, in order to see if the waters had now ceased upon the face of the earth.

9 But when she did not find a place where her foot might rest, she returned to him in the ark. For the waters were upon the whole earth. And he extended his hand and caught her, and he brought her into the ark.

10 And then, having waited a further seven days, he again sent forth the dove out of the ark.

11 And she came to him in the evening, carrying in her mouth an olive branch with green leaves. Noah then understood that the waters had ceased upon the earth.

12 And nevertheless, he waited another seven days. And he sent forth the dove, which no longer returned to him.

13 Therefore, in the six hundred and first year, in the first month, on the first day of the month, the waters were diminished upon the earth. And Noah, opening the cover of the ark, gazed out and saw that the surface of the earth had become dry.

14 In the second month, on the twenty-seventh day of the month, the earth was made dry.

15 Then God spoke to Noah, saying:

16 "Go out of the ark, you and your wife, your sons and the wives of your sons with you.

17 Bring out with you all the living things that are with you, all that is flesh: as with the birds, so also with the wild beasts and all the animals that move upon the earth. And enter upon the land: increase and multiply upon it."

18 And so Noah and his sons went out, and his wife and the wives of his sons with him.

19 Then also all living things, and the cattle, and the animals that move upon the earth, according to their kinds, departed from the ark.

20 Then Noah built an altar to the Lord. And, taking from each of the cattle and birds that were clean, he offered holocausts upon the altar.

21 And the Lord smelled the sweet odor and said: "I will no longer curse the earth because of man. For the feelings and thoughts of the heart of man are prone to evil from his youth. Therefore, I will no longer pierce every living soul as I have done.

22 All the days of the earth, seedtime and harvest, cold and heat, summer and winter, night and day, will not cease."

Genesis 9

1 And God blessed Noah and his sons. And he said to them: "Increase, and multiply, and fill the earth.

2 And let the fear and trembling of you be upon all the animals of the earth, and upon all the birds of the air, along with all that moves across the earth. All the fish of the sea have been delivered into your hand.

3 And everything that moves and lives will be food for you. Just as with the edible plants, I have delivered them all to you,

4 except that flesh with blood you shall not eat.

5 For I will examine the blood of your lives at the hand of every beast. So also, at the hand of mankind, at the hand of each man and his brother, I will examine the life of mankind.

6 Whoever will shed human blood, his blood will be poured out. For man was indeed made to the image of God.

7 But as for you: increase and multiply, and go forth upon the earth and fulfill it."

8 To Noah and to his sons with him, God also said this:

9 "Behold, I will establish my covenant with you, and with your offspring after you,

10 and with every living soul that is with you: as much with the birds as with the cattle and all the animals of the earth that have gone forth from the ark, and with all the wild beasts of the earth.

11 I will establish my covenant with you, and no longer will all that is flesh be put to death by the waters of a great flood, and, henceforth, there will not be a great flood to utterly destroy the earth."

12 And God said: "This is the sign of the pact that I grant between me and you, and to every living soul that is with you, for perpetual generations.

13 I will place my arc in the clouds, and it will be the sign of the pact between myself and the earth.

14 And when I obscure the sky with clouds, my arc will appear in the clouds.

15 And I will remember my covenant with you, and with every living soul that enlivens flesh. And there will no longer be waters from a great flood to wipe away all that is flesh.

16 And the arc will be in the clouds, and I will see it, and I will remember the everlasting covenant that was enacted between God and every living soul of all that is flesh upon the earth."

17 And God said to Noah, "This will be the sign of the covenant that I have established between myself and all that is flesh upon the earth."

18 And so the sons of Noah, who came out of the ark, were Shem, Ham, and Japheth. Now Ham himself is the father of Canaan.

19 These three are the sons of Noah. And from these all the family of mankind was spread over the whole earth.

20 And Noah, a good farmer, began to cultivate the land, and he planted a vineyard.

21 And by drinking its wine, he became inebriated and was naked in his tent.

22 Because of this, when Ham, the father of Canaan, had indeed seen the privates of his father to be naked, he reported it to his two brothers outside.

23 And truly, Shem and Japheth put a cloak upon their arms, and, advancing backwards, covered the privates of their father. And their faces were turned away, so that they did not see their father's manhood.

24 Then Noah, awaking from the wine, when he had learned what his younger son had done to him,

25 he said, "Cursed be Canaan, a servant of servants will he be to his brothers."

26 And he said: "Blessed be the Lord God of Shem, let Canaan be his servant.

27 May God enlarge Japheth, and may he live in the tents of Shem, and let Canaan be his servant."

28 And after the great flood, Noah lived for three hundred and fifty years.

29 And all his days were completed in nine hundred and fifty years, and then he died.

Genesis 10

1 These are the generations of the sons of Noah: Shem, Ham, and Japheth, and of the sons who were born to them after the great flood.

2 The sons of Japheth were Gomer, and Magog, and Madai, and Javan, and Tubal, and Meshech, and Tiras.

3 And then the sons of Gomer were Ashkenaz, and Riphath, and Togarmah.

4 And the sons of Javan were Elishah, and Tarshish, Kittim, and Rodanim.

5 The islands of the Gentiles were divided by these into their regions, each one according to his tongue, and their families in their nations.

6 And the Sons of Ham were Cush, and Mizraim, and Put, and Canaan.

7 And the sons of Cush were Seba, and Havilah, and Sabtah, and Raamah, and Sabteca. The sons of Raamah were Sheba and Dadan.

8 And then Cush conceived Nimrod; he began to be powerful on the earth.

9 And he was an able hunter before the Lord. From this, a proverb came forth: 'Just like Nimrod, an able hunter before the Lord.'

10 And so, the beginning of his kingdom was Babylon, and Erech, and Accad, and Chalanne, in the land of Shinar.

11 From that land, Assur came forth, and he built Nineveh, and the streets of the city, and Calah,

12 and also Resen, between Nineveh and Calah. This is a great city.

13 And truly, Mizraim conceived Ludim, and Anamim, and Lehabim, Naphtuhim,

14 and Pathrusim, and Casluhim, from whom came forth the Philistines and the Caphtorim.

15 Then Canaan conceived Sidon his firstborn, the Hittite,

16 and the Jebusite, and the Amorite, the Girgashite,

17 the Hivite, and the Arkite: the Sinite,

18 and the Arvadian, the Samarite, and the Hamathite. And after this, the peoples of the Canaanites became widespread.

19 And the borders of Chanaan went, as one travels, from Sidon to Gerar, even to Gaza, until one enters Sodom and Gomorrah, and from Admah and Zeboiim, even to Lesa.

20 These are the sons of Ham in their kindred, and tongues, and generations, and lands, and nations.

21 Likewise, from Shem, the father of all the sons of Heber, the elder brother of Japheth, sons were born.

22 The sons of Shem were Elam, and Asshur, and Arphaxad, and Lud, and Aram.

23 The sons of Aram were Uz, and Hul, and Gether, and Mash.

24 But truly, Arphaxad conceived Shelah, from whom was born Eber.

25 And to Eber were born two sons: the name of the one was Peleg, for in his days the earth became divided, and his brother's name was Joktan.

26 This Joktan conceived Almodad, and Sheleph, and Hazarmaveth, Jerah

27 and Hadoram, and Uzal and Diklah,

28 and Obal and Abimael, Sheba

29 and Ophir, and Havilah and Jobab. All these were the sons of Joktan.

30 And their habitation extended from Messa, as one sojourns, even to Sephar, a mountain in the east.

31 These are the sons of Shem according to their kindred, and tongues, and the regions within their nations.

32 These are the families of Noah, according to their peoples and nations. The nations became divided according to these, on the earth after the great flood.

Genesis 11

1 Now the earth was of one language and of the same speech.

2 And when they were advancing from the east, they found a plain in the land of Shinar, and they dwelt in it.

3 And each one said to his neighbor, "Come, let us make bricks, and bake them with fire." And they had bricks instead of stones, and pitch instead of mortar.

4 And they said: "Come, let us make a city and a tower, so that its height may reach to heaven. And let us make our name famous before we are divided into all the lands."

5 Then the Lord descended to see the city and the tower, which the sons of Adam were building.

6 And he said: "Behold, the people are united, and all have one tongue. And since they have begun to do this, they will not desist from their plans, until they have completed their work.

7 Therefore, come, let us descend, and in that place confound their tongue, so that they may not listen, each one to the voice of his neighbor."

8 And so the Lord divided them from that place into all the lands, and they ceased to build the city.

9 And for this reason, its name was called 'Babel,' because in that place the language of the whole earth became confused. And from then on, the Lord scattered them across the face of every region.

10 These are the generations of Shem. Shem was one hundred years old when he conceived Arphaxad, two years after the great flood.

11 And after he conceived Arphaxad, Shem lived for five hundred years, and he conceived sons and daughters.

12 Next, Arphaxad lived for thirty-five years, and then he conceived Shelah.

13 And after he conceived Shelah, Arphaxad lived for three hundred and three years, and he conceived sons and daughters.

14 Likewise, Shelah lived for thirty years, and then he conceived Eber.

15 And after he conceived Eber, Shelah lived for four hundred and three years, and he conceived sons and daughters.

16 Then Eber lived for thirty-four years, and he conceived Peleg.

17 And after he conceived Peleg, Eber lived for four hundred and thirty years, and he conceived sons and daughters.

18 Likewise, Peleg lived for thirty years, and then he conceived Reu.

19 And after he conceived Reu, Peleg lived for two hundred and nine years, and he conceived sons and daughters.

20 Then Reu lived for thirty-two years, and then he conceived Serug.

21 Likewise, after he conceived Serug, Reu lived for two hundred and seven years, and he conceived sons and daughters.

22 In truth, Serug lived for thirty years, and then he conceived Nahor.

23 And after he conceived Nahor, Serug lived for two hundred years, and he conceived sons and daughters.

24 And so Nahor lived for twenty-nine years, and then he conceived Terah.

25 And after he conceived Terah, Nahor lived for one hundred and nineteen years, and he conceived sons and daughters.

26 And Terah lived for seventy years, and then he conceived Abram, and Nahor, and Haran.

27 And these are the generations of Terah. Terah conceived Abram, Nahor, and Haran. Next Haran conceived Lot.

28 And Haran died before his father Terah, in the land of his nativity, in Ur of the Chaldeans.

29 Then Abram and Nahor took wives. The name of Abram's wife was Sarai. And the name of Nahor's wife was Milcah, the daughter of Haran, the father of Milcah, and the father of Iscah.

30 But Sarai was barren and had no children.

31 And so Terah took his son Abram, and his grandson Lot, the son of Haran, and his daughter-in-law Sarai, the wife of his son Abram, and he led them away from Ur of the Chaldeans, to go into the land of Canaan. And they approached as far as Haran, and they dwelt there.

32 And the days of Terah that passed were two hundred and five years, and then he died in Haran.

Genesis 12

1 Then the Lord said to Abram: "Depart from your land, and from your kindred, and from your father's house, and come into the land that I will show you.

2 And I will make of you a great nation, and I will bless you and magnify your name, and you will be blessed.

3 I will bless those who bless you, and curse those who curse you, and in you all the families of the earth will be blessed."

4 And so Abram departed just as the Lord had instructed him, and Lot went with him. Abram was seventy-five years old when he departed from Haran.

5 And he took his wife Sarai, and Lot, the son of his brother, and all the substance which they had come to possess, and the lives which they had acquired in Haran, and they departed in order to go to the land of Canaan. And when they arrived in it,

6 Abram passed through the land even to the place of Shechem, as far as the famous steep valley. Now at that time, the Canaanite was in the land.

7 Then the Lord appeared to Abram, and he said to him, "To your offspring, I will give this land." And there he built an altar to the Lord, who had appeared to him.

8 And passing on from there to a mountain, which was opposite the east of Bethel, he pitched his tent there, having Bethel to the west, and Hai on the east. He also built an altar there to the Lord, and he called upon his name.

9 And Abram traveled, going out and continuing further on, toward the south.

10 But a famine occurred in the land. And Abram descended to Egypt, to sojourn there. For famine prevailed over the land.

11 And when he was close to entering Egypt, he said to his wife Sarai: "I know you to be a beautiful woman.

12 And when the Egyptians see you, they will say, 'She is his wife.' And they will put me to death, and retain you.

13 Therefore, I beg you to say that you are my sister, so that it may be well with me because of you, and so that my soul may live by your favor."

14 And so, when Abram had arrived in Egypt, the Egyptians saw that the woman was exceedingly beautiful.

15 And the princes reported it to Pharaoh, and they praised her to him. And the woman was inducted into the house of Pharaoh.

16 In truth, they treated Abram well because of her. And he had sheep and oxen and male donkeys, and men servants, and women servants, and female donkeys, and camels.

17 But the Lord scourged Pharaoh and his house with great wounds because of Sarai, the wife of Abram.

18 And Pharaoh called Abram, and he said to him: "What is this that you have done to me? Why did you not tell me she was your wife?

19 For what reason did you claim her to be your sister, so that I would take her to me as a wife? Now therefore, behold your mate, receive her and go."

20 And Pharaoh instructed his men about Abram. And they led him away with his wife and all that he had.

Genesis 13

1 Therefore, Abram ascended from Egypt, he and his wife, and all that he had, and Lot with him, toward the southern region.

2 But he was very wealthy by the possession of gold and silver.

3 And he returned by the way that he came, from the meridian into Bethel, all the way to the place where before he had pitched his tent, between Bethel and Hai.

4 There, at the place of the altar he had made before, he again called upon the name of the Lord.

5 But Lot also, who was with Abram, had flocks of sheep, and cattle, and tents.

6 Neither was the land able to contain them, so that they might dwell together. Indeed, their substance was so great that they could not live in common.

7 And then there also arose a conflict between the shepherds of Abram and of Lot. Now at that time the Canaanite and the Perizzite lived in that land.

8 Therefore, Abram said to Lot: "I ask you, let there be no quarrel between me and you, and between my shepherds and your shepherds. For we are brothers.

9 Behold, the entire land is before your eyes. Withdraw from me, I beg you. If you will go to the left, I will take the right. If you choose the right, I will pass to the left."

10 And so Lot, lifting up his eyes, saw all the region around the Jordan, which was thoroughly irrigated, before the Lord overthrew Sodom and Gomorrah. It was like the Paradise of the Lord, and it was like Egypt, approaching toward Zoar.

11 And Lot chose for himself the region around the Jordan, and he withdrew by way of the east. And they were divided, one brother from the other.

12 Abram dwelt in the land of Canaan. In truth, Lot stayed in the towns that were around the Jordan, and he lived in Sodom.

13 But the men of Sodom were very wicked, and they were sinners before the Lord beyond measure.

14 And the Lord said to Abram, after Lot was divided from him: "Lift up your eyes, and gaze out from the place where you are now, to the north and to the meridian, to the east and to the west.

15 All the land that you see, I will give to you, and to your offspring even forever.

16 And I will make your offspring like the dust of the earth. If any man is able to number the dust of the earth, he will be able to number your offspring as well.

17 Arise and walk through the land in its length, and breadth. For I will give it to you."

18 Therefore, moving his tent, Abram went and dwelt by the steep valley of Mamre, which is in Hebron. And he built an altar there to the Lord.

Genesis 14

1 Now it happened in that time that Amraphel, king of Shinar, and Arioch, king of Pontus, and Chedorlaomer, king of the Elamites, and Tidal, king of the Nations,

2 went to war against Bera, king of Sodom, and against Birsha, king of Gomorrah, and against Shinab, king of Admah, and against Shemeber, king of Zeboiim, and against the king of Bela, that is Zoar.

3 All these came together in the wooded valley, which is now the Sea of Salt.

4 For they had served Chedorlaomer for twelve years, and in the thirteenth year they withdrew from him.

5 Therefore, in the fourteenth year, Chedorlaomer arrived, and the kings who were with him. And they struck the Rephaim at Ashteroth of the two horns, and the Zuzim with them, and the Emim at Shaveh-Kiriathaim.

6 and the Chorreans in the mountains of Seir, even to the plains of Paran, which is in wilderness.

7 And they returned and arrived at the fountain of Mishpat, which is Kadesh. And they struck the entire region of the Amalekites, and the Amorites who dwelt in Hazazontamar.

8 And the king of Sodom, and the king of Gomorrah, and the king of Admah, and the king of Zeboiim, and indeed the king of Bela, which is Zoar, went forth. And they directed their point against them in the wooded valley,

9 namely, against Chedorlaomer, king of the Elamites, and Tidal, king of the Nations, and Amraphel, king of Shinar, and Arioch, king of Pontus: four kings against five.

10 Now the wooded valley had many pits of bitumen. And so the king of Sodom and the king of Gomorrah turned back and they fell there. And those who remained, fled to the mountain.

11 Then they took all the substance of the Sodomites and the Gomorrahites, and all that pertained to food, and they went away,

12 along with both Lot, the son of Abram's brother, who lived in Sodom, and his substance.

13 And behold, one who had escaped reported it to Abram the Hebrew, who lived in the steep valley of Mamre the Amorite, who was the brother of Eshcol, and the brother of Aner. For these had formed an agreement with Abram.

14 When Abram had heard this, namely, that his brother Lot had been taken captive, he numbered three hundred and eighteen of his own armed men and he went in pursuit all the way to Dan.

15 And dividing his company, he rushed upon them in the night. And he struck them and pursued them as far as Hobah, which is on the left hand of Damascus.

16 And he brought back all the substance, and Lot his brother, with his substance, likewise the women and the people.

17 Then the king of Sodom went out to meet him, after he returned from the slaughter at Chedorlaomer, and the kings who were with him at the valley of Shaveh, which is the valley of the king.

18 Then in truth, Melchizedek, the king of Salem, brought forth bread and wine, for he was a priest of the Most High God;

19 he blessed him, and he said: "Blessed be Abram by the Most High God, who created heaven and earth.

20 And blessed be the Most High God, through whose protection the enemies are in your hands." And he gave him tithes from everything.

21 Then the king of Sodom said to Abram, "Give me these souls, and take the rest for yourself."

22 And he responded to him: "I lift up my hand to the Lord God, the Most High, the Possessor of heaven and earth,

23 that from one thread within a blanket, even to a single shoelace, I will not take anything from that which is yours, lest you say, 'I have enriched Abram,'

24 except that which the young men have eaten, and the shares for the men who came with me: Aner, Eshcol, and Mamre. These will take their shares."

Genesis 15

1 And so, these things having been transacted, the word of the Lord came to Abram by a vision, saying: "Do not be afraid, Abram, I am your protector, and your reward is exceedingly great."

2 And Abram said: "Lord God, what will you give to me? I may go without children. And the son of the steward of my house is this Eliezer of Damascus."

3 And Abram added: "Yet to me you have not given offspring. And behold, my servant born in my house will be my heir."

4 And immediately the word of the Lord came to him, saying: "This one will not be your heir. But he who will come from your loins, the same will you have for your heir."

5 And he brought him outside, and he said to him, "Take in the heavens, and number the stars, if you can." And he said to him, "So also will your offspring be."

6 Abram believed God, and it was reputed to him unto justice.

7 And he said to him, "I am the Lord who led you away from Ur of the Chaldeans, so as to give you this land, and so that you would possess it."

8 But he said, "Lord God, in what way may I be able to know that I will possess it?"

9 And the Lord responded by saying: "Take for me a cow of three years, and a she-goat of three years, and a ram of three years, also a turtle-dove and a pigeon."

10 Taking all these, he divided them through the middle, and placed both parts opposite one another. But the birds he did not divide.

11 And birds descended upon the carcasses, but Abram drove them away.

12 And when the sun was setting, a deep sleep fell upon Abram, and a dread, great and dark, invaded him.

13 And it was said to him: "Know beforehand that your future offspring will be sojourners in a land not their own, and they will subjugate them in servitude and afflict them for four hundred years.

14 Yet truly, I will judge the nation that they will serve, and after this they will depart with great substance.

15 But you will go to your fathers in peace and be buried at a good old age.

16 But in the fourth generation, they will return here. For the iniquities of the Amorites are not yet completed, even to this present time."

17 Then, when the sun had set, there came a dark mist, and there appeared a smoking furnace and a lamp of fire passing between those divisions.

18 On that day, God formed a covenant with Abram, saying: "To your offspring I will give this land, from the river of Egypt, even to the great river Euphrates:

19 the land of the Kenites and the Kenizzites, the Kadmonites

20 and the Hittites, and the Perizzites, likewise the Rephaim,

21 and the Amorites, and the Canaanites, and the Girgashites, and the Jebusites."

Genesis 16

1 Now Sarai, the wife of Abram, had not conceived children. But, having an Egyptian handmaid named Hagar,

2 she said to her husband: "Behold, the Lord has closed me, lest I give birth. Enter to my handmaid, so that perhaps I may receive sons of her at least." And when he agreed to her supplication,

3 she took Hagar the Egyptian, her handmaid, ten years after they began to live in the land of Canaan, and she gave her to her husband as a wife.

4 And he entered to her. But when she saw that she had conceived, she despised her mistress.

5 And Sarai said to Abram: "You have acted unfairly against me. I gave my handmaid into your bosom, who, when she saw that she had conceived, held me in contempt. May the Lord judge between me and you."

6 Abram responded to her by saying, "Behold, your handmaid is in your hand to treat as it pleases you." And so, when Sarai afflicted her, she took flight.

7 And when the Angel of the Lord had found her, near the fountain of water in the wilderness, which is on the way to Shur in the desert,

8 he said to her: "Hagar, handmaid of Sarai, where have you come from? And where will you go?" And she answered, "I flee from the face of Sarai, my mistress."

9 And the Angel of the Lord said to her, "Return to your mistress, and humble yourself under her hand."

10 And again he said, "I will multiply your offspring continuously, and they will not be numbered because of their multitude."

11 But thereafter he said: "Behold, you have conceived, and you will give birth to a son. And you shall call his name Ishmael, because the Lord has heard your affliction.

12 He will be a wild man. His hand will be against all, and all hands will be against him. And he will pitch his tents away from the region of all his brothers."

13 Then she called upon the name of the Lord who had spoken to her: "You are the God who has seen me." For she said, "Certainly, here I have seen the back of the one who sees me."

14 Because of this, she called that well: 'The well of the one who lives and who sees me.' The same is between Kadesh and Bered.

15 And Hagar gave birth to a son for Abram, who called his name Ishmael.

16 Abram was eighty-six years old when Hagar gave birth to Ishmael for him.

Genesis 17

1 In truth, after he began to be ninety-nine years of age, the Lord appeared to him. And he said to him: "I am the Almighty God. Walk in my sight and become complete.

2 And I will set my covenant between me and you. And I will multiply you very exceedingly."

3 Abram fell prone on his face.

4 And God said to him: "I AM, and my covenant is with you, and you will be the father of many nations.

5 No longer will your name be called Abram. But you will be called Abraham, for I have established you as the father of many nations.

6 And I will cause you to increase very greatly, and I will set you among the nations, and kings will come forth from you.

7 And I will establish my covenant between me and you, and with your offspring after you in their generations, by a perpetual covenant: to be God to you and to your offspring after you.

8 And I will give to you and to your offspring, the land of your sojourn, all the land of Canaan, as an eternal possession, and I will be their God."

9 Again God said to Abraham: "And you therefore shall keep my covenant, and your offspring after you in their generations.

10 This is my covenant, which you shall observe, between me and you, and your offspring after you: All the males among you shall be circumcised.

11 And you shall circumcise the flesh of your foreskin, so that it may be a sign of the covenant between me and you.

12 An infant of eight days will be circumcised among you, every male in your generations. So also servants born to you, as well as those bought, shall be circumcised, even those who are not of your stock.

13 And my covenant shall be with your flesh as an eternal covenant.

14 The male, the flesh of whose foreskin will not be circumcised, that soul shall be eliminated from his people. For he has made my covenant void."

15 God said also to Abraham: "Your wife Sarai, you shall not call Sarai, but Sarah.

16 And I will bless her, and from her I will give you a son, whom I will bless, and he will be among the nations, and the kings of the peoples will rise from him."

17 Abraham fell on his face, and he laughed, saying in his heart: "Do you think a son can be born to a one hundred year old man? And will Sarah give birth at the age of ninety?"

18 And he said to God, "If only Ishmael would live in your sight."

19 And God said to Abraham: "Your wife Sarah shall give birth to a son, and you shall call his name Isaac, and I will establish my covenant with him as a perpetual covenant, and with his offspring after him.

20 Likewise, concerning Ishmael, I have heard you. Behold, I will bless and enlarge him, and I will multiply him greatly. He will produce twelve leaders, and I will make him into a great nation.

21 Yet in truth, I will establish my covenant with Isaac, to whom Sarah will give birth for you at this time next year."

22 And when he had finished speaking with him, God ascended from Abraham.

23 Then Abraham took his son Ishmael, and all who were born in his house, and all whom he had bought, every male among the men of his house, and he circumcised the flesh of their foreskin promptly, the very same day, just as God had instructed him.

24 Abraham was ninety-nine years old when he circumcised the flesh of his foreskin.

25 And his son Ishmael had completed thirteen years at the time of his circumcision.

26 On the very same day, Abraham was circumcised with his son Ishmael.

27 And all the men of his house, those born in his house, as well as those who were bought, even the foreigners, were circumcised with him.

Genesis 18

1 Then the Lord appeared to him, in the steep valley of Mamre, when he was sitting at the door of his tent, in the very heat of the day.

2 And when he had lifted up his eyes, there appeared to him three men, standing near him. When he had seen them, he ran to meet them from the door of his tent, and he reverenced them on the ground.

3 And he said: "If I, O lord, have found grace in your eyes, do not pass by your servant.

4 But I will bring a little water, and you may wash your feet and rest under the tree.

5 And I will set out a meal of bread, so that you may strengthen your heart; after this you will pass on. It is for this reason that you have turned aside to your servant." And they said, "Do as you have spoken."

6 Abraham hurried into the tent to Sarah, and he said to her, "Quickly, mix together three measures of the finest wheat flour and make loaves baked under the ashes."

7 In truth, he himself ran to the herd, and he took a calf from there, very tender and very good, and he gave it to a servant, who hurried and boiled it.

8 Likewise, he took butter and milk, and the calf which he had boiled, and he placed it before them. Yet truly, he himself stood near them under the tree.

9 And when they had eaten, they said to him, "Where is Sarah your wife?" He answered, "Behold, she is in the tent."

10 And he said to him, "When returning, I will come to you at this time, with life as a companion, and your wife Sarah will have a son." Hearing this, Sarah laughed behind the door of the tent.

11 Now they were both old, and in an advanced state of life, and it had ceased to be with Sarah after the manner of women.

12 And she laughed secretly, saying, "After I have grown old, and my lord is elderly, shall I give myself to the work of delight?"

13 Then the Lord said to Abraham: "Why did Sarah laugh, saying: 'How can I, an old woman, actually give birth?'

14 Is anything difficult for God? According to the announcement, he will return to you at this same time, with life as a companion, and Sarah will have a son."

15 Sarah denied it, saying, "I did not laugh." For she was terribly afraid. But the Lord said, "It is not so; for you did laugh."

16 Therefore, when the men had risen up from there, they directed their eyes against Sodom. And Abraham traveled with them, leading them.

17 And the Lord said: "How could I hide what I am about to do from Abraham,

18 since he will become a great and very robust nation, and in him all the nations of the earth will be blessed?

19 For I know that he will instruct his sons, and his household after him, to keep to the way of the Lord, and to act with judgment and justice, so that, for the sake of Abraham, the Lord may bring about all the things that he has spoken to him."

20 And so the Lord said, "The outcry from Sodom and Gomorrah has been multiplied, and their sin has become exceedingly grievous.

21 I will descend and see whether they have fulfilled the work of the outcry that has reached me, or whether it is not so, in order that I may know."

22 And they turned themselves from there, and they went toward Sodom. Yet in truth, Abraham still stood in the sight of the Lord.

23 And as they drew near, he said: "Will you destroy the just with the impious?

24 If there were fifty of the just in the city, will they perish with the rest? And will you not spare that place for the sake of fifty of the just, if they were in it?

25 Far be it from you to do this thing, and to kill the just with the impious, and for the just to be treated like the impious. No, this is not like you. You judge all the earth; you would never make such a judgment."

26 And the Lord said to him, "If I find in Sodom fifty of the just in the midst of the city, I will release the entire place because of them."

27 And Abraham responded by saying: "Since now I have begun, I will speak to my Lord, though I am dust and ashes.

28 What if there were five less than fifty of the just? Would you, despite the forty-five, eliminate the entire city?" And he said, "I will not eliminate it, if I find forty-five there."

29 And again he said to him, "But if forty were found there, what would you do?" He said, "I will not strike, for the sake of the forty."

30 "I ask you," he said, "not to be angry, Lord, if I speak. What if thirty were found there?" He responded, "I will not act, if I find thirty there."

31 "Since now I have begun," he said, "I will speak to my Lord. What if twenty were found there?" He said, "I will not put to death, for the sake of the twenty."

32 "I beg you," he said, "not to be angry, Lord, if I speak yet once more. What if ten were found there?" And he said, "I will not destroy it for the sake of the ten."

33 And the Lord departed, after he had ceased speaking to Abraham, who then returned to his place.

Genesis 19

1 And the two Angels arrived at Sodom in the evening, and Lot was sitting at the gate of the city. And when he had seen them, he rose up and went to meet them. And he reverenced prone on the ground.

2 And he said: "I beg you, my lords, turn aside to the house of your servant, and lodge there. Wash your feet, and in the morning you will advance on your way." And they said, "Not at all. But we will lodge in the street."

3 He pressed them very much to turn aside to him. And when they had entered his house, he made a feast for them, and he cooked unleavened bread, and they ate.

4 But before they went to bed, the men of the city surrounded the house, from boys to old men, all the people together.

5 And they called out to Lot, and they said to him: "Where are the men who entered to you in the night? Bring them out here, so that we may know them."

6 Lot went out to them, and blocking the door behind him, he said:

7 "Do not, I ask you, my brothers, do not be willing to commit this evil.

8 I have two daughters who as yet have not known man. I will bring them out to you; abuse them as it pleases you, provided that you do no evil to these men, because they have entered under the shadow of my roof."

9 But they said, "Move away from there." And again: "You have entered," they said, "as a stranger; should you then judge? Therefore, we will afflict you yourself more than them." And they acted very violently against Lot. And they were now at the point of breaking open the doors.

10 And behold, the men put out their hand, and they pulled Lot in to them, and they closed the door.

11 And they struck those who were outside with blindness, from the least to the greatest, so that they were not able to find the door.

12 Then they said to Lot: "Do you have here anyone of yours? All who are yours, sons-in-law, or sons, or daughters, bring them out of this city.

13 For we will eliminate this place, because the outcry among them has increased before the Lord, who sent us to destroy them."

14 And so Lot, going out, spoke to his sons-in-law, who were going to receive his daughters, and he said: "Rise up. Depart from this place. For the Lord will destroy this city." And it seemed to them that he was speaking playfully.

15 And when it was morning, the Angels compelled him, saying, "Arise, take your wife, and the two daughters that you have, lest you also should perish amid the wickedness of the city."

16 And, since he ignored them, they took his hand, and the hand of his wife, as well as that of his two daughters, because the Lord was sparing him.

17 And they brought him out, and placed him beyond the city. And there they spoke to him, saying: "Save your life. Do not look not back. Neither should you stay in the entire surrounding region. But save yourself in the mountain, lest you also should perish."

18 And Lot said to them: "I beg you, my lord,

19 though your servant has found grace before you, and you have magnified your mercy, which you have shown to me in saving my life, I cannot be saved on the mountain, lest perhaps some misfortune take hold of me and I die.

20 There is a certain city nearby, to which I can flee; it is a little one, and I will be saved in it. Is it not a modest one, and will not my soul live?"

21 And he said to him: "Behold, even now, I have heard your petitions about this, not to overturn the city on behalf of which you have spoken.

22 Hurry and be saved there. For I cannot do anything until you enter there." For this reason, the name of that city is called Zoar.

23 The sun had risen over the land, and Lot had entered into Zoar.

24 Therefore, the Lord rained upon Sodom and Gomorrah sulphur and fire, from the Lord, out of heaven.

25 And he overturned these cities, and all the surrounding region: all the inhabitants of the cities, and everything that springs from the land.

26 And his wife, looking behind herself, was turned into a statue of salt.

27 Then Abraham, rising up in the morning, in the place where he had stood before with the Lord,

28 looked out toward Sodom and Gomorrah, and the entire land of that region. And he saw embers rising up from the land like smoke from a furnace.

29 For when God overthrew the cities of that region, remembering Abraham, he freed Lot from the overthrow of the cities, in which he had dwelt.

30 And Lot ascended from Zoar, and he stayed on the mountain, and likewise his two daughters with him, (for he was afraid to stay in Zoar) and he dwelt in a cave, he and his two daughters with him.

31 And the elder said to the younger: "Our father is old, and no man remains in the land who can enter to us according to the custom of the whole world.

32 Come, let us inebriate him with wine, and let us sleep with him, so that we may be able to preserve offspring from our father."

33 And so they gave their father wine to drink that night. And the elder went in, and she slept with her father. But he did not perceive it, neither when his daughter lay down, nor when she rose up.

34 Likewise, the next day, the elder said to the younger: "Behold, yesterday I slept with my father, let us give him wine to drink yet again this night, and you will sleep with him, so that we may save offspring from our father."

35 And then they gave their father wine to drink that night also, and the younger daughter went in, and slept with him. And not even then did he perceive when she lay down, or when she rose up.

36 Therefore, the two daughters of Lot conceived by their father.

37 And the elder gave birth to a son, and she called his name Moab. He is the father of the Moabites, even to the present day.

38 Likewise, the younger gave birth to a son, and she called his name Ammon, that is, 'the son of my people.' He is the father of the Ammonites, even today.

Genesis 20

1 Abraham advanced from there into the southern land, and he lived between Kadesh and Shur. And he sojourned in Gerar.

2 And he said about his wife Sarah: "She is my sister." Therefore, Abimelech, the king of Gerar, sent for her and took her.

3 Then God came to Abimelech through a dream in the night, and he said to him: "Lo, you shall die because of the woman that you have taken. For she has a husband."

4 In truth, Abimelech had not touched her, and so he said: "Lord, would you put to death a people, ignorant and just?

5 Did he not say to me, 'She is my sister,' and did she not say, 'He is my brother?' In the sincerity of my heart and the purity of my hands, I have done this."

6 And God said to him: "And I know that you have acted with a sincere heart. And therefore I kept you from sinning against me, and I did not release you to touch her.

7 Now therefore, return his wife to the man, for he is a prophet. And he will pray for you, and you will live. But if you are not willing to return her, know this: you shall die a death, you and all that is yours."

8 And immediately Abimelech, rising up in the night, called all his servants. And he spoke all these words in their hearing, and all the men were very afraid.

9 Then Abimelech called also for Abraham, and he said to him: "What have you done to us? How have we sinned against you, so that you would bring so great a sin upon me and upon my kingdom? You have done to us what you ought not to have done."

10 And remonstrating him again, he said, "What did you see, so that you would do this?"

11 Abraham responded: "I thought to myself, saying: Perhaps there is no fear of God in this place. And they will put me to death because of my wife.

12 Yet, in another way, she is also truly my sister, the daughter of my father, and not the daughter of my mother, and I took her as a wife.

13 Then, after God led me out of my father's house, I said to her: 'You will show this mercy to me. In every place, to which we will travel, you will say that I am your brother.' "

14 Therefore, Abimelech took sheep and oxen, and men servants and women servants, and he gave them to Abraham. And he returned his wife Sarah to him.

15 And he said, "The land is in your sight. Dwell wherever it will please you."

16 Then to Sarah he said: "Behold, I have given your brother one thousand silver coins. This will be for you as a veil for your eyes, to all who are with you and wherever you will travel. And so, remember that you were taken."

17 Then when Abraham prayed, God healed Abimelech and his wife, and his handmaids, and they gave birth.

18 For the Lord had closed every womb of the house of Abimelech, because of Sarah, the wife of Abraham.

Genesis 21

1 Then the Lord visited Sarah, just as he had promised; and he fulfilled what he had spoken.

2 And she conceived and gave birth to a son in her old age, at the time that God had foretold to her.

3 And Abraham called the name of his son, whom Sarah bore for him, Isaac.

4 And he circumcised him on the eighth day, just as God had instructed him,

5 when he was one hundred years old. Indeed, at this stage of his father's life, Isaac was born.

6 And Sarah said: "God has brought laughter to me. Whoever will hear of it will laugh with me."

7 And again, she said: "Hearing this, who would believe Abraham, that Sarah breast-fed a son, to whom she gave birth, despite being elderly?"

8 And the boy grew and was weaned. And Abraham made a great feast on the day of his weaning.

9 And when Sarah had seen the son of Hagar the Egyptian playing with her son Isaac, she said to Abraham:

10 "Cast out this woman servant and her son. For the son of a woman servant will not be heir with my son Isaac."

11 Abraham took this grievously, for the sake of his son.

12 And God said to him: "Let it not seem harsh to you concerning the boy and your woman servant. In all that Sarah has said to you, listen to her voice. For your offspring will be invoked in Isaac.

13 Yet I will also make the son of the woman servant into a great nation, for he is your offspring."

14 And so Abraham arose in the morning, and taking bread and a skin of water, he placed it upon her shoulder, and he handed over the boy, and he released her. And when she had departed, she wandered in the wilderness of Beersheba.

15 And when the water in the skin had been consumed, she set aside the boy, under one of the trees that were there.

16 And she moved away and sat in a distant area, as far as a bow can reach. For she said, "I shall not see the boy die." And so, sitting opposite her, he lifted up his voice and wept.

17 But God heard the voice of the boy. And an Angel of God called to Hagar from heaven, saying: "What are you doing, Hagar? Do not be afraid. For God has heeded the voice of the boy, from the place where he is.

18 Rise up. Take the boy and hold him by the hand. For I will make of him a great nation."

19 And God opened her eyes. And seeing a well of water, she went and filled the skin, and she gave the boy to drink.

20 And God was with him. And he grew, and he stayed in the wilderness, and he became a young man, an archer.

21 And he lived in the desert of Paran, and his mother took a wife for him from the land of Egypt.

22 At the same time, Abimelech and Phicol, the leader of his army, said to Abraham: "God is with you in everything that you do.

23 Therefore, swear by God that you will do no harm to me, and to my posterity, and to my stock. But according to the mercy that I have done to you, you will do to me and to the land, to which you have turned as a newcomer."

24 And Abraham said, "I will swear."

25 And he reproved Abimelech because of a well of water, which his servants had taken away by force.

26 And Abimelech responded, "I do not know who did this thing, but you also did not reveal it to me, nor have I heard of it, before today."

27 And so Abraham took sheep and oxen, and he gave them to Abimelech. And both of them struck a pact.

28 And Abraham set aside seven female lambs from the flock.

29 Abimelech said to him, "What purpose have these seven female lambs, which you have caused to stand separately?"

30 But he said, "You will receive seven female lambs from my hand, so that they may be a testimony for me, that I dug this well."

31 For this reason, that place was called Beersheba, because there both of them did swear.

32 And they initiated a pact on behalf of the well of oath.

33 Then Abimelech and Phicol, the leader of his army, rose up, and they returned to the land of the Palestinians. In truth, Abraham planted a grove in Beersheba, and there he called upon the name of the Lord God Eternal.

34 And he was a settler in the land of the Palestinians for many days.

Genesis 22

1 After these things occurred, God tested Abraham, and he said to him, "Abraham, Abraham." And he answered, "Here I am."

2 He said to him: "Take your only begotten son Isaac, whom you love, and go into the land of vision. And there you shall offer him as a holocaust upon one of the mountains, which I will show to you."

3 And so Abraham, getting up in the night, harnessed his donkey, taking with him two youths, and his son Isaac. And when he had cut wood for the holocaust, he traveled toward the place, as God had instructed him.

4 Then, on the third day, lifting up his eyes, he saw the place at a distance.

5 And he said to his servants: "Wait here with the donkey. I and the boy will hurry further ahead to that place. After we have worshipped, will return to you."

6 He also took the wood for the holocaust, and he imposed it upon his son Isaac. And he himself carried in his hands fire and a sword. And as the two continued on together,

7 Isaac said to his father, "My father." And he answered, "What do you want, son?" "Behold," he said, "fire and wood. Where is the victim for the holocaust?"

8 But Abraham said, "God himself will provide the victim for the holocaust, my son." Thus they continued on together.

9 And they came to the place that God had shown to him. There he built an altar, and he set the wood in order upon it. And when he had bound his son Isaac, he laid him on the altar upon the pile of wood.

10 And he reached out his hand and took hold of the sword, in order to sacrifice his son.

11 And behold, an Angel of the Lord called out from heaven, saying, "Abraham, Abraham." And he answered, "Here I am."

12 And he said to him, "Do not extend your hand over the boy, and do not do anything to him. Now I know that you fear God, since you have not spared your only begotten son for my sake."

13 Abraham lifted up his eyes, and he saw behind his back a ram among the thorns, caught by the horns, which he took and offered as a holocaust, instead of his son.

14 And he called the name of that place: 'The Lord Sees.' Thus, even to this day, it is said: 'On the mountain, the Lord will see.'

15 Then the Angel of the Lord called out to Abraham a second time from heaven, saying:

16 "By my own self, I have sworn, says the Lord. Because you have done this thing, and have not spared your only begotten son for my sake,

17 I will bless you, and I will multiply your offspring like the stars of heaven, and like the sand which is on the seashore. Your offspring will possess the gates of their enemies.

18 And in your offspring, all the nations of the earth will be blessed, because you obeyed my voice."

19 Abraham returned to his servants, and they went to Beersheba together, and he lived there.

20 After these things occurred, it was reported to Abraham that Milcah, likewise, had borne sons for his brother Nahor:

21 Uz, the firstborn, and Buz, his brother, and Kemuel, the father of the Syrians,

22 and Chesed, and Hazo, likewise Pildash, and Jidlaph,

23 as well as Bethuel, of whom was born Rebekah. These eight Milcah bore for Nahor, the brother of Abraham.

24 In truth, his concubine, named Reumah, bore Tebah, and Gaham, and Tahash, and Maacah.

Genesis 23

1 Now Sarah lived for one hundred and twenty-seven years.

2 And she died in the city of Arba, which is Hebron, in the land of Canaan. And Abraham came to mourn and weep for her.

3 And when he had risen up from the funeral duties, he spoke to the sons of Heth, saying:

4 "I am a newcomer and a sojourner among you. Give me the right of a sepulcher among you, so that I may bury my dead."

5 The sons of Heth responded by saying:

6 "Hear us, O lord, you are a leader of God among us. Bury your dead in our chosen sepulchers. And no man shall be able to prohibit you from burying your dead within his memorial."

7 Abraham arose, and he reverenced the people of the land, namely, the sons of Heth.

8 And he said to them: "If it pleases your soul that I should bury my dead, hear me, and intercede on my behalf with Ephron, the son of Zohar,

9 so that he may give me the double cave, which he has at the far end of his field. He may transfer it to me for as much money as it is worth in your sight, for the possession of a sepulcher."

10 Now Ephron dwelt in the midst of the sons of Heth. And Ephron responded to Abraham in the hearing of everyone who was entering at the gate of his city, saying:

11 "Let it never be so, my lord, but you should pay greater heed to what I say. The field I will transfer to you, and the cave that is in it. In the presence of the sons of my people, bury your dead."

12 Abraham reverenced in the sight of the people of the land.

13 And he spoke to Ephron, standing in the midst of the people: "I ask you to hear me. I will give you money for the field. Take it, and so I will bury my dead in it."

14 And Ephron responded: "My lord, hear me.

15 The land that you request is worth four hundred shekels of silver. This is the price between me and you. But how much is this? Bury your dead."

16 And when Abraham had heard this, he weighed out the money that Ephron had requested, in the hearing of the sons of Heth, four hundred shekels of silver, of the approved public currency.

17 And having confirmed that the field, in which there was a double cave overlooking Mamre, formerly belonged to Ephron, both it and the sepulcher, and all its trees, with all its surrounding limits,

18 Abraham took it as a possession, in the sight of the sons of Heth and of everyone who was entering at the gate of his city.

19 So then, Abraham buried his wife Sarah in the double cave of the field that overlooked Mamre. This is Hebron in the land of Canaan.

20 And the field was confirmed to Abraham, with the cave that was in it, as a memorial possession before the sons of Heth.

Genesis 24

1 Now Abraham was old and of many days. And the Lord had blessed him in all things.

2 And he said to the elder servant of his house, who was in charge of all that he had: "Place your hand under my thigh,

3 so that I may make you swear by the Lord, the God of heaven and earth, that you will not take a wife for my son from the daughters of the Canaanites, among whom I live.

4 But that you will proceed to my land and kindred, and from there take a wife for my son Isaac."

5 The servant responded, "If the woman is not willing to come with me into this land, must I lead your son back to the place from which you departed?"

6 And Abraham said: "Beware that you never lead my son back to that place.

7 The Lord God of heaven, who took me from my father's house, and from the land of my nativity, who spoke to me and swore to me, saying, 'To your offspring I will give this land,' himself will send his Angel before you, and you will take from there a wife for my son.

8 But if the woman is not willing to follow you, you will not be held by the oath. Only do not lead my son back to that place."

9 Therefore, the servant placed his hand under the thigh of Abraham, his lord, and he swore to him on his word.

10 And he took ten camels from his lord's herd, and he went forth, carrying with him things from all of his goods. And he set out, and continued on, to the city of Nahor, in Mesopotamia.

11 And when he had made the camels lie down outside of the town, near a well of water, in the evening, at the time when women are accustomed to go out to draw water, he said:

12 "O Lord, the God of my lord Abraham, meet with me today, I beg you, and show mercy to my lord Abraham.

13 Behold, I stand near the fountain of water, and the daughters of the inhabitants of this city will go forth to draw water.

14 Therefore, the girl to whom I will say, 'Tip your pitcher, so that I may drink,' and she will respond, 'Drink. In fact, I will give your camels a drink also,' the same one is she whom you have prepared for your servant Isaac. And by this, I will understand that you have shown mercy to my lord."

15 But he had not yet completed these words within himself, when, behold, Rebekah went out, the daughter of Bethuel, son of Milcah, the wife of Nahor, the brother of Abraham, having a pitcher on her shoulder.

16 She was an exceedingly elegant girl, and a most beautiful virgin, and unknown by man. And she descended to the spring, and she filled her pitcher, and then was returning.

17 And the servant ran to meet her, and he said, "Provide me with a little water to drink from your pitcher."

18 And she responded, "Drink, my lord." And she quickly brought down the pitcher on her arm, and she gave him a drink.

19 And after he drank, she added, "In fact, I will draw water for your camels also, until they all drink."

20 And pouring out the pitcher into the troughs, she ran back to the well to draw water; and having drawn, she gave it to all the camels.

21 But he was contemplating her silently, wanting to know whether the Lord had caused his journey to prosper or not

22 Then, after the camels drank, the man took out gold earrings, weighing two shekels, and the same number of bracelets, ten shekels in weight.

23 And he said to her: "Whose daughter are you? Tell me, is there any place in your father's house to lodge?"

24 She responded, "I am the daughter of Bethuel, the son of Milcah, to whom she gave birth for Nahor."

25 And she continued, saying, "There is very much straw and hay with us, and a spacious place to stay."

26 The man bowed himself down, and he adored the Lord,

27 saying, "Blessed be the Lord, the God of my lord Abraham, who has not taken away his mercy and truth from my lord, and who has led me on a direct journey to the house of the brother of my lord."

28 And so the girl ran, and she reported all that she had heard in the house of her mother.

29 Now Rebekah had a brother, named Laban, who went out quickly to the man, where the spring was.

30 And when he had seen the earrings and bracelets in his sister's hands, and he had heard all the words being repeated, "This is what the man spoke to me," he came to the man who stood by the camels and near the spring of water,

31 and he said to him: "Enter, O blessed of the Lord. Why do you stand outside? I have prepared the house, and a place for the camels."

32 And he brought him into his guest quarters. And he unharnessed the camels, and he distributed straw and hay, and water to wash his feet and that of the men who arrived with him.

33 And bread was set out in his sight. But he said, "I will not eat, until I have spoken my words." He answered him, "Speak."

34 Then he said: "I am the servant of Abraham.

35 And the Lord has blessed my lord greatly, and he has become great. And he has given him sheep and oxen, silver and gold, men servants and women servants, camels and donkeys.

36 And Sarah, the wife of my lord, has given birth to a son for my lord in her old age, and he has given him all that he had.

37 And my lord made me swear, saying: 'You shall not take a wife for my son from the Canaanites, in whose land I dwell.

38 But you shall travel to my father's house, and you shall take a wife of my own kindred for my son.'

39 But truly, I answered my lord, 'What if the woman is not willing to come with me?'

40 'The Lord,' he said, 'in whose sight I walk, will send his Angel with you, and he will direct your way. And you shall take a wife for my son from my own kindred and from my father's house.

41 But you will be innocent of my curse, if, when you will arrive at my close relatives, they will not grant this to you.'

42 And so, today I arrived at the well of water, and I said: 'O Lord, the God of my lord Abraham, if you have directed my way, in which I now walk,

43 behold, I stand next to the well of water, and the virgin, who will go forth to draw water, will hear from me, "Give me a little water to drink from your pitcher."

44 And she will say to me, "You drink, and I will also draw for your camels." Let the same be the woman, whom the Lord has prepared for the son of my lord.'

45 And while I thought over these things silently within myself, Rebekah appeared, arriving with a pitcher, which she carried on her shoulder. And she descended to the spring and drew water. And I said to her, 'Give me a little to drink.'

46 And she quickly let down the pitcher from her arm, and said to me, 'You drink, and to your camels I will also distribute drinking water.' I drank, and she watered the camels.

47 And I questioned her, saying, 'Whose daughter are you?' And she responded, 'I am the daughter of Bethuel, the son of Nahor, whom Milcah bore to him.' And so, I hung the earrings on her, to adorn her face, and I put the bracelets on her hands.

48 And falling prostrate, I adored the Lord, blessing the Lord, the God of my lord Abraham, who has led me along the straight path so as to take the daughter of my lord's brother to his son.

49 For this reason, if you would act according to mercy and truth with my lord, tell me so. But if it pleases you otherwise, say that to me also, so that I may go either to the right, or to the left."

50 And Laban and Bethuel responded: "A word has proceeded from the Lord. We are not able to speak anything else to you, beyond what pleases him.

51 Lo, Rebekah is in your sight. Take her and continue on, and let her be the wife of the son of your lord, just as the Lord has spoken."

52 When Abraham's servant had heard this, falling down to the ground, he adored the Lord.

53 And bringing forth vessels of silver and gold, as well as garments, he gave them to Rebekah as a tribute. Likewise, he offered gifts to her brothers and her mother.

54 And a banquet began, and they feasted and drank together, and they lodged there. And rising up in the morning, the servant said, "Release me, so that I may go to my lord."

55 And her brothers and mother responded, "Let the girl remain for at least ten days with us, and after that, she will continue on."

56 "Do not be willing," he said, "to delay me, for the Lord has directed my way. Release me, so that I may journey to my lord."

57 And they said, "Let us call the girl, and ask her will."

58 And when, having been called, she arrived, they wanted to know, "Will you go with this man?" And she said, "I will go."

59 Therefore, they released her and her nurse, and the servant of Abraham and his companions,

60 wishing prosperity for their sister, by saying: "You are our sister. May you increase to thousands of thousands. And may your offspring possess the gates of their enemies."

61 And so, Rebekah and her maids, riding upon camels, followed the man, who quickly returned to his lord.

62 Then, at the same time, Isaac was walking along the way that leads to the well, whose name is: 'of the One who lives and who sees.' For he dwelt in the southern land.

63 And he had gone out to meditate in the field, as daylight was now declining. And when he had lifted up his eyes, he saw camels advancing from afar.

64 Likewise, Rebekah, having seen Isaac, descended from the camel.

65 And she said to the servant, "Who is that man who advances to meet us through the field?" And he said to her, "That is my lord." And so, quickly taking up her cloak, she covered herself.

66 Then the servant explained to Isaac all that he had done.

67 And he led her into the tent of Sarah his mother, and he accepted her as wife. And he loved her so very much, that it tempered the sorrow which befell him at his mother's death.

Genesis 25

1 In truth, Abraham took another wife, named Keturah.

2 And she bore to him Zimran, and Jokshan, and Medan, and Midian, and Ishbak, and Shuah.

3 Likewise, Jokshan conceived Sheba and Dedan. The sons of Dedan were Asshurim, and Letushim, and Leummim.

4 And truly, from Midian was born Ephah, and Epher, and Hanoch, and Abida, and Eldaah. All these were the sons of Keturah.

5 And Abraham gave everything that he possessed to Isaac.

6 But to the sons of the concubines he gave generous gifts, and he separated them from his son Isaac, while he still lived, toward the eastern region.

7 Now the days of Abraham's life were one hundred and seventy-five years.

8 And declining, he died in a good old age, and at an advanced stage of life, and full of days. And he was gathered to his people.

9 And his sons Isaac and Ishmael buried him in the double cave, which was situated in the field of Ephron, of the son of Zohar the Hittite, across from the region of Mamre,

10 which he had bought from the sons of Heth. There he was buried, with his wife Sarah.

11 And after his passing, God blessed his son Isaac, who lived near the well named 'of the One who lives and who sees.'

12 These are the generations of Ishmael, the son of Abraham, whom Hagar the Egyptian, Sarah's servant, bore to him.

13 And these are the names of his sons according to their language and generations. The firstborn of Ishmael was Nebaioth, then Kedar, and Adbeel, and Mibsam,

14 likewise Mishma, and Dumah, and Massa,

15 Hadad, and Tema, and Jetur, and Naphish, and Kedemah.

16 These are the sons of Ishmael. And these are their names throughout their fortresses and towns: the twelve princes of their tribes.

17 And the years of the life of Ishmael that passed were one hundred and thirty-seven. And declining, he died and was placed with his people.

18 Now he had lived from Havilah as far as Shur, which overlooks Egypt as it approaches the Assyrians. He passed away in the sight of all his brothers.

19 Likewise, these are the generations of Isaac, the son of Abraham. Abraham conceived Isaac,

20 who, when he was forty years old, took Rebekah, the sister of Laban, the daughter of Bethuel the Syrian from Mesopotamia, as a wife.

21 And Isaac beseeched the Lord on behalf of his wife, because she was barren. And he heard him, and he gave conception to Rebekah.

22 But the little ones struggled in her womb. So she said, "If it was to be so with me, what need was there to conceive?" And she went to consult the Lord.

23 And responding, he said, "Two nations are in your womb, and two peoples will be divided out of your womb, and one people will overcome the other people, and the elder will serve the younger."

24 Now the time had arrived to give birth, and behold, twins were discovered in her womb.

25 He who departed first was red, and entirely hairy like a pelt; and his name was called Esau. At once the other departed and he held his brother's foot in his hand; and because of this he was called Jacob.

26 Isaac was sixty years old when the little ones were born to him.

27 And as adults, Esau became a knowledgeable hunter and a man of agriculture, but Jacob, a simple man, dwelt in tents.

28 Isaac was fond of Esau, because he was fed from his hunting; and Rebekah loved Jacob.

29 Then Jacob boiled a small meal. Esau, when he had arrived weary from the field,

30 said to him, "Give me this red stew, for I am very tired." For this reason, his name was called Edom.

31 Jacob said to him, "Sell me your right of the firstborn."

32 He answered, "Lo, I am dying, what will the right of the firstborn provide for me?"

33 Jacob said, "So then, swear to me." Esau swore to him, and he sold his right of the firstborn.

34 And so, taking bread and the food of lentils, he ate, and he drank, and he went away, giving little weight to having sold the right of the firstborn.

Genesis 26

1 Then, when a famine arose over the land, after that barrenness which had happened in the days of Abraham, Isaac went to Abimelech, king of the Palestinians, in Gerar.

2 And the Lord appeared to him, and he said: "Do not descend into Egypt, but rest in the land that I will tell you,

3 and sojourn in it, and I will be with you, and I will bless you. For to you and to your offspring I will give all these regions, completing the oath that I promised to Abraham your father.

4 And I will multiply your offspring like the stars of heaven. And I will give to your posterity all these regions. And in your offspring all the nations of the earth will be blessed,

5 because Abraham obeyed my voice, and kept my precepts and commandments, and observed the ceremonies and the laws."

6 And so Isaac remained in Gerar.

7 And when he was questioned by the men of that place about his wife, he answered, "She is my sister." For he was afraid to confess her to be his mate, thinking that perhaps they would put him to death because of her beauty.

8 And when very many days had passed, and he had remained in the same place, Abimelech, king of the Palestinians, gazing through a window, saw him being playful with Rebekah, his wife.

9 And summoning him, he said: "It is clear that she is your wife. Why did you falsely claim her to be your sister?" He answered, "I was afraid, lest I might die because of her."

10 And Abimelech said: "Why have you burdened us? Someone from the people could have lain with your wife, and you would have brought a great sin upon us." And he instructed all the people, saying,

11 "Whoever will touch the wife of this man will die a death."

12 Then Isaac sowed in that land, and he found, in that same year, one hundredfold. And the Lord blessed him.

13 And the man was enriched, and he continued prospering as well as increasing, until he became very great.

14 Likewise, he had possessions of sheep and of herds, and a very large family. Because of this, the Palestinians envied him,

15 so, at that time, they obstructed all the wells that the servants of his father Abraham had dug, filling them with soil.

16 It reached a point where Abimelech himself said to Isaac, "Move away from us, for you have become very much more powerful than we."

17 And departing, he then went toward the torrent of Gerar, and he dwelt there.

18 Again, he dug up other wells, which the servants of his father Abraham had dug, and which, after his death, the Philistines had formerly obstructed. And he called them by the same names that his father had called them before.

19 And they dug in the torrent, and they found living water.

20 But in that place also the shepherds of Gerar argued against the shepherds of Isaac, by saying, "It is our water." For this reason, he called the name of the well, because of what had happened, 'Calumny.'

21 Then they dug up yet another one. And over that one also they fought, and he called it, 'Enmity.'

22 Advancing from there, he dug another well, over which they did not contend. And so he called its name, 'Latitude,' saying, "Now the Lord has expanded us and caused us to increase across the land."

23 Then he ascended from that place into Beersheba,

24 where the Lord appeared to him on the same night, saying: "I am the God of Abraham your father. Do not be afraid, for I am with you. I will bless you, and I will multiply your offspring because of my servant Abraham."

25 And so he built an altar there. And he invoked the name of the Lord, and he stretched out his tent. And he instructed his servants to dig a well.

26 When Abimelech, and Ahuzzath, his friend, and Phicol, the leader of the military, had arrived from Gerar to that place,

27 Isaac said to them, "Why have you come to me, a man whom you hate, and whom you have expelled from among you?"

28 And they responded: "We saw that the Lord is with you, and therefore we said: Let there be an oath between us, and let us initiate a pact,

29 so that you may not do us any kind of harm, just as we have touched nothing of yours, and have not caused any injury to you, but with peace we released you, augmented by the blessing of the Lord."

30 Therefore, he made them a feast, and after the food and drink,

31 arising in the morning, they swore to one another. And Isaac sent them away peacefully to their own place.

32 Then, behold, on the same day the servants of Isaac came, reporting to him about a well which they had dug, and saying: "We have found water."

33 Therefore, he called it, 'Abundance.' And the name of the city was established as 'Beersheba,' even to the present day.

34 In truth, at forty years of age, Esau took wives: Judith, the daughter of Beeri, the Hittite, and Basemath, the daughter of Elon, of the same place.

35 And they both offended the mind of Isaac and Rebekah.

Genesis 27

1 Now Isaac was old, and his eyes were cloudy, and so he was not able to see. And he called his elder son Esau, and he said to him, "My son?" And he responded, "Here I am."

2 His father said to him: "You see that I am old, and I do not know the day of my death.

3 Take your weapons, the quiver and the bow, and go out. And when you have taken something by hunting,

4 make from it a small meal for me, just as you know I like, and bring it, so that I may eat and my soul may bless you before I die."

5 And when Rebekah had heard this, and he had gone out into the field to fulfill his father's order,

6 she said to her son Jacob: "I heard your father speaking with your brother Esau, and saying to him,

7 'Bring to me from your hunting, and make me foods, so that I may eat and bless you in the sight of the Lord before I die.'

8 Therefore, now my son, agree to my counsel,

9 and go straight to the flock, and bring me two of the best young goats, so that from them I may make meat for your father, such as he willingly eats.

10 Then, when you have brought these in and he has eaten, he may bless you before he dies."

11 He answered her: "You know that my brother Esau is a hairy man, and I am smooth.

12 If my father should lay hands on me and perceive it, I am afraid lest he think me willing to mock him, and I will bring a curse upon myself, instead of a blessing."

13 And his mother said to him: "Let this curse be upon me, my son. Yet listen to my voice, and go directly to bring what I said."

14 He went out, and he brought, and he gave to his mother. She prepared the meats, just as she knew his father liked.

15 And she clothed him with the very fine garments of Esau, which she had at home with her.

16 And she encircled his hands with little pelts from the young goats, and she covered his bare neck.

17 And she gave him the small meal, and she handed him the bread that she had baked.

18 When he had carried these in, he said, "My father?" And he answered, "I'm listening. Who are you, my son?"

19 And Jacob said: "I am Esau, your firstborn. I have done as you instructed me. Arise; sit and eat from my hunting, so that your soul may bless me."

20 And again Isaac said to his son, "How were you able to find it so quickly, my son?" He answered, "It was the will of God, so that what I sought met with me quickly."

21 And Isaac said, "Come here, so that I may touch you, my son, and may prove whether you are my son Esau, or not."

22 He approached his father, and when he had felt him, Isaac said: "The voice indeed is the voice of Jacob. But the hands are the hands of Esau."

23 And he did not recognize him, because his hairy hands made him seem similar to the elder one. Therefore, blessing him,

24 he said, "Are you my son Esau?" He answered, "I am."

25 Then he said, "Bring me the foods from your hunting, my son, so that my soul may bless you." And when he had eaten what was offered, he also brought forth wine for him. And after he finished it,

26 he said to him, "Come to me and give me a kiss, my son."

27 He approached and kissed him. And immediately he perceived the fragrance of his garments. And so, blessing him, he said: "Behold, the smell of my son is like the smell of a plentiful field, which the Lord has blessed.

28 May God give to you, from the dew of heaven and from the fatness of the earth, an abundance of grain and wine.

29 And may the peoples serve you, and may the tribes reverence you. May you be the lord of your brothers, and may your mother's sons bow down before you. Whoever curses you, may he be cursed, and whoever blesses you, may he be filled with blessings."

30 Scarcely had Isaac completed his words, and Jacob departed, when Esau arrived.

31 And he brought his father foods cooked from his hunting, saying, "Arise, my father, and eat from your son's hunting, so that your soul may bless me."

32 And Isaac said to him, "But who are you?" And he answered, "I am your firstborn son, Esau."

33 Isaac became frightened and very astonished. And wondering beyond what can be believed, he said: "Then who is he that a while ago brought me the prey from his hunting, from which I ate, before you arrived? And I blessed him, and he will be blessed."

34 Esau, having heard his father's words, roared out with a great outcry. And, being confounded, he said, "But bless me also, my father."

35 And he said, "Your twin came deceitfully, and he received your blessing."

36 But he responded: "Justly is his name called Jacob. For he has supplanted me yet another time. My birthright he took away before, and now, this second time, he has stolen my blessing." And again, he said to his father, "Have you not reserved a blessing for me also?"

37 Isaac answered: "I have appointed him as your lord, and I have subjugated all his brothers as his servants. I have reinforced him with grain and wine, and after this, my son, what more shall I do for you?"

38 And Esau said to him: "Have you only one blessing, father? I beg you, bless me also." And when he wept with a loud wail,

39 Isaac was moved, and he said to him: "In the fatness of the earth, and in the dew of heaven from above,

40 will your blessing be. You will live by the sword, and you will serve your brother. But the time will arrive when you will shake off and release his yoke from your neck."

41 Therefore, Esau always hated Jacob, for the blessing with which his father had blessed him. And he said in his heart, "The days will arrive for the mourning of my father, and I will kill my brother Jacob."

42 These things were reported to Rebekah. And sending and calling for her son Jacob, she said to him, "Behold, your brother Esau is threatening to kill you.

43 Therefore, now my son, listen to my voice. Rise up and flee to my brother Laban, in Haran.

44 And you will dwell with him for a few days, until the fury of your brother subsides,

45 and his indignation ceases, and he forgets the things that you have done to him. After this, I will send for you and bring you from there to here. Why should I be bereaved of both my sons in one day?"

46 And Rebekah said to Isaac, "I am weary of my life because of the daughters of Heth. If Jacob accepts a wife from the stock of this land, I would not be willing to live."

Genesis 28

1 And so Isaac called for Jacob, and he blessed him, and he instructed him, saying: "Do not be willing to accept a mate from the family of Canaan.

2 But go, and journey to Mesopotamia of Syria, to the house of Bethuel, your mother's father, and there accept for yourself a wife from the daughters of Laban, your maternal uncle.

3 And may God almighty bless you, and may he cause you to increase and also to multiply, so that you may be influential among the people.

4 And may he give the blessings of Abraham to you, and to your offspring after you, so that you may possess the land of your sojourning, which he promised to your grandfather."

5 And when Isaac had dismissed him, setting out, he went to Mesopotamia of Syria, to Laban, the son of Bethuel, the Syrian, the brother to Rebekah, his mother.

6 But Esau, seeing that his father had blessed Jacob and had sent him into Mesopotamia of Syria, to take a wife from there, and that, after the blessing, he had instructed him, saying: 'You shall not accept a wife from the daughters of Canaan,'

7 and that Jacob, obeying his parents, had gone into Syria,

8 having evidence also that his father did not look with favor upon the daughters of Canaan,

9 he went to Ishmael, and he took as a wife, beside those he had before, Mahalath, the daughter of Ishmael, Abraham's son, the sister of Nebaioth.

10 Meanwhile Jacob, having departed from Beersheba, continued on to Haran.

11 And when he had arrived at a certain place, where he would rest after the setting of the sun, he took some of the stones that lay there, and placing them under his head, he slept in the same place.

12 And he saw in his sleep: a ladder standing upon the earth, with its top touching heaven, also, the Angels of God ascending and descending by it,

13 and the Lord, leaning upon the ladder, saying to him: "I am the Lord, the God of Abraham your father, and the God of Isaac. The land, in which you sleep, I will give to you and to your offspring.

14 And your offspring will be like the dust of the earth. You will spread abroad to the West, and to the East, and to the North, and to the Meridian. And in you and in your offspring, all the tribes of the earth shall be blessed.

15 And I will be your guardian wherever you will journey, and I will bring you back into this land. Neither will I dismiss you, until I have accomplished all that I have said."

16 And when Jacob had awakened from sleep, he said, "Truly, the Lord is in this place, and I did not know it."

17 And being terrified, he said: "How terrible this place is! This is nothing other than the house of God and the gateway of heaven."

18 Therefore, Jacob, arising in the morning, took the stone which he had placed under his head, and he set it up as monument, pouring oil over it.

19 And he called the name of the city, 'Bethel,' which before was called Luz.

20 And then he made a vow, saying: "If God will be with me, and will guard me along the way by which I walk, and will give me bread to eat and clothing to wear,

21 and if I will return prosperously to my father's house, then the Lord will be my God,

22 and this stone, which I have set up as a monument, will be called 'the House of God.' And from all the things that you will give to me, I will offer tithes to you."

Genesis 29

1 And so Jacob, setting out, arrived in the eastern land.

2 And he saw a well in a field, and also three flocks of sheep reclining near it. For the animals were watered from it, and its mouth was closed with a great stone.

3 And the custom was, when all the sheep were gathered together, to roll away the stone. And when the flocks had been refreshed, they placed it over the mouth of the well again.

4 And he said to the shepherds, "Brothers, where are you from?" And they answered. "From Haran."

5 And questioning them, he said, "Do you know Laban, the son of Nahor?" They said, "We know him."

6 He said, "Is he well?" "He is very well," they said. "And behold, his daughter Rachel approaches with his flock."

7 And Jacob said, "There is still much daylight remaining, and it is not time to return the flocks to the sheepfold. Give the sheep to drink first, and then lead them back to pasture."

8 They responded, "We cannot, until all the animals are gathered together and we remove the stone from the mouth of the well, so that we may water the flocks."

9 They were still speaking, and behold, Rachel arrived with her father's sheep; for she pastured the flock.

10 When Jacob had seen her, and he realized that she was his maternal first cousin, and that these were the sheep of his uncle Laban, he removed the stone which closed the well.

11 And having watered the flock, he kissed her. And lifting up his voice, he wept.

12 And he revealed to her that he was a brother of her father, and the son of Rebekah. And so, hurrying, she announced it to her father.

13 And when he had heard that Jacob, his sister's son, had arrived, he ran to meet him. And embracing him, and kissing him heartily, he brought him into his house. But when he had heard the reasons for his journey,

14 he responded, "You are my bone and my flesh." And after the days of one month were completed,

15 he said to him: "Though you are my brother, will you serve me for nothing? Tell me what wages you would accept."

16 In truth, he had two daughters: the name of the elder was Leah; and truly the younger was called Rachel.

17 But while Leah was bleary-eyed, Rachel had an elegant appearance and was attractive to behold.

18 And Jacob, loving her, said, "I will serve you for seven years, for your younger daughter Rachel."

19 Laban responded, "It is better that I give her to you than to another man; remain with me."

20 Therefore, Jacob served for seven years for Rachel. And these seemed like only a few days, because of the greatness of love.

21 And he said to Laban, "Give my wife to me. For now the time has been fulfilled, so that I may go in to her."

22 And he, having called a great crowd of his friends to the feast, agreed to the marriage.

23 And at night, he brought in his daughter Leah to him,

24 giving his daughter a handmaid named Zilpah. After Jacob had gone in to her, according to custom, when morning had arrived, he saw Leah.

25 And he said to his father-in-law, "What is it that you intended to do? Did I not serve you for Rachel? Why have you deceived me?"

26 Laban responded, "It is not the practice in this place to give the younger in marriage first.

27 Complete a week of days with this mating. And then I will give this one to you also, for the service that you will provide to me for another seven years."

28 He agreed to his pleading. And after the week had passed, he took Rachel as a wife.

29 To her, the father had given Bilhah as her servant.

30 And, having at last obtained the marriage he desired, he preferred the love of the latter before the former, and he served with him another seven years.

31 But the Lord, seeing that he despised Leah, opened her womb, but her sister remained barren.

32 Having conceived, she gave birth to a son, and she called his name Reuben, saying: "The Lord saw my humiliation; now my husband will love me."

33 And again she conceived and bore a son, and she said, "Because the Lord heard that I was treated with contempt, he has also given this one to me." And she called his name Simeon.

34 And she conceived a third time, and she gave birth to another son, and she said: "Now likewise my husband will unite with me, because I have borne him three sons." And because of this, she called his name Levi.

35 A fourth time she conceived and bore a son, and she said, "Only now will I confess to the Lord." And for this reason, she called him Judah. And she ceased from child-bearing.

Genesis 30

1 Then Rachel, discerning that she was infertile, envied her sister, and so she said to her husband, "Give me children, otherwise I will die."

2 Jacob, being angry, responded to her, "Am I in the place of God, who has deprived you of the fruit of your womb?"

3 But she said: "I have a handmaid Bilhah. Go in to her, so that she may give birth upon my knees, and I may have sons by her."

4 And she gave him Bilhah in marriage.

5 And when her husband had gone in to her, she conceived and bore a son.

6 And Rachel said, "The Lord has judged for me, and he has heeded my voice, giving me a son." And because of this, she called his name Dan.

7 And conceiving again, Bilhah bore another,

8 about whom Rachel said, "God has compared me with my sister, and I have prevailed." And she called him Naphtali.

9 Leah, perceiving that she had desisted from child-bearing, delivered Zilpah, her handmaid, to her husband.

10 And she, after having borne a son with difficulty,

11 said: "Happiness!" And for this reason, she called his name Gad.

12 Likewise, Zilpah bore another.

13 And Leah said, "This one is for my happiness. Indeed, women will call me blessed." Because of this, she called him Asher.

14 Then Reuben, going out into the field at the time of the wheat harvest, found mandrakes. These he brought to his mother Leah. And Rachel said, "Give me a portion of your son's mandrakes."

15 She responded, "Does it seem like such a small matter to you, that you have usurped from me my husband, unless you will also take my son's mandrakes?" Rachel said, "He will sleep with you this night because of your son's mandrakes."

16 And when Jacob returned from the field in the evening, Leah went out to meet him, and she said, "You will enter to me, because I have hired you for the reward of my son's mandrakes." And he slept with her that night.

17 And God heard her prayers. And she conceived and bore a fifth son.

18 And she said, "God has given a reward to me, because I gave my handmaid to my husband." And she called his name Issachar.

19 Conceiving again, Leah bore a sixth son.

20 And she said: "God has endowed me with a good dowry. And now, at this turn, my husband will be with me, because I have conceived six sons for him." And therefore she called his name Zebulun.

21 After him, she bore a daughter, named Dinah.

22 The Lord, likewise remembering Rachel, heeded her and opened her womb.

23 And she conceived and bore a son, saying, "God has taken away my reproach."

24 And she called his name Joseph, saying, "The Lord has added to me another son."

25 But when Joseph was born, Jacob said to his father-in-law: "Release me, so that I may return to my native country and to my land.

26 Give me my wives, and my children, for whom I have served you, so that I may depart. You know the servitude with which I have served you."

27 Laban said to him: "May I find grace in your sight. I have learned by experience that God has blessed me because of you.

28 Choose your wages, which I will give you."

29 But he responded: "You know how I have served you, and how great your possession became in my hands.

30 You had little before I came to you, and now you have achieved riches. And the Lord has blessed you since my arrival. It is just, therefore, that at sometime I also should provide for my own house."

31 And Laban said, "What shall I give to you?" But he said, "I want nothing. But if you will do what I ask, I will feed and guard your sheep again.

32 Go around through all your flocks and separate all the sheep of variegated or spotted fleece; and whatever will be darkened or blemished or variegated, as much among the sheep as among the goats, will be my wages.

33 And my justice will answer on my behalf tomorrow, when the time of settlement arrives before you. And all that is not variegated or blemished or darkened, as much among the sheep as among the goats, these will prove me to be a thief."

34 And Laban said, "I hold favor for this request."

35 And on that day he separated the she-goats, and the sheep, and the he-goats, and the rams with variegations or with blemishes. But every one of the flock which was of one color, that is, of white or of black fleece, he delivered into the hands of his sons.

36 And he established a distance of three days journey between himself and his son-in-law, who pastured the remainder of his flock.

37 Then Jacob, taking green branches of poplar, and almond, and sycamore trees, debarked them in part. And when the bark was pulled off, in the parts that were stripped, there appeared whiteness, yet the parts that were left whole, remained green. And so, in this way the color was made variegated.

38 And he placed them in the troughs, where the water was poured out, so that when the flocks had arrived to drink, they would have the branches before their eyes, and in their sight they might conceive.

39 And it happened that, in the very heat of joining together, the sheep looked upon the branches, and they bore the blemished and the variegated, those speckled with diverse color.

40 And Jacob divided the flock, and he set the branches in the troughs before the eyes of the rams. Now whatever was white or black belonged to Laban, but, in truth, the others belonged to Jacob, for the flocks were dispersed among one another.

41 Therefore, when the first to arrive were climbing on the ewes, Jacob placed the branches in the troughs of water before the eyes of the rams and the sheep, so that they might conceive while they were gazing upon them.

42 Yet when the late arrivals and the last to conceive were let in, he did not place these. And so those that arrived late became Laban's, and those that arrived first became Jacob's.

43 And the man was enriched beyond limit, and he had many flocks, women servants and men servants, camels and donkeys.

Genesis 31

1 But afterwards, he heard the words of the sons of Laban, saying, "Jacob has taken all that was our father's, and being enlarged by his ability, he has become famous."

2 Likewise, he observed that Laban's face was not the same toward him as it was yesterday and the day before.

3 Most importantly, the Lord was saying to him, "Return to the land of your fathers and to your generation, and I will be with you."

4 He sent and called for Rachel and Leah, in the field where he pastured the flocks,

5 and he said to them: "I see that your father's face is not the same toward me as it was yesterday and the day before. But the God of my father has been with me.

6 And you know that I have served your father with all my strength.

7 Even so, your father has circumvented me, and he has changed my wages ten times. And yet God has not permitted him to harm me.

8 Whenever he said, 'The speckled will be your wages,' all the sheep gave birth to speckled newborns. Yet truly, when he said the contrary, 'You will take whatever is white for your wages,' all the flocks gave birth to white ones.

9 And it is God who has taken your father's substance and given it to me.

10 For after the time had arrived for the ewes to conceive, I lifted up my eyes, and I saw in my sleep that the males climbing on the females were of variegated, and spotted, and diverse colors.

11 And the Angel of God said to me in my sleep, 'Jacob.' And I responded, 'Here I am.'

12 And he said: 'Lift up your eyes, and see that all the males climbing on the females are variegated, spotted, and also speckled. For I have seen all that Laban has done to you.

13 I am the God of Bethel, where you anointed the stone and made a vow to me. Now therefore arise, and depart from this land, returning to the land of your nativity.' "

14 And Rachel and Leah responded: "Have we anything left behind among the resources and inheritance of our father's house?

15 Has he not considered us as foreigners, and sold us, and consumed our price?

16 But God has taken our father's riches and handed these to us and to our sons. Therefore, do all that God has instructed you."

17 And so Jacob rose up, and having placed the children and his wives upon camels, he went forth.

18 And he took all his substance and flocks, and whatever he had acquired in Mesopotamia, and he journeyed to his father Isaac, in the land of Canaan.

19 At that time, Laban had gone to shear the sheep, and so Rachel stole her father's idols.

20 And Jacob was not willing to confess to his father-in-law that he was fleeing.

21 And when he had gone away with all such things that were justly his, and, having crossed the river, was continuing on toward Mount Gilead,

22 it was reported to Laban on the third day that Jacob had fled.

23 And taking his brothers with him, he pursued him for seven days. And he overtook him at Mount Gilead.

24 And he saw in a dream, God saying to him, "Beware that you not speak anything harsh against Jacob."

25 And now Jacob had pitched his tent at the mountain. And when he, with his brothers, had overtaken him, he set his tent at the same place at Mount Gilead.

26 And he said to Jacob: "Why have you acted this way, departing from me in secret, with my daughters like captives of the sword?

27 Why would you want to flee without my knowledge and without telling me, though I might have led you forward with gladness, and songs, and timbrels, and lyres?

28 You have not permitted me to kiss my sons and daughters. You have acted foolishly. And now, indeed,

29 my hand has power to repay you with harm. But the God of your father said to me yesterday, 'Beware that you not speak anything stern against Jacob.'

30 It may be that you desired to go to your own, and that you longed for the house of your father. But why have you stolen my gods?"

31 Jacob answered: "I set out, unknown to you, because I feared that you might take away your daughters by violence.

32 But, since you accuse me of theft, with whomever you will find your gods, let him be slain in the sight of our brothers. Search; anything of yours that you will find with me, take it away." Now when he said this, he did not know that Rachel had stolen the idols.

33 And so Laban, entering the tent of Jacob, and of Leah, and of both the handmaids, did not find them. And when he had entered the tent of Rachel,

34 she quickly hid the idols under the camel's bedding, and she sat upon them. And when he had searched the entire tent and found nothing,

35 she said: "Do not be angry, my lord, that I am unable to rise up in your sight, because it has now happened to me according to the custom of women." So his careful search was thwarted.

36 And Jacob, being inflated, said with contention: "For which fault of mine, or for what sin of mine, have you become so enraged against me

37 and searched all the items of my house? What have you found from all the substance of your house? Place it here before my brothers, and your brothers, and let them judge between me and you.

38 For what reason have I been with you for twenty years? Your ewes and she-goats were not barren; the rams of your flocks I did not consume.

39 Neither did I reveal to you what was seized by the wild beast. I replaced all that was damaged. Whatever was lost by theft, you collected it from me.

40 Day and night, I was burned by heat and by frost, and sleep fled from my eyes.

41 And in this way, for twenty years, I have served you in your house: fourteen for your daughters, and six for your flocks. You have also changed my wages ten times.

42 If the God of my father Abraham and the fear of Isaac had not been close to me, perhaps by now you would have sent me away naked. But God looked kindly on my affliction and the labor of my hands, and he rebuked you yesterday."

43 Laban answered him: "My daughters and sons, and your flocks, and all that you discern are mine. What can I do to my sons and grandchildren?

44 Come, therefore, let us enter into a pact, so that it may be a testimony between me and you."

45 And so Jacob took a stone, and he set it up as a memorial.

46 And he said to his brothers, "Bring stones." And they, gathering together stones, made a tomb, and they ate upon it.

47 And Laban called it, 'Tomb of Witness,' and Jacob, 'Pile of Testimony;' each of them according to the fitness of his own language.

48 And Laban said: "This tomb will be a witness between me and you this day." (And for this reason, its name has been called Gilead, that is, 'Tomb of Witness.')

49 "May the Lord consider and judge between us, when we will have withdrawn from one another.

50 If you afflict my daughters, and if you bring in other wives over them, no one is a witness of our words except God, who understands beforehand."

51 And again he said to Jacob. "Lo, this tomb and the stone that I have set up between me and you,

52 will be a witness. This tomb," I say, "and the stone, they are for testimony, in case either I cross beyond it going toward you, or you cross beyond it thinking to harm me.

53 May the God of Abraham, and the God of Nahor, the God of their father, judge between us." Therefore, Jacob swore by the fear of his father Isaac.

54 And after he had immolated sacrifices on the mountain, he called his brothers to eat bread. And when they had eaten, they lodged there.

55 In truth, Laban rose up in the night, and he kissed his sons and daughters, and he blessed them. And he returned to his place.

Genesis 32

1 Likewise, Jacob continued on the journey that he had begun. And the Angels of God met him.

2 When he had seen them, he said, "These are the Encampments of God." And he called the name of that place Mahanaim, that is, 'Encampments.'

3 Then he also sent messengers before him to his brother Esau, in the land of Seir, in the region of Edom.

4 And he instructed them, saying: "You shall speak in this way to my lord Esau: 'Your brother Jacob says these things: "I have sojourned with Laban, and I have been with him until the present day.

5 I have oxen, and donkeys, and sheep, and men servants, and women servants. And now I send an ambassador to my lord, so that I may find favor in your sight." ' "

6 And the messengers returned to Jacob, saying, "We went to your brother Esau, and behold, he rushes to meet you with four hundred men."

7 Jacob was very afraid. And in his terror, he divided the people who were with him, likewise the flocks, and the sheep, and the oxen, and the camels, into two companies,

8 saying: "If Esau goes to one company, and strikes it, the other company, which is left behind, will be saved."

9 And Jacob said: "God of my father Abraham, and God of my father Isaac, O Lord who said to me: 'Return to your land, and to the place of your nativity, and I will do well for you.'

10 I am less than any of your compassions and your truth, which you have fulfilled to your servant. With my staff I crossed over this Jordan. And now I go back with two companies.

11 Rescue me from the hand of my brother Esau, for I am very afraid of him, lest perhaps he may come and strike down the mother with the sons.

12 You did say that you would do well by me, and that you would expand my offspring like the sand of the sea, which, because of its multitude, cannot be numbered."

13 And when he had slept there that night, he separated, from the things that he had, gifts for his brother Esau:

14 two hundred she-goats, twenty he-goats, two hundred ewes, and twenty rams,

15 thirty milking camels with their young, forty cows, and twenty bulls, twenty she-donkeys, and ten of their young.

16 And he sent them by the hands of his servants, each flock separately, and he said to his servants: "Pass before me, and let there be a space between flock and flock."

17 And he instructed the first, saying: "If you happen to meet my brother Esau, and he questions you: "Whose are you?" or, "Where are you going?" or, "Whose are these which follow you?"

18 you shall respond: "Your servant Jacob's. He has sent them as a gift to my lord Esau. And he is also coming after us."

19 Similarly, he gave orders to the second, and the third, and to all who followed the flocks, saying: "Speak these same words to Esau, when you find him.

20 And you will add: 'Your servant Jacob himself also follows after us, for he said: "I will appease him with the gifts that go ahead, and after this, I will see him; perhaps he will be gracious to me." ' "

21 And so the gifts went before him, but he himself lodged that night in the camp.

22 And when he had arisen early, he took his two wives, and the same number of handmaids, with his eleven sons, and he crossed over the ford of Jabbok.

23 And having delivered over all the things that belonged to him,

24 he remained alone. And behold, a man wrestled with him until morning.

25 And when he saw that he would not be able to overcome him, he touched the nerve of his thigh, and immediately it withered.

26 And he said to him, "Release me, for now the dawn ascends." He responded, "I will not release you, unless you bless me."

27 Therefore he said, "What is your name?" He answered, "Jacob."

28 But he said, "Your name will not be called Jacob, but Israel; for if you have been strong against God, how much more will you prevail against men?"

29 Jacob questioned him, "Tell me, by what name are you called?" He responded, "Why do you ask my name?" And he blessed him in the same place.

30 And Jacob called the name of the place Peniel, saying, "I have seen God face to face, and my soul has been saved."

31 And immediately the sun rose upon him, after he had crossed beyond Peniel. Yet in truth, he limped on his foot.

32 For this reason, the sons of Israel, even to the present day, do not eat the nerve that withered in Jacob's thigh, because he touched the nerve of his thigh and it was obstructed.

Genesis 33

1 Then Jacob, lifting up his eyes, saw Esau arriving, and with him four hundred men. And he divided the sons of Leah and Rachel, and of both the handmaids.

2 And he placed the two handmaids and their children at the beginning. Truly, Leah and her sons were in the second place. Then Rachel and Joseph were last.

3 And advancing, he reverenced prostrate on the ground seven times, until his brother approached.

4 And so Esau ran to meet his brother, and he embraced him. And drawing him by his neck and kissing him, he wept.

5 And lifting up his eyes, he saw the women and their little ones, and he said: "What do these want for themselves?" and "Are they related to you?" He responded, "These are the little ones that God has given as a gift to me, your servant."

6 Then the handmaids and their sons approached and bowed down.

7 Likewise Leah, with her sons, came near. And when they had reverenced similarly, last of all, Joseph and Rachel reverenced.

8 And Esau said, "What are these companies that I have been meeting?" He responded, "So may I find favor before my lord."

9 But he said, "I have plenty, my brother; let these be for yourself."

10 And Jacob said: "I beg you, let it not be so. But if I have found favor in your eyes, receive a small present from my hands. For I have looked upon your face as I would look upon the countenance of God. Be gracious to me,

11 and take the blessing which I have brought to you, and which God, who bestows all things, has given as a gift to me." Accepting it reluctantly, at the insistence of his brother,

12 he said, "Let us go on together, and I will accompany you on your journey."

13 And Jacob said: "My lord, you know that I have with me tender little ones, and sheep, and cows with young. If I cause these to labor too much in walking, all the flocks will die in one day.

14 May it please my lord to go before his servant. And I will follow gradually in his steps, as much as I see my little ones to be able, until I arrive to my lord in Seir."

15 Esau responded, "I beg you, that at least some of the people who are with me may remain to accompany you on the way." But he said, "There is no need. I have need of one thing only: to find favor in your sight, my lord."

16 And so Esau returned that day, by the way that he had arrived, to Seir.

17 And Jacob went to Succoth, where, having built a house and pitched tents, he called the name of that place Succoth, that is, 'Tents.'

18 And he crossed over to Salem, a city of the Shechemites, which is in the land of Canaan, after he returned from Mesopotamia of Syria. And he lived near the town.

19 And he bought the part of the field in which he had pitched his tents from the sons of Hamor, the father of Shechem, for one hundred lambs.

20 And erecting an altar there, he invoked upon it the most strong God of Israel.

Genesis 34

1 Then Dinah, the daughter of Leah, went out to see the women of that region.

2 And when Shechem, the son of Hamor the Hivite, the leader of that land, had seen her, he fell in love with her. And so he seized her and slept with her, overwhelming the virgin by force.

3 And his soul was closely bound to her, and, since she was sorrowful, he soothed her with flattery.

4 And going on to Hamor, his father, he said, "Obtain this girl for me as a mate."

5 But when Jacob had heard this, since his sons were absent and he was occupied in pasturing the cattle, he remained silent until they came back.

6 Then, when Hamor, the father of Shechem, had gone out to speak to Jacob,

7 behold, his sons arrived from the field. And hearing what had happened, they were very angry, because he had done a filthy thing in Israel and, in violating a daughter of Jacob, had perpetrated an unlawful act.

8 And so Hamor spoke to them: "The soul of my son Shechem has become attached to your daughter. Give her to him as a wife.

9 And let us celebrate marriages with one with another. Give us your daughters, and receive our daughters.

10 And live with us. The land is in your power: cultivate, trade, and possess it."

11 And Shechem even said to her father and to her brothers: "May I find favor in your sight, and whatever you will appoint, I will give.

12 Increase the dowry, and request gifts, and I will freely bestow what you will ask. Only give me this girl as a wife."

13 The sons of Jacob answered Shechem and his father with deceit, being enraged at the rape of their sister:

14 "We are not able to do what you ask, nor to give our sister to an uncircumcised man. For us, this is unlawful and abominable.

15 But we may succeed in this, so as to be allied with you, if you are willing to become like us, and if all the male sex among you will be circumcised.

16 Then we will mutually give and receive your daughters as well as ours; and we will live with you, and we will become one people.

17 But if you will not be circumcised, we will take our daughter and withdraw."

18 Their offer pleased Hamor and his son Shechem.

19 Neither did the young man cause any delay; in fact he immediately fulfilled what was requested. For he loved the girl very much, and he was well-known throughout his father's house.

20 And entering at the gate of the city, they spoke to the people:

21 "These men are peaceful, and they want to live among us. Let them trade in the land and cultivate it, for, being spacious and broad, it is in need of cultivation. We will receive their daughters as wives, and we will give them ours.

22 There is one thing that prevents so great a good: whether we will circumcise our males, imitating the ritual of their nation.

23 And their substance, and cattle, and all that they possess, will be ours, if only we will acquiesce to this, and so, in living together, will form one people."

24 And they all agreed to circumcise every one of the males.

25 And behold, on the third day, when the pain of the wound was greatest, two of the sons of Jacob, Simeon and Levi, the brothers of Dinah, boldly entered the city with swords. And they put to death all of the males.

26 They killed Hamor and Shechem together, taking their sister Dinah from the house of Shechem.

27 And when they had departed, the other sons of Jacob rushed over the slain, and they plundered the city in vengeance for the rape.

28 Taking their sheep, and herds, and donkeys, and laying waste to everything else that was in their houses and in their fields,

29 they also took their little ones and their wives captive.

30 When they had boldly completed these acts, Jacob said to Simeon and Levi: "You have troubled me, and you have made me hateful to the Canaanites and the Perizzites, the inhabitants of this land. We are few. They, gathering themselves together, may strike me down, and then both I and my house will be wiped away."

31 They responded, "Should they abuse our sister like a prostitute?"

Genesis 35

1 About this time, God said to Jacob, "Arise and go up to Bethel, and live there, and make an altar to God, who appeared to you when you fled from your brother Esau."

2 In truth, Jacob, having called together all his house, said: "Cast away the foreign gods that are in your midst and be cleansed, and also change your garments.

3 Arise, and let us go up to Bethel, so that we may make an altar there to God, who heeded me in the day of my tribulation, and who accompanied me on my journey."

4 Therefore, they gave him all the foreign gods which they had, and the earrings which were in their ears. And then he buried them under the terebinth tree, which is beyond the city of Shechem.

5 And when they had set out, the terror of God invaded all the surrounding cities, and they dared not pursue them as they withdrew.

6 And so, Jacob arrived at Luz, which is in the land of Canaan, also named Bethel: he and all the people with him.

7 And he built an altar there, and he called the name of that place, 'House of God.' For there God appeared to him when he fled from his brother.

8 About the same time, Deborah, the nurse of Rebekah, died, and she was buried at the base of Bethel, under an oak tree. And the name of that place was called, 'Oak of Weeping.'

9 Then God appeared again to Jacob, after he returned from Mesopotamia of Syria, and he blessed him,

10 saying: "You will no longer be called Jacob, for your name shall be Israel." And he called him Israel,

11 and he said to him: "I am Almighty God: increase and multiply. Tribes and peoples of nations will be from you, and kings will go forth from your loins.

12 And the land that I gave to Abraham and Isaac, I will give to you, and to your offspring after you."

13 And he withdrew from him.

14 In truth, he set up a monument of stone, in the place where God had spoken to him, pouring out libations over it, and pouring oil,

15 and he called the name of that place, 'Bethel.'

16 Then, departing from there, he arrived in springtime at the land that leads to Ephrath. And there, when Rachel was giving birth,

17 because it was a difficult birth, she began to be in danger. And the midwife said to her, "Do not be afraid, for you will have this son also."

18 Then, when her life was departing because of the pain, and death was now imminent, she called the name of her son Benoni, that is, the son of my pain. Yet truly, his father called him Benjamin, that is, the son of the right hand.

19 And so Rachel died, and she was buried in the way that leads to Ephrath: this place is Bethlehem.

20 And Jacob erected a monument over her sepulcher. This is the monument to Rachel's tomb, even to the present day.

21 Departing from there, he pitched his tent beyond the Tower of the Flock.

22 And when he was living in that region, Reuben went out, and he slept with Bilhah the concubine of his father, which was not such a small matter as to be hidden from him. Now the sons of Jacob were twelve.

23 The sons of Leah: Reuben the first born, and Simeon, and Levi, and Judah, and Issachar, and Zebulun.

24 The sons of Rachel: Joseph and Benjamin.

25 The sons of Bilhah, handmaid of Rachel: Dan and Naphtali.

26 The sons of Zilpah, handmaid of Leah: Gad and Asher. These are the sons of Jacob, who were born to him in Mesopotamia of Syria.

27 And then he went to his father Isaac in Mamre, the city of Arba: this place is Hebron, where Abraham and Isaac sojourned.

28 And the days of Isaac were completed: one hundred and eighty years.

29 And being consumed by old age, he died. And he was placed with his people, being old and full of days. And his sons, Esau and Jacob, buried him.

Genesis 36

1 Now these are the generations of Esau, who is Edom.

2 Esau took wives from the daughters of Canaan: Adah the daughter of Elon the Hittite, and Oholibamah the daughter of Anah, the daughter of Zibeon the Hivite,

3 and Basemath, the daughter of Ishmael, sister of Nebaioth.

4 Then Adah bore Eliphaz. Basemath conceived Reuel.

5 Oholibamah conceived Jeush, and Jalam, and Korah. These are the sons of Esau, who were born to him in the land of Canaan.

6 Then Esau took his wives, and sons, and daughters, and every soul of his house, and his substance, and cattle, and whatever he was able to obtain in the land of Canaan, and he went into another region, withdrawing from his brother Jacob.

7 For they were very wealthy and were not able to live together. Neither was the land of their sojourn able to sustain them, because of the multitude of their flocks.

8 And Esau lived at mount Seir: he is Edom.

9 So these are the generations of Esau, the father of Edom, at mount Seir,

10 and these are the names of his sons: Eliphaz the son of Adah, the wife of Esau, likewise Reuel, the son of Basemath, his wife.

11 And Eliphaz had sons: Teman, Omar, Zepho, and Gatam, and Kenez.

12 Now Timna was the concubine of Eliphaz, the son of Esau. And she bore him Amalek. These are the sons of Adah, the wife of Esau.

13 And the sons of Reuel were Nahath and Zerah, Shammah and Mizzah. These are the sons of Basemath, the wife of Esau.

14 Likewise, these were the sons of Oholibamah, the daughter of Anah, the daughter of Zibeon, the wife of Esau, whom she bore to him: Jeush, and Jalam, and Korah.

15 These were leaders of the sons of Esau, the sons of Eliphaz, the firstborn of Esau: leader Teman, leader Omar, leader Zepho, leader Kenez,

16 leader Korah, leader Gatam, leader Amalek. These are the sons of Eliphaz, in the land of Edom, and these the sons of Adah.

17 Likewise, these are the sons of Reuel, the son of Esau: leader Nahath, leader Zerah, leader Shammah, leader Mizzah. And these were the leaders of Reuel, in the land of Edom. These are the sons of Basemath, the wife of Esau.

18 Now these are the sons of Oholibamah, the wife of Esau: leader Jeush, leader Jalam, leader Korah. These were the leaders of Oholibamah, the daughter of Anah and the wife of Esau.

19 These are the sons of Esau, and these were their leaders: this is Edom.

20 These are the sons of Seir, the Horite, the inhabitants of the land: Lotan, and Shobal, and Zibeon, and Anah,

21 and Dishon, and Ezer, and Dishan. These were the leaders of the Horites, the sons of Seir, in the land of Edom.

22 Now Lotan produced sons: Hori and Heman. But the sister of Lotan was Timna.

23 And these are the sons of Shobal: Alvan, and Manahath, and Ebal, and Shepho, and Onam.

24 And these are the sons of Zibeon: Aiah and Anah. This is the Anah who found the hot springs in the wilderness, when he was pasturing the donkeys of his father Zibeon.

25 And he had a son Dishon, and a daughter Oholibamah.

26 And these are the sons of Dishon: Hemdan, and Esheban, and Ithran, and Cheran.

27 Likewise, these are the sons of Ezer: Bilhan, and Zaavan, and Akan.

28 Then Dishan had sons: Uz and Aran.

29 These were the leaders of the Horites: leader Lotan, leader Shobal, leader Zibeon, leader Anah,

30 leader Dishon, leader Ezer, leader Disan. These were leaders of the Horites who ruled in the land of Seir.

31 Now before the sons of Israel had a king, the kings who ruled in the land of Edom were these:

32 Bela the son of Beor, and the name of his city was Dinhabah.

33 Then Bela died, and Jobab, the son of Zerah from Bozrah, reigned in his place.

34 And when Jobab was dead, Husham of the land of the Temanites reigned in his place.

35 Likewise, this one having died, Hadad the son of Bedad reigned in his place. He struck down Midian in the region of Moab. And the name of his city was Avith.

36 And when Adad was dead, Samlah of Masrekah reigned in his place.

37 Likewise, this one being dead, Shaul of the river Rehoboth, reigned in his place.

38 And when he also had passed away, Baal-hanan, the son of Achbor, succeeded to the kingdom.

39 Likewise, this one being dead, Hadar reigned in his place; and the name of his city was Pau. And his wife was called Mehetabel, the daughter of Matred, daughter of Mezahab.

40 Therefore, these were the names of the leaders of Esau, by their families, and places, and in their vocabulary: leader Timna, leader Alvah, leader Jetheth,

41 leader Oholibamah, leader Elah, leader Pinon,

42 leader Kanez, leader Teman, leader Mibzar,

43 leader Magdiel, leader Iram. These were the leaders of Edom living in the land of their rule: this is Esau, the father of Idumea.

Genesis 37

1 Now Jacob lived in the land of Canaan, where his father sojourned.

2 And these are his generations. Joseph, when he was sixteen years old, was pasturing the flock with his brothers, when he was still a boy. And he was with the sons of Bilhah and Zilpah, the wives of his father. And he accused his brothers to their father of a most sinful crime.

3 Now Israel loved Joseph above all his sons, because he had conceived him in his old age. And he made him a tunic, woven of many colors.

4 Then his brothers, seeing that he was loved by his father more than all his other sons, hated him, and they were not able to say anything peacefully to him.

5 Then it also happened that he recounted the vision of a dream to his brothers, for which reason a greater hatred began to be nurtured.

6 And he said to them, "Listen to my dream that I saw.

7 I thought we were binding sheaves in the field. And my sheaf seemed to rise up and stand, and your sheaves, standing in a circle, reverenced my sheaf."

8 His brothers responded: "Would you be our king? Or will we be subject to your dominion?" Therefore, this matter of his dreams and words provided kindling to their envy and hatred.

9 Likewise, he saw another dream, which he explained to his brothers, saying, "I saw by a dream, as if the sun, and the moon, and eleven stars were reverencing me."

10 And when he had related this to his father and brothers, his father rebuked him, and he said: "What does it mean to you, this dream that you have seen? Should I, and your mother, and your brothers reverence you upon the earth?"

11 Therefore, his brothers were envious of him. Yet truly, his father considered the matter silently.

12 And while his brothers were lodging at Shechem, pasturing their father's flocks,

13 Israel said to him: "Your brothers are pasturing the sheep at Shechem. Come, I will send you to them." And when he answered,

14 "I am ready," he said to him, "Go, and see if everything is prospering with your brothers and the cattle, and report to me what is happening." So, having been sent from the valley of Hebron, he arrived at Shechem.

15 And a man found him wandering in a field, and he asked him what he was seeking.

16 So he responded: "I seek my brothers. Tell me where they pasture the flocks."

17 And the man said to him: "They have withdrawn from this place. But I heard them saying, 'Let us go to Dothan.' " Therefore, Joseph continued on after his brothers, and he found them at Dothan.

18 And, when they had seen him from afar, before he approached them, they decided to kill him.

19 And they said one to another: "Behold, the dreamer approaches.

20 Come, let us kill him and cast him into the old cistern. And let us say: 'an evil wild beast has devoured him.' And then it will become apparent what his dreams will do for him."

21 But Reuben, on hearing this, strove to free him from their hands, and he said:

22 "Do not take away his life, nor shed blood. But throw him into this cistern, which is in the wilderness, and so keep your hands harmless." But he said this, wanting to rescue him from their hands, so as to return him to his father.

23 And so, as soon as he came to his brothers, they very quickly stripped him of his tunic, which was ankle-length and woven of many colors,

24 and they cast him into an old cistern, which held no water.

25 And sitting down to eat bread, they saw some Ishmaelites, travelers coming from Gilead, with their camels, carrying spices, and resin, and oil of myrrh into Egypt.

26 Therefore, Judah said to his brothers: "What will it profit us, if we kill our brother and conceal his blood?

27 It is better that he be sold to the Ishmaelites, and then our hands will not be defiled. For he is our brother and our flesh." His brothers agreed to his words.

28 And when the Midianite merchants were passing by, they drew him from the cistern, and they sold him to the Ishmaelites for twenty pieces of silver. And these led him into Egypt.

29 And Reuben, returning to the cistern, did not find the boy.

30 And rending his garments, he went to his brothers and said, "The boy is not present, and so where shall I go?"

31 Then they took his tunic, and they dipped it in the blood of a young goat, which they had killed,

32 sending those who carried it to their father, and they said: "We found this. See whether it is the tunic of your son or not."

33 And when the father acknowledged it, he said: "It is the tunic of my son. An evil wild beast has eaten him; a beast has devoured Joseph."

34 And tearing his garments, he was clothed in haircloth, mourning his son for a long time.

35 Then, when all of his sons gathered together to ease their father's sorrow, he was not willing to accept consolation, but he said: "I will descend in mourning to my son in the underworld." And while he persevered in weeping,

36 the Midianites in Egypt sold Joseph to Potiphar, a eunuch of Pharaoh, instructor of the soldiers.

Genesis 38

1 About the same time, Judah, descending from his brothers, turned toward an Adullamite man, named Hirah.

2 And he saw there the daughter of a man called Shua, of Canaan. And taking her as a wife, he entered to her.

3 And she conceived and bore a son, and she called his name Er.

4 And conceiving offspring again, having given birth to a son, she called him Onan.

5 Likewise, she bore a third, whom she called Shelah, after whose birth, she ceased to bear any more.

6 Then Judah gave a wife to his first born Er, whose name was Tamar.

7 And it also happened that Er, the first born of Judah, was wicked in the sight of the Lord and was killed by him.

8 Therefore, Judah said to his son Onan: "Enter to the wife of your brother, and associate with her, so that you may raise offspring to your brother."

9 He, knowing that the sons to be born would not be his, when he entered to the wife of his brother, he spilled his seed on the ground, lest children should be born in his brother's name.

10 And for this reason, the Lord struck him down, because he did a detestable thing.

11 Because of this matter, Judah said to his daughter-in-law Tamar, "Be a widow in your father's house, until my son Shelah grows up." For he was afraid, lest he also might die, just as his brothers did. She went away, and she lived in her father's house.

12 Then, after many days had passed, the daughter of Shua, the wife of Judah, died. And when he accepted consolation after his mourning, he went up to the shearers of his sheep at Timnah, he and Hirah, the herdsman of the Adullamite flock.

13 And it was reported to Tamar that her father-in-law had gone up to Timnah to shear the sheep.

14 And storing away the garments of her widowhood, she took up a veil. And changing her clothing, she sat at the crossroad that leads to Timnah, because Shelah had grown up, and she had not received him as a husband.

15 And when Judah saw her, he thought her to be a harlot. For she had covered her face, lest she be recognized.

16 And entering to her, he said, "Permit me to join with you." For he did not know her to be his daughter-in-law. And she responded, "What will you give to me, to enjoy me as a concubine?"

17 He said, "I will send you a young goat from the flock." And again, she said, "I will allow what you want, if you give me a pledge, until you may send what you promise."

18 Judah said, "What do you want to be given for a pledge?" She responded, "Your ring and bracelet, and the staff that you hold in your hand." Thereupon, the woman, from one sexual encounter, conceived.

19 And she arose and went away. And storing away the garments that she had taken up, she was clothed in the garments of her widowhood.

20 Then Judah sent a young goat by his shepherd, the Adullamite, so that he might receive the pledge that he had given to the woman. But, when he had not found her,

21 he questioned the men of that place: "Where is the woman who sat at the crossroad?" And they all responded, "There has been no harlot in this place."

22 He returned to Judah, and he said to him: "I did not find her. Moreover, the men of that place told me that a prostitute had never sat there."

23 Judah said: "Let her hold herself to blame. Certainly, she is not able to accuse us of a lie. I sent the young goat that I had promised, and you did not find her."

24 And behold, after three months, they reported to Judah, saying, "Tamar, your daughter-in-law, has committed fornication and her abdomen appears to be enlarged." And Judah said, "Produce her, so that she may be burned."

25 But when she was led out to the punishment, she sent to her father-in-law, saying: "I conceived by the man to whom these things belong. Recognize whose ring, and bracelet, and staff this is."

26 But he, acknowledging the gifts, said: "She is more just than I am. For I did not deliver her to my son Shelah." However, he knew her no more.

27 Then, at the moment of birth, there appeared twins in the womb. And so, in the very delivery of the infants, one put forth a hand, on which the midwife tied a scarlet thread, saying,

28 "This one will go out first."

29 But in truth, drawing back his hand, the other came out. And the woman said, "Why is the partition divided for you?" And for this reason, she called his name Perez.

30 After this, his brother came out, on whose hand was the scarlet thread. And she called him Zerah.

Genesis 39

1 Meanwhile, Joseph was led into Egypt. And Putiphar, a eunuch of Pharaoh, a leader of the army, an Egyptian man, purchased him from the hand of the Ishmaelites, by whom he was brought.

2 And the Lord was with him, and he was a man who prospered in everything that he did. And he lived in the house of his lord,

3 who knew very well that the Lord was with him, and that all the things that were done by him were directed by his hand.

4 And Joseph found favor in the sight of his lord, and he ministered to him. And, having been placed in charge of everything by him, he governed the house that was entrusted to him and all the things that had been delivered to him.

5 And the Lord blessed the house of the Egyptian, because of Joseph, and he multiplied all his substance, as much in the buildings, as in the fields.

6 Neither did he know anything other than the bread that he ate. Now Joseph was beautiful in form, and stately in appearance.

7 And so, after many days, his mistress cast her eyes on Joseph, and she said, "Sleep with me."

8 And without consenting at all to the wicked act, he said to her: "Behold, my lord has delivered all things to me, and he does not know what he has in his own house.

9 Neither is there anything which is not in my power, or that he has not delivered to me, except you, for you are his wife. How then can I do this evil act and sin against my God?"

10 With such words as these, throughout each day, the woman was pestering the young man, and he was refusing the adultery.

11 Then it happened, on a certain day, that Joseph entered the house, and he was doing something, without any witnesses.

12 And she, grasping the hem of his garment, said, "Sleep with me." But he, leaving behind the cloak in her hand, fled and went outside.

13 And when the woman saw the garment in her hands and herself being treated with disrespect,

14 she called to herself the men of her house, and she said to them: "Lo, he has brought in a Hebrew man to abuse us. He entered toward me, in order to join with me; and when I had shouted out,

15 and he had heard my voice, he left behind the cloak that I held, and he fled outside."

16 As a proof, therefore, of her fidelity, she retained the cloak, and she showed it to her husband, when he returned home.

17 And she said: "The Hebrew servant, whom you have brought in to me, approached me to abuse me.

18 And when he had heard me cry out, he left behind the cloak that I held, and he fled outside."

19 His lord, upon hearing these things, and having excessive trust in the words of his mate, was very angry.

20 And he delivered Joseph into prison, where the prisoners of the king were kept, and he was enclosed in that place.

21 But the Lord was with Joseph, and, having mercy on him, he gave him favor in the sight of the leader of the prison,

22 who delivered into his hand all the prisoners who were held in custody. And whatever was done, was under him.

23 Neither did he himself know anything, having entrusted all things to him. For the Lord was with him, and he directed everything that he did.

Genesis 40

1 While these things were going on, it happened that two eunuchs, the cupbearer of the king of Egypt, and the miller of grain, offended their lord.

2 And Pharaoh, being angry with them, (now the one was in charge of the cupbearers, the other of the millers of grain)

3 sent them to the prison of the leader of the military, in which Joseph also was a prisoner.

4 But the keeper of the prison delivered them to Joseph, who ministered to them also. Some little time passed by, while they were held in custody.

5 And they both saw a similar dream on one night, whose interpretations should be related to one another.

6 And when Joseph had entered to them in the morning, and had seen them sad,

7 he consulted them, saying, "Why is your expression sadder today than usual?"

8 They responded, "We have seen a dream, and there is no one to interpret it for us." And Joseph said to them, "Doesn't interpretation belong to God? Recount for me what you have seen."

9 The chief cupbearer explained his dream first. "I saw before me a vine,

10 on which were three shoots, which grew little by little into buds, and, after the flowers, it matured into grapes.

11 And the cup of Pharaoh was in my hand. Therefore, I took the grapes, and I pressed them into the cup that I held, and I handed the cup to Pharaoh."

12 Joseph responded: "This is the interpretation of the dream. The three shoots are the next three days,

13 after which Pharaoh will remember your service, and he will restore you to your former position. And you will give him the cup according to your office, as you were accustomed to do before.

14 Only remember me, when it will be well with you, and do me this mercy, to suggest to Pharaoh to lead me out of this prison.

15 For I have been stolen from the land of the Hebrews, and here, innocently, I was cast into the pit."

16 The chief miller of grain, seeing that he had wisely unraveled the dream, said: "I also saw a dream: that I had three baskets of meal above my head,

17 and in one basket, which was the highest, I carried all foods that are made by the art of baking, and the birds ate from it."

18 Joseph responded: "This is the interpretation of the dream. The three baskets are the next three days,

19 after which Pharaoh will carry away your head, and also suspend you from a cross, and the birds will tear your flesh."

20 The third day thereafter was the birthday of Pharaoh. And making a great feast for his servants, he remembered, during the banquet, the chief cupbearer and the chief miller of grain.

21 And he restored the one to his place, to present him the cup;

22 the other he hanged on a gallows, and thus the truth of the interpreter of dreams was proven.

23 And although he advanced with so much prosperity, the chief cupbearer forgot his interpreter of dreams.

Genesis 41

1 After two years, Pharaoh saw a dream. He thought himself to be standing above a river,

2 from which ascended seven cows, exceedingly beautiful and stout. And they pastured in marshy places.

3 Likewise, another seven emerged from the river, filthy and thoroughly emaciated. And they pastured on the same bank of the river, in green places.

4 And they devoured those whose appearance and condition of body was so wonderful. Pharaoh, having been awakened,

5 slept again, and he saw another dream. Seven ears of grain sprung up on one stalk, full and well-formed.

6 Likewise, other ears of grain, of the same number, rose up, thin and struck with blight,

7 devouring all the beauty of the first. Pharaoh, when he awakened after his rest,

8 and when morning arrived, being terrified with fear, sent to all the interpreters of Egypt and to all of the wise men. And when they were summoned, he explained to them his dream; but there was no one who could interpret it.

9 Then at last the chief cupbearer, remembering, said, "I confess my sin.

10 The king, being angry with his servants, ordered me and the chief miller of grain to be forced into the prison of the leader of the military.

11 There, in one night, both of us saw a dream presaging the future.

12 In that place, there was a Hebrew, a servant of the same commander of the military, to whom we explained our dreams.

13 Whatever we heard was proven afterwards by the event of the matter. For I was restored to my office, and he was suspended on a cross."

14 Immediately, by the king's authority, Joseph was led out of prison, and they shaved him. And changing his apparel, they presented him to him.

15 And he said to him, "I have seen dreams, and there is no one who can unfold them. I have heard that you are very wise at interpreting these."

16 Joseph responded, "Apart from me, God will respond favorably to Pharaoh."

17 Therefore, Pharaoh explained what he had seen: "I thought myself to be standing on the bank of a river,

18 and seven cows climbed up from the river, exceedingly beautiful and full of flesh. And they grazed in a pasture of a marshy greenery.

19 And behold, there followed after these, another seven cows, with such deformity and emaciation as I had never seen in the land of Egypt.

20 These devoured and consumed the first,

21 giving no indication of being full. But they remained in the same state of emaciation and squalor. Awakening, but being weighed down into sleep again,

22 I saw a dream. Seven ears of grain sprang up on one stalk, full and very beautiful.

23 Likewise, another seven, thin and struck with blight, rose up from the stalk.

24 And they devoured the beauty of the first. I explained this dream to the interpreters, and there is no one who can unfold it."

25 Joseph responded: "The dream of the king is one. What God will do, he has revealed to Pharaoh.

26 The seven beautiful cows, and the seven full ears of grain, are seven years of abundance. And so the force of the dreams is understood to be the same.

27 Likewise, the seven thin and emaciated cows, which ascended after them, and the seven thin ears of grain, which were struck with the burning wind, are seven approaching years of famine.

28 These will be fulfilled in this order.

29 Behold, there will arrive seven years of great fertility throughout the entire land of Egypt.

30 After this, there will follow another seven years, of such great barrenness that all the former abundance will be delivered into oblivion. For the famine will consume all the land,

31 and the greatness of this destitution will cause the greatness of the abundance to be lost.

32 Now, as to what you saw the second time, it is a dream pertaining to the same thing. It is an indication of its firmness, because the word of God shall be done, and it shall be completed swiftly.

33 Now therefore, let the king provide a wise and industrious man, and place him over the land of Egypt,

34 so that he may appoint overseers throughout all the regions. And let a fifth part of the fruits, throughout the seven fertile years

35 that now have already begun to occur, be gathered into storehouses. And let all the grain be stored away, under the power of Pharaoh, and let it be kept in the cities.

36 And let it be prepared for the future famine of seven years, which will oppress Egypt, and then the land will not be consumed by destitution."

37 The counsel pleased Pharaoh and all his ministers.

38 And he said to them, "Would we be able to find another such man, who is full of the Spirit of God?"

39 Therefore, he said to Joseph: "Because God has revealed to you all that you have said, would I be able to find anyone wiser and as much like you?

40 You will be over my house, and to the authority of your mouth, all the people will show obedience. Only in one way, in the throne of the kingdom, will I go before you."

41 And again, Pharaoh said to Joseph, "Behold, I have appointed you over the entire land of Egypt."

42 And he took the ring from his own hand, and he gave it into his hand. And he clothed him with a robe of fine linen, and he placed a necklace of gold around his neck.

43 And he caused him to ascend upon his second swift chariot, with the herald proclaiming that everyone should bend their knee before him, and that they should know that he was governor over the entire land of Egypt.

44 Likewise, the king said to Joseph: "I am Pharaoh: apart from your authority, no one will move hand or foot in all the land of Egypt."

45 And he changed his name and called him, in the Egyptian tongue: 'Savior of the world.' And he gave him as a wife, Asenath, the daughter of Potiphera, priest of Heliopolis. And so Joseph went out into the land of Egypt.

46 (Now he was thirty years old when he stood in the sight of king Pharaoh.) And he traveled throughout the regions of Egypt.

47 And the fertility of the seven years arrived. And when the grain fields were reduced to sheaves, these were gathered into the storehouses of Egypt.

48 And now all the abundance of grain was stored away in every city.

49 And there was such a great abundance of wheat that it was comparable to the sands of the sea, and its bounty exceeded all measure.

50 Then, before the famine arrived, Joseph had two sons born, whom Asenath, the daughter of Potiphera, priest of Heliopolis, bore for him.

51 And he called the name of the firstborn Manasseh, saying, "God has caused me to forget all my labors and the house of my father."

52 Likewise, he named the second Ephraim, saying, "God has caused me to increase in the land of my poverty."

53 And so, when the seven years of fertility that occurred in Egypt had passed,

54 the seven years of destitution, which Joseph had predicted, began to arrive. And the famine prevailed throughout the whole world, but there was bread in all the land of Egypt.

55 And being hungry, the people cried out to Pharaoh, asking for provisions. And he said to them: "Go to Joseph. And do whatever he will tell you."

56 Then the famine increased daily in all the land. And Joseph opened all of the storehouses and sold to the Egyptians. For the famine had oppressed them also.

57 And all the provinces came to Egypt, to buy food and to temper the misfortune of their destitution.

Genesis 42

1 Then Jacob, hearing that food was being sold in Egypt, said to his sons: "Why are you negligent?

2 I have heard that wheat is being sold in Egypt. Go down and buy necessities for us, so that we may be able to live, and not be consumed by destitution."

3 And so, when ten brothers of Joseph went down to buy grain in Egypt,

4 Benjamin was kept at home by Jacob, who said to his brothers, "Lest perhaps he may suffer harm on the journey."

5 And they entered into the land of Egypt with the others who traveled to buy. For the famine was in the land of Canaan.

6 And Joseph was governor in the land of Egypt, and grain was sold under his direction to the people. And when his brothers had reverenced him

7 and he had recognized them, he spoke harshly, as if to foreigners, questioning them: "Where did you come from?" And they responded, "From the land of Canaan, to buy necessary provisions."

8 And although he knew his brothers, he was not known by them.

9 And remembering the dreams, which he had seen in another time, he said to them: "You are scouts. You have come in order to see which parts of the land are weaker."

10 And they said: "It is not so, my lord. But your servants have arrived in order to buy food.

11 We are all sons of one man. We have come in peace, nor do any of your subjects devise evil."

12 And he answered them: "It is otherwise. You have come to examine the unguarded parts of this land."

13 But they said: "We, your servants, are twelve brothers, the sons of one man in the land of Canaan. The youngest is with our father; the other is not living."

14 He said: "This is just as I have said. You are scouts.

15 I will now continue to put you to the test. By the health of Pharaoh, you will not depart from here, until your youngest brother arrives.

16 Send one of you and bring him. But you will be in chains, until what you have said is proven to be either true or false. Otherwise, by the health of Pharaoh, you are scouts."

17 Therefore, he delivered them into custody for three days.

18 Then, on the third day, he brought them out of prison, and he said: "Do as I have said, and you will live. For I fear God.

19 If you are peaceful, let one of your brothers be bound in prison. Then you may go away and carry the grain that you have bought to your houses.

20 And bring your youngest brother to me, so that I may be able to test your words, and you may not die." They did as he had said,

21 and they spoke to one another: "We deserve to suffer these things, because we have sinned against our brother, seeing the anguish of his soul, when he begged us and we would not listen. For that reason, this tribulation has come upon us."

22 And Reuben, one of them, said: "Did not I say to you, 'Do not sin against the boy,' and you would not listen to me? See, his blood is exacted."

23 But they did not know that Joseph understood, because he was speaking to them through an interpreter.

24 And he turned himself away briefly and wept. And returning, he spoke to them.

25 And taking Simeon, and binding him in their presence, he ordered his ministers to fill their sacks with wheat, and to replace each one's money in their sacks, and to give them, in addition, provisions for the way. And they did so.

26 Then, having loaded their donkeys with the grain, they set out.

27 And one of them, opening a sack to give his beast of burden fodder at the inn, looked upon the money at the sack's mouth,

28 and he said to his brothers: "My money has returned to me. See, it is held in the sack." And they were astonished and troubled, and they said to one another, "What is this that God has done to us?"

29 And they went to their father Jacob in the land of Canaan, and they explained to him all the things that had befallen them, saying:

30 "The lord of the land spoke harshly to us, and he considered us to be scouts of the province.

31 And we answered him: 'We are peaceful, and we do not intend any treachery.

32 We are twelve brothers conceived of one father. One is not living; the youngest is with our father in the land of Canaan.'

33 And he said to us: 'Thus will I prove that you are peaceful. Release one of your brothers to me, and take necessary provisions for your houses, and go away,

34 and bring your youngest brother to me, so that I may know that you are not scouts. And this one, who is held in chains, you may be able to receive again. And thereafter, you shall have permission to buy what you want.' "

35 Having said this, when they poured out their grain, each found his money tied to the mouth of his sack. And all were terrified together.

36 Their father Jacob said, "You have caused me to be without children. Joseph is not living, Simeon is held in chains, and Benjamin you would carry away. All these evils have fallen back upon me."

37 And Reuben answered him, "Put my two sons to death, if I do not lead him back to you. Deliver him into my hand, and I will restore him to you."

38 But he said: "My son will not go down with you. His brother is dead, and he is left alone. If any adversity will befall him in the land to which you travel, you would lead my grey hairs down with sorrow to the grave."

Genesis 43

1 Meanwhile, the famine pressed heavily on all the land.

2 And having consumed the provisions that they had brought out of Egypt, Jacob said to his sons, "Return and buy us a little food."

3 Judah answered: "The man himself declared to us, under the attestation of an oath, saying: 'You will not see my face, unless you bring your youngest brother with you.'

4 If therefore you are willing to send him with us, we will travel together, and we will buy necessities for you.

5 But if you are not willing, we will not go. For the man, as we have often said, declared to us, saying: 'You will not see my face without your youngest brother.' "

6 Israel said to them, "You have done this for my misery, in that you revealed to him that you also had another brother."

7 But they responded: "The man questioned us in order, concerning our family: whether our father lived, if we had a brother. And we answered him respectively, according to what he demanded. How could we know that he would say, 'Bring your brother with you?' "

8 Likewise, Judah said to his father: "Send the boy with me, so that we may set out and be able to live, lest we and our little ones should die.

9 I accept the boy; require him at my hand. Unless I lead him back and restore him to you, I will be guilty of a sin against you for all time.

10 If a delay had not intervened, by now we would have returned here a second time."

11 Therefore, their father Israel said to them: "If it is necessary to do so, then do what you will. Take, in your vessels, from the best fruits of the land, and carry down gifts to the man: a little resin, and honey, and storax ointment, oil of myrrh, turpentine, and almonds.

12 Also, take with you double the money, and carry back what you found in your sacks, lest perhaps it was done in error.

13 But also take your brother, and go to the man.

14 Then may my Almighty God cause him to be pleased by you. And send your brother, whom he holds, back with you, along with this one, Benjamin. But as for me, without my children, I will be like one who is bereaved."

15 Therefore, the men took the gifts, and double the money, and Benjamin. And they went down into Egypt, and they stood in the presence of Joseph.

16 And when he had seen them and Benjamin together, he instructed the steward of his house, saying: "Lead the men into the house, and kill victims, and prepare a feast, because they will be eating with me at midday."

17 He did what he had been ordered to do, and he brought the men into the house.

18 And there, being terrified, they said one to another: "Because of the money, which we carried back the first time in our sacks, we have been brought in, so that he may unleash a false accusation against us, and by violence subjugate both us and our donkeys into servitude."

19 For this reason, approaching the steward of the house at his door,

20 they said: "We beg you, lord, to hear us. We came down once before to buy food.

21 And having bought it, when we arrived at the inn, we opened our sacks and found the money in the mouths of the sacks, which we now have carried back in the same amount.

22 But we have also brought other silver, so that we may buy those things that are necessary for us. It is not on our conscience who had placed it in our bags."

23 But he responded: "Peace be with you. Do not be afraid. Your God, and the God of your father, has given you the treasure in your sacks. As for the money that you gave to me, I held it as a test." And he led Simeon out to them.

24 And having led them into the house, he brought water, and they washed their feet, and he gave fodder to their donkeys.

25 But they also prepared the gifts, until Joseph entered at midday. For they had heard that they would eat bread there.

26 And so Joseph entered his house, and they offered him the gifts, holding them in their hands. And they reverenced prone on the ground.

27 But he, gently greeting them again, questioned them, saying: "Is your father, the old man about whom you spoke to me, in good health? Is he still alive?"

28 And they answered: "Your servant, our father, is safe; he is still alive." And bowing, they reverenced him.

29 Then Joseph, lifting up his eyes, saw Benjamin, his brother of the same womb, and he said, "Is this your little brother, about whom you spoke to me?" And again, he said, "May God be compassionate to you, my son."

30 And he hurried out, because his heart had been moved over his brother, and tears gushed out. And going into his chamber, he wept.

31 And when he had washed his face, coming out again, he composed himself, and he said, "Set out bread."

32 And when it was set out, separately for Joseph, and separately for his brothers, likewise separately for the Egyptians, who ate at the same time, (for it is unlawful for Egyptians to eat with Hebrews, and they consider feasting in this way to be profane)

33 they sat before him, the firstborn according to his birthright, and the youngest according to his state of life. And they wondered exceedingly,

34 taking the portions that they received from him. And the greater portion went to Benjamin, so much so that it exceeded five parts. And they drank and became inebriated along with him.

Genesis 44

1 Then Joseph instructed the steward of his house, saying: "Fill their sacks with grain, as much as they are able to hold. And place each one's money at the top of the sack.

2 But place my silver bowl, and the price that he gave for the wheat, in the mouth of the sack of the youngest." And so it was done.

3 And when morning arose, they were sent away with their donkeys.

4 And now they had departed from the city and had set out a short distance. Then Joseph, sending for the steward of his house, said: "Rise up and pursue the men. And when you have overtaken them, say: 'Why have you returned evil for good?

5 The cup that you have stolen, it is that from which my lord drinks, and in which he is accustomed to discern signs. You have done a very sinful thing.' "

6 He did as he had been ordered. And having overtaken them, he spoke to them according to the order.

7 And they responded: "Why does our lord speak in this way, as though your servants had committed such a shameful act?

8 The money, which we found at the top of our sacks, we carried back to you from the land of Canaan. So in what way does it follow that we would steal, from the house of your lord, gold or silver?

9 Whichever of your servants will be found to have what you seek, may he die, and we shall be the servants of my lord."

10 And he said to them: "Let it be according to your verdict. With whomever it will be found, let him be my servant, but you will be unharmed."

11 And so, they quickly placed their sacks down to the ground, and each one was opened.

12 And when he had searched, beginning with the oldest, all the way to the youngest, he found the cup in Benjamin's sack.

13 But they, tearing their garments and burdening their donkeys again, returned to the town.

14 And Judah, first among his brothers, entered to Joseph (for he had not yet departed from the place) and together they all fell down before him to the ground.

15 And he said to them: "Why would you choose to act in this way? Could you be ignorant that there is no one like me in the knowledge of discerning signs?"

16 And Judah said to him, "What could we answer to my lord? And what would we be able to say, or to justly claim? God has discovered the iniquity of your servants. See, we have all become servants to my lord, both we, and he with whom the cup was found."

17 Joseph responded: "Far be it from me that I should act in this way. He who stole the cup, he will be my servant. But you may go away free to your father."

18 Then Judah, approaching closer, said confidently: "I beg you, my lord, let your servant speak a word in your ears, and do not be angry with your servant. For you are next to Pharaoh.

19 My lord, you questioned your servants before: 'Do you have a father or a brother?'

20 And we answered you, my lord: 'There is our father, an old man, and a young boy, who was born in his old age. His brother of the same womb has died, and he alone is left to his mother and father, who truly love him tenderly.'

21 And you said to your servants, 'Bring him to me, and I will set my eyes on him.'

22 We suggested to my lord: 'The boy is not able to leave his father. For if he sends him away, he will die.'

23 And you said to your servants: 'Unless your youngest brother arrives with you, you will not see my face any more.'

24 Therefore, when we had gone up to your servant our father, we explained to him all that my lord had spoken.

25 And our father said: 'Return and buy us a little wheat.'

26 And we said to him: 'We cannot go. If our youngest brother descends with us, we will set out together. Otherwise, in his absence, we do not dare to see the face of the man.'

27 To which he responded: 'You know that my wife conceived twice by me.

28 One went out, and you said, "A beast devoured him." And since then, he has not appeared.

29 If you take this one also, and anything happens to him on the way, you will lead my grey hairs down with grief to the grave.'

30 Therefore, if I would have gone to your servant, our father, with the boy not present, (though his life depends upon the life of him)

31 and if he were to see that he is not with us, he would die, and your servants will lead his grey hairs down with sorrow to the grave.

32 Let me be your very own servant, for I accepted this one into my trust, and I promised, saying: 'Unless I lead him back, I will be guilty of a sin against my father for all time.'

33 And so I, your servant, will remain in place of the boy, in ministry to my lord, and then let the boy go up with his brothers.

34 For I cannot return to my father without the boy, lest I appear as a witness to the calamity that will oppress my father."

Genesis 45

1 Joseph was unable to restrain himself any longer, standing before so many. Therefore, he instructed that all should go outside, and that no stranger should be among them as they recognized one another.

2 And he lifted up his voice with weeping, which the Egyptians heard, along with the entire house of Pharaoh.

3 And he said to his brothers: "I am Joseph. Is my father still alive?" His brothers were unable to respond, being terrified by a very great fear.

4 And he said to them mildly, "Approach toward me." And when they had approached close by, he said: "I am Joseph, your brother, whom you sold into Egypt.

5 Do not be afraid, and let it not seem to you to be a hardship that you sold me into these regions. For God sent me before you into Egypt for your salvation.

6 For it is two years since the famine began to be upon the land, and five years more remain, in which there can be neither plowing, nor reaping.

7 And God sent me ahead, so that you may be preserved upon the earth, and so that you would be able to have food in order to live.

8 I was sent here, not by your counsel, but by the will of God. He has caused me to be like a father to Pharaoh, and to be the lord of his entire house, as well as governor throughout all the land of Egypt.

9 Hurry, and go up to my father, and say to him: 'Your son Joseph commands this: God has caused me to be lord of the entire land of Egypt. Come down to me, do not delay,

10 and you will live in the land of Goshen. And you will be next to me, you and your sons and the sons of your sons, your sheep and your herds, and all that you possess.

11 And there I will pasture you, (for there are still five years of famine remaining) lest both you and your house perish, along with all that you possess.'

12 Behold, your eyes and the eyes of my brother Benjamin can see that it is my mouth speaking to you.

13 You will report to my father about all my glory, and about all that you have seen in Egypt. Hurry, and bring him to me."

14 And then falling upon the neck of his brother Benjamin, he embraced him and wept. And likewise, Benjamin wept at the same time on his neck.

15 And Joseph kissed all his brothers, and he cried over each one. After this, they were emboldened to speak to him.

16 And it was overheard, and the news spread by word throughout the king's court. The brothers of Joseph had arrived, and Pharaoh was gladdened along with all his family.

17 And he told Joseph that he should command his brothers, saying: " 'Burden your beasts, and go into the land of Canaan,

18 and take from there your father and kindred, and come to me. And I will give you all the good things of Egypt, so that you may eat from the marrow of the land.' "

19 "And you may even instruct that they take wagons from the land of Egypt, in order to transport their little ones as well as their wives. And say: 'Take your father, and come quickly, as soon as possible.

20 You need not give up anything from your household, for all the riches of Egypt will be yours.' "

21 And the sons of Israel did just as they were commanded. And Joseph gave them wagons, according to the command of Pharaoh, and provisions for the journey.

22 Likewise, he ordered two robes for each of them to be brought. Yet truly, to Benjamin he gave three hundred pieces of silver along with five of the best robes.

23 And he sent just as much money and clothing to his father, adding also ten male donkeys, with which to transport all the riches of Egypt, and as many female donkeys, carrying wheat and bread for the journey.

24 Thus he sent away his brothers, and as they set out he said, "Do not become angry on the way."

25 And they ascended out of Egypt, and they arrived in the land of Canaan, to their father Jacob.

26 And they reported to him, saying: "Your son Joseph is alive, and he is ruler throughout all the land of Egypt. When Jacob heard this, he was stirred up, as if from a deep sleep, yet he did not believe them.

27 To the contrary, they explained the entire matter in order. And when he had seen the wagons, and all that he had sent, his spirit revived,

28 and he said: "It is enough for me, if my son Joseph is still alive. I will go and see him before I die."

Genesis 46

1 And Israel, setting out with all that he had, arrived at the Well of the Oath. And sacrificing victims there to the God of his father Isaac,

2 he heard him, by a vision in the night, calling him, and saying to him: "Jacob, Jacob." And he answered him, "Behold, here I am."

3 God said to him: "I am the most strong God of your father. Do not be afraid. Descend into Egypt, for there I will make of you a great nation.

4 I will descend with you to that place, and I will lead you back from there, returning. Also, Joseph will place his hands over your eyes.

5 Then Jacob rose up from the Well of the Oath. And his sons took him, with their little ones and wives, in the wagons that Pharaoh had sent to carry the old man,

6 along with all that he possessed in the land of Canaan. And he arrived in Egypt with all his offspring:

7 his sons and his grandsons, his daughters and all his progeny together.

8 Now these are the names of the sons of Israel, who entered into Egypt, he with his children. The firstborn is Reuben.

9 The sons of Reuben: Hanoch and Pallu, and Hezron and Carmi.

10 The sons of Simeon: Jemuel and Jamin and Ohad, and Jachin and Zohar, and Shaul, the son of a Canaanite woman.

11 The sons of Levi: Gershon and Kohath, and Merari.

12 The sons of Judah: Er and Onan, and Shelah, and Perez and Zerah. Now Er and Onan died in the land of Canaan. And sons were born to Perez: Hezron and Hamul.

13 The sons of Issachar: Tola and Puvah, and Job and Shimron.

14 The sons of Zebulun: Sered and Elon and Jahleel.

15 These are the sons of Leah, whom she bore, along with his daughter Dinah, in Mesopotamia of Syria. All the souls of her sons and daughters are thirty-three.

16 The sons of Gad: Ziphion and Haggi, and Shuni and Ezbon, and Eri and Arodi, and Areli.

17 The sons of Asher: Imnah and Jesua, and Jessui and Beriah, and also their sister Sarah. The sons of Beria: Heber and Malchiel.

18 These are the sons of Zilpah, whom Laban gave to his daughter Leah. And these she bore to Jacob: sixteen souls.

19 The sons of Rachel, the wife of Jacob: Joseph and Benjamin.

20 And sons were born to Joseph in the land of Egypt, whom Asenath, the daughter of Potiphera, priest of Heliopolis, bore for him: Manasseh and Ephraim.

21 The sons of Benjamin: Bela and Becher, and Ashbel and Gera, and Naaman and Ehi, and Rosh and Moppim, and Huppim and Ard.

22 These are the sons of Rachel, whom she bore to Jacob: all these souls are fourteen.

23 The sons of Dan: Hushim.

24 The sons of Naphtali: Jahzeel and Guni, and Jezer and Shillem.

25 These are the sons of Bilhah, whom Laban gave to his daughter Rachel, and these she bore to Jacob: all these souls are seven.

26 All the souls who went into Egypt with Jacob and who went out from his thigh, besides the wives of his sons, were sixty-six.

27 Now the sons of Joseph, who were born to him in the land of Egypt, were two souls. All the souls of the house of Jacob, who went into Egypt, were seventy.

28 Then he sent Judah ahead of himself, to Joseph, in order to report to him, and so that he would meet him in Goshen.

29 And when he had arrived there, Joseph harnessed his chariot, and he went up to meet his father at the same place. And seeing him, he fell upon his neck, and, amid embraces, he wept.

30 And the father said to Joseph, "Now I will die happy, because I have seen your face, and I am leaving you behind alive."

31 And he said to his brothers and to all his father's house: "I will go up and report to Pharaoh, and I will say to him: 'My brothers, and my father's house, who were in the land of Canaan, have come to me.

32 And these honorable men are pastors of sheep, and they have the task of feeding the flock. Their cattle, and herds, and all that they were able to hold, they have brought with them.'

33 And when he will call you and will say, 'What is your work?'

34 You will respond, 'Your servants are pastors of honor, from our infancy even to the present time, both we and our fathers.' Now you will say this so that you may be able to live in the land of Goshen, because the Egyptians detest all pastors of sheep."

Genesis 47

1 And so Joseph entered and reported to Pharaoh, saying: "My father and brothers, their sheep and herds, and everything that they possess, have arrived from the land of Canaan. And behold, they stand together in the land of Goshen."

2 Likewise, he stood in the sight of the king five men, the last of his brothers.

3 And he questioned them, "What do you have for work?" They responded: "Your servants are pastors of sheep, both we and our fathers.

4 We came to sojourn in your land, because there is no grass for the flocks of your servants, the famine being very grievous in the land of Canaan. And we petition you that you may order us, your servants, to be in the land of Goshen."

5 And so the king said to Joseph: "Your father and brothers have come to you.

6 The land of Egypt is in your sight. Cause them to live in the best place, and deliver to them the land of Goshen. And if you know there to be industrious men among them, appoint these as foremen over my cattle."

7 After this, Joseph brought in his father to the king, and he stood him in his sight. He blessed him,

8 and he questioned him: "How many are the days of the years of your life?"

9 He responded, "The days of my sojourn are one hundred and thirty years, few and unworthy, and they do not reach even to the days of the sojourning of my fathers."

10 And blessing the king, he went outside.

11 Truly, Joseph gave his father and brothers a possession in Egypt, in the best place of the land, in Rameses, as Pharaoh had instructed.

12 And he fed them, along with all his father's house, providing portions of food to each one.

13 For in the whole world there was a lack of bread, and a famine had oppressed the land, most of all Egypt and Canaan,

14 from which he gathered together all the money for the grain that they bought, and he took it into the treasury of the king.

15 And when the buyers had run out of money, all Egypt came to Joseph, saying: "Give us bread. Why should we die in your sight, lacking money?"

16 And he responded to them: "Bring me your cattle, and I will give food to you in exchange for them, if you do not have money."

17 And when they had brought them, he gave them food for their horses, and sheep, and oxen, and donkeys. And he sustained them in that year in exchange for their cattle.

18 Likewise, they came the second year, and they said to him: "We will not conceal from our lord that our money is gone; likewise our cattle are gone. Neither are you unaware that we have nothing left but our bodies and our land.

19 Therefore, why should you watch us die? Both we and our land will be yours. Buy us into royal servitude, but provide seed, lest by the dying off of cultivators the land be reduced to a wilderness."

20 Therefore, Joseph bought all the land of Egypt, each one selling his possessions because of the magnitude of the famine. And he subjected it to Pharaoh,

21 along with all of its people, from the newest borders of Egypt, even to its furthest limits,

22 except the land of the priests, which had been delivered to them by the king. To these also a portion of food was supplied out of the public storehouses, and, for this reason, they were not compelled to sell their possessions.

23 Therefore, Joseph said to the people: "So, as you discern, both you and your lands are possessed by Pharaoh; take seed and sow the fields,

24 so that you may be able to have grain. One fifth part you will give to the king; the remaining four I permit to you, as seed and as food for your families and children.

25 And they responded: "Our health is in your hand; only let our lord look kindly upon us, and we will serve the king with gladness."

26 From that time, even to the present day, in the entire land of Egypt, the fifth part is turned over to the kings, and it has become like a law, except in the land of the priests, which was free from this condition.

27 And so, Israel lived in Egypt, that is, in the land of Goshen, and he possessed it. And he increased and was multiplied exceedingly.

28 And he lived in it seventeen years. And all the days of his life that passed were one hundred and forty-seven years.

29 And when he discerned that the day of his death was approaching, he called his son Joseph, and he said to him: "If I have found favor in your sight, place your hand under my thigh. And you shall show me mercy and truth, not to bury me in Egypt.

30 But I shall sleep with my fathers, and you will carry me from this land and bury me in the sepulcher of my ancestors." And Joseph answered him, "I will do what you have ordered."

31 And he said, "Then swear it to me." And as he was swearing, Israel adored God, turning to the head of his resting place.

Genesis 48

1 After these things were done, it was reported to Joseph that his father was sick. And taking his two sons Manasseh and Ephraim, he went directly to him.

2 And it was told to the old man, "Behold, your son Joseph is coming to you." And being strengthened, he sat up in bed.

3 And when he had entered to him, he said: "Almighty God appeared to me at Luz, which is in the land of Canaan, and he blessed me.

4 And he said: 'I will increase and multiply you, and I will make you influential among the people. And I will give this land to you, and to your offspring after you, as an everlasting possession.'

5 Therefore, your two sons, who were born to you in the land of Egypt before I came here to you, will be mine. Ephraim and Manasseh will be treated by me just like Reuben and Simeon.

6 But the remainder, whom you will conceive after them, will be yours, and they will be called by the name of their brothers among their possessions.

7 As for me, when I came from Mesopotamia, Rachel died in the land of Canaan on the very journey, and it was springtime. And I entered Ephrath and buried her next to the way of Ephrath, which by another name is called Bethlehem."

8 Then, seeing his sons, he said to him: "Who are these?"

9 He responded, "They are my sons, whom God gave to me as a gift in this place." "Bring them to me," he said, "so that I may bless them."

10 For Israel's eyes were clouded by reason of his great age, and he was unable to see clearly. And when they were placed up against him, he kissed and embraced them.

11 And he said to his son: "I have not been cheated out of seeing you. Moreover, God has shown me your offspring."

12 And when Joseph had taken them from his father's lap, he reverenced prone on the ground.

13 And he placed Ephraim on his right, that is, towards the left hand of Israel. Yet truly Manasseh was on his left, namely, towards his father's right hand. And he placed them both up against him.

14 And he, extending his right hand, placed it over the head of Ephraim, the younger brother, but the left hand was on the head of Manasseh, who was the elder, so that his hands were crossed.

15 And Jacob blessed the sons of Joseph, and he said: "God, in whose sight my fathers Abraham and Isaac walked, God who pastured me from my youth until the present day,

16 the Angel, who rescues me from all evils: bless these boys. And let my name be invoked over them, and also the names of my fathers, Abraham and Isaac. And may they increase into a multitude across the earth."

17 But Joseph, seeing that his father had placed his right hand over the head of Ephraim, took it gravely. And grasping his father's hand, he tried to lift it from Ephraim's head and transfer it onto the head of Manasseh.

18 And he said to his father: "It should not have come to pass this way, father. For this one is the firstborn. Place your right hand over his head."

19 But refusing, he said: "I know, my son, I know. And this one, indeed, will be among the people and will be multiplied. But his younger brother will be greater than he. And his offspring will increase among the nations."

20 And he blessed them at that time, saying: "In you, Israel will be blessed, and it will be said: 'May God treat you like Ephraim, and like Manasseh.' " And he established Ephraim before Manasseh.

21 And he said to his son Joseph: "See, I am dying, and God will be with you, and he will lead you back to the land of your fathers.

22 I give you one part beyond that of your brothers, which I took from the hand of the Amorite with my sword and my bow."

Genesis 49

1 Then Jacob called his sons, and he said to them: "Gather together, so that I may announce what will happen to you in the last days.

2 Gather together and listen, O sons of Jacob. Listen to Israel, your father.

3 Reuben, my firstborn, you are my strength and the beginning of my sorrow: first in gifts, greater in authority.

4 You are being poured out like water, may you not increase. For you climbed onto your father's bed, and you defiled his resting place.

5 The brothers Simeon and Levi: vessels of iniquity waging war.

6 Let not my soul go by their counsel, nor my glory be within their meeting. For in their fury they killed a man, and in their self-will they undermined a wall.

7 Cursed be their fury, because it was obstinate, and their indignation, because it was harsh. I will divide them in Jacob, and I will scatter them in Israel.

8 Judah, your brothers will praise you. Your hand will be at the necks of your enemies; the sons of your father will reverence you.

9 Judah is a lion's young. You have gone up to the prey, my son. While resting, you have lain like a lion. And just like a lioness, who would rouse him?

10 The scepter from Judah and the leader from his thigh will not be taken away, until he who will be sent arrives, and he will be the expectation of Gentiles.

11 Tying his young colt to the vineyard, and his donkey, O my son, to the vine, he will wash his robe in wine, and his cloak in the blood of the grape.

12 His eyes are more beautiful than wine, and his teeth whiter than milk.

13 Zebulun will live at the seashore and by the outpost of ships, reaching as far as Sidon.

14 Issachar will be a strong donkey, reclining between the borders.

15 He saw that rest would be good, and that the land was excellent. And so he bent his shoulder to carry, and he became a servant under tribute.

16 Dan will judge his people just like any other tribe in Israel.

17 Let Dan be a snake in the way, a viper in the path, biting the hooves of horses, so that his rider may fall backward.

18 I will wait for your salvation, O Lord.

19 Gad, being girded, will fight before him. And he himself will be girded backward.

20 Asher: his bread will be fat, and he will provide delicacies to the kings.

21 Naphtali is a stag sent forth, offering words of eloquent beauty.

22 Joseph is a growing son, a growing son and stately to behold; the daughters run back and forth on the wall.

23 But those who held darts, provoked him, and they contend with him, and they envied him.

24 His bow sits in strength, and the bands of his arms and hands have been let loose by the hands of the mighty one of Jacob. From there he went forth as a pastor, the stone of Israel.

25 The God of your father will be your helper, and the Almighty will bless you with the blessings of heaven above, with the blessings of the abyss that lies beneath, with the blessings of the breasts and of the womb.

26 The blessings of your father are strengthened by the blessings of his fathers, until the desire of the hills of eternity shall arrive. May they be at the head of Joseph, and at the summit of the Nazarite, among his brothers.

27 Benjamin is a ravenous wolf, in the morning he will eat the prey, and in the evening he will divide the spoil."

28 All these are the twelve tribes of Israel. These things their father spoke to them, and he blessed each one with their proper blessings.

29 And he instructed them, saying: "I am being gathered to my people. Bury me with my fathers in the double cave, which is in the field of Ephron the Hittite,

30 opposite Mamre, in the land of Canaan, which Abraham bought, along with its field, from Ephron the Hittite, as a possession for burial.

31 There they buried him, with his wife Sarah." And there Isaac was buried with his wife Rebekah. There also Leah lies preserved.

32 And having finished these commands by which he instructed his sons, he drew his feet onto the bed, and he passed away. And he was gathered to his people.

Genesis 50

1 Joseph, realizing this, fell upon his father's face, weeping and kissing him.

2 And he instructed his servant physicians to embalm his father with aromatics.

3 And while they were fulfilling his orders, forty days passed. For this was the method of embalming dead bodies. And Egypt wept for him for seventy days.

4 And when the time for mourning was fulfilled, Joseph spoke to the family of Pharaoh: "If I have found favor in your sight, speak to the ears of Pharaoh.

5 For my father made me swear, saying: 'See, I am dying. You shall bury me in my sepulcher which I dug for myself in the land of Canaan.' Therefore, I shall go up and bury my father, and then return."

6 And Pharaoh said to him, "Go up and bury your father, just as he made you swear."

7 So as he went up, all the elders of the house of Pharaoh went with him, along with every patriarch in the land of Egypt,

8 and the house of Joseph with his brothers, except their little ones and flocks and also the herds, which they left behind in the land of Goshen.

9 Likewise, he had in his company chariots and horsemen. And it became a crowd without restraint.

10 And they arrived at the threshing place of Atad, which is situated beyond the Jordan. There they spent seven full days celebrating the funeral rites with a great and vehement lamentation.

11 And when the inhabitants of the land of Canaan had seen this, they said, "This is a great Lamentation for the Egyptians." And for this reason, the name of that place was called, "The Lamentation of Egypt."

12 And so, the sons of Jacob did just as he had instructed them.

13 And carrying him into the land of Canaan, they buried him in the double cave, which Abraham had bought along with its field, from Ephron the Hittite, as a possession for burial, opposite Mamre.

14 And Joseph returned into Egypt with his brothers and all those of his company, having buried his father.

15 Now that he was dead, his brothers were afraid, and they said to one another: "Perhaps now he may remember the injury that he suffered and requite us for all the evil that we did to him."

16 So they sent a message to him, saying: "Your father instructed us before he died,

17 that we should say these words to you from him: 'I beg you to forget the wickedness of your brothers, and the sin and malice that they practiced against you.' Likewise, we petition you to release the servants of the God of your father from this iniquity." Hearing this, Joseph wept.

18 And his brothers went to him. And reverencing prostrate on the ground, they said, "We are your servants."

19 And he answered them: "Do not be afraid. Are we able to resist the will of God?

20 You devised evil against me. But God turned it into good, so that he might exalt me, just as you presently discern, and so that he might bring about the salvation of many peoples.

21 Do not be afraid. I will pasture you and your little ones." And he consoled them, and he spoke mildly and leniently.

22 And he lived in Egypt with all his father's house; and he survived for one hundred and ten years. And he saw the sons of Ephraim to the third generation. Likewise, the sons of Machir, the son of Manasseh, were born onto Joseph's knees.

23 After these things happened, he said to his brothers: "God will visit you after my death, and he will make you ascend from this land into the land which he swore to Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob."

24 And when he had made them swear and had said, "God will visit you; carry my bones with you from this place,"

25 he died, having completed one hundred and ten years of his life. And having been embalmed with aromatics, he was laid to rest in a coffin in Egypt.

Exodus 1

1 These are the names of the sons of Israel, who went into Egypt with Jacob. They entered, each one with his house:

2 Reuben, Simeon, Levi, Judah,

3 Issachar, Zebulun, and Benjamin,

4 Dan and Naphtali, Gad and Asher.

5 Therefore, all the souls of those who went forth from Jacob's thigh were seventy. Now Joseph was in Egypt.

6 When he had died, along with all of his brothers and all of that generation,

7 the sons of Israel increased, and they multiplied like seedlings. And having been strengthened exceedingly, they filled the land.

8 Meanwhile, there arose a new king over Egypt, who was ignorant of Joseph.

9 And he said to his people: "Behold, the people of the sons of Israel are many, and they are stronger than we are.

10 Come, let us wisely oppress them, lest they multiply; and if any war should advance against us, they may be added to our enemies, and having fought against us, they might depart from the land."

11 And so he set over them masters of the works, in order to afflict them with burdens. And they built for Pharaoh the cities of the tabernacles: Pithom and Raamses.

12 And the more they oppressed them, so much more did they multiply and increase.

13 And the Egyptians hated the sons of Israel, and they afflicted them and mocked them.

14 And they led their life directly into bitterness, with hard work in clay and brick, and with all kinds of servitude, so that they were being overwhelmed with the works of the land.

15 Then the king of Egypt spoke to the midwives of the Hebrews, (one of whom one was called Shiphrah, another Puah)

16 instructing them: "When you will act as a midwife to the Hebrew women, and the time of delivery has arrived: if it is male, put it to death; if it is female, retain it."

17 But the midwives feared God, and so they did not act according to the precept of the king of Egypt, but they kept the males safe.

18 And summoning them, the king said, "What did you intend to do, so that you would save the boys?"

19 They responded: "The Hebrew women are not like the Egyptian women. For they themselves have the wisdom of a midwife, and so they give birth before we can come to them."

20 Therefore, God acted favorably toward the midwives. And the people increased, and they were strengthened exceedingly.

21 And because the midwives feared God, he built houses for them.

22 Therefore, Pharaoh instructed all his people, saying: "Whatever will be born of the male sex, cast it into the river; whatever will be born of the female sex, retain it."

Exodus 2

1 After these things, a man from the house of Levi went out, and he took a wife from his own stock.

2 And she conceived and bore a son. And seeing him to be handsome, she hid him for three months.

3 And when she was no longer able to hide him, she took a small basket woven of bulrushes, and she smeared it with pitch as well as tar. And she placed the little infant inside, and she laid him in the sedges by the bank of the river.

4 His sister was standing at a distance and was wondering what would happen.

5 Then, behold, the daughter of Pharaoh descended to wash in the river. And her maids walked along the edge of the cove. And when she had seen the small basket among the papyruses, she sent one of her servants for it. And when it was brought,

6 she opened it; and realizing that within it was a little one crying, she took pity on him, and she said: "This is one of the infants of the Hebrews."

7 And the sister of the boy said to her: "If you wish, I will go and call to you a Hebrew woman, who will be able nurse the infant."

8 She responded, "Go." The maid went directly and called her mother.

9 And the daughter of Pharaoh said to her: "Take this boy and nurse him for me. I will give you your wages." The woman took and nursed the boy. And when he was mature, she delivered him to the daughter of Pharaoh.

10 And she adopted him in place of a son, and she called his name Moses, saying, "Because I took him from the water."

11 In those days, after Moses had grown up, he went out to his brothers. And he saw their affliction and an Egyptian man striking a certain one of the Hebrews, his brothers.

12 And when he had looked around this way and that, and had seen no one nearby, he struck down the Egyptian and hid him in the sand.

13 And going out the next day, he spotted two Hebrews quarrelling violently. And he said to him who was causing the injury, "Why do you strike your neighbor?"

14 But he responded: "Who appointed you as leader and judge over us? Do you want to kill me, just as yesterday you killed the Egyptian?" Moses was afraid, and he said, "How has this word become known?"

15 And Pharaoh heard this talk, and he sought to kill Moses. But fleeing from his sight, he stayed in the land of Midian, and he sat down next to a well.

16 Now there was a priest of Midian with seven daughters, who came to draw water. And having filled the troughs, they desired to water their father's flocks.

17 The shepherds overcame them and drove them away. And Moses rose up, and defending the girls, he watered their sheep.

18 And when they had returned to their father, Reuel, he said to them, "Why have you arrived sooner than usual?"

19 They responded: "A man of Egypt freed us from the hands of the shepherds. Moreover, he also drew water with us and gave the sheep to drink."

20 But he said: "Where is he? Why have you dismissed the man? Call him, so that he may eat bread."

21 Therefore, Moses swore that he would live with him. And he accepted his daughter Zipporah as a wife.

22 And she bore a son to him, whom he called Gershom, saying, "I have been a newcomer in a foreign land." In truth, she bore another, whom he called Eliezer, saying, "For the God of my father, my helper, has rescued me from the hand of Pharaoh."

23 In truth, after a long time, the king of Egypt was dead. And the sons of Israel, groaning, cried out because of the works. And their cry ascended to God from the works.

24 And he heard their groaning, and he also remembered the covenant which he formed with Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob.

25 And the Lord looked with favor on the sons of Israel, and he knew them.

Exodus 3

1 Now Moses was pasturing the sheep of his father-in-law Jethro, a priest of Midian. And when he had driven the flock into the interior of the desert, he came to the mountain of God, Horeb.

2 And the Lord appeared to him in a flame of fire from the midst of a bush. And he saw that the bush was burning and was not burnt.

3 Therefore, Moses said, "I will go and see this great sight, why the bush is not burnt."

4 Then the Lord, discerning that he proceeded on to see it, called to him from the midst of the bush, and he said, "Moses, Moses." And he responded, "Here I am."

5 And he said: "Lest you should approach here, remove the shoes from your feet. For the place on which you stand is holy ground."

6 And he said, "I am the God of your father: the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob." Moses hid his face, for he dared not look directly at God.

7 And the Lord said to him: "I have seen the affliction of my people in Egypt, and I have heard their outcry because of the harshness of those who are over the works.

8 And knowing their sorrow, I have descended in order to free them from the hands of the Egyptians, and to lead them from that land into a good and spacious land, into a land which flows with milk and honey, to the places of the Canaanite, and Hittite, and Amorite, and Perizzite, and Hivite, and Jebusite.

9 And so, the outcry of the sons of Israel has come to me. And I have seen their affliction, with which they are oppressed by the Egyptians.

10 But come, and I will send you to Pharaoh, so that you may lead my people, the sons of Israel, out of Egypt."

11 And Moses said to God, "Who am I that I should go to Pharaoh and that I should lead the sons of Israel out of Egypt?"

12 And he said to him: "I will be with you. And you will have this as a sign that I have sent you: When you will have brought my people out of Egypt, you will offer sacrifice to God upon this mountain."

13 Moses said to God: "Behold, I will go to the sons of Israel, and I will say to them, 'The God of your fathers has sent me to you.' If they say to me, 'What is his name?' What shall I say to them?"

14 God said to Moses, "I AM WHO AM." He said: "Thus shall you say to the sons of Israel: 'HE WHO IS has sent me to you.' "

15 And God said again to Moses: "Thus shall you say to the sons of Israel: 'The Lord God of your fathers, the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob, has sent me to you.' This is the name for me in eternity, and this is my memorial from generation to generation.

16 Go and gather together the elders of Israel, and you shall say to them: 'The Lord God of your fathers, the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob, has appeared to me, saying: When visiting, I have visited you, and I have seen all that has befallen you in Egypt.

17 And I have spoken in order to lead you out of the affliction of Egypt, into the land of the Canaanite, and Hittite, and Amorite, and Perizzite, and Hivite, and Jebusite, into a land flowing with milk and honey.'

18 And they shall hear your voice. And you shall enter, you and the elders of Israel, to the king of Egypt, and you shall say to him: 'The Lord God of the Hebrews has called us. We shall go three days' journey into the wilderness, in order to offer sacrifice to the Lord our God.'

19 But I know that the king of Egypt will not release you, unless you go out by a powerful hand.

20 For I will extend my hand, and I will strike Egypt with all my wonders that I will do in the midst of them. After these things, he will release you.

21 And I will grant favor to this people in the sight of the Egyptians. And so, when you go forth, you shall not go out empty.

22 But every woman shall ask of her neighbor and of her hostess vessels of silver and of gold, as well as garments. And you shall set them upon your sons and daughters, and you shall despoil Egypt."

Exodus 4

1 Responding, Moses said, "They will not believe me, and they will not listen to my voice, but they will say: 'The Lord has not appeared to you.' "

2 Therefore, he said to him, "What is that you hold in your hand?" He answered, "A staff."

3 And the Lord said, "Cast it down upon the ground." He cast it down, and it was turned into a snake, so that Moses fled away.

4 And the Lord said, "Reach out your hand, and take hold of its tail." He reached out his hand and took hold, and it was turned into a staff.

5 "So may they believe," he said, "that the Lord God of their fathers, the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob, has appeared to you."

6 And the Lord said again, "Put your hand into your bosom." And when he had put it into his bosom, he brought it out leprous, resembling snow.

7 "Put your hand back," he said, "into your bosom." He put it back and brought it out again, and it was like the rest of his flesh.

8 "If they will not believe you," he said, "and will not listen to the sermon of the first sign, then they will believe the word of the subsequent sign.

9 But if they will not believe even these two signs, and they will not listen to your voice: take from the water of the river, and pour it upon the dry land, and whatever you will have drawn from the river will be turned into blood."

10 Moses said: "I beg you, O Lord, I was not eloquent yesterday or the day before. And from the time that you have spoken to your servant, I have a greater impediment and slowness of tongue."

11 The Lord said to him: "Who made the mouth of man? And who has formed the mute and the deaf, the seeing and the blind? Was it not I?

12 Go on, therefore, and I will be in your mouth. And I will teach you what you shall say."

13 But he said, "I beg you, O Lord, send whomever else you would send."

14 The Lord, being angry at Moses, said: "Aaron the Levite is your brother. I know that he is eloquent. Behold, he is going out to meet you, and seeing you, he will rejoice in heart.

15 Speak to him, and put my words in his mouth. And I will be in your mouth and in his mouth, and I will reveal to you what you must do.

16 He will speak for you to the people, and he will be your mouth. But you will be with him in those things that pertain to God.

17 Also, take this staff into your hand; with it you will accomplish the signs."

18 Moses went forth, and he returned to Jethro, his father in law, and he said to him, "I shall go and return to my brothers in Egypt, so that I may see if they are still alive." And Jethro said to him, "Go in peace."

19 And so the Lord said to Moses in Midian: "Go, and return to Egypt. For all those who sought your life have died."

20 Therefore, Moses took his wife and his sons, and he placed them upon a donkey, and he returned into Egypt, carrying the staff of God in his hand.

21 And the Lord said to him, as he was returning to Egypt: "See that you accomplish, in the sight of Pharaoh, all the wonders that I have placed in your hand. I will harden his heart, and he will not release the people.

22 And you shall say to him: 'Thus says the Lord: Israel is my firstborn son.

23 I have said to you: Release my son, so that he may serve me. And you were not willing to release him. Behold, I will put to death your firstborn son.' "

24 And while he was on the journey, at an inn, the Lord met him, and he was willing to kill him.

25 For this reason, Zipporah took a very sharp stone, and she circumcised the foreskin of her son, and she touched his feet, and she said, "You are a bloody spouse to me."

26 And he released him, after she had said, "You are a bloody spouse," because of the circumcision.

27 Then the Lord said to Aaron, "Go into the desert to meet Moses." And he went directly to meet him on the mountain of God, and he kissed him.

28 And Moses explained to Aaron all the words of the Lord, by which he had sent him, and the signs which he had commanded.

29 And they arrived at the same time, and they gathered together all the elders of the sons of Israel.

30 And Aaron spoke all the words which the Lord had said to Moses. And he accomplished the signs in the sight of the people,

31 and the people believed. And they heard that the Lord had visited the sons of Israel, and that he had looked with favor upon their affliction. And falling prostrate, they worshiped.

Exodus 5

1 After these things, Moses and Aaron entered, and they said to Pharaoh: "Thus says the Lord God of Israel: Release my people, so that they may sacrifice to me in the desert."

2 But he responded: "Who is the Lord, that I should listen to his voice and release Israel? I do not know the Lord, and I will not release Israel."

3 And they said: "The God of the Hebrews has called us, so that we may go three days' journey into the wilderness and sacrifice to the Lord our God. Otherwise, a pestilence or the sword may befall us."

4 The king of Egypt said to them: "Why do you, Moses and Aaron, distract the people from their works? Go back to your burdens."

5 And Pharaoh said: "The people of the land are many. You see that the turmoil has increased: how much more if you give them rest from the works?"

6 Therefore, on the same day, he instructed the overseers of the works, and the taskmasters of the people, saying:

7 "You shall no longer give chaff to the people to form bricks, as before. But they may go and gather straw.

8 And you shall impose upon them the same quota of bricks that they made before. Neither will you lessen anything, for they are idle, and therefore they cry out, saying: 'We shall go and sacrifice to our God.'

9 They shall be oppressed with works, and these shall occupy them, so that they may not agree to lying words."

10 And so the overseers of the works and the taskmasters went out and said to the people: "Thus says Pharaoh: I give you no chaff.

11 Go, and collect it wherever you are able to find it. Neither will anything of your work be diminished."

12 And the people were dispersed through all the land of Egypt, in order to gather straw.

13 Likewise, the overseers of the works pressured them, saying: "Complete your work each day, just as you were accustomed to do before, when straw was given to you."

14 And those who were first in the works of the sons of Israel were scourged by Pharaoh's taskmasters, saying: "Why have you not filled the quota of bricks, neither yesterday, nor today, just as before?"

15 And the first among the sons of Israel came, and they cried out to Pharaoh, saying: "Why do act against your servants in this way?

16 Straw is not given to us, and yet the same amount of bricks is commanded. So we, your servants, are cut up by scourging, and injustice is done against your people."

17 And he said: "You are idle. And for this reason you say, 'We shall go and sacrifice to the Lord.'

18 Therefore, go and work. Straw will not be given to you, and you will return the customary number of bricks."

19 And the first among the sons of Israel saw themselves in a crisis, because it was said to them, "Nothing at all will be lessened from the bricks throughout each day."

20 And they met with Moses and Aaron, who stood opposite them as they departed from Pharaoh.

21 And they said to them: "May the Lord see and judge, because you have caused our odor to become foul before Pharaoh and his servants, and you have provided him with a sword, in order to kill us."

22 And Moses returned to the Lord, and he said: "Lord, why have you afflicted this people? Why have you sent me?

23 For from the time that I entered to Pharaoh, so as to speak in your name, he has afflicted your people. And you have not freed them."

Exodus 6

1 And the Lord said to Moses: "Now you will see what I shall do to Pharaoh. For through a strong hand he will release them, and by a mighty hand he will cast them from his land."

2 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying: "I am the Lord,

3 who appeared to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob as Almighty God. And I did not reveal to them my name: ADONAI.

4 And I formed a covenant with them, in order to give them the land of Canaan, the land of their sojourning, in which they were newcomers.

5 I have heard the groaning of the sons of Israel, with which the Egyptians have oppressed them. And I have remembered my covenant.

6 For this reason, say to the sons of Israel: I am the Lord who will lead you away from the work house of the Egyptians, and rescue you from servitude, and also redeem you with an exalted arm and great judgments.

7 And I will take you to myself as my people, and I will be your God. And you will know that I am the Lord your God, who led you away from the work house of the Egyptians,

8 and who brought you into the land, over which I lifted up my hand in order to grant it to Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob. And I will grant it to you as a possession. I am the Lord."

9 And so, Moses explained all these things to the sons of Israel, who did not agree with him, because of their anguish of spirit and very difficult work.

10 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

11 "Enter and speak to Pharaoh, king of Egypt, so that he may release the sons of Israel from his land."

12 Moses responded in the sight the Lord: "Behold, the sons of Israel do not listen to me. And how will Pharaoh listen to me, especially since I am of uncircumcised lips?"

13 And the Lord spoke to Moses and Aaron, and he gave them a commandment for the sons of Israel, and for Pharaoh, the king of Egypt, that they should lead the sons of Israel away from the land of Egypt.

14 These are the leaders of the houses by their families. The sons of Reuben, the firstborn of Israel: Hanoch and Pallu, Hezron and Carmi.

15 These are the kindred of Reuben. The sons of Simeon: Jemuel and Jamin, and Ohad, and Jachin, and Zohar, and Shaul, the son of a Canaanite women. These are the progeny of Simeon.

16 And these are the names of the sons of Levi by their kindred: Gershon, and Kohath, and Merari. Now the years of the life of Levi were one hundred and thirty-seven.

17 The sons of Gershon: Libni and Shimei, by their kindred.

18 The sons of Kohath: Amram, and Izhar, and Hebron and Uzziel. Likewise, the years of the life of Kohath were one hundred and thirty-three.

19 The sons of Merari: Mahli and Mushi. These are the kindred of Levi by their families.

20 Now Amram took as a wife Jochebed, his paternal aunt, who bore for him Aaron and Moses. And the years of the life of Amram were one hundred and thirty-seven.

21 Likewise, the sons of Izhar: Korah, and Nepheg, and Zichri.

22 Likewise, the sons of Uzziel: Mishael, and Elzaphan, and Sithri.

23 Now Aaron took as a wife Elizabeth, the daughter of Amminadab, sister of Nahshon, who bore for him Nadab, and Abihu, and Eleazar, and Ithamar.

24 Likewise, the sons of Korah: Assir, and Elkanah, and Abiasaph. These are the kindred of the Korahites.

25 And truly Eleazar, the son of Aaron, took a wife from the daughters of Putiel. And she bore him Phinehas. These are the heads of the Levitical families by their kindred.

26 These are Aaron and Moses, whom the Lord instructed to lead the sons of Israel away from the land of Egypt by their companies.

27 These are those who speak to Pharaoh, king of Egypt, in order to lead the sons of Israel out of Egypt. These are Moses and Aaron,

28 in the day when the Lord spoke to Moses in the land of Egypt.

29 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying: "I am the Lord. Speak to Pharaoh, king of Egypt, all that I speak to you."

30 And Moses said in the sight of the Lord: "Lo, I am of uncircumcised lips, how will Pharaoh listen to me?"

Exodus 7

1 And the Lord said to Moses: "Behold, I have appointed you as the god of Pharaoh. And Aaron, your brother, will be your prophet.

2 You will speak to him all that I command you. And he will speak to Pharaoh, so that he may release the sons of Israel from his land.

3 But I will harden his heart, and I will multiply my signs and wonders in the land of Egypt,

4 and he will not listen to you. And I will send my hand over Egypt, and I will lead my army and my people, the sons of Israel, from the land of Egypt, through very great judgments.

5 And the Egyptians will know that I am the Lord, who has extended my hand over Egypt, and who has led the sons of Israel from their midst."

6 And so, Moses and Aaron did just as the Lord had instructed. And so it was done.

7 Now Moses was eighty years old, and Aaron eighty-three, when they spoke to Pharaoh.

8 And the Lord said to Moses and Aaron:

9 "When Pharaoh will say to you, 'Show signs,' you shall say to Aaron, 'Take your staff, and cast it down before Pharaoh, and it will be turned into a snake.' "

10 And so Moses and Aaron entered to Pharaoh, and they did just as the Lord had commanded. And Aaron took the staff in the sight of Pharaoh and his servants, and it was turned into a snake.

11 Then Pharaoh called the wise men and the sorcerers. And they also, by Egyptian incantations and certain secrets, did similarly.

12 And each one cast down their staffs, and they were turned into serpents. But the staff of Aaron devoured their staffs.

13 And the heart of Pharaoh was hardened, and he did not listen to them, just as the Lord had instructed.

14 Then the Lord said to Moses: "The heart of Pharaoh has been hardened; he is not willing to release the people.

15 Go to him in the morning; behold, he will go out to the waters. And you will stand to meet him above the bank of the river. And you will take, in your hand, the staff that was turned into a serpent.

16 And you will say to him: 'The Lord God of the Hebrews sent me to you, saying: Release my people in order to sacrifice to me in the desert. And even until the present time, you were not willing to listen.

17 Therefore, thus says the Lord: In this you will know that I am the Lord. Behold, I will strike, with the staff that is in my hand, the water of the river, and it will be turned into blood.

18 Also, the fishes that are in the river will die, and the waters will be polluted, and the Egyptians will be afflicted when they drink the water of the river.' "

19 The Lord also said to Moses: "Say to Aaron: 'Take your staff; and extend your hand over the waters of Egypt, and over their rivers and streams and marshes and all the pools of waters, so that they may be turned into blood. And let there be blood throughout all the land of Egypt, as much in vessels of wood as in those of stone.' "

20 And Moses and Aaron did just as the Lord had instructed. And lifting up the staff, he struck the water of the river in the sight of Pharaoh and his servants. And it was turned into blood.

21 And the fishes that were in the river died, and the river was polluted, and the Egyptians were not able to drink the water of the river, and there was blood throughout the entire land of Egypt.

22 And the sorcerers of the Egyptians, with their incantations, did similarly. And the heart of Pharaoh was hardened, he did not listen to them, just as the Lord had instructed.

23 And he turned himself away, and he entered his house, neither did he apply his heart to this turn of events.

24 Then all the Egyptians dug along the borders of the river for water to drink. For they were not able to drink from the water of the river.

25 And seven days were completed, after the Lord struck the river.

Exodus 8

1 The Lord also said to Moses: "Enter to Pharaoh, and you will say to him: 'Thus says the Lord: Release my people in order to sacrifice to me.

2 But if you are not willing to release them, behold, I will strike all your coasts with frogs.

3 And the river will seethe with frogs, which will go up and enter into your house, and your bedroom, and upon your bed, and into the houses of your servants and your people, and into your ovens, and into the remains of your foods.

4 And to you, and to your people, and to all your servants, the frogs will enter.' "

5 And the Lord said to Moses: "Say to Aaron: 'Extend your hand over the rivers, and also over the streams and the marshes, and bring forth frogs over the land of Egypt.' "

6 And Aaron extended his hand over the waters of Egypt, and the frogs came up and covered the land of Egypt.

7 Then the sorcerers also, by their incantations, did similarly, and they brought forth frogs upon the land of Egypt.

8 But Pharaoh called Moses and Aaron, and he said to them: "Pray to the Lord, so as to take away the frogs from me and from my people. And I will release the people, so as to sacrifice to the Lord."

9 And Moses said to Pharaoh: "Appoint for me a time, when I should petition on behalf of you, and your servants, and your people, so that the frogs may be driven away from you, and from your house, and from your servants, and from your people, and so that they may remain only in the river."

10 And he responded, "Tomorrow." Then he said, "I will act according to your word, so that you may know that there is no one like the Lord our God.

11 And the frogs will withdraw from you, and from your house, and from your servants, and from your people. And they will remain only in the river."

12 And Moses and Aaron departed from Pharaoh. And Moses cried out to the Lord on behalf of the promise that he had made to Pharaoh concerning the frogs.

13 And the Lord acted according to the word of Moses. And the frogs died out of the houses, and out of the villages, and out of the fields.

14 And they gathered them together into immense piles, and the land was polluted.

15 Then Pharaoh, seeing that relief had been provided, hardened his own heart, and he did not listen to them, just as the Lord had instructed.

16 And the Lord said to Moses: "Say to Aaron: 'Extend your staff and strike the dust of the earth. And let there be stinging insects throughout the entire the land of Egypt.' "

17 And they did so. And Aaron extended his hand, holding the staff, and he struck the dust of the earth, and there came stinging insects upon men and upon beasts. All the dust of the earth was turned into stinging insects through all the land of Egypt.

18 And the sorcerers, with their incantations, did similarly, in order to bring forth stinging insects, but they were not able. And there were stinging insects, as much on men as on beasts.

19 And the sorcerers said to Pharaoh: "This is the finger of God." And the heart of Pharaoh was hardened, and he did not listen to them, just as the Lord had instructed.

20 The Lord also said to Moses: "Arise at first light, and stand in the sight of Pharaoh, for he will go out to the waters. And you will say to him: 'Thus says the Lord: Release my people to sacrifice to me.

21 But if you will not release them, behold, I will send upon you, and upon your servants, and upon your people, and into your houses, diverse kinds of flies. And the houses of the Egyptians will be filled with diverse kinds of flies, as well as the whole land in which they will be.

22 And in that day, I will cause a miracle in the land of Goshen, where my people are, so that flies will not be there. And you will know that I am the Lord in the midst of the earth.

23 And I will set a division between my people and your people. Tomorrow this sign will be.' "

24 And the Lord did so. And there came very grievous flies into the houses of Pharaoh and of his servants, and into all the land of Egypt. And the land was polluted, in this way, by the flies.

25 And Pharaoh called Moses and Aaron, and he said to them, "Go and sacrifice to your God in this land."

26 And Moses said: "It cannot be so. For we will immolate the abominations of the Egyptians to the Lord our God. For if we slaughter those things which the Egyptians worship, in their presence, they will stone us.

27 We will sojourn three days' journey into the wilderness. And we will sacrifice to the Lord our God, just as he has instructed us."

28 And Pharaoh said: "I will release you in order to sacrifice to the Lord your God in the desert. Yet you may only go so far. Petition for me."

29 And Moses said: "After departing from you, I will pray to the Lord. And the flies will withdraw from Pharaoh, and from his servants, and from his people, tomorrow. Yet do not be willing to deceive any longer, so that you would not release the people to sacrifice to the Lord."

30 And Moses, departing from Pharaoh, prayed to the Lord.

31 And he acted according to his word. And he took away the flies from Pharaoh, and from his servants, and from his people. There was not even one left behind.

32 And the heart of Pharaoh was hardened, so that, even at this turn, he would not release the people.

Exodus 9

1 Then the Lord said to Moses: "Enter to Pharaoh, and say to him: 'Thus says the Lord God of the Hebrews: Release my people, to sacrifice to me.

2 But if you still refuse, and you retain them,

3 behold, my hand will be over your fields. And a very grievous pestilence will be upon the horses, and the donkeys, and the camels, and the oxen, and the sheep.

4 And the Lord will cause a miracle between the possessions of Israel and the possessions of the Egyptians, so that nothing at all will perish from those things which belong to the sons of Israel."

5 And the Lord appointed a time, saying: "Tomorrow, the Lord will accomplish this word in the land."

6 Therefore, the Lord accomplished this word the next day. And all the animals of the Egyptians died. Yet truly, of the animals of the sons of Israel, nothing at all perished.

7 And Pharaoh sent to see; neither was there anything dead of those things that Israel possessed. And the heart of Pharaoh was hardened, and he did not release the people.

8 And the Lord said to Moses and to Aaron: "Take handfuls of ashes from the oven, and let Moses sprinkle it into the air, in the sight of Pharaoh.

9 And let there be dust upon all the land of Egypt. For there will be sores and swelling pustules on men and on beasts, throughout the entire land of Egypt."

10 And they took ashes from the oven, and they stood in the sight of Pharaoh, and Moses sprinkled it in the air. And there came sores with swelling pustules on men and on beasts.

11 Neither could the sorcerers stand in the sight of Moses, because of the sores that were on them and on all the land of Egypt.

12 And the Lord hardened the heart of Pharaoh, and he did not listen to them, just as the Lord said to Moses.

13 And the Lord said to Moses: "Rise up in the morning, and stand in the sight of Pharaoh, and you will say to him: 'Thus says the Lord God of the Hebrews: Release my people to sacrifice to me.

14 For at this turn, I will send all my plagues upon your heart, and upon your servants, and upon your people. So may you know that there is no one like me in all the earth.

15 For now, extending my hand, I shall strike you and your people with pestilence, and you will perish from the earth.

16 But it was for this reason that I appointed you, so that I may reveal my strength by you, and so that my name may be described throughout all the earth.

17 Do you still retain my people, and are you still unwilling to release them?

18 So then, tomorrow, at this same hour, I will rain down exceedingly great hail, such as has not been in Egypt from the day that it was founded, even until this present time.

19 Therefore, send immediately and gather together your cattle, and all that you have in the field. For men and beasts, and all things that will be found outside, not gathered in from the fields, and on which the hail will fall, shall die.' "

20 He who feared the word of the Lord among the servants of Pharaoh caused his servants and cattle to flee together into the houses.

21 But he who neglected the word of the Lord released his servants and cattle into the fields.

22 And the Lord said to Moses: "Extend your hand into the sky, so that there may be hail in the entire land of Egypt, on men, and on beasts, and on every plant of the field in the land of Egypt."

23 And Moses extended his staff into the sky, and the Lord sent thunder and hail, and also lightning dashing across the earth. And the Lord rained down hail upon the land of Egypt.

24 And the hail and intermingled fire drove on together. And it was of such magnitude as had never before been seen in the entire land of Egypt, from the time when that nation was formed.

25 And the hail struck, throughout all the land of Egypt, everything that was in the fields, from man even to beast. And the hail struck down every plant of the field, and it broke every tree of the region.

26 Only in the land of Goshen, where the sons of Israel were, did the hail not fall.

27 And Pharaoh sent and called Moses and Aaron, saying to them: "I have sinned even until now. The Lord is just. I and my people are impious.

28 Pray to the Lord, so that the thundering of God and the hail may cease, so that I may release you, and so that you may by no means remain here any longer."

29 Moses said: "When I have departed from the city, I will extend my hands to the Lord, and the thunders will cease, and the hail will not be, so that you may know that the earth belongs to the Lord.

30 But I know that both you and your servants do not yet fear the Lord God."

31 And so, the flax and the barley were damaged, because the barley was growing, and the flax was already developing grains.

32 But the wheat and the spelt were not damaged, because they were late.

33 And Moses, departing from Pharaoh out of the city, reached out his hands toward the Lord. And the thunders and hail ceased, neither did there drop any more rain upon the land.

34 Then Pharaoh, seeing that the rain, and the hail, and the thunders had ceased, added to his sin.

35 And his heart was weighed down, along with that of his servants, and it was hardened exceedingly. Neither did he release the sons of Israel, just as the Lord had instructed by the hand of Moses.

Exodus 10

1 And the Lord said to Moses: "Enter to Pharaoh. For I have hardened his heart, and that of his servants, so that I may accomplish these, my signs, in him,

2 and so that you may describe to the ears of your sons and your grandsons how often I opposed the Egyptians and wrought my signs among them, and so that you may know that I am the Lord."

3 Therefore, Moses and Aaron entered to Pharaoh, and they said to him: "Thus says the Lord God of the Hebrews: How long will you be unwilling to be subject to me? Release my people to sacrifice to me.

4 But if you resist, and you are unwilling to release them, behold, tomorrow I will bring locusts into your borders.

5 And they shall cover the face of the earth, lest any part of it be seen. Yes, and what remains from the hail shall be eaten. For they will gnaw away all the trees that spring up in the fields.

6 And they will fill your houses, and those of your servants and of all the Egyptians: so many as your fathers and ancestors have not seen, from the time that they rose up over the earth, even until this present day." And he turned himself away, and he departed from Pharaoh.

7 Then the servants of Pharaoh said to him: "How long must we endure this scandal? Release the men, in order to sacrifice to the Lord their God. Do you not see that Egypt is perishing?"

8 And they called back Moses and Aaron to Pharaoh, who said to them: "Go, sacrifice to the Lord your God. Who are they who would go?"

9 Moses said: "We will travel with our little ones and our elderly, with our sons and daughters, with our sheep and herds. For it is a solemnity of the Lord our God."

10 And Pharaoh responded: "So let the Lord be with you. But if I were to release you and your little ones, who would doubt that you intend some great wickedness?

11 It will not be so. However, go only with the men, and sacrifice to the Lord. For this, too, is what you yourselves requested." And immediately they were cast out from the sight of Pharaoh.

12 Then the Lord said to Moses: "Extend your hand over the land of Egypt, toward the locusts, so that they may rise up over it, and devour every plant which remains from the hail."

13 And Moses extended his staff over the land of Egypt. And the Lord brought a burning wind all that day and night. And when morning came, the burning wind lifted up the locusts.

14 And they ascended over the entire land of Egypt. And they settled into all the parts of the Egyptians: innumerable, such as had not been before that time, nor ever would be thereafter.

15 And they covered the entire face of the land, laying waste to all things. And the plants of the land were devoured, along with whatever fruits were on the trees, which the hail had left behind. And nothing at all of the greenery remained on the trees or on the plants of the earth in all of Egypt.

16 For this reason, Pharaoh hurriedly called Moses and Aaron, and he said to them: "I have sinned against the Lord your God, and against you.

17 But now, release me from my sin even this time, and petition the Lord your God, so that he may take this death away from me."

18 And Moses, departing from the sight of Pharaoh, prayed to the Lord.

19 And he caused a very strong wind to blow from the west, and, seizing the locusts, it cast them into the Red Sea. There remained not so much as one in all the parts of Egypt.

20 And the Lord hardened the heart of Pharaoh; neither did he release the sons of Israel.

21 Then the Lord said to Moses: "Extend your hand into the sky. And let there be a darkness over the land of Egypt, so dense that they may be able to feel it."

22 And Moses extended his hand into the sky. And there came a horrible darkness in the entire land of Egypt for three days.

23 No one saw his brother, nor moved himself out of the place where he was. But wherever the sons of Israel were living, there was light.

24 And Pharaoh called Moses and Aaron, and he said to them: "Go, sacrifice to the Lord. Only let your sheep and herds remain behind. Your little ones may go with you."

25 Moses said: "You must also permit us victims and holocausts, which we may offer to the Lord our God.

26 All the flocks shall travel with us. Not one hoof of them shall remain behind. For they are necessary for the worship of the Lord our God, especially since we do not know what ought to be immolated, until we arrive at the very place."

27 But the Lord hardened the heart of Pharaoh, and he was not willing to release them.

28 And Pharaoh said to Moses: "Withdraw from me, and beware that you no longer see my face. On whatever day you will appear in my sight, you shall die."

29 Moses responded: "So be it, just as you have said. I will no longer see your face."

Exodus 11

1 And the Lord said to Moses: "I will touch Pharaoh and Egypt with one more plague, and after these things he will release you, and he will compel you to go out.

2 Therefore, you will tell all the people to ask, a man of his friend, and a woman of her neighbor, for vessels of silver and of gold.

3 Then the Lord will grant favor to his people in the sight of the Egyptians." And Moses was a very great man in the land of Egypt, in the sight of the servants of Pharaoh and of all the people.

4 And he said: "Thus says the Lord: 'In the middle of the night I will enter into Egypt.

5 And every firstborn in the land of the Egyptians shall die, from the firstborn of Pharaoh, who sits on his throne, even to the firstborn of the handmaid, who is at the millstone, and all the firstborn of the beasts of burden.

6 And there will be a great outcry throughout the entire land of Egypt, such as has not been before, nor ever will be afterward.

7 But among all the sons of Israel there shall not be even a mutter from a dog, from man, even to cattle, so that you may know how miraculously the Lord divides the Egyptians from Israel.'

8 And all these, your servants, shall descend to me and shall reverence me, by saying: 'Depart, you and all the people who are subject to you.' After these things, we will depart."

9 And he went out from Pharaoh exceedingly angry. Then the Lord said to Moses: "Pharaoh will not listen to you, so that many signs may be accomplished in the land of Egypt."

10 Now Moses and Aaron did all the wonders that are written, in the sight of Pharaoh. And the Lord hardened the heart of Pharaoh; neither did he release the sons of Israel from his land.

Exodus 12

1 The Lord also said to Moses and Aaron in the land of Egypt:

2 "This month will be for you the beginning of the months. It will be first in the months of the year.

3 Speak to the entire assembly of the sons of Israel, and say to them: On the tenth day of this month, let everyone take a lamb, by their families and houses.

4 But if the number is less than may suffice to be able to consume the lamb, he shall accept his neighbor, who has been joined with his house according to the number of souls that may suffice to be able to eat the lamb.

5 And it shall be a lamb without blemish, a one year old male. According to this rite, you shall also take a young goat.

6 And you shall keep it until the fourteenth day of this month. And the entire multitude of the sons of Israel shall immolate it toward evening.

7 And they shall take from its blood, and place it on both the door posts and the upper threshold of the houses, in which they will consume it.

8 And that night they shall eat the flesh, roasted by fire, and unleavened bread with wild lettuce.

9 You shall not consume anything from it raw, nor boiled in water, but only roasted by fire. You shall devour the head with its feet and entrails.

10 Neither shall there remain anything from it until morning. If anything will have been left over, you shall burn it with fire.

11 Now you shall consume it in this way: You shall gird your waist, and you shall have shoes on your feet, holding staves in your hands, and you shall consume it in haste. For it is the Passover (that is, the Crossing) of the Lord.

12 And I will cross through the land of Egypt that night, and I will strike down all the firstborn in the land of Egypt, from man, even to cattle. And I will bring judgments against all the gods of Egypt. I am the Lord.

13 But the blood will be for you as a sign in the buildings where you will be. And I will see the blood, and I will pass over you. And the plague will not be with you to destroy, when I strike the land of Egypt.

14 Then you shall have this day as a memorial, and you shall celebrate it as a solemnity to the Lord, in your generations, as an everlasting devotion.

15 For seven days, you shall eat unleavened bread. On the first day there shall be no leaven in your houses. Whoever will consume anything leavened, from the first day, even until the seventh day, that soul shall perish from Israel.

16 The first day shall be holy and solemn, and the seventh day shall be venerated with the same festivity. You shall do no work in these days, except that which pertains to the eating.

17 And you shall observe the feast of unleavened bread. For on this same day, I will lead your army out of the land of Egypt, and you shall keep this day, in your generations, as a perpetual ritual.

18 In the first month, on the fourteenth day of the month, toward evening, you shall consume the unleavened bread, until the twenty-first day of the same month, toward evening.

19 For seven days, there shall not be found leaven in your houses. Whoever will eat leaven, his soul will perish from the assembly of Israel, as much with the newcomers as with the natives of the land.

20 You shall not consume any leaven. In all your dwelling places, you shall eat unleavened bread."

21 Then Moses called all the elders of the sons of Israel, and he said to them: "Go, taking an animal by your families, and sacrifice the Passover.

22 And dip a little bundle of hyssop in the blood which is at the entrance, and sprinkle the upper threshold with it, and both of the door posts. Let none of you go out of the door of his house until morning.

23 For the Lord will cross through, striking the Egyptians. And when he will see the blood on the upper threshold, and on both the door posts, he will pass over the door of the house and not permit the Striker to enter into your houses or to do harm.

24 You shall keep this word as a law for you and for your sons, forever.

25 And when you have entered into the land that the Lord will give to you, just as he has promised, you shall observe these ceremonies.

26 And when your sons will say to you, 'What is the meaning of this religious observance?'

27 You shall say to them: 'It is the victim of the crossing of the Lord, when he passed over the houses of the sons of Israel in Egypt, striking the Egyptians, and freeing our houses.' " And the people, bowing down, worshipped.

28 And the sons of Israel, departing, did just as the Lord had instructed Moses and Aaron.

29 Then it happened, in the middle of the night: the Lord struck down every firstborn in the land of Egypt, from the firstborn of Pharaoh, who sits on his throne, even to the firstborn of the captive woman who was in prison, and all the firstborn of the cattle.

30 And Pharaoh rose up in the night, and all his servants, and all of Egypt. And there arose a great outcry in Egypt. For there was not a house in which no one lay dead.

31 And Pharaoh, calling Moses and Aaron in the night, said: "Rise up and go forth from among my people, you and the sons of Israel. Go, sacrifice to the Lord, just as you say.

32 Your sheep and herds take along with you, as you requested, and as you go away, bless me."

33 And the Egyptians urged the people to go away from the land quickly, saying, "We will all die."

34 Therefore, the people took bread dough before it was leavened. And tying it in their cloaks, they placed it on their shoulders.

35 And the sons of Israel did just as Moses had instructed. And they petitioned the Egyptians for vessels of silver and of gold, and very many garments.

36 Then the Lord granted favor to the people in the sight of the Egyptians, so that they bestowed on them. And they despoiled the Egyptians.

37 And the sons of Israel set out from Rameses to Soccoth, about six hundred thousand men on foot, besides little ones.

38 But also an innumerable mix of common people ascended with them, sheep and herds and animals of diverse kinds, exceedingly many.

39 And they baked the bread, which a little while ago they had taken out of Egypt as dough. And they made unleavened bread baked under ashes. For it was not able to be leavened, with the Egyptians compelling them to leave and not permitting them to cause any delay. Neither did they have occasion to prepare any meat.

40 Now the habitation of the sons of Israel, while they remained in Egypt, was four hundred and thirty years.

41 Having been completed, on the same day all the army of the Lord departed from the land of Egypt.

42 This night is a worthy observance of the Lord, when he led them out of the land of Egypt. This all the sons of Israel must observe in their generations.

43 And the Lord said to Moses and to Aaron: "This is the religious observance of the Passover. No foreigner shall eat from it.

44 But every bought servant shall be circumcised, and so he may eat from it.

45 The newcomer and the hired hand shall not eat from it.

46 In one house it shall be eaten; you shall not carry its flesh outside, nor shall you break its bone.

47 The entire assembly of the sons of Israel shall do this.

48 And if any sojourner will be willing to cross over into your settlement, and to keep the Passover of the Lord, all his males shall first be circumcised, and then he shall celebrate the rite. And he shall be just like a native of the land. But if any man is not circumcised, he shall not eat from it.

49 The law shall be the same for the native born and for the settler who sojourns with you."

50 And all the sons of Israel did just as the Lord had instructed Moses and Aaron.

51 And on the same day, the Lord led the sons of Israel out of the land of Egypt by their companies.

Exodus 13

1 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

2 "Sanctify to me every firstborn which opens the womb among the sons of Israel, as much of men as of cattle. For they are all mine."

3 And Moses said to the people: "Remember this day, on which you were taken away from Egypt and from the house of servitude. For with a strong hand the Lord has led you away from this place. Thus, you shall eat no leavened bread.

4 Today, you go forth in the month of new grain.

5 And when the Lord has brought you into the land of the Canaanite, and the Hittite, and the Amorite, and the Hivite, and the Jebusite, which he swore to your fathers that he would give to you, a land flowing with milk and honey, you will celebrate this manner of sacred rites in this month.

6 For seven days, you shall feed on unleavened bread. And on the seventh day, it will be the solemnity of the Lord.

7 You shall consume unleavened bread for seven days. There shall not be seen anything leavened with you, nor in all your parts.

8 And you will explain to your son in that day, saying: 'This is what the Lord did for me when I was taken away from Egypt.'

9 And it will be like a sign in your hand and like a memorial before your eyes. And so may the law of the Lord be always in your mouth. For with a strong hand, the Lord led you away from the land of Egypt.

10 You will keep this observance, at the established time, from day to day.

11 And when the Lord has brought you into the land of the Canaanite, just as he swore to you and to your fathers, and when he will give it you,

12 then you shall set aside for the Lord all that opens the womb and all that is first to go forth among your cattle. Whatever you will have of the male sex, you shall consecrate to the Lord.

13 The firstborn of a donkey you will exchange for a sheep. And if you will not redeem it, you shall put it to death. But every firstborn of man among your sons, you shall redeem with a price.

14 And when your son will question you tomorrow, saying, 'What is this?' you will respond, 'With a strong hand the Lord led us away from the land of Egypt, from the house of servitude.

15 For when Pharaoh had been hardened and was unwilling to release us, the Lord killed every firstborn in the land of Egypt, from the firstborn of man, even to the firstborn of beasts. For this reason, I immolate to the Lord all of the male sex that opens the womb, and all the firstborn of my sons I redeem.'

16 Therefore, it will be like a sign in your hand and like something hanging between your eyes as a remembrance, because with a strong hand the Lord has led us away from Egypt."

17 And so, when Pharaoh had sent the people away, God did not lead them by the way of the land of the Philistines, which is nearby, considering that perhaps they might relapse, if they saw wars rise up against them, and then they might return to Egypt.

18 But he led them around by the way of the desert, which is next to the Red Sea. And so the sons of Israel ascended, armed, out of the land of Egypt.

19 Also, Moses took the bones of Joseph with him, because he had sworn to the sons of Israel, saying: "God will visit you. Carry my bones away from here with you."

20 And setting out from Soccoth, they encamped at Etham, in the most distant parts of the wilderness.

21 Now the Lord preceded them to show them the way, by day with a pillar of cloud, and by night with a pillar of fire, so that he might be the leader of their journey at both times.

22 These never failed: a pillar of cloud by day, and a pillar of fire by night, in the sight of the people.

Exodus 14

1 Then the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

2 "Speak to the sons of Israel. Let them turn back and encamp away from the region of Pihahiroth, which is between Migdol and the sea, opposite Baal-zephon. In its sight you shall place your camp, above the sea.

3 And Pharaoh will say about the sons of Israel, 'They have been confined by the land; the desert has enclosed them.'

4 And I will harden his heart, and so he will pursue you. And I will be glorified in Pharaoh, and in all his army. And the Egyptians will know that I am the Lord." And they did so.

5 And it was reported to the king of the Egyptians that the people had fled. And the heart of Pharaoh and of his servants was changed about the people, and they said, "What did we intend to do, so that we released Israel from serving us?"

6 Therefore, he harnessed his chariot, and he took all his people with him.

7 And he took six hundred chosen chariots, and whatever chariots were in Egypt, and also the leaders of the whole army.

8 And the Lord hardened the heart of Pharaoh, king of Egypt, and he pursued the sons of Israel. But they were taken away by an exalted hand.

9 And when the Egyptians followed the footsteps of those who preceded them, they found them in a camp above the sea. All the horses and chariots of Pharaoh, and the entire army, were in Pihahiroth, opposite Baal-zephon.

10 And when Pharaoh had drawn near, the sons of Israel, lifting up their eyes, saw the Egyptians behind them. And they were very afraid. And they cried out to the Lord.

11 And they said to Moses: "Perhaps there were no graves in Egypt, for which reason you took us to die in the wilderness. What is it that you intended to do, in leading us out of Egypt?

12 Is this not the word that we spoke to you in Egypt, saying: Withdraw from us, so that we may serve the Egyptians? For it was much better to serve them, than to die in the wilderness."

13 And Moses said to the people: "Do not be afraid. Stand firm and see the great wonders of the Lord, which he will do today. For the Egyptians, whom you now see, will never again be seen, forever.

14 The Lord will fight on your behalf, and you will remain silent."

15 And the Lord said to Moses: "Why cry out to me? Tell the sons of Israel to continue on.

16 Now, lift up your staff, and extend your hand over the sea and divide it, so that the sons of Israel may walk through the midst of the sea on dry ground.

17 Then I will harden the heart of the Egyptians, so as to pursue you. And I will be glorified in Pharaoh, and in all his army, and in his chariots, and in his horsemen.

18 And the Egyptians will know that I am the Lord, when I will be glorified in Pharaoh, and in his chariots, as well as in his horsemen."

19 And the Angel of God, who preceded the camp of Israel, lifting himself up, went behind them. And the pillar of cloud, together with him, left the front for the rear

20 and stood between the camp of the Egyptians and the camp of Israel. And it was a dark cloud, yet it illuminated the night, so that they could not succeed at approaching one another at any time all that night.

21 And when Moses had extended his hand over the sea, the Lord took it away by an intense burning wind, blowing throughout the night, and he turned it into dry ground. And the water was divided.

22 And the sons of Israel went in through the midst of the dried sea. For the water was like a wall at their right hand and at their left hand.

23 And the Egyptians, pursuing them, went in after them, along with all of the horses of Pharaoh, his chariots and horsemen, through the midst of the sea.

24 And now the morning watch had arrived, and behold, the Lord, looking down upon the camp of the Egyptians through the pillar of fire and of cloud, put to death their army.

25 And he overturned the wheels of the chariots, and they were carried into the deep. Therefore, the Egyptians said: "Let us flee from Israel. For the Lord fights on their behalf against us."

26 And the Lord said to Moses: "Extend your hand over the sea, so that the waters may return on the Egyptians, over their chariots and horsemen."

27 And when Moses had extended his hand opposite the sea, it was returned, at first light, to its former place. And the fleeing Egyptians met with the waters, and the Lord immersed them in the midst of the waves.

28 And the waters were returned, and they covered the chariots and horsemen of the entire army of Pharaoh, who, in following, had entered into the sea. And not so much as one of them was left alive.

29 But the sons of Israel continued directly through the midst of the dried sea, and the waters were to them like a wall on the right and on the left.

30 And so the Lord freed Israel on that day from the hand of the Egyptians.

31 And they saw the Egyptians dead on the shore of the sea and the great hand that the Lord had exercised against them. And the people feared the Lord, and they believed in the Lord and in Moses his servant.

Exodus 15

1 Then Moses and the sons of Israel sang this song to the Lord, and they said: "Let us sing to the Lord, for he has been gloriously magnified: the horse and the rider he has cast into the sea.

2 The Lord is my strength and my praise, and he has become my salvation. He is my God, and I shall glorify him. He is the God of my father, and I shall exalt him.

3 The Lord is like a fighting man. Almighty is his name.

4 The chariots of Pharaoh, and his army, he has cast into the sea; his elect leaders have been submerged in the Red Sea.

5 The abyss has covered them. They descended into the depths like a stone.

6 Your right hand, O Lord, has been magnified in strength. Your right hand, O Lord, has struck down the enemy.

7 And in the multitude of your glory you have put down your adversaries. You sent out your wrath, which devoured them like stubble.

8 And by the breath of your fury, the waters were gathered together. The flowing waves stood still. The abyss was gathered into the midst of the sea.

9 The enemy said: 'I will pursue and overtake them. I will divide the spoils. My soul will be filled. I will unsheathe my sword. My hand will put them to death.'

10 Your breath blew, and the sea covered them. They were submerged like lead into the mighty waters.

11 Who is like you in strength, O Lord? Who is like you: magnificent in sanctity, terrible and yet praiseworthy, accomplishing miracles?

12 You extended your hand, and the earth devoured them.

13 In your mercy, you have been a leader to the people whom you have redeemed. And in your strength, you have carried them to your holy dwelling place.

14 Peoples rose up and became angry. Sorrows took hold of the inhabitants of Philistia.

15 Then the leaders of Edom were stirred up, and trembling took hold of the robust of Moab. All the inhabitants of Canaan were petrified.

16 Let fear and dread fall upon them, by the magnitude of your arm. Let them become immobilized like stone, until your people cross through, O Lord, until this, your people whom you possess, cross through.

17 You shall lead them in and plant them, on the mountain of your inheritance, in your most firm dwelling place, which you have formed, O Lord, your sanctuary, O Lord, which your hands have made firm.

18 The Lord will reign in eternity and beyond.

19 For the rider Pharaoh, with his chariots and horsemen, was brought into the sea. And the Lord brought back upon them the waters of the sea. But the sons of Israel walked across dry ground in its midst."

20 And so Miriam, the prophetess, the sister of Aaron, took up a timbrel in her hand. And all the women followed her with timbrels and dancing.

21 And she prophesied, saying: "Let us sing to the Lord, for he has been gloriously magnified. The horse and its rider, he has thrown into the sea."

22 Then Moses took Israel from the Red Sea, and they went forth into the desert of Shur. And they wandered for three days through the wilderness, and they found no water.

23 And they arrived at Marah. They were unable to drink the waters of Marah because they were bitter. Therefore, he also established a name befitting the place, calling it 'Marah,' that is, bitterness.

24 And the people murmured against Moses, saying: "What shall we drink?"

25 So he cried out to the Lord, who showed him a tree. And when he had cast it into the waters, they were turned into sweetness. In that place, he established instructions for him, and also judgments. And he tested him there,

26 saying: "If you will listen to the voice of the Lord your God, and do what is right in his sight, and obey his commands, and keep all his precepts, I will not bring upon you any of the distress that I imposed on Egypt. For I am the Lord, your healer."

27 Then the sons of Israel arrived in Elim, where there were twelve fountains of water and seventy palm trees. And they camped next to the waters.

Exodus 16

1 And they set out from Elim. And the entire multitude of the sons of Israel arrived at the desert of Sin, which is between Elim and Sinai, on the fifteenth day of the second month, after they departed from the land of Egypt.

2 And the entire congregation of the sons of Israel murmured against Moses and Aaron in the wilderness.

3 And the sons of Israel said to them: "If only we had died by the hand of the Lord in the land of Egypt, when we sat around bowls of meat and ate bread until filled. Why have you led us away, into this desert, so that you might kill the entire multitude with famine?"

4 Then the Lord said to Moses: "Behold, I will rain down bread from heaven for you. Let the people go out and collect what is sufficient for each day, so that I may test them, as to whether or not they will walk in my law.

5 But on the sixth day, let them prepare what they use for carrying, and let there be double what they were accustomed to collect on a single day."

6 And Moses and Aaron said to the sons of Israel: "In the evening, you will know that the Lord has led you away from the land of Egypt.

7 And in the morning, you will see the glory of the Lord. For he has heard your murmuring against the Lord. But as for us, truly what are we, that you would whisper against us?"

8 And Moses said: "In the evening, the Lord will give you flesh to eat, and in the morning, bread in fullness. For he has heard your murmurings that you have murmured against him. For what are we? Your murmuring is not against us, but against the Lord."

9 Moses also said to Aaron: "Say to the whole congregation of the sons of Israel, 'Approach before the Lord. For he has heard your murmuring.' "

10 And when Aaron spoke to the entire assembly of the sons of Israel, they looked out toward the wilderness. And behold, the glory of the Lord appeared in a cloud.

11 Then the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

12 "I have heard the murmuring of the sons of Israel. Say to them: 'In the evening, you will eat flesh, and in the morning, you will be filled with bread. And you shall know that I am the Lord your God.' "

13 Therefore, it happened in the evening: quails, rising up, covered the camp. Likewise, in the morning, a dew lay all around the camp.

14 And when it had covered the face of the earth, it appeared, in the wilderness, small and as if crushed with a pestle, similar to hoar-frost on the ground.

15 When the sons of Israel had seen it, they said one to another: "Manhu?" which means "What is this?" For they did not know what it was. And Moses said to them: "This is the bread that the Lord has given you to eat.

16 This is the word that the Lord has instructed. Let each one collect as much of it as is sufficient to eat. One omer for each head. According to the number of your souls which live in a tent, so will you take of it."

17 And the sons of Israel did so. And they collected: some more, others less.

18 And they measured by the measure of an omer. He who collected more, did not have too much; nor did he who prepared less, find too little. But each one gathered according to what they were able to eat.

19 And Moses said to them, "Let no one leave any of it behind until morning."

20 And they did not listen to him, but they left some of it behind until morning, and it began to swarm with worms, and it putrefied. And Moses became angry against them.

21 Then each one collected, in the morning, as much as would be sufficient to eat. And after the sun became hot, it melted.

22 But on the sixth day, they collected a double portion, that is, two omers for each man. Then all the leaders among the multitude came, and they discoursed with Moses.

23 And he said to them: "This is what the Lord has spoken: Tomorrow, the rest day of the Sabbath, has been sanctified to the Lord. Whatever would be done, do it now. And whatever would be cooked, cook it now. Then anything that will have been left over, store it until morning."

24 And they did just as Moses had instructed, and it did not putrefy, nor were there any worms found in it.

25 And Moses said: "Eat it today, because it is the Sabbath of the Lord. Today it will not be found in the field.

26 Gather for six days. But on the seventh day, it is the Sabbath of the Lord, for which reason it will not be found."

27 And the seventh day arrived. And some of the people, going out to collect it, did not find it.

28 Then the Lord said to Moses: "How long will you be unwilling to keep my commandments and my law?

29 See how the Lord has given you the Sabbath, and, because of this, on the sixth day he distributes to you a double portion. Let each one remain with his own, and let no one go forth from his place on the seventh day."

30 And the people kept the Sabbath on the seventh day.

31 And the house of Israel called its name 'Manna.' It was like white coriander seed, and its taste was like wheat flour with honey.

32 Then Moses said: "This is the word that the Lord has instructed: Fill an omer of it, and let it be kept for future generations hereafter, so that they may know the bread, with which I nourished you in the wilderness, when you had been led away from the land of Egypt."

33 And Moses said to Aaron, "Take one vessel, and put manna into it, as much as an omer is able to hold. And store it in the sight of the Lord, to keep for your generations,

34 just as the Lord instructed Moses." And so, Aaron placed it in the tabernacle, in reserve.

35 Now the sons of Israel ate manna for forty years, until they arrived in a habitable land. With this food they were nourished, even until they touched the borders of the land of Canaan.

36 Now an omer is a tenth part of an ephah.

Exodus 17

1 And so, the entire multitude of the sons of Israel, having set out from the desert of Sin in stages, according to the word of the Lord, made camp at Rephidim, where there was no water for the people to drink.

2 And arguing against Moses, they said, "Give us water, so that we may drink." And Moses answered them: "Why argue against me? For what reason do you tempt the Lord?"

3 And so the people were thirsty in that place, due to the scarcity of water, and they murmured against Moses, saying: "Why did you cause us to go out of Egypt, so as to kill us and our children, as well as our cattle, with thirst?"

4 Then Moses cried out to the Lord, saying: "What shall I do with this people? A little while more and they will stone me."

5 And the Lord said to Moses: "Go before the people, and take with you some of the elders of Israel. And take in your hand the staff, with which you struck the river, and advance.

6 Lo, I will stand in that place before you, on the rock of Horeb. And you shall strike the rock, and water will go forth from it, so that the people may drink." Moses did so in the sight of the elders of Israel.

7 And he called the name of that place 'Temptation,' because of the arguing of the sons of Israel, and because they tempted the Lord, saying: "Is the Lord with us, or not?"

8 And Amalek came and fought against Israel at Rephidim.

9 And Moses said to Joshua: "Choose men. And when you go out, fight against Amalek. Tomorrow, I will stand at the top of the hill, holding the staff of God in my hand."

10 Joshua did as Moses had spoken, and he fought against Amalek. But Moses and Aaron and Hur ascended to the top of the hill.

11 And when Moses lifted up his hands, Israel prevailed. But when he released them a little while, Amalek overcame.

12 Then the hands of Moses became heavy. And so, taking a stone, they placed it beneath him, and he sat on it. Then Aaron and Hur sustained his hands from both sides. And it happened that his hands did not tire until the setting of the sun.

13 And Joshua put to flight Amalek and his people by the edge of the sword.

14 Then the Lord said to Moses: "Write this, as a memorial in a book, and deliver it to the ears of Joshua. For I will wipe away the memory of Amalek from under heaven."

15 And Moses built an altar. And he called its name, 'The Lord, my Exaltation.' For he said:

16 "The hand of the throne of the Lord, and the war of the Lord, will be against Amalek from generation to generation."

Exodus 18

1 And when Jethro, the priest of Midian, the kinsman of Moses, had heard all that God had done for Moses, and for his people Israel, and that the Lord had led Israel away from Egypt,

2 he brought Zipporah, the wife of Moses, whom he was to return to him,

3 and her two sons, of whom one was called Gershom, (for his father said, "I have been a newcomer in a foreign land,")

4 and the other in truth was Eliezer, ("For the God of my father," he said, "is my helper, and has rescued me from the sword of Pharaoh.")

5 And so Jethro, the kinsman of Moses, with his sons and his wife, came to Moses in the desert, where he was encamped next to the mountain of God.

6 And he sent word to Moses, saying: "I, Jethro, your kinsman, have come to you, with your wife, and your two sons with her."

7 And going out to meet his kinsman, he reverenced and kissed him. And they saluted each other with peaceful words. And when he had arrived at the tent,

8 Moses explained to his kinsman all that the Lord had done to Pharaoh and to the Egyptians on behalf of Israel, and all the hardships which had befallen them on the journey, and how the Lord had freed them.

9 And Jethro was gladdened over all the good that the Lord had done for Israel, because he had rescued them from the hand of the Egyptians.

10 And he said: "Blessed is the Lord, who has freed his people from the hand of the Egyptians and from the hand of Pharaoh; he has rescued his people from the hand of Egypt.

11 Now I know that the great Lord is above all gods. This is why they acted arrogantly against them."

12 And so Jethro, the kinsman of Moses, offered holocausts and sacrifices to God. And Aaron arrived with all the elders of Israel, in order to eat bread with him in the sight of God.

13 Then, the next day, Moses sat down in order to judge the people, and they stood beside Moses from morning, even until evening.

14 And when, of course, his kinsman saw all that he did among the people, he said: "What is this that you do among the people? Why do you sit alone, while all the people stand before you, from morning, even until evening?"

15 And Moses answered him: "The people come to me seeking the verdict of God.

16 And when any kind of dispute occurs among them, they come to me to judge between them, and to reveal the precepts of God and of his laws."

17 But he said, "This is not good, what you are doing.

18 You will be consumed by foolish efforts, both you and this people who are with you. The task is beyond your strength; you will not be able bear it alone.

19 But listen to my words and counsels, and then God will be with you. Be available to the people in that which pertains to God, so as to refer what they say to him,

20 and to reveal to the people the ceremonies, and the rituals of worship, and the way by which they should progress, and the work that they should do.

21 Then provide, from all of the people, men capable and fearing God, in whom there is truth and who hate avarice, and appoint from them tribunes, and leaders of hundreds, and of fifties, and of tens,

22 who may judge the people at all times. Then, when anything greater will have occurred, they may refer it to you, and let them judge the lesser matters only. And so it may be lighter for you, the burden being divided among others.

23 If you will do this, you will fulfill the orders of God, and you will be able to uphold his precepts. And this entire people will return to their places in peace."

24 Having heard this, Moses did everything that he had suggested to him.

25 And choosing virtuous men from all of Israel, he appointed them as leaders of the people: tribunes, and leaders of hundreds, and of fifties, and of tens.

26 And they judged the people at all times. But whatever was more serious, they referred to him, and they judged easier matters only.

27 And he dismissed his kinsman, who, turning back, went to his own land.

Exodus 19

1 In the third month of the departure of Israel from the land of Egypt, in that day, they arrived in the wilderness of Sinai.

2 Thus, setting out from Raphidim, and going directly to the desert of Sinai, they encamped in the same place, and there Israel pitched their tents away from the region of the mountain.

3 Then Moses ascended to God. And the Lord called to him from the mountain, and he said: "This you shall say to the house of Jacob, and announce to the sons of Israel:

4 'You have seen what I have done to the Egyptians, in what way I carried you upon the wings of eagles and how I have taken you for myself.

5 If, therefore, you will hear my voice, and you will keep my covenant, you will be to me a particular possession out of all people. For all the earth is mine.

6 And you will be to me a priestly kingdom and a holy nation.' These are the words that you will speak to the sons of Israel."

7 Moses went, and calling together those greater by birth among the people, he set forth all the words which the Lord had commanded.

8 And all the people responded together: "Everything that the Lord has spoken, we shall do." And when Moses had related the words of the people to the Lord,

9 the Lord said to him: "Soon now, I will come to you in the mist of a cloud, so that the people may hear me speaking to you, and so that they may believe you continuously." Therefore, Moses reported the words of the people to the Lord,

10 who said to him: "Go to the people, and sanctify them today, and tomorrow, and let them wash their garments.

11 And let them be prepared on the third day. For on the third day, the Lord will descend, in the sight of all the people, over Mount Sinai.

12 And you will establish limits for the people all around, and you will say to them: 'Take care not to ascend to the mountain, and that you do not touch its parts. All who touch the mountain, shall die a death.'

13 Hands shall not touch him, but he shall be crushed with stones, or he shall be pierced through with darts. Whether it be a beast or a man, he shall not live. For when the trumpet begins to sound, perhaps they might go up toward the mountain."

14 And Moses came down from the mountain to the people, and he sanctified them. And when they had washed their garments,

15 he said to them, "Be prepared on the third day, and do not draw near to your wives."

16 And now, the third day arrived and the morning dawned. And behold, thunders began to be heard, and also lightning flashed, and a very dense cloud covered the mountain, and the noise of the trumpet resounded vehemently. And the people who were in the camp were fearful.

17 And when Moses had led them out to meet God, from the place of the camp, they stood at the base of the mountain.

18 Then all of Mount Sinai was smoking. For the Lord had descended over it with fire, and smoke ascended from it, as from a furnace. And the entire mountain was terrible.

19 And the sound of the trumpet gradually increased to be louder, and extended to be longer. Moses was speaking, and God was answering him.

20 And the Lord descended over Mount Sinai, to the very top of the mountain, and he called Moses to its summit. And when he had ascended there,

21 he said to him: "Descend, and call the people to witness, lest they might be willing to transgress the limits, so as to see the Lord, and a very great multitude of them might perish.

22 Likewise, the priests who approach toward the Lord, let them be sanctified, lest he strike them down."

23 And Moses said to the Lord: "The people are not able to ascend to Mount Sinai. For you testified, and you commanded, saying: 'Set limits around the mountain, and sanctify it.' "

24 And the Lord said to him, "Go, descend. And you shall ascend, and Aaron with you. But let not the priests or the people transgress the limits, nor ascend to the Lord, lest perhaps he may put them to death."

25 And Moses descended to the people, and he explained everything to them.

Exodus 20

1 And the Lord spoke all these words:

2 "I am the Lord your God, who led you away from the land of Egypt, out of the house of servitude.

3 You shall not have strange gods before me.

4 You shall not make for yourself a graven image, nor a likeness of anything that is in heaven above or on earth below, nor of those things which are in the waters under the earth.

5 You shall not adore them, nor shall you worship them. I am the Lord your God: strong, zealous, visiting the iniquity of the fathers on the sons to the third and fourth generation of those who hate me,

6 and showing mercy to thousands of those who love me and keep my precepts.

7 You shall not take the name of the Lord your God in vain. For the Lord will not hold harmless one who takes the name of the Lord his God falsely.

8 Remember that you are to sanctify the day of the Sabbath.

9 For six days, you will work and accomplish all your tasks.

10 But the seventh day is the Sabbath of the Lord your God. You shall not do any work in it: you and your son and your daughter, your male servant and your female servant, your beast and the newcomer who is within your gates.

11 For in six days the Lord made heaven and earth, and the sea, and all the things that are in them, and so he rested on the seventh day. For this reason, the Lord has blessed the day of the Sabbath and sanctified it.

12 Honor your father and your mother, so that you may have a long life upon the land, which the Lord your God will give to you.

13 You shall not murder.

14 You shall not commit adultery.

15 You shall not steal.

16 You shall not speak false testimony against your neighbor.

17 You shall not covet the house of your neighbor; neither shall you desire his wife, nor male servant, nor female servant, nor ox, nor donkey, nor anything that is his."

18 Then all the people considered the voices, and the lights, and the sound of the trumpet, and the smoking mountain. And being terrified and struck with fear, they stood at a distance,

19 saying to Moses: "Speak to us, and we will listen. Let not the Lord speak to us, lest perhaps we may die."

20 And Moses said to the people: "Do not be afraid. For God came in order to test you, and so that the dread of him might be with you, and you would not sin."

21 And the people stood far away. But Moses approached toward the mist, in which was God.

22 Thereafter, the Lord said to Moses: "This you shall say to the sons of Israel: You have seen that I have spoken to you from heaven.

23 You shall not make gods of silver, nor shall you make for yourselves gods of gold.

24 You shall make an altar from the earth for me, and you shall offer upon it your holocausts and peace-offerings, your sheep and oxen, in every place where the memory of my name shall be. I will come to you, and I will bless you.

25 And if you make an altar of stone for me, you shall not build it from cut stones; for if you lift up a tool over it, it will be defiled.

26 You shall not ascend by steps to my altar, lest your nakedness be revealed."

Exodus 21

1 "These are the judgments which you shall place before them:

2 If you buy a Hebrew servant, six years shall he serve you; in the seventh, he shall depart freely, without charge.

3 With whatever clothing he arrived, with the like let him depart. If he has a wife, his wife also shall depart, at the same time.

4 But if his lord gave him a wife, and she has borne sons and daughters, the woman and her children shall belong to her lord. Yet still, he himself will go out with his clothing.

5 And if the servant will say, 'I love my lord, and my wife and children, I will not depart freely,'

6 then his lord shall make an offering for him to the heavens, and it shall be applied to the door and the posts, and he will pierce his ear with an awl. And he shall be his servant in perpetuity.

7 If anyone sells his daughter to be a servant, she shall not depart as a female servant is accustomed to go out.

8 If she displeases the eyes of her lord, to whom she had been delivered, he shall dismiss her. But he shall have no authority to sell her to a foreign people, even if he despises her.

9 But if he has betrothed her to his son, he shall treat her according to the custom with daughters.

10 And if he takes another for him, he shall provide to the maiden a marriage, and clothing, and he shall not refuse the price of her chastity.

11 If he does not do these three things, she shall depart freely, without money.

12 Whoever strikes a man, intending to murder, shall be put to death.

13 But if he did not lie in wait for him, but God delivered him into his hands, then I will appoint for you a place to which he must flee.

14 If someone murders his neighbor with deliberation, by lying in wait, you shall tear him away from my altar, so that he may die.

15 Whoever strikes his father or mother shall die a death.

16 Whoever will have stolen a man and sold him, having been convicted of the crime, shall be put to death.

17 Whoever speaks evil of his father or mother shall die a death.

18 If men will have quarreled, and one of them has struck his neighbor with a stone or a fist, and he does not die, but lies in bed,

19 if he gets up again and can walk outside on his staff, he who struck him will be innocent, but only if he makes sufficient restitution for his deeds and for the cost of the physicians.

20 Whoever strikes his male or female servant with a staff, and if they have died by his hands, he shall be guilty of a crime.

21 But if he survives for one day or two, he shall not be subject to punishment, because it is his money.

22 If men will have quarreled, and one of them has struck a pregnant woman, and as a result she miscarries, but she herself survives, he shall be subject to as much damage as the husband of the woman shall petition from him, or as arbitrators shall judge.

23 But if her death will have followed, he will repay a life for a life,

24 an eye for an eye, a tooth for a tooth, a hand for a hand, a foot for a foot,

25 a scrape for a scrape, a wound for a wound, a bruise for a bruise.

26 If anyone will have struck the eye of his male or female servant, having left them with one eye, he shall release them freely, because of the eye that he has put out.

27 Likewise, if he knocks out a tooth of his male or female servant, he shall similarly release them freely.

28 If an ox has struck a man or a woman with his horn, and if they die, it shall be stoned. And its flesh shall not be eaten; also, the owner of the ox will be innocent.

29 But if the ox had been pushing with his horn, from yesterday and the day before, and they warned his owner, but he did not confine it, and it will have killed a man or a woman, then the ox shall be stoned, and his owner shall be killed.

30 But if they have imposed a price on him, he shall give, in exchange for his life, whatever is asked.

31 Likewise, if it has struck a son or a daughter with its horns, it shall be subject to a similar verdict.

32 If it attacks a male or female servant, he shall give thirty shekels of silver to their lord, yet truly the ox shall be stoned.

33 If a man digs or opens a cistern, and does not cover it, and an ox or a donkey falls into it,

34 then the owner of the cistern shall repay the price of the beasts, and what is dead will belong to him.

35 If the ox of a stranger wounds the ox of another, and it has died, then they shall sell the live ox and divide the price, but the carcass of the dead one they shall distribute between them.

36 But if he knew that his ox had pushed with its horns, yesterday and the day before, and its owner did not confine it, then he shall repay an ox for an ox, and he will receive the whole carcass."

Exodus 22

1 "If anyone will have stolen an ox or a sheep, and if he kills it or sells it, then he will restore five oxen for one ox, and four sheep for one sheep.

2 If a thief will have been discovered breaking into a house, or digging under it, and he has received a mortal wound, he who struck him down will not be guilty of blood.

3 But if he did this when the sun was risen, he has perpetrated a homicide, and he shall die. If he does not have the means to make restitution for the theft, he shall be sold.

4 If whatever he stole should be found with him, a living thing, either an ox, or a donkey, or a sheep, he shall repay double.

5 If there is any damage to a field or a vineyard, when he has released his cattle to pasture on the land of a stranger, he shall repay the best of what he has in his own field, or in his own vineyard, according to the estimation of the damage.

6 If a fire will have been discovered departing from brush, and taking hold in stacks of grain, or in crops standing in the fields, whoever ignited the fire shall repay the damages.

7 If anyone will have entrusted money, or a container, to his friend to keep, and if these have been stolen from the one who received them: if the thief is found, he shall repay double.

8 If the thief is unknown, the lord of the house will be brought before the heavens to swear that he did not lay his hand on the goods of his neighbor,

9 so as to perpetrate any fraud, such as with an ox, or a donkey, or a sheep, or clothing, nor to do anything that would be able to cause damage. The case of both shall be brought before the heavens. And if they give judgment against him, he shall repay double to his neighbor.

10 If anyone will have entrusted a donkey, an ox, a sheep, or any animal to the keeping of his neighbor, and it will have died, or become disabled, or have been captured by enemies, and no one saw it,

11 then there shall be an oath between them, that he did not lay his hand on the goods of his neighbor. And the owner shall accept the oath, and he will not be compelled to make restitution.

12 But if it will have been taken away by theft, he shall repay the damages to the owner.

13 If it has been eaten by a wild beast, let him carry what was killed to him, and then he shall not make restitution.

14 If anyone borrows from his neighbor any of these things, and it has died or been disabled when the owner was not present, he shall be compelled to make restitution.

15 But if the owner was present, he shall not make restitution, especially if it had been brought for hired work.

16 If a man has led astray a virgin not yet betrothed, and he has slept with her, he shall pay her dowry and have her as a wife.

17 If the father of the virgin is not willing to give her, he shall pay money according to manner of a dowry, which virgins are accustomed to receive.

18 You shall not permit practitioners of the black arts to live.

19 Whoever has sexual intercourse with an animal shall be put to death.

20 Whoever immolates to gods, other than to the Lord, shall be killed.

21 You shall not harass the newcomer, nor shall you afflict him. For you yourselves were once newcomers in the land of Egypt.

22 You shall not harm a widow or an orphan.

23 If you hurt them, they will cry out to me, and I will hear their cry.

24 And my fury will be enraged, and I will strike you down with the sword. And your wives will become widows, and your sons will become orphans.

25 If you lend money to the poor of my people who live among you, you shall not coerce them like a collector, nor oppress them with usury.

26 If you take a garment from your neighbor as a pledge, you shall return it to him again before the setting of the sun.

27 For it is all that he has to cover himself, to clothe his body; nor does he have anything else in which to sleep. If he cries out to me, I will hear him, because I am compassionate.

28 You shall not disparage the heavens, and you shall not speak evil of the leader of your people.

29 You shall not delay in paying your tithes and your first-fruits. You shall give the firstborn of your sons to me.

30 You shall do likewise with those of the oxen and the sheep. For seven days, let it be with its mother; on the eighth day you shall repay it to me.

31 You shall be holy men for me. The flesh, from which beasts will have tasted, you shall not eat, but you will throw it to the dogs."

Exodus 23

1 "You shall not accept a lying voice. Neither shall you join your hand so as to give false testimony on behalf on the impious.

2 You shall not follow the crowd in doing evil. Neither shall you go astray in judgment, by agreeing with the majority opinion, apart from the truth.

3 Likewise, you shall not show pity in judgment of the poor.

4 If you come across an ox or a donkey of your enemy, which has gone astray, lead it back to him.

5 If you see the donkey of one who hates you, fallen under its burden, you shall not pass by without lifting it up with him.

6 You shall not deviate in judgment of the poor.

7 You shall flee from lies. The innocent and the just you shall not kill. For I shun the impious.

8 Neither shall you accept bribes, which blind even the prudent and subvert the words of the just.

9 You shall not harass a sojourner, for you know the life of a newcomer. For you yourselves also were sojourners in the land of Egypt.

10 For six years, you shall sow your land and gather its produce.

11 But in the seventh year, you shall release it and cause it to rest, so that the poor of your people may eat. And whatever remains, let the beasts of the field eat it. So shall you do with your vineyard and your olive grove.

12 For six days, you shall work. On the seventh day, you shall cease, so that your ox and your donkey may rest, and so that the newcomer and the son of your handmaid may be refreshed.

13 Preserve all that I have said to you. And by the names of foreign gods you shall not swear; neither shall these be heard from your mouth.

14 Three times in each year, you shall celebrate feasts to me.

15 You shall keep the solemnity of unleavened bread. For seven days you shall eat unleavened bread, just as I instructed you, at the time of the month of new grain, when you departed from Egypt. You shall not appear empty-handed in my sight,

16 for it is the solemnity of the harvest of the first-fruits of your work, of whatever you have sown in the field. Likewise, it is a solemnity at the end of the season, when you will have gathered in all your crops from the field.

17 Three times a year, all your males shall appear before the Lord your God.

18 You shall not immolate the blood of my victim over leaven, nor shall the fat of my solemnity remain until morning.

19 You shall carry the first grain of the land to the house of the Lord your God. You shall not cook a young goat in the milk of its mother.

20 Behold, I will send my Angel, who will go before you, and preserve you on your journey, and lead you into the place that I have prepared.

21 Heed him, and hear his voice, and do not hold him in disregard. For he will not release you when you have sinned, and my name is in him.

22 But if you listen to his voice and do all that I say, I will be an enemy to your enemies, and I will afflict those who afflict you.

23 And my Angel will go before you, and he will bring you to the Amorite, and the Hittite, and the Perizzite, and the Canaanite, and the Hivite, and the Jebusite, whom I will crush.

24 You shall not adore their gods, nor worship them. You shall not do their works, but you shall destroy them and break apart their statues.

25 And you shall serve the Lord your God, so that I may bless your bread and your waters, and so that I may take away sickness from your midst.

26 There will not be fruitless or barren ones in your land. I will fill up the number of your days.

27 I will send my terror to run ahead of you, and I will kill all the people to whom you will enter. And I will turn the backs of all your enemies before you,

28 sending wasps ahead, so that they will put to flight the Hivite, and the Canaanite, and the Hittite, before you enter.

29 I will not cast them out from your face in one year, lest the land be reduced to a wilderness and the wild beasts increase against you.

30 I will expel them little by little from your sight, until you have expanded and may possess the land.

31 Then I will set your limits to be from the Red Sea to the Sea of the Palestinians, and from the desert all the way to the river. I will deliver into your hands the inhabitants of the land, and I will cast them out from your sight.

32 You shall not enter into a pact with them, nor with their gods.

33 They may not live on your land, lest perhaps they may cause you to sin against me, if you serve their gods, which certainly would be a temptation for you."

Exodus 24

1 He also said to Moses: "Ascend to the Lord, you and Aaron, Nadab and Abihu, and seventy elders out of Israel, and adore from a distance.

2 And only Moses will ascend to the Lord, and these shall not approach. Neither shall the people ascend with him."

3 Therefore, Moses went and explained to the people all the words of the Lord, as well as the judgments. And all the people responded with one voice: "We will do all the words of the Lord, which he has spoken."

4 Then Moses wrote all the words of the Lord. And rising up in the morning, he built an altar at the base of the mountain, with twelve titles according to the twelve tribes of Israel.

5 And he sent youths from the sons of Israel, and they offered holocausts, and they immolated calves as peace-offerings to the Lord.

6 And so Moses took one half part of the blood, and he put it into bowls. Then the remaining part he poured over the altar.

7 And taking up the book of the covenant, he read it in the hearing of the people, who said: "All that the Lord has spoken, we will do, and we will be obedient."

8 In truth, taking up the blood, he sprinkled it on the people, and he said, "This is the blood of the covenant, which the Lord has formed with you concerning all these words."

9 And Moses and Aaron, Nadab and Abihu, and seventy of the elders of Israel ascended.

10 And they saw the God of Israel. And under his feet was something like a work of sapphire stone, or like the sky, when it is serene.

11 Neither did he lay his hand upon those of the sons of Israel who were at a distance. And they saw God, and they ate and drank.

12 Then the Lord said to Moses: "Ascend to me on the mountain, and be there. And I will give to you tablets of stone, and the law and the commandments that I have written. So may you teach them."

13 Moses rose up, with Joshua his minister. And Moses, ascending on the mountain of God,

14 said to the elders: "Wait here, until we return to you. You have Aaron and Hur with you. If any question arises, you shall refer it to them."

15 And when Moses had ascended, a cloud covered the mountain.

16 And the glory of the Lord dwelt upon Sinai, covering it with a cloud for six days. And on the seventh day, he called to him from the middle of the mist.

17 Now the appearance of the glory of the Lord was like a burning fire over the summit of the mountain in the sight of the sons of Israel.

18 And Moses, entering into the midst of the cloud, ascended the mountain. And he was there for forty days and forty nights.

Exodus 25

1 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

2 "Speak to the sons of Israel, so that they may take the first-fruits to me. You shall accept these from every man who offers of his own accord.

3 Now these are the things that you must accept: Gold, and silver, and brass,

4 hyacinth and purple, and twice-dyed scarlet, and fine linen, the hair of goats,

5 and the skins of rams, dyed red, and skins of violet, and setim wood,

6 oil to prepare lights, aromatics as ointments and sweet-smelling incense,

7 onyx stones and gems to adorn the ephod as well as the breastplate.

8 And they shall make a sanctuary for me, and I will live in their midst.

9 According to exact likeness of the tabernacle, and all of the vessels for its rituals, that I will reveal to you, so shall you make it.

10 Join together an ark of setim wood, whose length shall hold two and one half cubits; the width, one and one half cubits; the height, likewise, one and one half cubits.

11 And you shall overlay it with the finest gold, inside and out. And over it, you shall fashion a gold crown all around,

12 and four gold rings, which you shall set into the four corners of the ark. Let two rings be on one side and two on the other.

13 Likewise, you shall make bars of setim wood and cover them with gold.

14 And you shall put them through the rings that are in the sides of the ark, so that it may be carried on them.

15 These must always be in the rings, neither shall they ever be drawn out of them.

16 And you shall place the testimony, which I will give to you, in the ark.

17 You shall also make a propitiatory of the finest gold. Its length shall hold two and one half cubits, and the width, one and one half cubits.

18 Likewise, you shall make two Cherubim of formed gold, on both sides of the oracle.

19 Let one Cherub be on the one side, and the other be on the other.

20 And let them cover both sides of the propitiatory, spreading their wings and covering the oracle, and let them look out toward one another, their faces being turned toward the propitiatory, with which the ark is to be covered,

21 in which you will place the testimony that I will give to you.

22 From there, I will warn you and speak to you, above the propitiatory and from the middle of the two Cherubim, which will be over the ark of the testimony, about everything that I will command of the sons of Israel through you.

23 You shall also make a table of setim wood, having two cubits of length, and one cubit in width, and one cubit and one half cubits in height.

24 And you shall overlay it with the purest gold. And you shall make it with a gold lip all around,

25 and for the lip itself an engraved crown, four fingers high, and above it another little gold crown.

26 Likewise, you shall prepare four gold rings and set them in the four corners of the same table, over each foot.

27 Under the crown, there shall be gold rings, so that the bars may be put through them and the table may be carried.

28 Likewise, the bars themselves you shall make of setim wood, and surround them with gold, to lift up the table.

29 You shall also prepare small cups, as well as bowls, censers, and measuring cups, with which the libations shall be offered, out of the purest gold.

30 And you shall place upon the table the bread of the presence, in my sight always.

31 You shall also make a lampstand, formed from the finest gold, along with its stem and arms, its bowl and little spheres, as well as the lilies proceeding from it.

32 Six branches shall go out from the sides: three out of one side and three out of the other.

33 Three bowls, the size of nuts, shall be on each branch, and a little sphere with it, and a lily. And three similar bowls, in the likeness of nuts, shall be on the other branch, and a little sphere with it, and a lily. This shall be the form of the six branches, which are to proceed from the stem.

34 Then, in the lampstand itself, there shall be four bowls, the size of nuts, and each with little spheres and lilies.

35 Little spheres under two branches in three places, which together make six, shall proceed from one of the stems.

36 Thus both the little spheres and the branches shall be made out of the same thing: entirely formed from the purest gold.

37 You shall also make seven lamps, and you shall place them upon the lampstand, so that they may give light in every direction.

38 Likewise, the candle snuffers, and the place where the candles will be extinguished, shall be made from the purest gold.

39 The entire weight of the candlestick, with all its parts, shall hold one talent of the purest gold.

40 Observe, and then make it according to the example that was shown to you on the mountain."

Exodus 26

1 "Truly, thus shall you make the tabernacle: You shall make ten curtains of fine twisted linen, and hyacinth as well as purple, and twice-dyed scarlet, with diverse embroidery.

2 The length of one curtain shall have twenty-eight cubits. The width shall be four cubits. The entire set of curtains shall be of one measure.

3 Five curtains shall be joined to one another, and the other five shall be similarly coupled together.

4 You shall make loops of hyacinth on the sides at the edges of the curtains, so that they will be able to be joined to one another.

5 A curtain shall have fifty loops on each of two sides, inserted in such a manner that loop may come against loop, and one can be fitted to the other.

6 You shall also make fifty rings of gold, with which the veils of the curtains are to be joined, so that it shall be one tabernacle.

7 You shall also make eleven haircloth canopies to cover the roof of the tabernacle.

8 The length of one canopy shall hold thirty cubits, and the width, four. The measure of all the canopies shall be equal.

9 Five of these you shall join by themselves, and six of these you shall couple to one another, in such a manner as to double the sixth canopy at the front of the roof.

10 You shall also make fifty loops along the edge of one canopy, so that it may be able to be joined with the other, and fifty loops along the edge of the other canopy, so that it may be coupled with the other.

11 You shall also make fifty brass buckles, with which the loops may be joined, so that there may be one covering out of all.

12 Then what will be left over of the canopies which are prepared for the roof, that is, one canopy which is in excess, from half of it you shall cover the back of the tabernacle.

13 And one cubit will hang down on one side, and another on the other side, which is more than the length of the curtains, protecting both sides of the tabernacle.

14 You shall also make another covering for the roof from the skins of rams, dyed-red, and above that again, another covering of violet-colored skins.

15 You shall also make the standing panels of the tabernacle from setim wood.

16 Of these, each shall have ten cubits in length, and in width, one and one half.

17 At the sides of the panels, there shall be made two dovetails, by which one panel may be connected to another panel; and in this way all the panels shall be prepared.

18 Of these, twenty shall be at the meridian, which lies toward the south.

19 For these, you shall cast forty bases of silver, so that two bases will lie under each panel at its two corners.

20 Likewise, at the second side of the tabernacle, which lies to the north, there shall be twenty panels,

21 having forty bases of silver; two bases shall support each panel.

22 Truly, toward the western part of the tabernacle, you shall make six panels,

23 and again another two, which will be raised at the corners, behind the back of the tabernacle.

24 And these shall be joined together from bottom to top, and one joint shall retain them all. Likewise, two of the panels, which will be set at the corners, shall be served by similar joints.

25 And together these will be eight panels, and their bases of silver, sixteen, counting two bases for each panel.

26 You shall also make five bars of setim wood, to connect the panels on one side of the tabernacle,

27 and five others on the other side, and the same number toward the western part.

28 These shall be set along the middle of the panels, from one end all the way to the other end.

29 Likewise, the panels themselves you shall overlay with gold, and you shall establish rings of gold in them, by which the bars of the panels may be connected. These you shall cover with layers of gold.

30 And you shall raise the tabernacle according to the example which was shown to you on the mountain.

31 You shall also make a veil of hyacinth, and purple, and twice-dyed scarlet, and fine twisted linen, wrought with a diversity of continuous and beautiful embroidery.

32 And you shall suspend it before four columns of setim wood, which themselves certainly shall be overlaid with gold, and have heads of gold, but bases of silver.

33 Then the veil shall be inserted through the rings. Beyond the veil, you shall place the ark of the testimony, where both the Sanctuary and the Sanctuary of Sanctuaries shall be divided.

34 And you shall place the propitiatory over the ark of the testimony, in the Holy of Holies.

35 And the table shall be outside the veil. And opposite the table shall be the lampstand, in the meridian of the tabernacle. For the table shall stand at the north side.

36 You shall also make a tent at the entrance of the tabernacle from hyacinth, and purple, and twice-dyed scarlet, and fine twisted linen, wrought with embroidery.

37 And you shall overlay with gold five columns of setim wood, over which the tent shall be drawn. The heads of these shall be of gold, and the bases of brass."

Exodus 27

1 "You shall also make an altar of setim wood, which will have five cubits in length, and the same in width, that is, four equal sides, and three cubits in height.

2 Now there shall be horns at the four corners of it, and you shall cover it with brass.

3 And you shall make, for its uses, pans to receive the ashes, and tongs as well as small hooks, and receptacles for fire. You shall fabricate all of its vessels from brass,

4 along with a grating of brass in the manner of a net. At its four corners there shall be four rings of brass,

5 which you shall place under the base of the altar. And the grating will extend even to the middle of the altar.

6 You shall also make, for the altar, two bars of setim wood, which you shall cover with layers of brass.

7 And you shall lead them through the rings, and they will be on both sides of the altar to carry it.

8 You shall not make it solid, but empty and hollow at the interior, just as it was shown to you on the mountain.

9 You shall also make the atrium of the tabernacle, at the southern part of which, opposite the meridian, there shall be hangings of fine twisted linen: one side extending for one hundred cubits in length.

10 And you shall make twenty columns with the same number of bases of brass, the heads of which, with their engravings, shall be made of silver.

11 In like manner also, throughout the length of the north side, there shall be hangings of one hundred cubits, and twenty columns, and the same number of bases of brass, and their heads with their engravings of silver.

12 Yet truly, along the width of the atrium that looks out toward the west, there shall be hangings of fifty cubits, and ten columns, and the same number of bases.

13 Likewise, along the width of the atrium that looks out toward the east, there shall be fifty cubits,

14 along which there shall be assigned hangings of fifteen cubits for one side, and three columns, and the same number of bases.

15 And, along the other side, there shall be hangings occupying fifteen cubits, with three columns and the same number of bases.

16 Yet truly, at the entrance of the atrium, there shall be made a hanging of twenty cubits, of hyacinth and purple, and twice-dyed scarlet, and fine twisted linen, wrought with embroidery. It shall have four columns, with the same number of bases.

17 All the columns surrounding the atrium shall be clothed with layers of silver, with silver heads, and with bases of brass.

18 In length, the atrium shall occupy one hundred cubits, in width, fifty; the height shall be of five cubits. And it shall be made of fine twisted linen, and it shall have bases of brass.

19 All the vessels of the tabernacle, for all uses and ceremonies, even to the tent pegs for its atrium, you shall make of brass.

20 Instruct the sons of Israel so that they may bring you the purest oil of the olive trees, crushed with a pestle, so that a lamp may always burn

21 in the tabernacle of the testimony, outside of the veil that enshrouds the testimony. And Aaron and his sons shall arrange it, so that it may give light in the presence of the Lord, until morning. This shall be a perpetual observance among the sons of Israel, throughout their successions."

Exodus 28

1 "Also, join to yourself your brother Aaron, with his sons from the midst of the sons of Israel, so that they may exercise the priesthood for me: Aaron, Nadab and Abihu, Eleazar and Ithamar.

2 And you shall make a holy vestment for Aaron, your brother, with glory and elegance.

3 And you shall speak to all the wise of heart, whom I have filled with the spirit of prudence, so that they may make the vestments of Aaron, in which, having been sanctified, he may minister to me.

4 Now these shall be the vestments that they shall make: A breastplate and an ephod, a tunic and a close-fit linen garment, a headdress and a wide belt. They shall make the holy vestments for your brother Aaron and his sons, so that they may exercise the priesthood for me.

5 And they shall receive gold, and hyacinth, and purple, and twice-dyed scarlet, and fine linen.

6 Then they shall make the ephod of gold, and hyacinth, and purple, and twice-dyed scarlet, and fine twisted linen, wrought with diverse colors.

7 It shall have two edges joined at the top on both sides, so that they may respond as one.

8 Likewise, the weaving and all the detail work shall be of gold, and hyacinth, and purple, and twice-dyed scarlet, and fine twisted linen.

9 And you shall take two onyx stones and engrave on them the names of the sons of Israel:

10 six names on one stone, and the remaining six on the other, according to the order of their birth.

11 By the work of a sculptor and the skill of a jeweler, you shall engrave them with the names of the sons of Israel, enclosed and encompassed with gold.

12 And you shall place them on both sides of the ephod, as a memorial to the sons of Israel. And Aaron shall carry their names before the Lord, upon both shoulders, as a remembrance.

13 You shall also make hooks of gold,

14 and two little chains of the purest gold, linked to one another, which you shall insert into the hooks.

15 Likewise, you shall make the breastplate of judgment, wrought with diverse colors according to weaving of the ephod: of gold, hyacinth and purple, and twice-dyed scarlet, and fine twisted linen.

16 It shall have four corners and be doubled. It shall have the measure of the palm of a hand, both in length and in width.

17 And you shall set within it four rows of stones. In the first row, there shall be a sardius stone, and a topaz, and an emerald.

18 In the second, there shall be a garnet, a sapphire, and a jasper.

19 In the third, there shall be a zircon, an agate, and an amethyst.

20 In the fourth, there shall be a chrysolite, an onyx, and a beryl. They shall be set in gold by their rows.

21 And these shall have the names of the sons of Israel. With twelve names shall they be engraved: each stone with one name from the twelve tribes.

22 You shall make chains of the purest gold, linked one to another, on the breastplate,

23 and two rings of gold, which you shall place at both ends of the breastplate.

24 And the golden chains, you shall join to the rings, which are at its edges.

25 And the ends of the chains themselves, you shall couple with two hooks, on both sides of the ephod, which looks toward the breastplate.

26 You shall also make two rings of gold, which you shall place at the ends of the breastplate, at the borders which are away from the region of the ephod and which look toward its back.

27 And then you shall also make two other rings of gold, which are to be suspended on both sides at the bottom of the ephod, which looks out opposite the face of the lower juncture, so that the breastplate can be fitted to the ephod.

28 And it shall be drawn tight to the rings of the breastplate, by the rings of the ephod, with a hyacinth band, so that the well-constructed juncture will remain in place, and the breastplate and the ephod will not be able to be separated from one another.

29 And Aaron shall carry the names of the sons of Israel on the breastplate of judgment upon his chest, when he enters into the Sanctuary, as a memorial in the presence of the Lord in eternity.

30 Then you shall place in the breastplate of judgment, Doctrine and Truth, which shall then be upon Aaron's chest, when he enters before the Lord. And he shall wear the judgment of the sons of Israel on his chest, in the sight of the Lord always.

31 And you shall make the tunic for the ephod entirely of hyacinth,

32 and the head will be above its middle, with a hem woven around it, just as is usually made at the end parts of a garment, so that it may not be easily broken.

33 Yet truly, beneath it, at the base of the same tunic, all around, you shall make something like pomegranates, from hyacinth, and purple, and twice-dyed scarlet, with little bells set in their midst.

34 So then, there shall be a little golden bell and a pomegranate, and again another golden bell and a pomegranate.

35 And Aaron will be vested with it during the office of his ministry, so that the sound may be heard when he enters and exits the Sanctuary, in the sight of the Lord, and so that he may not die.

36 And you shall make a plate of the purest gold, in which you shall engrave, with the skill of a sculptor, 'Holy to the Lord.'

37 And you shall fasten it with a band of hyacinth, and it shall be upon the headdress,

38 hanging in front of the high priest. And Aaron shall carry the iniquities of that which the sons of Israel have offered and sanctified, in all their gifts and donations. But the plate will always be at his forehead, so that the Lord may be well pleased with them.

39 And you shall draw the tunic tight with fine linen, and you shall make a headdress of fine linen, and a wide belt, wrought with embroidery.

40 Furthermore, for the sons of Aaron, you shall prepare linen tunics, and wide belts as well as headdresses, with glory and elegance.

41 And with all these you shall vest your brother Aaron, and his sons with him. And you shall consecrate all their hands, and you shall sanctify them, so that they may exercise the priesthood for me.

42 You shall also make linen undergarments, in order to cover the flesh of their nakedness, from the kidneys all the way to the thighs.

43 And Aaron and his sons will use them when they enter the tabernacle of the testimony, and when they approach toward the altar, in order to minister in the sanctuary, lest, being guilty of iniquity, they may die. It shall be a law forever for Aaron, and for his offspring after him."

Exodus 29

1 "But you shall also do this, so that they may be consecrated to me in the priesthood: Take a calf from the herd, and two immaculate rams,

2 and unleavened bread, and a crust without leaven that has been sprinkled with oil, likewise, unleavened cakes smeared with oil. You shall make them all from the same wheat flour.

3 And, having placed them in baskets, you shall offer them, along with the calf and the two rams.

4 And you shall bring forward Aaron and his sons, to the door of the tabernacle of the testimony. And when you will have washed the father with his sons in water,

5 you shall clothe Aaron in his vestments, that is, with the linen, and the tunic, and the ephod, and the breastplate, which you shall draw together with the wide belt.

6 And you shall place the headdress on his head and the holy plate upon the headdress.

7 And you shall pour the oil of unction over his head. And so, by this rite, he shall be consecrated.

8 Likewise, you shall bring forward his sons, and you shall clothe them in the linen tunics, and wrap them with the wide belt:

9 Aaron, certainly, as well as his sons. And you shall impose headdresses upon them. And they shall be priests to me by a perpetual ordinance. After you have initiated their hands,

10 you shall bring forward also the calf, in the presence of the tabernacle of the testimony. And Aaron and his sons shall lay their hands upon its head.

11 And you shall sacrifice it in the sight of the Lord, beside the door of the tabernacle of the testimony.

12 And taking some of the blood of the calf, you shall place it upon the horns of the altar with your finger, but the remainder of the blood you shall pour next to its base.

13 And you shall take all the fat which covers its intestines, and the mesh of the liver, as well as the two kidneys, and the fat that is on them, and you shall offer them as a burnt offering upon the altar.

14 Yet truly, the flesh of the calf, and the hide and the dung, you shall burn outside, beyond the camp, because it is for sin.

15 Likewise, you shall take one ram, and upon its head Aaron and his sons shall lay their hands.

16 And when you will have sacrificed it, you shall take from its blood and pour it around the altar.

17 Then you shall cut the ram into pieces, and, having washed its intestines and feet, you shall place these upon the cut-up flesh and upon its head.

18 And you shall offer the entire ram as a burnt offering upon the altar. It is an oblation to the Lord, a most sweet odor of the victim of the Lord.

19 Likewise, you shall take the other ram, upon whose head Aaron and his sons shall lay their hands.

20 And when you will have immolated it, you shall take of its blood, and place it on the tip of the right ear of Aaron and his sons, and on the thumbs and big toes of their right hand and right foot, and you shall pour the blood upon the altar, all around.

21 And when you have taken from the blood that is on the altar, and from the oil of unction, you shall sprinkle Aaron and his vestment, his sons and their vestments. And after they and their vestments have been consecrated,

22 you shall take the fat of the ram, and the rump, and the lard that covers the internal organs, and the mesh of the liver, and the two kidneys along with the fat that is on them, and the right shoulder, because it is the ram of consecration,

23 and one turn of bread, a crust sprinkled with oil, and a cake from the basket of unleavened bread, which was placed in the sight of the Lord.

24 And you shall place all these in the hands of Aaron and his sons, and you shall sanctify them, lifting them up in the sight of the Lord.

25 And you shall take all these things from their hands and burn them upon the altar as a holocaust, as a most sweet odor in the sight of the Lord, because it is his oblation.

26 Likewise, you shall take the chest of the ram, with which Aaron was initiated, and you shall sanctify it, lifting it up in the sight of the Lord, and it will fall to your share.

27 And you shall sanctify both the consecrated chest and the shoulder that you separated from the ram,

28 with which Aaron was initiated with his sons, and these will fall to the share of Aaron and his sons, as a perpetual oath by the sons of Israel. For these are the greatest and the first of their victims of peace, which they offer to the Lord.

29 But the holy vestment, which Aaron shall use, his sons shall possess after him, so that they may be anointed in it and their hands may be consecrated.

30 For seven days, he who is high priest in his place and who enters the tabernacle of the testimony to minister in the Sanctuary shall use it.

31 But you shall take the ram of consecration and cook its flesh in the holy place.

32 And Aaron and his sons shall feed on it. Likewise, the loaves which are in the basket, they shall consume in the vestibule of the tabernacle of the testimony,

33 so that it may be an appeasing sacrifice, and so that the hands of those who offer may be sanctified. A stranger shall not eat from these, for they are holy.

34 And what may remain until morning, of the consecrated flesh or of the bread, you shall burn these remnants with fire. These shall not be eaten, because they have been sanctified.

35 All that I have instructed you concerning Aaron and his sons, you shall do. For seven days shall you consecrate their hands,

36 and you shall offer a calf for sin on each day, as an atonement. And you shall cleanse the altar when you will have immolated the victim of expiation, and you shall anoint it for sanctification.

37 For seven days, you shall expiate and sanctify the altar, and it shall be the Holy of holies. All those who will touch it must be sanctified.

38 This is what you shall acquire for the altar: Two one-year-old lambs, each day continually,

39 one lamb in the morning, and the other in the evening;

40 for the one lamb, a tenth part of fine flour sprinkled with crushed oil, which shall have the measure of the fourth part of a hin, and wine for a libation, of the same measure;

41 truly, the other lamb you shall offer in the evening, according to the ritual of the morning oblation, and according to what we have said, as an odor of sweetness.

42 It is a sacrifice to the Lord, by a perpetual oblation among your generations, at the door of the tabernacle of the testimony before the Lord, where I resolve to speak to you.

43 And there I will instruct the sons of Israel, and the altar shall be sanctified by my glory.

44 I will also sanctify the tabernacle of the testimony with the altar, and Aaron with his sons, to exercise the priesthood for me.

45 And I will live in the midst of the sons of Israel, and I will be their God.

46 And they shall know that I am the Lord their God, who led them away from the land of Egypt, so that I might dwell among them. I am the Lord their God."

Exodus 30

1 "You shall also make an altar, for the burning of incense, from setim wood,

2 having one cubit in length, and another in width, that is, four equal sides, and two cubits in height. Horns shall proceed from the same.

3 And you shall clothe it with the purest gold, both its grating and the walls around it, and also the horns. And you shall make for it a crown of gold in a circle,

4 and two gold rings under the crown on each side, so that the bars may be set in them and the altar may be carried.

5 Also, you shall make its bars of setim wood, and you shall overlay them with gold.

6 And you shall set the altar opposite the veil, which hangs in front of the ark of the testimony, before the propitiatory with which the testimony is covered, where I will speak to you.

7 And Aaron shall burn incense upon it, a sweet fragrance, in the morning. When he lights the lamps, he shall burn it.

8 And when he assembles them in the evening, he shall burn an everlasting incense before the Lord throughout your generations.

9 You shall not offer upon it incense of another composition, nor an oblation, nor a victim; neither shall you offer libations.

10 And Aaron shall pray over its horns once a year, with the blood of what was offered for sin. And he shall make atonement over it in your generations. It shall be the Holy of holies to the Lord."

11 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

12 "When you have taken the sum of the sons of Israel, according to their number, each shall give a price for their souls to the Lord, and there will be no scourge among them, when they will be reviewed.

13 Then all those who pass shall give by name: one half shekel, according to the measure at the temple. A shekel has twenty obols. The half part of a shekel shall be offered to the Lord.

14 He who has been numbered from twenty years and above shall give the price.

15 The rich shall not add to the half shekel, and the poor shall diminish nothing.

16 And the money received, which was collected from the sons of Israel, you shall deliver for the uses of the tabernacle of the testimony, so that it may be a memorial of them before the Lord, and he may act favorably toward their souls."

17 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

18 "You shall also make a bronze washtub with its base to wash in; and you shall place it between the tabernacle of the testimony and the altar. And when water has been added,

19 Aaron and his sons shall wash their hands and feet in it:

20 when they enter the tabernacle of the testimony, and when they approach to the altar so as to offer incense to the Lord upon it,

21 otherwise, they may die. This shall be an everlasting law to him, and to his offspring, throughout their successions."

22 And the Lord spoke to Moses,

23 saying: "Take for yourself aromatics: of the first and best myrrh, five hundred shekels, and of cinnamon half as much, that is, two hundred and fifty shekels; of sweet flag similarly two hundred and fifty,

24 but of cassia, five hundred shekels by the weight of the sanctuary, and of the oil of olives the measure of a hin.

25 And you shall make the holy oil of unction, an ointment composed with the skills of a perfumer,

26 and with it you shall anoint the tabernacle of the testimony, and the ark of the testament,

27 and the table with its vessels, and the lampstand and it utensils, the altars of incense

28 and of holocaust, and all the items that pertain to their rituals.

29 And you shall sanctify everything, and they shall be the Holy of holies. He who will touch them must be sanctified.

30 You shall anoint Aaron and his sons, and you shall sanctify them, so that they may exercise the priesthood for me.

31 Likewise, you shall say to the sons of Israel: 'This oil of unction will be holy to me throughout your generations.

32 The flesh of man shall not be anointed from it, and you shall not make any similar compound, for it has been sanctified and it shall be holy to you.

33 Whatever man will have composed such a thing and have given it to a stranger, he shall be exterminated from his people.' "

34 And the Lord said to Moses: "Take to yourself aromatics: stacte, and onycha, galbanum of sweet odor, and the clearest frankincense, all these shall be of equal weight.

35 And you shall make incense composed with the skills of a perfumer, diligently mixed, and pure, and most worthy of sanctification.

36 And when you have crushed all these into a very fine powder, you shall place some of it before the tabernacle of the testimony, in the place where I will appear to you. The Holy of holies shall this incense be to you.

37 You shall not make such a compound for your own uses, because it is holy to the Lord.

38 Whatever man will have made anything similar, so as to thoroughly enjoy its smell, he shall perish from his people."

Exodus 31

1 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

2 "Behold, I have called by name Bezalel the son of Uri, the son of Hur, from the tribe of Judah,

3 and I have filled him with the Spirit of God, with wisdom, and understanding, and knowledge in every craft,

4 in order to design whatever must be fabricated from gold, and silver, and brass,

5 from marble, and precious stones, and various woods.

6 And I have given to him, as his associate, Oholiab the son of Ahisamach, from the tribe of Dan. And I have placed wisdom in the heart of every artisan, so that they may make everything as I have instructed you:

7 the tabernacle of the covenant, and the ark of the testimony, and the propitiatory which is over it, and all the vessels of the tabernacle,

8 and the table and its vessels, the most pure lampstand with its vessels, and the altars of incense

9 and of holocaust and all their vessels, the washtub with its base,

10 the holy vestments for the ministry of Aaron the priest, and for his sons, so that they may execute their office of sacred rites,

11 the oil of unction, and the incense of aromatics in the Sanctuary. All the things that I have instructed you, they shall make."

12 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

13 "Speak to the sons of Israel, and you shall say to them: See that you keep my Sabbath. For it is a sign between me and you among your generations, so that you may know that I am the Lord, who sanctifies you.

14 Keep my Sabbath, for it is holy to you. Whoever will have polluted it, shall die a death. Whoever will have done any work in it, his soul shall perish from the midst of his people.

15 For six days you shall do work. On the seventh day, it is the Sabbath, a rest sanctified by the Lord. All who will have done work on this day shall die.

16 Let the sons of Israel keep the Sabbath, and let them celebrate it throughout their generations. It is an everlasting covenant

17 between me and the sons of Israel, and a perpetual sign. For in six days the Lord made heaven and earth, and in the seventh he ceased from work."

18 And the Lord, having completed speaking in this way on Mount Sinai, gave to Moses two stone tablets of testimony, written with the finger of God.

Exodus 32

1 Then the people, seeing that Moses made a delay in descending from the mountain, gathered together against Aaron, and said: "Rise up, make us gods, who may go before us. But as for this man Moses, who led us away from the land of Egypt, we do not know what has befallen him."

2 And Aaron said to them, "Take the golden earrings from the ears of your wives, and your sons and daughters, and bring them to me."

3 And the people did what he had commanded, carrying the earrings to Aaron.

4 And when he had received them, he formed these by the work of a casting furnace, and he made from these a molten calf. And they said: "These are your gods, O Israel, who led you away from the land of Egypt."

5 And when Aaron had seen it, he built an altar before it, and he cried out with a voice of proclamation, saying, "Tomorrow is the solemnity of the Lord."

6 And rising up in the morning, they offered holocausts, and peace victims, and the people sat down to eat and to drink, and they rose up to play.

7 Then the Lord spoke to Moses, saying: "Go, descend. Your people, whom you led away from the land of Egypt, have sinned.

8 They have quickly withdrawn from the way which you revealed to them. And they have made for themselves a molten calf, and they have worshiped it. And immolating victims to it, they have said: 'These are your gods, O Israel, who led you away from the land of Egypt.' "

9 And again, the Lord said to Moses: "I discern that this people is stiff-necked.

10 Release me, so that my fury may be enraged against them, and I may destroy them, and then I will make of you a great nation."

11 Then Moses prayed to the Lord his God, saying: "Why, O Lord, is your fury enraged against your people, whom you led away from the land of Egypt, with great strength and with a mighty hand?

12 I beg you, let not the Egyptians say, 'He cleverly led them away, so that he could put them to death in the mountains and destroy them from the earth.' Let your anger be quieted and appeased concerning the wickedness of your people.

13 Remember Abraham, Isaac, and Israel, your servants, to whom you swore by your very self, saying: 'I will multiply your offspring like the stars of heaven. And this entire land, about which I have spoken, I will give to your offspring. And you shall possess it forever.' "

14 And the Lord was appeased from doing the evil which he had spoken against his people.

15 And Moses returned from the mountain, carrying the two tablets of the testimony in his hand, written on both sides,

16 and accomplished by the work of God. Also, the writing of God was engraved on the tablets.

17 Then Joshua, hearing the tumult of the people shouting, said to Moses: "The outcry of battle is heard in the camp."

18 But he responded: "It is not the clamor of men being exhorted to battle, nor the shout of men being compelled to flee. But I hear the voice of singing."

19 And when he had approached to the camp, he saw the calf and the dances. And being very angry, he threw down the tablets from his hand, and he broke them at the base of the mountain.

20 And seizing the calf, which they had made, he burnt it and crushed it, even to dust, which he scattered into water. And he gave from it to the sons of Israel to drink.

21 And he said to Aaron, "What has this people done to you, so that you would bring upon them the greatest sin?"

22 And he answered him: "Let not my lord be indignant. For you know this people, that they are prone to evil.

23 They said to me: 'Make gods for us, who may go before us. For this Moses, who led us away from the land of Egypt, we do not know what has befallen him.'

24 And I said to them, 'Which of you has gold?' And they took it and gave it to me. And I threw it into the fire, and this calf came out."

25 Therefore, Moses, seeing that the people were naked (for Aaron had stripped them because of the disgrace of their sordidness, and he had set them naked among their enemies),

26 and standing at the gate of the camp, said: "If anyone is for the Lord, let him join with me." And all the sons of Levi gathered themselves together to him.

27 And he said to them: "Thus says the Lord God of Israel: Let a man place his sword at his thigh. Go forth, and then return, from gate to gate, through the midst of the camp, and let each one kill his brother, and friend, and neighbor."

28 And the sons of Levi did according to the words of Moses, and there fell on that day about twenty-three thousand men.

29 And Moses said: "On this day, you have consecrated your hands to the Lord, each one in his son and in his brother, so that a blessing may be given to you."

30 Then, when the next day arrived, Moses spoke to the people: "You have sinned the greatest sin. I will ascend to the Lord. Perhaps, in some way, I might be able to entreat him for your wickedness."

31 And returning to the Lord, he said: "I beg you, this people has sinned the greatest sin, and they have made for themselves gods of gold. Either release them from this offense,

32 or, if you do not, then delete me from the book that you have written."

33 And the Lord answered him: "Whoever has sinned against me, him I will delete from my book.

34 But as for you, go and lead this people where I have told you. My angel will go before you. Then, on the day of retribution, I will also visit this sin of theirs."

35 Therefore, the Lord struck the people for the guilt of the calf, which Aaron had made.

Exodus 33

1 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying: "Go forth, ascend from this place, you and your people, whom you led away from the land of Egypt, into the land that I swore to Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, saying: To your offspring, I will give it.

2 And I will send an Angel to precede you, so that I may cast out the Canaanite, and the Amorite, and the Hittite, and the Perizzite, and the Hivite, and the Jebusite,

3 and so that you may enter into a land flowing with milk and honey. For I will not go up with you, since you are a stiff-necked people, lest perhaps I may destroy you on the way."

4 And upon hearing this very bad news, the people mourned; and no one put on his finery according to custom.

5 And the Lord said to Moses: "Say to the sons of Israel: You are a stiff-necked people. I should at once go up into your midst and destroy you. Now immediately put aside your ornaments, so that I may know what to do to you."

6 Therefore, the sons of Israel put aside their ornaments before Mount Horeb.

7 Also, Moses took the tabernacle and pitched it beyond the camp at a distance, and he called its name: 'Tabernacle of the Covenant.' And all the people, who had any kind of question, went out to the Tabernacle of the Covenant, beyond the camp.

8 And when Moses went out to the tabernacle, all the people rose up, and each one stood at the door of his pavilion, and they beheld the back of Moses until he entered the tent.

9 And when he had gone into the Tabernacle of the Covenant, the pillar of cloud descended and stood at the door, and he spoke with Moses.

10 And all discerned that the pillar of cloud stood at the door of the Tabernacle. And they stood and worshipped at the doors of their tents.

11 But the Lord spoke to Moses face to face, just as a man is used to speaking to his friend. And when he returned to the camp, his minister Joshua, the son of Nun, a young man, did not withdraw from the Tabernacle.

12 Then Moses said to the Lord: "You instruct me to lead this people away, and you do not reveal to me whom you will send with me, particularly since you have said: 'I know you by name, and you have found favor before me.'

13 If, therefore, I have found favor in your sight, show your face to me, so that I may know you and may find grace before your eyes. Look favorably on your people, this nation."

14 And the Lord said, "My face will precede you, and I will give you rest."

15 And Moses said: "If you will not yourself precede us, then do not lead us away from this place.

16 For how will we be able to know, I and your people, that we have found grace in your sight, unless you walk with us, so that we may be glorified out of all the people who live upon the earth?"

17 Then the Lord said to Moses: "This word also, which you have spoken, I will do. For you have found grace before me, and I have known you by name."

18 And he said, "Show me your glory."

19 He responded: "I will show you all that is good, and I will call out with the name of the Lord before you. And I will take pity on whomever I will, and I will be lenient to whomever it will please me."

20 And again he said: "You are not able to see my face. For man shall not see me and live."

21 And again, he said: "Behold, there is a place with me, and you shall stand upon the rock.

22 And when my glory will cross over, I will set you in a cleft of the rock, and I will protect you with my right hand, until I pass by.

23 And I will take away my hand, and you shall see my back. But my face you are not able to see."

Exodus 34

1 And after this he said: "Cut out for yourself two tablets of stone similar to the first ones, and I will write upon them the words which were held on the tablets that you broke.

2 Be prepared in the morning, so that you may immediately ascend onto Mount Sinai, and you shall stand with me on the summit of the mountain.

3 Let no one ascend with you, and do not let anyone be seen throughout the entire mountain. Likewise, do not let the oxen or the sheep pasture up against it."

4 And so he cut out two tablets of stone, like those that were before. And rising up in the night, he ascended onto Mount Sinai, just as the Lord had instructed him, carrying with him the tablets.

5 And when the Lord had descended in a cloud, Moses stood with him, calling upon the name of the Lord.

6 And as he was crossing before him, he said: "The Ruler, the Lord God, merciful and lenient, patient and full of compassion and also truthful,

7 who preserves mercy a thousand fold, who takes away iniquity, and wickedness, and also sin; and with you no one, in and of himself, is innocent. You render the iniquity of the fathers to the sons, and also to their descendents to the third and fourth generation."

8 And hurrying, Moses bowed down prostrate to the ground; and worshiping,

9 he said: "If I have found grace in your sight, O Lord, I beg you to walk with us, (for the people are stiff-necked) and take away our iniquities and our sin, and so possess us."

10 The Lord responded: "I will enter into a pact in the sight of all. I will perform signs which have never been seen on earth, nor among any nation, so that this people, in whose midst you are, may discern the terrible work of the Lord that I will do.

11 Observe everything that I command you this day. I myself will drive out before your face the Amorite, and the Canaanite, and the Hittite, and the Perizzite, and the Hivite, and the Jebusite.

12 Beware that you do not ever join in friendship with the inhabitants of that land, which may be your ruin.

13 But destroy their altars, break their statues, and cut down their sacred groves.

14 Do not be willing to worship any strange god. The jealous Lord is his name. God is a rival.

15 Do not enter into a pact with the men of those regions, lest, when they will have fornicated with their gods and worshiped their idols, someone might call upon you to eat from what was immolated.

16 Neither shall you take a wife for your son from their daughters, lest, after they themselves have fornicated, they may cause your sons also to fornicate with their gods.

17 You shall not make for yourselves any molten gods.

18 You shall keep the solemnity of unleavened bread. For seven days, you shall eat unleavened bread, just as I instructed you, in the time of the month of what is new. For in the month of springtime you departed from Egypt.

19 All of the male kind, which open the womb, shall be mine: from all the animals, as much of oxen as of sheep, it shall be mine.

20 The firstborn of a donkey, you shall redeem with a sheep. But if you will not give a price for it, it shall be slain. The firstborn of your sons you shall redeem. You shall not appear empty in my sight.

21 For six days you shall work. On the seventh day you shall cease to cultivate and to harvest.

22 You shall observe the Solemnity of Weeks with the first-fruits of the grain from the harvest of your wheat, and a Solemnity when the time of the year returns and everything is stored away.

23 Three times a year, all your males shall appear in the sight of the Almighty, the Lord God of Israel.

24 For when I will have taken away the nations before your face, and enlarged your borders, no one shall lie in wait against your land when you will go up to appear in the sight of the Lord your God, three times a year.

25 You shall not immolate the blood of my victim over leaven; and there shall not remain, in the morning, any of the victim of the Solemnity of the Passover.

26 The first of the fruits of your land you shall offer in the house of the Lord your God. You shall not boil a young goat in the milk of its mother."

27 And the Lord said to Moses, "Write these words to you, through which I have formed a covenant, both with you and with Israel."

28 Therefore, he was in that place with the Lord for forty days and forty nights; he did not eat bread and he did not drink water, and he wrote on the tablets the ten words of the covenant.

29 And when Moses descended from Mount Sinai, he held the two tablets of the testimony, and he did not know that his face was radiant from the sharing of words with the Lord.

30 Then Aaron and the sons of Israel, seeing that the face of Moses was radiant, were afraid to approach close by.

31 And being called by him, they turned back, both Aaron and the leaders of the assembly. And after he had spoken to them,

32 all the sons of Israel also now came to him. And he instructed them in all the things that he had heard from the Lord on Mount Sinai.

33 And having completed these words, he placed a veil over his face.

34 But when he entered to the Lord and was speaking with him, he took it off, until he exited. And then he spoke to the sons of Israel all that had been commanded to him.

35 And they saw that the face of Moses, when he came out, was radiant, but he covered his face again, whenever he spoke to them.

Exodus 35

1 Therefore, when all the multitude of the sons of Israel had gathered together, he said to them: "These are the things that the Lord has ordered to be done:

2 For six days you shall do work; the seventh day, the Sabbath and the rest of the Lord, will be holy to you; whoever will have done any work in it shall be killed.

3 You shall not kindle a fire in any of your dwelling places throughout the day of the Sabbath."

4 And Moses said to the entire crowd of the sons of Israel: "This is the word which the Lord has instructed, saying:

5 Separate from among you the first-fruits to the Lord. Let all who are willing and have a ready soul offer these to the Lord: gold, and silver, and brass,

6 hyacinth, and purple, and twice-dyed scarlet, and fine linen, the hair of goats,

7 and the skins of rams, dyed red, and violet skins, setim wood,

8 and oil to prepare lights and to produce ointment, and most sweet incense,

9 onyx stones and gems, to adorn the ephod and the breastplate.

10 And whoever among you is wise, let him come and make what the Lord has commanded:

11 the tabernacle, certainly, and its roof, and also the covering, the rings, and the panels with the bars, the tent pegs and the bases,

12 the ark and its bars, the propitiatory, and the veil that is drawn before it,

13 the table with its bars and vessels, and the bread of the presence,

14 the lampstand to hold up the lights, its vessels and lamps, and the oil to the nourish the fire,

15 the altar of incense and its bars, and the oil of unction, and the incense of aromatics, the tent at the door of the tabernacle,

16 the altar of holocaust and its grate of brass, with the bars and vessels, the washtub and its base,

17 the curtains of the atrium, with the columns and the bases, the hanging at the doors of the vestibule,

18 the tent pegs of the tabernacle and the atrium, with their little cords,

19 the vestments, which are to be used in the ministry of the Sanctuary, the vestments of Aaron, the high priest, as well as those of his sons, in order to exercise the priesthood to me."

20 And all the multitude of the sons of Israel, departing from the sight of Moses,

21 offered the first-fruits to the Lord with a most ready and devout mind, to accomplish the work of the tabernacle of the testimony. Whatever was needed for worship and for the holy vestments,

22 men along with women provided: arm bands and earrings, rings and bracelets. And every vessel of gold was separated, to be donated to the Lord.

23 If anyone had hyacinth, and purple, and twice-dyed scarlet, fine linen and the hair of goats, the skins of rams, dyed red, and violet skins,

24 metal of silver and brass, they offered it to the Lord, along with setim wood for various uses.

25 But the skillful women also gave whatever they had spun: hyacinth, purple, and vermillion, as well as fine linen,

26 and the hair of goats, donating everything of their own accord.

27 Yet truly, the leaders offered onyx stones and gems, for the ephod and the breastplate,

28 and aromatics and oil, to maintain the lights, and to prepare ointment, and also to produce incense with a most sweet odor.

29 All the men and women offered donations with a devout mind, so that the works might be done which the Lord had ordered by the hand of Moses. All the sons of Israel dedicated voluntary offerings to the Lord.

30 And Moses said to the sons of Israel: "Behold, the Lord has called by name Bezalel, the son of Uri, the son of Hur, from the tribe of Judah,

31 and he has filled him with the Spirit of God, with wisdom, and understanding, and knowledge, and all teaching,

32 to design and to fashion, with gold and silver and brass,

33 and with engraving stones, and with the skill of a carpenter. Whatever can be skillfully invented,

34 he has given to his heart. It is likewise with Oholiab, the son of Ahisamach from the tribe of Dan.

35 He has taught both of them wisdom, in order to do the work of carpentry, tapestry, and embroidery, from hyacinth, and purple, and twice-dyed scarlet, and fine linen, and every textile, and to discover whatever may be new."

Exodus 36

1 Therefore, Bezalel, and Oholiab, and every wise man, to whom the Lord gave wisdom and intelligence, so as to know how to work skillfully, made that which was necessary for the uses of the Sanctuary and which the Lord had instructed.

2 And when Moses had called them and every man of learning, to whom the Lord had given wisdom, and who, of their own accord, had offered themselves in order to accomplish this work,

3 he handed over to them all the donations of the sons of Israel. And while they were pursuing this work, the people offered what they had vowed each day, in the morning.

4 The artisans were compelled by this to go

5 to Moses and to say, "The people offer more than is needed."

6 Therefore, Moses ordered this to be recited, with a voice of proclamation: "Let neither man nor woman offer anything further for the work of the Sanctuary." And so they ceased from offering gifts,

7 because what was offered was sufficient and was more than an abundance.

8 And all those who were wise of heart, in order to accomplish the work of the tabernacle, made ten curtains of fine twisted linen, and hyacinth, and purple, and twice-dyed scarlet, with diverse workmanship by the art of embroidery.

9 Each of these was twenty-eight cubits in length, and in width, four. All the curtains were of one measure.

10 And he joined five curtains to one another, and the other five he coupled to one another.

11 He also made loops of hyacinth along the edge of one curtain on both sides, and similarly along the edge of the other curtain,

12 so that the loops might meet against one another and might be joined together.

13 For these, he also cast fifty gold rings, which would retain the loops of the curtains and so make the tabernacle one.

14 He also made eleven canopies from the hair of goats, in order to cover the roof of the tabernacle:

15 one canopy held in length thirty cubits, and in width four cubits. All the canopies were of one measure.

16 Five of these he joined by themselves, and the other six separately.

17 And he made fifty loops along the edge of one canopy, and fifty along the edge of the other canopy, so that they might be joined to one another,

18 and fifty buckles of brass, with which the roof might be woven together, so that from all the canopies there would be made one covering.

19 He also made a covering for the tabernacle from the skins of rams, dyed-red; and another cover above it, from violet skins.

20 He also made the standing panels of the tabernacle, from setim wood.

21 Ten cubits was the length of one panel, and one and one half cubits comprised the width.

22 There were two dovetails along every panel, so that one might be joined to the other. Thus did he make all the panels of the tabernacle.

23 Of these, twenty were toward the meridian area, opposite the south,

24 with forty bases of silver. Two bases were set under one panel at each of two sides at the corners, where the joints of the sides terminate in corners.

25 Likewise, at that side of the tabernacle which looks toward the north, he made twenty panels,

26 with forty bases of silver, two bases for each board.

27 Yet truly, opposite the west, that is, toward that part of the tabernacle which looks out toward the sea, he made six panels,

28 and two others at each corner of the tabernacle at the back,

29 which were joined from bottom to top and held together by one joint. So did he make both corners on that side.

30 So then, there were altogether eight panels, and they had sixteen bases of silver, with, of course, two bases under each panel.

31 He also made bars from setim wood: five to hold together the panels at one side of the tabernacle,

32 and five others to fit together the panels of the other side, and, in addition to these, five other bars toward the western area of the tabernacle, opposite the sea.

33 He also made another bar, which came through the middle of the panels from corner to corner.

34 But the panels themselves he overlaid with gold, casting silver bases for them. And he made their rings from gold, through which the bars might be able to be drawn. And he covered the bars themselves with layers of gold.

35 He also made a veil from hyacinth, and purple, from vermillion as well as fine twisted linen, with varied and distinctive embroidery,

36 and four columns of setim wood, which, along with their heads, he overlaid with gold, casting silver bases for them.

37 He also made a tent at the entrance of the tabernacle from hyacinth, purple, vermillion, and fine twisted linen, wrought with embroidery,

38 and five columns with their heads, which he covered with gold, and he cast their bases from brass.

Exodus 37

1 Now Bezalel also made the ark from setim wood, having two and one half cubits in length, and one and one half cubits in width, and the height was also one and one half cubits. And he clothed it with the purest gold, inside and out.

2 And for it he made a crown of gold all around,

3 casting four gold rings at its four corners: two rings on one side, and two on the other.

4 Likewise, he made bars from setim wood, which he clothed with gold,

5 and he placed them into the rings, which were at the sides of the ark, to carry it.

6 He also made the propitiatory, that is, the oracle, from the finest gold, two and one half cubits in length, and one and one half cubits in width,

7 and then two Cherubim of ductile gold, which he positioned at the two sides of the propitiatory:

8 one Cherub at the top of one side, and the other Cherub at the top of the other side. The two Cherubim were at each end of the propitiatory,

9 spreading their wings, and protecting the propitiatory, and gazing toward it and toward one another.

10 He also made the table from setim wood, with a length of two cubits, and a width of one cubit, which had a height of one and one half cubits.

11 And he surrounded it with the finest gold, and for it he made a ledge of gold all around,

12 and for the ledge itself he made a polished crown of gold, four fingers high, and upon the same, another crown of gold.

13 And he cast four gold rings, which he set at the four corners at each foot of the table,

14 opposite the crown. And he placed the bars into them, so that the table could be carried.

15 Likewise, the bars themselves he made from setim wood, and he surrounded them with gold.

16 And he made vessels for the diverse uses of the table, as well as the little cups, and bowls, and measuring cups, and the censers, from pure gold, in which the libations would be offered.

17 He also made the lampstand, formed from the finest gold. The branches, bowls, and little spheres, as well as the lilies, proceeded from its bar:

18 six on the two sides, three branches on one side, and three on the other.

19 Three bowls, the size of a nut, were on each branch, with little spheres and lilies, and three bowls, in the likeness of a nut, were on the other branch, with the little spheres together with the lilies. The workmanship of the six branches, which proceeded from the shaft of the lampstand, was equal.

20 Now on the shaft itself were four bowls, the size of a nut, and little spheres together with each one, and lilies,

21 and little spheres under two branches in three places, which together made six branches proceeding from one bar.

22 Thus, both the little spheres and the branches were from the same thing: all hand-worked from the purest gold.

23 He also made the seven lamps with their candle snuffers, and the vessels where the candles would be extinguished, from the finest gold.

24 The lampstand with all its vessels weighed a talent of gold.

25 He also made the altar of incense from setim wood, having one cubit on each of four sides, and in height, two. From its corners proceeded horns.

26 And he clothed it with the purest gold, with its grating, as well as the sides and the horns.

27 And for it he made a crown of gold all around, and two gold rings under the crown at each side, so that the bars might be put into them, and the altar could be carried.

28 Now the bars themselves he also made from setim wood, and he covered them with layers of gold.

29 He also composed the oil for the ointment of sanctification, and the incense, from the purest aromatics, with the skill of a perfumer.

Exodus 38

1 He also made the altar of holocaust from setim wood: five cubits square, and three in height,

2 the horns of which proceeded from the corners. And he covered it with layers of brass.

3 And for its uses, he prepared diverse vessels out of brass: kettles, forceps, little hooks, larger hooks, and receptacles for the fire.

4 And he made its grating of brass, in the manner of a net, and under it, in the midst of the altar, its base,

5 casting four rings at the four ends of the net in order to set the bars, so as to carry it.

6 These bars he also made of setim wood, and he covered them with layers of brass.

7 And he drew them through the rings, which projected from the sides of the altar. But the altar itself was not solid, but hollow, made from panels and empty inside.

8 He also made the washtub of brass, with its base made from the mirrors of the women who kept watch at the door of the tabernacle.

9 He also made the atrium, at the south side of which were hangings of fine twisted linen of one hundred cubits and

10 twenty columns of brass with their bases. The heads of the columns and all of the engraving work were of silver.

11 Equally, at the northern area, the hangings, the columns, and the bases and heads of the columns were of the same measure and work and metal.

12 Yet truly, on that side which looks out toward the west, there were hangings of fifty cubits, and ten columns with their bases of brass. And the heads of the columns and all of the engraving work were of silver.

13 Furthermore, toward the east, he prepared hangings of fifty cubits:

14 of which, there were fifteen cubits, among three columns with their bases, holding up one side,

15 and on the other side, (for between the two he made the entrance of the tabernacle) there were equally hangings of fifteen cubits, and three pillars, and the same number of bases.

16 All the hangings of the atrium were woven from fine twisted linen.

17 The bases of the columns were of brass, but their heads with all of their engravings were of silver. Now he also overlaid the columns of the atrium themselves with silver.

18 And he made, at its entrance, a hanging, wrought with embroidery, of hyacinth, purple, vermillion, and fine twisted linen, which held twenty cubits in length, yet truly it was five cubits in height, as with the measure of all the hangings of the atrium.

19 Now the columns at the entrance were four, with bases of brass, and their heads and engravings were of silver.

20 Likewise, the tent pegs of the tabernacle and the atrium all around he made of brass.

21 These are the instruments of the tabernacle of the testimony, which were enumerated according to the instruction of Moses, with the ceremonies of the Levites, by the hand of Ithamar, the son of Aaron the priest,

22 which Bezalel, the son of Uri, the son of Hur from the tribe of Judah, had completed, just as the Lord decreed through Moses.

23 He was joined by his associate, Oholiab, the son of Ahisamach, from the tribe of Dan, who himself was also an exceptional artisan of wood, and of weaving, as well as of embroidery, with hyacinth, purple, vermillion, and fine linen.

24 All of the gold that was expended in the work of the Sanctuary, and that was offered in donation, was twenty-nine talents and seven hundred thirty shekels, according to the measure of the Sanctuary.

25 Now it was offered by those who were past the numbering of twenty years and above: from six hundred and three thousand, five hundred and fifty men able to bear arms.

26 There were, beyond that, one hundred talents of silver, from which were cast the bases for the Sanctuary and for the entrance where the veil hangs.

27 One hundred bases were made from one hundred talents, a single talent being counted for each base.

28 But from one thousand seven hundred and seventy-five, he made the heads of the columns, which he also clothed with silver.

29 Likewise, of brass, there was offered seventy-two thousand talents, and four hundred more shekels,

30 from which were cast the bases at the entrance of the tabernacle of the testimony, and the altar of brass with its grating, and the vessels which pertain to its use,

31 and the bases of the atrium, as much at the circumference as at its entrance, and the tent pegs of the tabernacle and of the atrium all round.

Exodus 39

1 Truly, from hyacinth and purple, vermillion and fine linen, he made the vestments with which Aaron was clothed when he ministered in the holy places, just as the Lord instructed Moses.

2 And so he made an ephod of gold, hyacinth, and purple, and twice-dyed scarlet, and fine twisted linen,

3 wrought with embroidery. And he cut thin strips of gold and drew them into threads, so that they could be twisted into the weave of the first colors.

4 And he made two edges, coupled to one another at the top of both sides,

5 and a wide belt from the same colors, just as the Lord had instructed Moses.

6 He also prepared two onyx stones, set and enclosed in gold, and engraved with the skill of a jeweler, with the names of the sons of Israel.

7 And he set them in the sides of the ephod, as a memorial to the sons of Israel, just as the Lord had instructed Moses.

8 He also made a breastplate, wrought with embroidery, according to the work of the ephod, from gold, hyacinth, purple, and twice-dyed scarlet, and fine twisted linen:

9 with four equal sides, doubled, of the measure of the palm of a hand.

10 And he set four rows of gems in it. In the first row was a sardius stone, a topaz, an emerald;

11 in the second was a garnet, a sapphire, and a jasper;

12 in the third was a zircon, an agate, and an amethyst;

13 in the fourth was a chrysolite, an onyx, and a beryl, surrounded and enclosed in gold by their rows.

14 And these twelve stones were engraved with the names of the twelve tribes of Israel, each one with a single name.

15 They also made, in the breastplate, little chains linked to one another, from the purest gold,

16 and two hooks, and the same number of gold rings. Moreover, they set the rings at both sides of the breastplate,

17 from which two golden chains would hang, which they connected with the hooks that projected from the corners of the ephod.

18 These were both in front and in back so that they met one another, and so that the ephod and the breastplate were woven together,

19 being fastened to the wide belt and strongly coupled with rings, to which a hyacinth band was joined, lest they should shake loose and be moved away from one another, just as the Lord instructed Moses.

20 They also made the tunic of the ephod entirely from hyacinth,

21 with the head in the upper part at the middle, and a woven edge all around the head.

22 Then, at the feet below, they also made pomegranates from hyacinth, purple, vermillion, and fine twisted linen,

23 and little bells from the purest gold, which they set between the pomegranates at the very bottom of the tunic all around.

24 So then, the high priest approached, adorned with gold bell and pomegranate, when he performed his ministry, just as the Lord had instructed Moses.

25 They also made fine linen tunics with woven work, for Aaron and his sons,

26 and headdresses with their little crowns of fine linen,

27 and also linen undergarments of fine linen.

28 Truly, they also made a wide band of fine twisted linen, hyacinth, purple, as well as vermillion, twice-dyed, with skillful embroidery, just as the Lord had instructed Moses.

29 They also made the plate of sacred veneration from the purest gold, and they wrote on it, with the skill of a jeweler: "Holy to the Lord."

30 And they fastened it to the headdress with a hyacinth band, just as the Lord had instructed Moses.

31 And so all the work of the tabernacle and of the covering of the testimony was completed. And the sons of Israel did all that the Lord had instructed Moses.

32 And they offered the tabernacle, and the covering, and all of the articles: the rings, the panels, the bars, the columns and bases,

33 the cover of the skins of rams, dyed red, and the other cover of violet skins,

34 the veil, the ark, the bars, the propitiatory,

35 the table, with its vessels and the bread of the presence,

36 the lampstand, the lamps, and their utensils with the oil,

37 the altar of gold, and the ointment, and the incense of aromatics,

38 and the tent at the entrance of the tabernacle,

39 the altar of brass, the grating, the bars, and all of its vessels, the washtub with its base, the hangings of the atrium, and the columns with their bases,

40 the hanging at the entrance of the atrium, and their little cords and pegs. Nothing was lacking of the articles that were commanded to be made for the ministry of the tabernacle and for the covering of the covenant.

41 Likewise, the vestments, which the priests, namely, Aaron and his sons, make use of use in the Sanctuary,

42 the sons of Israel offered, just as the Lord had instructed.

43 After this, when Moses saw that everything was completed, he blessed them.

Exodus 40

1 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

2 "In the first month, on the first day of the month, you shall raise the tabernacle of the testimony,

3 and you shall place the ark in it, and you shall release the veil before it.

4 And having brought in the table, you shall place the things which were solemnly commanded upon it. The lampstand shall stand with its lamps,

5 and the altar of gold, in which the incense is burned, shall stand before the ark of the testimony. You shall place the tent at the entrance of the tabernacle,

6 and before it, the altar of holocaust.

7 The washtub shall stand between the altar and the tabernacle, and you shall fill it with water.

8 And you shall encompass the atrium and its entrance with hangings.

9 And, having taken up the oil of unction, you shall anoint the tabernacle along with its articles, so that they may be sanctified.

10 The altar of holocaust and all its vessels,

11 the washtub with its base, and all things, you shall consecrate with the oil of unction, so that they may be the Holy of holies.

12 And you shall bring forward Aaron and his sons to the entrance of the tabernacle of the testimony, and, having washed them with water,

13 you shall clothe them in the holy vestments, so that they may minister to me, and so that their unction may accomplish an everlasting priesthood."

14 And Moses did all that the Lord had instructed.

15 Therefore, in the first month of the second year, on the first day of the month, the tabernacle was put in place.

16 And Moses raised it up, and he positioned the panels as well as the bases and the bars, and he set up the columns,

17 and he stretched out the roof over the tabernacle, imposing a cover above it, just as the Lord had decreed.

18 And he placed the testimony in the ark, applying the bars beneath, and the oracle above.

19 And when he had brought the ark into the tabernacle, he drew the veil before it, in order to fulfill the commandment of the Lord.

20 And he placed the table in the tabernacle of the testimony, at the north side, beyond the veil,

21 arranging before it the bread of the presence, just as the Lord had instructed Moses.

22 And he placed the lampstand in the tabernacle of the testimony, away from the table, on the south side,

23 setting the lamps in order, according to the precept of the Lord.

24 He also positioned the altar of gold under the roof of the testimony, opposite the veil,

25 and he heaped upon it the incense of aromatics, just as the Lord had commanded Moses.

26 And he positioned the tent at the entrance of the tabernacle of the testimony,

27 and the altar of holocaust in the vestibule of the testimony, offering the holocaust and the sacrifices upon it, just as the Lord had decreed.

28 Likewise, he stationed the washtub between the tabernacle of the testimony and the altar, filling it with water.

29 And Moses and Aaron, along with his sons, washed their hands and feet,

30 whenever they would enter the covering of the covenant, and when they approached to the altar, just as the Lord had instructed Moses.

31 And he raised up the atrium around the tabernacle and the altar, drawing the hanging at its entrance. After all these things were perfected,

32 the cloud covered the tabernacle of the testimony, and the glory of the Lord filled it.

33 Neither could Moses enter the covering of the covenant: the cloud was covering all things, and the majesty of the Lord was flashing. For the cloud had covered everything.

34 Whenever the cloud departed from the tabernacle, the sons of Israel set out by their companies.

35 But if it remained hanging over it, they remained in the same place.

36 Certainly, the cloud of the Lord lay over the tabernacle by day, and the fire by night, being seen by all the people of Israel throughout all their resting places.

Leviticus 1

1 Then the Lord called Moses and spoke to him from the tabernacle of the testimony, saying:

2 Speak to the sons of Israel, and you shall say to them: The man among you who will offer to the Lord a sacrifice from the cattle, that is, an offering of victims of oxen or sheep:

3 if his offering will be a holocaust, as well as from the herd, he shall offer an immaculate male at the door of the tabernacle of the testimony, to make himself pleasing to the Lord.

4 And he shall place his hand on the head of the sacrifice, and so it shall be acceptable and effective, in its expiation.

5 And he shall immolate the calf in the sight of the Lord. And the priests, the sons of Aaron, shall offer its blood, pouring it all around the altar, which is before the door of the tabernacle.

6 And having pulled away the skin of the victim, they shall cut up the joints into pieces,

7 and they shall toss fire under the altar, having arranged beforehand a stack of wood.

8 And they shall lay the parts which are cut up in order upon it: namely, the head, and all the things that adjoin to the liver,

9 the intestines and feet having been washed with water. And the priest shall burn them on the altar as a holocaust and as a sweet odor to the Lord.

10 But if the offering is from the flocks, a holocaust either of sheep or goats, he shall offer a male without blemish.

11 And he shall immolate it at the side of the altar which looks out toward the north, in the sight of the Lord. Yet truly, the sons of Aaron shall pour its blood upon the altar all around.

12 And they shall divide the limbs, the head, and everything that adjoins to the liver. And they shall place them on the wood, under which the fire is to be thrown.

13 Yet truly, the intestines and the feet they shall wash with water. And the priest, having offered everything, shall burn it upon the altar as a holocaust and as a most sweet odor to the Lord.

14 But if the oblation of a holocaust to the Lord is of birds, either of turtledoves, or young pigeons,

15 the priest shall offer it at the altar: and twisting back the neck with the head, and also rupturing the place of the wound, he shall make the blood run down over the edge of the altar.

16 Yet truly, the craw of the throat and the feathers he shall cast near the altar at the eastern section, in the place where the ashes are usually poured out.

17 And he shall break its wing joints, but he shall neither cut, nor divide it with metal, and he shall burn it upon the altar, placing fire under the wood. It is a holocaust and an oblation of a most sweet odor to the Lord.

Leviticus 2

1 When a soul will offer an oblation of sacrifice to the Lord, his oblation shall be of fine wheat flour, and he shall pour oil over it, and he shall set down frankincense,

2 and he shall bring it to the sons of Aaron, the priests. One of them shall take a handful of the flour with oil, as well as all the frankincense, and he shall place it as a memorial upon the altar, as a most sweet odor to the Lord.

3 Then what will remain of the sacrifice shall be for Aaron and his sons, the Holy of holies from the oblations of the Lord.

4 But when you will offer a sacrifice baked in the oven from fine wheat flour, specifically: loaves without leaven, sprinkled with oil, and unleavened wafers, rubbed with oil:

5 if your oblation will be from the frying pan, of flour tempered with oil and without leaven,

6 you shall divide it into little pieces and pour oil over it.

7 But if the sacrifice will be from the oven grating, equally the fine wheat flour shall be sprinkled with oil.

8 When you are offering it to the Lord, you shall deliver it into the hands of the priest.

9 And when he has offered it, he shall take a memorial from the sacrifice and burn it upon the altar as a sweet odor to the Lord.

10 But whatever is left shall be for Aaron and his sons, the Holy of holies from the oblations of the Lord.

11 Every oblation that is offered to the Lord shall be made without leaven; neither shall any leaven or honey be burned with the sacrifice to the Lord.

12 You shall offer only the first-fruits of these along with the gifts. Yet truly, these shall not be placed upon the altar as an odor of sweetness.

13 Whatever sacrifice you will offer, you shall season it with salt; neither shall you take away the salt of the covenant of your God from your sacrifice. In all your oblations, you shall offer salt.

14 But if you will offer a gift of the first-fruits of your grain to the Lord, from ears of grain still green, you shall parch it at the fire, and break it open in the manner of meal. And so shall you offer your first-fruits to the Lord:

15 pouring oil over it, and imposing frankincense, because it is an oblation of the Lord.

16 From this, the priest shall burn, as a memorial of the gift, a portion of the cracked grain and the oil, as well as all of the frankincense.

Leviticus 3

1 But if his oblation will be a sacrifice of peace offerings, and he wishes to offer it from the oxen, whether male or female, he shall offer what is immaculate, in the sight of the Lord.

2 And he shall place his hand upon the head of his victim, which shall be immolated at the entrance of the tabernacle of the testimony. And the sons of Aaron, the priests, shall pour the blood all around the altar.

3 And they shall offer from the sacrifice of peace offerings, as an oblation to the Lord: the fat which covers the vital organs, and whatever fat is interior,

4 the two kidneys with the fat that covers the sides, and the mesh of the liver with the two little kidneys.

5 And they shall burn them upon the altar as a holocaust, placing fire under the wood, as an oblation of a most sweet odor to the Lord.

6 Yet truly, if his oblation and the sacrifice of peace offerings will be from the sheep, whether he will offer a male or a female, they shall be immaculate.

7 If he will offer a lamb in the sight of the Lord,

8 he shall place his hand upon the head of the victim. And it shall be immolated at the vestibule of the tabernacle of the testimony. And the sons of Aaron shall pour its blood all around the altar.

9 And they shall offer from the victim of peace offerings, as a sacrifice to the Lord: the fat, and the entire rump

10 with the kidneys, and the fat that covers the abdomen, and all the vital organs, and both the little kidneys with the fat that is near the sides, and the mesh of the liver with the little kidneys.

11 And the priest shall burn them upon the altar, as fuel for the fire and as an oblation of the Lord.

12 If his oblation will be a goat, and he will offer it to the Lord,

13 he shall place his hand upon its head, and he shall immolate it at the entrance of the tabernacle of the testimony. And the sons of Aaron shall pour its blood all around the altar.

14 And they shall take from it, to feed the Lord's fire: the fat which covers the abdomen, and that which covers all the vital organs,

15 the two little kidneys with the mesh that is over them near the sides, and the fat of the liver with the little kidneys.

16 And the priest shall burn them upon the altar, as nourishment for the fire and as a most sweet odor. All the fat shall be for the Lord;

17 by a perpetual law, in your generations and in all of your habitations, neither blood nor fat shall you eat at all.

Leviticus 4

1 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

2 Say to the sons of Israel: The soul which will have sinned through ignorance, and concerning any of the commandments of the Lord that he instructed not to be done, if anything at all has been done:

3 if the priest, who is anointed, will have sinned, causing the people to commit a transgression, he shall offer to the Lord for his sin an immaculate calf.

4 And he shall lead it to the door of the tabernacle of the testimony in the sight of the Lord. And he shall place his hand upon its head, and he shall immolate it to the Lord.

5 Likewise, he shall take from the blood of the calf, carrying it into the tabernacle of the testimony,

6 and having dipped his finger into the blood, he shall sprinkle it seven times in the sight of the Lord, opposite the veil of the Sanctuary.

7 And he shall place some of the same blood over the horns of the altar of most pleasing incense to the Lord, which is in the tabernacle of the testimony. Then he shall pour out the remainder of the blood at the base of the altar of holocaust at the entrance of the tabernacle.

8 And, on behalf of the sin, he shall take the fat of the calf, both that which covers the vital organs and all that is interior,

9 the two little kidneys, and the mesh that is on them near the sides, and the fat of the liver with the little kidneys,

10 just as it is taken from the calf of the sacrifice of peace offerings. And he shall burn them upon the altar of holocaust.

11 Yet truly, the skin and all the flesh, with the head and the feet, and the intestines and the dung,

12 and the remainder of the body, he shall carry away, beyond the camp, to the clean place where the ashes are usually poured out. And he shall burn them upon a stack of wood. There, in the place where the ashes have been poured out, they will be burned.

13 But if all the crowd of Israel will have been ignorant, and through inexperience will have done what is contrary to the commandment of the Lord,

14 and afterwards shall understand their sin: they shall offer a calf on behalf of their sin, and they shall lead it to the door of the tabernacle.

15 And the elders of the people shall place their hands upon its head in the sight of the Lord. And when the calf has been immolated in the sight of the Lord,

16 the priest who is anointed shall carry some of its blood into the tabernacle of the testimony.

17 and he shall dip his finger in it, sprinkling it seven times opposite the veil.

18 And he shall place some of the same blood on the horns of the altar, which is in the presence of the Lord in the tabernacle of the testimony. But the remainder of the blood he shall pour out at the base of the altar of holocaust, which is at the door of the tabernacle of the testimony.

19 And he shall take all its fat and burn it upon the altar,

20 doing so with this calf in the same manner as he did before. And while the priest is praying for them, the Lord will forgive them.

21 But the calf itself he shall carry away, beyond the camp, and he shall also burn it, just as with the previous calf, because it is for the sin of the multitude.

22 If a leader will have sinned, and through ignorance will have done one of the many things which the law of the Lord prohibits,

23 and afterwards he shall understand his sin: he shall offer an immaculate he-goat from among the goats, as a sacrifice to the Lord.

24 And he shall place his hand upon its head. And when he will have immolated it, in the place where the holocaust is usually slain, in the sight of the Lord, because it is for sin,

25 the priest shall dip his finger in the blood of the victim for sin, touching the horns of the altar of holocaust, and pouring out the remainder at its base.

26 Yet truly, the fat he shall burn upon it, just as is usually done with the victims of peace offerings. And the priest shall pray for him and for his sin, and he shall be released from it.

27 But if a soul from the people of the land will have sinned through ignorance, so as to have done any of those things that the law of the Lord prohibits, and so commit a transgression,

28 and he shall realize his sin: he shall offer an immaculate she-goat.

29 And he shall place his hand upon the head of the victim which is for sin. And he shall immolate it in the place of the holocaust.

30 And the priest shall take some of the blood with his finger, and touching the horns of the altar of holocaust, he shall pour out the remainder at its base.

31 But taking away all the fat, just as it is usually taken away from the victims of peace offerings, he shall burn it upon the altar as a sweet odor to the Lord. And he shall pray for him, and he shall be released from it.

32 But if instead he will offer from the flock a victim for his sin, specifically, an immaculate female sheep:

33 he shall place his hand upon its head, and he shall immolate it in the place where the victims of holocausts are usually slain.

34 And the priest shall take some of its blood with his finger, and touching the horns of the altar of holocaust, he shall pour out the remainder at its base.

35 Likewise, all of the fat shall be taken away, just as the fat of the ram, which is immolated for peace offerings, is usually taken away. And he shall burn it upon the altar as an incense of the Lord. And he shall pray for him and for his sin, and he shall be released from it.

Leviticus 5

1 If a soul will have sinned, and heard the voice of one testifying under oath, and he is a witness because either he has seen it himself, or he is aware of it: if he does not reveal it, he shall carry his iniquity.

2 The soul that will have touched anything unclean, either that which has been killed by a beast, or that which has died on its own, or any other creeping thing, and will have forgotten its uncleanness, he is guilty and has committed a transgression.

3 And if he will have touched anything from the uncleanness of man, according to every kind of impurity by which he may be defiled, and having forgotten it, afterwards realizes it, he shall be guilty of committing a transgression.

4 The soul who swears and offers from his own lips that he would do either evil or good, and who will have bound the same with an oath and with his own words, and, having forgotten it, afterwards understands his transgression,

5 let him do penance for his sin,

6 and let him offer from the flocks a female lamb or a she-goat, and the priest shall pray for him and for his sin.

7 But if he is not able to offer a beast, let him offer two turtledoves or two young pigeons to the Lord, one for sin, and the other for a holocaust.

8 And he shall give them to the priest, who, offering the first for sin, shall twist back its head to the little wings, so that it adheres to the neck and is not entirely broken off.

9 And he shall sprinkle some of its blood at the side of the altar. But whatever will remain, he shall cause it to drip down to the base, because it is for sin.

10 Yet truly, the other he shall burn as a holocaust, just as is usually done. And the priest shall pray for him, and for his sin, and he shall be released from it.

11 But if his hand is unable to offer two turtledoves or two young pigeons, he shall offer, for his sin, the tenth part of an ephah of fine wheat flour. He shall not put oil in it, nor place upon it any frankincense, because it is for sin.

12 And he shall deliver it to the priest, who shall take a handful of it, and shall burn it upon the altar as a memorial for him who offered it,

13 praying for him and making atonement. Yet truly, the remaining part he himself shall have as a gift.

14 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

15 If a soul, by mistake, shall have transgressed the ceremonies in those things that are sanctified to the Lord, he shall offer for his offense an immaculate ram from the flocks, such as can be bought for two shekels, according to the weight of the Sanctuary.

16 And he shall make restitution for the damage that he has brought, and he shall add a fifth part more, delivering it to the priest, who shall pray for him while offering the ram, and he shall be released from it.

17 If a soul will have sinned through ignorance, and will have done one of those things which the law of the Lord prohibits, and, being guilty of sin, understands his iniquity,

18 he shall offer from the flocks an immaculate ram to the priest, according to the measure and estimation of the sin, who shall pray for him, because he did it unknowingly, and he shall be released from it,

19 because by mistake he transgressed against the Lord.

Leviticus 6

1 The Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

2 The soul who will have sinned, and, despising the Lord, will have denied to his neighbor the deposit which he had entrusted to his safekeeping, or who will have extorted anything by force, or who will have made a false accusation,

3 or who will have found a lost thing and then also withheld it by swearing falsely, or who will have done any other of the many things by which men usually sin:

4 being convicted of the offense, he shall restore

5 all that he wanted to obtain by fraud, the whole plus an additional fifth part, to the owner against whom he brought the damage.

6 Then, on behalf of his sin, he shall offer an immaculate ram from the flock, and he shall give it to the priest, according to the estimation and measure of the offense.

7 And he shall pray for him in the sight of the Lord, and he shall be released from any one of those things that he did when he sinned.

8 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

9 Instruct Aaron and his sons: This is the law of a holocaust. It shall be burned upon the altar, all night until morning. The fire shall be from the same altar.

10 The priest shall be vested with the tunic and the linen undergarments. And he shall take up the ashes of that which the devouring fire has consumed, and, placing them next to the altar,

11 he shall strip off his former vestments, and being clothed with others, he shall carry them beyond the camp, and he shall cause them to be consumed, even to glowing embers, in a very clean place.

12 But the fire on the altar shall burn always, for the priest shall nourish it by placing wood under it each day in the morning. And, laying down the holocaust, he shall burn the fat of the peace offerings upon it.

13 This is the perpetual fire which shall never fail upon the altar.

14 This is the law of the sacrifice and the libations, which the sons of Aaron shall offer in the sight of the Lord, and before the altar.

15 The priest shall take a handful of fine wheat flour, which has been sprinkled with oil, and all the frankincense, which has been placed upon the flour, and he shall burn it upon the altar as a memorial of most sweet odor to the Lord.

16 And the remaining portion of the flour, Aaron shall eat with his sons, without leaven. And he shall eat it in the holy place, in the atrium of the tabernacle.

17 Yet for this reason, it shall not be leavened, because part of it is offered as an incense of the Lord. The Holy of holies shall it be, just as what is offered on behalf of sin and of transgression.

18 Only the males of the stock of Aaron shall eat it. This shall be an everlasting ordinance in your generations concerning the sacrifices of the Lord. All who will touch these shall be sanctified.

19 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

20 This is the oblation of Aaron and of his sons, which they must offer to the Lord in the day of their anointing. They shall offer a tenth part of an ephah of fine wheat flour as a perpetual sacrifice, half of it in the morning, and half of it in the evening.

21 It shall be sprinkled with oil and fried in a frying pan. Then it shall be offered hot, as a most sweet odor to the Lord,

22 by the priest who by law succeeds his father. And it shall be entirely burned on the altar.

23 For every sacrifice of the priest shall be consumed by fire; neither shall anyone eat from it.

24 Then the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

25 Say to Aaron and his sons: This is the law of the victim for sin. In the place where the holocaust is offered, it shall be immolated in the sight of the Lord. It is the Holy of holies.

26 The priest who offers it shall eat it in the holy place, in the atrium of the tabernacle.

27 Whatever will touch its flesh shall be sanctified. If a garment will be sprinkled with its blood, it shall be washed in a holy place.

28 Then the earthen vessel, in which it was soaked, shall be broken. But if the vessel will be of brass, it shall be scoured and washed with water.

29 Every male of priestly descent shall feed on its flesh, because it is the Holy of holies.

30 For the victim that is slain for sin, whose blood is carried into the tabernacle of the testimony, for expiation in the Sanctuary, shall not be eaten, but it shall be consumed by fire.

Leviticus 7

1 Likewise, this is the law of the sacrifice for a transgression. It is the Holy of holies.

2 Therefore, where the holocaust is immolated, the victim for a transgression shall also be slain. Its blood shall be poured out all around the altar.

3 They shall offer from it: the rump, and the fat that covers the vital organs,

4 the two little kidneys, and the fat that is near the sides, and the mesh of the liver with the little kidneys.

5 And the priest shall burn them upon the altar. It is the incense of the Lord on behalf of a transgression.

6 Every male of priestly descent shall feed on this flesh in a holy place, because it is the Holy of holies.

7 Just as the sacrifice for sin is offered, so also for a transgression; one law shall be for both sacrifices. It shall belong to the priest who offers it.

8 The priest who offers the victim of holocaust shall have its skin.

9 And every sacrifice of fine wheat flour which is baked in the oven, and whatever is prepared on the oven grating or in the frying pan, shall be for the priest who offers it.

10 Whether these will be sprinkled with oil, or left dry, an equal measure shall be divided to each one of the sons of Aaron.

11 This is the law of the victim of peace offerings, which is offered to the Lord.

12 If the oblation will be an act for giving thanks, they shall offer bread without leaven sprinkled with oil, and unleavened wafers anointed with oil, and fine wheat flour fried, and cakes sprinkled and mixed with oil,

13 and also, leavened bread with the sacrifice of thanksgiving, which is immolated for peace offerings.

14 Of these, one shall be offered to the Lord as the first-fruits, and one shall be for the priest who will pour out the blood of the victim.

15 The flesh of it shall be eaten on the same day; neither shall any of it remain until morning.

16 If anyone, by a vow or of his own accord, will have offered a sacrifice, it shall be eaten in a similar manner on the same day. But then if any of it will have remained until tomorrow, it is lawful to eat it.

17 Then whatever will be found on the third day shall be consumed with fire.

18 If anyone will have eaten from the flesh of the victim of peace offerings on the third day, the oblation will be nullified; neither will it benefit the one who offered it. But instead, whatever soul will contaminate itself with such foods will be guilty of a betrayal.

19 The flesh that has touched anything unclean shall not be eaten, but it shall be burnt with fire. He that is clean will feed on it.

20 If a soul which is polluted will have eaten from the flesh of the sacrifice of peace offerings, which is offered to the Lord, he shall perish from his people.

21 And whoever will have touched the uncleanness of man, or of beast, or of anything which is able to defile, and who will have eaten from this kind of flesh, shall be cut off from his people.

22 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

23 Say to the sons of Israel: The fat of a sheep, and of an ox, and of a goat you shall not eat.

24 The fat of a carcass that has died on its own, or of an animal that has been seized by a wild beast, you shall have for various uses.

25 If anyone will have eaten the fat which ought to be offered as a burnt sacrifice of the Lord, he shall perish from his people.

26 Likewise, you shall not take as food the blood of any animals at all, whether of birds or beasts.

27 Every soul that will have eaten blood shall perish from his people.

28 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

29 Speak to the sons of Israel, saying: Whoever offers a victim of peace offerings to the Lord, let him also offer at the same time a sacrifice, that is, its libations.

30 He shall hold in his hands the fat of the victim, and the breast. And when he will have offered and consecrated both to the Lord, he shall deliver them to the priest,

31 who shall burn the fat upon the altar. But the breast shall be for Aaron and his sons.

32 Likewise also, the right shoulder of the victim of peace offerings shall fall to the priest as first-fruits.

33 Among the sons of Aaron, whoever will have offered the blood and the fat, the same one shall also have the right shoulder for his portion.

34 So then, the breast that is lifted up, and the shoulder that is separated, I have taken from the sons of Israel, from their victims of peace offerings, and I have given these to Aaron the priest and to his sons, as a law in perpetuity, from all the people of Israel.

35 This is the anointing of Aaron and his sons, by the ceremonies of the Lord, in the day when Moses offered them, so that they may fulfill the priesthood,

36 and this is what the Lord instructed to be given to them by the sons of Israel, as a perpetual observance in their generations.

37 This is the law of the holocaust, and of the sacrifice for sin, and for transgression, and for consecration, and for the victims of peace offerings,

38 which the Lord appointed to Moses on mount Sinai, when he commanded the sons of Israel to offer their oblations to the Lord in the desert of Sinai.

Leviticus 8

1 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

2 Take Aaron, with his sons, their vestments, and the oil of anointing, a calf for sin, two rams, and a basket with unleavened bread,

3 and gather together all the assembly at the door of the tabernacle.

4 And Moses did as the Lord had commanded. And when all the crowd was gathered together before the entrance of the tabernacle,

5 he said: "This is the word that the Lord has ordered to be done."

6 And immediately, he brought forward Aaron and his sons. And when he had washed them,

7 he vested the high priest with the linen undergarment, wrapped him with the wide belt, and clothed him with the hyacinth tunic, and over it he imposed the ephod.

8 And tying it to the belt, he fitted it to the breastplate, on which was Doctrine and Truth.

9 Also, he wrapped the headdress on his head, and over it, opposite the forehead, he placed the plate of gold, consecrated with sanctification, just as the Lord had instructed him.

10 He also took up the oil of anointing, with which he anointed the tabernacle, along with all of its articles.

11 And when he had sprinkled the altar seven times to sanctify it, he anointed it and all its vessels. And the washtub with its base he sanctified with the oil.

12 And pouring the oil over Aaron's head, he anointed and consecrated him.

13 Likewise, after he had offered his sons, he vested them with linen tunics, and wrapped them with wide belts, and placed headdresses on them, just as the Lord had ordered.

14 He also offered the calf for sin. And when Aaron and his sons had placed their hands upon its head,

15 he immolated it. And drawing the blood, and dipping his finger in it, he touched the horns of the altar all around. And when it was expiated and sanctified, he poured out the remainder of the blood at its base.

16 Yet truly, the fat which was on the vital organs, and the mesh of the liver, and the two little kidneys with their fat, he burned upon the altar.

17 And the calf with the skin, and the flesh, and the dung, he burned beyond the camp, just as the Lord had instructed.

18 He also offered a ram as a holocaust. And when Aaron and his sons had imposed their hands upon its head,

19 he immolated it, and he poured out its blood around the altar.

20 And cutting the ram into pieces, he burned its head, and the limbs, and the fat in the fire,

21 having first washed the intestines and the feet. And then he burned the whole of the ram upon the altar, because it was a holocaust of most sweet odor to the Lord, just as he had instructed him.

22 He also offered the second ram, as a consecration of priests. And Aaron and his sons placed their hands upon its head.

23 And when Moses had immolated it, taking up some of its blood, he touched the tip of Aaron's right ear, and the thumb of his right hand, and similarly also his foot.

24 He also offered the sons of Aaron. And when, from the blood of the ram which was immolated, he had touched the tip of the right ear of each one, and the thumbs of their right hands, as well as their feet, he poured out the remainder upon the altar all around.

25 Yet truly, the fat, and the rump, and all the fat that covers the intestines, and the mesh of the liver, and the two kidneys with their fat, and the right shoulder, he separated.

26 Then, taking bread without leaven from the basket of unleavened bread, which was before the Lord, and a cake sprinkled with oil, and a wafer, he placed them upon the fat and the right shoulder,

27 delivering all these to Aaron and his sons. And when they had lifted them up in the sight of the Lord,

28 he received them again from their hands, and he burned them upon the altar of holocaust, because it was an oblation of consecration, as a sweet odor of sacrifice to the Lord.

29 And he took his portion from the ram of consecration, and he lifted up its breast in the sight of the Lord, just as the Lord had instructed him.

30 And taking up the ointment, and the blood that was on the altar, he sprinkled it over Aaron and his vestments, and over his sons and their vestments.

31 And when he had sanctified them with their vestments, he instructed them, saying: "Cook the flesh before the entrance of the tabernacle, and eat it there. Likewise, eat the loaves of consecration, which have been placed in the basket, just as the Lord instructed me, saying: 'Aaron and his sons shall eat them.'

32 Then whatever will remain of the flesh and the loaves shall be consumed with fire.

33 Also, you shall not exit from the door of the tabernacle for seven days, until the day on which the time of your consecration shall be completed. For in seven days the consecration is finished,

34 even as it has begun at this present time, so that the rite of the sacrifice might be accomplished.

35 Day and night you shall remain in the tabernacle, observing the watches of the Lord, otherwise you shall die. For so it has been commanded to me."

36 And Aaron and his sons did everything that the Lord spoke by the hand of Moses.

Leviticus 9

1 Then, the eighth day having arrived, Moses called Aaron and his sons, and those greater by birth from Israel, and he said to Aaron:

2 "Take a calf for sin from the herd, and a ram as a holocaust, both immaculate, and offer them in the sight of the Lord.

3 And to the sons of Israel, you shall say: 'Take a he-goat for sin, and a calf as well as a lamb, both one-year-old and without blemish, as a holocaust.

4 Take also an ox and a ram for peace offerings. And immolate them before the Lord, offering with the sacrifice of each one fine wheat flour sprinkled with oil. For today the Lord will appear to you.' "

5 And so they brought everything that Moses had ordered before the door of the tabernacle, where, when all the multitude stood together,

6 Moses said: "This is the word, which the Lord has instructed. Accomplish it, and his glory will appear to you."

7 And he said to Aaron: "Approach toward the altar, and immolate on behalf of your sin. Offer the holocaust, and pray for yourself and for the people. And when you have slain the victim for the people, pray for them, just as the Lord has instructed."

8 And immediately Aaron, approaching toward the altar, immolated the calf for his sin.

9 And his sons brought its blood to him, and dipping his finger in it, he touched the horns of the altar, and he poured out the remainder at its base.

10 And the fat, and the little kidneys, and the mesh of the liver, which are for sin, he burned upon the altar, just as the Lord had instructed Moses.

11 Yet truly, the flesh and its skins he burned with fire beyond the camp.

12 He also immolated the victim of holocaust. And his sons brought its blood to him, which he poured out all around the altar.

13 And when the victim itself was cut into pieces, they brought him the head and each of the limbs, all of which he burned with fire upon the altar,

14 having first washed the intestines and the feet with water.

15 And making an offering for the sin of the people, he slew the he-goat. And expiating the altar,

16 he accomplished the holocaust,

17 adding to it the sacrifice of the libations, which are to be offered together, and burning them upon the altar, separately from the ceremonies of the morning holocaust.

18 He also immolated the ox, as well as the ram, as peace offerings for the people. And his sons brought him the blood, which he poured out upon the altar all around.

19 Then the fat of the ox, and the rump of the ram, and the two little kidneys with their fat, and the mesh of the liver,

20 they placed upon the breasts. And when the fat had been burned upon the altar,

21 Aaron separated their breasts and the right shoulders, lifting them up in the sight of the Lord, as Moses had instructed.

22 And extending his hands to the people, he blessed them. And so, the victims for sin, and the holocausts, and the peace offerings being completed, he descended.

23 Then Moses and Aaron entered the tabernacle of the testimony, and afterwards came out and blessed the people. And the glory of the Lord appeared to the entire multitude.

24 And, behold, a fire from the Lord devoured the holocaust, and the fat which was on the altar. When the crowd had seen this, they praised the Lord, falling on their faces.

Leviticus 10

1 And the sons of Aaron, Nadab and Abihu, picking up their censers, placed fire in them and incense upon them, offering in the sight of the Lord a strange fire, such as was not instructed of them.

2 And fire coming out from the Lord destroyed them, and they died in the sight of the Lord.

3 And Moses said to Aaron: "This is what the Lord has spoken: 'I will be sanctified in those who approach me, and I will be glorified in the sight of all the people.' " And upon hearing this, Aaron was silent.

4 Then Moses called Mishael and Elzaphan, the sons of Uzziel, the paternal uncle of Aaron, and he said to them, "Go and take your brothers from the sight of the Sanctuary, and carry them beyond the camp."

5 And moving quickly, they took them as they lay, vested with linen tunics, and cast them outside, just as had been commanded them.

6 And Moses said to Aaron, and to his sons, Eleazar and Ithamar: "Do not uncover your heads, and do not rend your garments, lest perhaps you may die, and indignation may rise up over the entire assembly. Let your brothers, and all the house of Israel, bewail the burning that the Lord has kindled.

7 But you shall not depart from the door of the tabernacle; otherwise, you shall perish. For certainly the oil of holy anointing is upon you." And they did all things according to the precept of Moses.

8 The Lord also said to Aaron:

9 "You shall not drink wine, nor anything that is able to inebriate you or your sons, when you enter into the tabernacle of the testimony, lest you die. For it is an everlasting precept in your generations.

10 And so may you have the knowledge to discern between holy and profane, between polluted and clean.

11 And so may you teach the sons of Israel all my ordinances, which the Lord has spoken to them by the hand of Moses."

12 And Moses spoke to Aaron, and to his sons, Eleazar and Ithamar, who were remaining: "Take the sacrifice which remains from the oblation of the Lord, and eat it without leaven next to the altar, because it is the Holy of holies.

13 For you shall eat it in a holy place, which is given to you and to your sons, from the oblations of the Lord, just as has been instructed me.

14 Likewise, the breast which is offered, and the shoulder which is separated, you shall eat in a most clean place, you and your sons, and your daughters with you. For these have been set aside for you and your children from the victims which benefit the sons of Israel.

15 Since they have lifted up in the sight of the Lord, the shoulder, and the breast, and the fat that is burned on the altar, these also belong to you and to your sons as a perpetual law, just as the Lord has instructed."

16 Meanwhile, when Moses was searching for the he-goat, which had been offered for sin, he discovered it burned up. And being angry against Eleazar and Ithamar, the sons of Aaron who were remaining, he said:

17 "Why did you not eat the sacrifice for sin in the holy place, which is the Holy of holies, and which was given to you, so that you might carry the iniquity of the people, and might pray for them in the sight of the Lord,

18 especially since none of its blood has been brought into the holy places, and since you should have eaten it in the Sanctuary, as was instructed me?"

19 Aaron responded: "This day, the victim for sin has been offered, and the holocaust in the sight of the Lord. But you see what has happened to me. How could I eat it, or please the Lord in the ceremonies, having a sorrowful mind?"

20 But when Moses had heard this, he was satisfied.

Leviticus 11

1 And the Lord spoke to Moses and Aaron, saying:

2 Say to the sons of Israel: These are the animals that you ought to eat out of all the living things of the earth.

3 All that has a divided hoof, and that chews over again, among the cattle, you shall eat.

4 But whatever certainly chews over again, but has a hoof that is not divided, such as the camel and others, these you shall not eat, and you shall consider them to be among what is unclean.

5 The rock rabbit which chews over again, and whose hoof is not divided, is unclean,

6 and so also is the hare, for it too chews over again, yet its hoof is not divided,

7 and also the swine, which, though its hoof is divided, does not chew over again.

8 The flesh of these you shall not eat, nor shall you touch their carcasses, because they are unclean to you.

9 These are the things that breed in the waters, and which it is lawful to eat. All that has little fins and scales, as much in the sea, as in the rivers and ponds, you shall eat.

10 But whatever does not have fins and scales, of those things that live and move in the waters, shall be abominable to you,

11 and detestable; their flesh you shall not eat, and their carcasses you shall avoid.

12 All that does not have fins and scales in the waters shall be polluted.

13 These are those things among the birds which you must not eat, and which are to be avoided by you: the eagle, and the griffin, and the osprey,

14 and the kite, as well as the vulture, according to their kind.

15 and all that is of the raven kind, according to their likeness,

16 the ostrich, and the owl, and the gull, and the hawk, according to its kind,

17 the owl, and the sea bird, and the ibis,

18 and the swan, and the pelican, and the marsh hen,

19 the heron, and the plover according to its kind, the crested hoopoe, and also the bat.

20 Of all that flies, whatever steps upon four feet shall be abominable to you.

21 But whatever certainly walks upon four feet, and also has longer legs behind, with which it hops upon the earth,

22 you shall eat, such as the beetle in its kind, and the cricket, and grasshopper, and the locust, each one according to its kind.

23 But among flying things, whatever has only four feet shall be detestable to you.

24 And whoever will have touched their carcasses shall be defiled, and he shall be unclean until evening.

25 And if it will be necessary to carry any of these dead things, he shall wash his clothes, and he shall be unclean until the sun sets.

26 Every animal that certainly has a hoof, but which is not divided, nor does it chew over again, shall be unclean. And whoever will have touched it shall be contaminated.

27 Whatever walks upon its hands, out of all the animals that advance on all fours, shall be unclean. Whoever will have touched their carcasses shall be polluted until evening.

28 And whoever will have carried this kind of carcass shall wash his clothes, and he shall be unclean until evening. For all these are unclean to you.

29 Likewise, these shall be considered among the polluted things, out of all that moves upon the earth: the weasel, and the mouse, and the crocodile, each one according to its kind,

30 the shrew, and the chameleon, and the gecko, and the lizard, and the mole.

31 All these are unclean. Whoever will have touched their carcasses shall be unclean until evening.

32 And anything upon which something from their carcasses will have fallen shall be defiled, whether it is a vessel of wood, or a garment, or skins, or haircloths, or anything by which work is done. These shall be dipped in water and shall be defiled until evening, but then afterwards these shall be clean.

33 But an earthen vessel, into which something from these will fall, shall be defiled; and therefore it is to be broken.

34 Any of the foods that you eat, if water from such a vessel will have been poured upon it, it shall be unclean. And every liquid which one may drink from such a vessel shall be unclean.

35 And if anything from among these kinds of dead things has fallen upon it, it shall be unclean, whether it be an oven, or a pot with feet, these shall be unclean and shall be destroyed.

36 Yet truly, fountains and cisterns, and all reservoirs of water shall be clean. Whoever will have touched their carcasses shall be defiled.

37 If it falls upon seed grain, it shall not defile it.

38 But if anyone has poured water upon the seed grain, and afterwards it was touched by the carcasses, it shall be immediately defiled.

39 If any animals will have died, from which it is lawful for you to eat, whoever will have touched its carcass shall be unclean until evening.

40 And whoever will have eaten or carried anything of these shall wash his clothes, and he shall be unclean until evening.

41 All that creeps across the earth shall be abominable, neither shall it taken up as food.

42 Whatever advances by four feet upon the chest, or that has many feet, or that drags across the soil, you shall not eat, because it is abominable.

43 Do not be willing to contaminate your souls, nor shall you touch any of these, lest you become unclean.

44 For I am the Lord your God. Be holy, for I am Holy. Do not pollute your souls with any creeping thing, which moves across the land.

45 For I am the Lord, who led you away from the land of Egypt, so that I would be your God; you shall be holy, for I am Holy.

46 This is the law of animals and flying things, and of every living soul that moves in the waters or creeps upon the land,

47 so that you may know the difference between clean and unclean, and so that you may know what you ought to eat, and what you ought to refuse.

Leviticus 12

1 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

2 Speak to the sons of Israel, and you shall say to them: A woman, if she has received the seed to bear a male, shall be unclean for seven days, just as in the days of separation due to menstruation.

3 And on the eighth day, the little infant shall be circumcised.

4 Yet truly, she herself shall remain for thirty-three days in the blood of her purification. She shall not touch anything holy, nor shall she enter into the Sanctuary, until the days of her purification are completed.

5 But if she will bear a female, she shall be unclean for two weeks, according to the custom of her monthly flow, and she shall remain in the blood of her purification for sixty-six days.

6 And when the days of her purification have been completed, for a son or for a daughter, she shall bring to the door of the tabernacle of the testimony, a one-year-old lamb as a holocaust, and a young pigeon or a turtledove for sin, and she shall deliver them to the priest.

7 He shall offer them in the sight of the Lord, and he shall pray for her. And so she shall be cleansed from the issue of her blood. This is the law for one who bears a male or a female.

8 And if her hand has not obtained or been able to offer a lamb, she shall take two turtledoves or two young pigeons: one as a holocaust, and the other for sin. And the priest shall pray for her, and so she shall be cleansed.

Leviticus 13

1 And the Lord spoke to Moses and Aaron, saying:

2 The man in whose skin or flesh there will have arisen a diverse color, or a pustule, or something that seems to shine, which is the mark of leprosy, shall be brought to Aaron the priest, or to anyone you wish among his sons.

3 And if he sees that leprosy is in his skin, and that the hair has turned a white color, and that the place where the leprosy appears is lower than the rest of the skin and the flesh, then it is the mark of leprosy, and at his judgment he shall be separated.

4 But if there will be a shining whiteness in the skin, but it is not lower than the rest of the flesh, and the hair is of unaffected color, the priest shall seclude him for seven days.

5 And on the seventh day he shall examine him, and if the leprosy certainly has not increased further, and has not spread itself in the skin, he shall seclude him again, for another seven days.

6 And on the seventh day, he shall evaluate him. If the leprosy has become obscured, and has not increased in the skin, he shall declare him clean, because it is a scab. And the man shall wash his clothes, and he shall be clean.

7 But if the leprosy increases again, after he was seen by the priest and restored to cleanness, he shall be brought to him,

8 and he shall be condemned of uncleanness.

9 If the mark of leprosy has been in a man, he shall be brought to the priest,

10 and he shall look upon him. And when there is a white color in the skin, and it has an altered appearance in its hair, and also the same flesh seems alive,

11 it shall be judged a chronic leprosy, which has grown into the skin. And so the priest shall declare him contaminated, and he shall not seclude him, because he is clearly unclean.

12 But if the leprosy will have flourished, coursing through the skin, and will have covered all the skin from the head even to the feet, whatever falls under the sight of the eyes,

13 the priest shall examine him, and he shall judge that the leprosy that he possesses is very clean, because it has all turned to whiteness, and for this reason the man shall be clean.

14 Yet truly, when the living flesh shall appear in him,

15 then by the judgment of the priest he shall be polluted, and he shall be considered to be among the unclean. For the live flesh, if it is spotted with leprosy, is unclean.

16 And if again it will have turned into whiteness, and will have covered the entire man,

17 the priest shall examine him, and he shall discern him to be clean.

18 But when there has been an ulcer in the flesh and the skin, and it has healed,

19 and in the place of the ulcer, there appears a white or reddish scar, the man shall be brought to the priest.

20 And when he will have seen the place of the leprosy lower than the rest of the flesh, and that the hair has turned white, he shall declare him contaminated. For the plague of leprosy has arisen from the ulcer.

21 But if the hair is of the usual color, and the scar is somewhat obscure and is not lower than the nearby flesh, he shall seclude him for seven days.

22 And if it will have certainly increased, he shall judge him to have leprosy.

23 But if it stays in its place, it is the scar of an ulcer, and the man shall be clean.

24 But if flesh and skin has been burned by fire, and, having been healed, now has a white or red scar,

25 the priest shall examine it, and if he sees that it has turned white, and that its place is lower than the rest of the skin, he shall declare him contaminated, for the mark of leprosy has arisen in the scar.

26 But if the color of the hair has not been changed, nor is the mark lower than the rest of the flesh, and the leprosy itself appears to be somewhat obscure, he shall seclude him for seven days,

27 and on the seventh day he shall evaluate him. If the leprosy will have increased further in the skin, he shall declare him contaminated.

28 But if the whiteness stays in its place and is not very clear, it is the mark of a burn, and for this reason he shall be declared clean, because it is only the scar from a burn.

29 If leprosy will have sprung up in the head or the beard of a man or woman, the priest shall look upon them,

30 and if the place is certainly lower than the rest of the flesh, and the hair is golden, and thinner than usual, he shall declare them contaminated, because it is the leprosy of the head and the beard.

31 But if he sees that the place of the spot is equal with the nearby flesh, and that the hair is black, he shall seclude him for seven days,

32 and on the seventh day he shall examine it. If the spot has not increased, and the hair has kept its color, and the place of the mark is equal with the rest of the flesh,

33 the man shall be shaven, except in the place of the spot, and he shall be secluded for another seven days.

34 On the seventh day, if the mark seems to have stayed in its place, and it is not lower than the rest of the flesh, he shall declare him clean, and, his clothes having been washed, he shall be clean.

35 But if, after his cleansing, the spot will have increased again in the skin,

36 he shall no longer inquire as to whether the hair has turned yellow, because he is plainly unclean.

37 Furthermore, if the spot has not increased, and the hair is black, let him know that the man is healed: and let him confidently pronounce him clean.

38 If a whiteness will have appeared in the skin of a man or a woman,

39 the priest shall examine them. If he detects an obscured whiteness shining in the skin, may he know that it is not leprosy, but a white-colored blemish, and that the man is clean.

40 The man whose hair falls off of his head is bald and clean.

41 And if the hair falls off of his forehead, he is bald in front and clean.

42 But if in the bald head or bald forehead there has arisen a white or reddish color,

43 and the priest will have seen this, he shall condemn him without doubt of leprosy, which has arisen in the baldness.

44 Therefore, whoever will have been spotted by leprosy, and who has been separated at the judgment of the priest,

45 shall have his clothes unstitched, his head bare, his mouth covered with a cloth, and he himself shall cry out that he is contaminated and filthy.

46 The entire time that he is a leper and unclean he shall live alone outside the camp.

47 A woolen or linen garment that will have held the leprosy,

48 in the main fibers or in any of the threads, or certainly in a skin, or whatever has been made from a skin,

49 if it has been infected with a white or red spot, it shall be considered to be leprosy, and it shall be shown to the priest.

50 And he, having examined it, shall close it up for seven days.

51 And on the seventh day, having looked at it again, if he detects an increase, it is a persistent leprosy; he shall judge the garment to be polluted, along with everything with which it has been found.

52 And because of this, it shall be burned in flames.

53 But if he will have seen that it has not increased,

54 he shall instruct them, and they shall wash whatever has the leprosy in it, and he shall close it up for another seven days.

55 And when he will have seen that the former appearance has not returned, even if the leprosy has not increased, he shall judge it to be unclean, and he shall burn it with fire, for the leprosy has been infused in the exterior of the garment, or throughout the whole.

56 But if the place of the leprosy has become somewhat darker, after the garment has been washed, he shall tear it away, and separate it from the part that is sound.

57 But if, after this, there will appear in those places which before were immaculate, a flying and wandering leprosy, it must be burned with fire.

58 If it will have ceased, he shall wash with water the parts which are pure for a second time, and they shall be clean.

59 This is the law about leprosy for any woolen or linen garment, in the weave and in the threads, and for all items made from skins, how it must be declared either clean or contaminated.

Leviticus 14

1 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

2 This is the rite for a leper, when he is to be cleansed. He shall be brought to the priest,

3 who, departing from the camp, when he has found the leprosy to be cleansed,

4 shall instruct him who is to be purified to offer for himself two living sparrows, which it is lawful to eat, and cedar wood, and vermillion, and hyssop.

5 And he shall order that one of the sparrows be immolated in an earthen vessel over living waters.

6 But the other living one, with the cedar wood, and the scarlet, and the hyssop, he shall dip in the blood of the immolated sparrow.

7 And he shall sprinkle him who is to be cleansed seven times, so that he may be purified justly. And he shall release the living sparrow, so that it may fly away into the field.

8 And when the man will have washed his clothes, he shall shave all the hair from his body, and he shall be washed with water. And having been purified, he shall enter into the camp, only to this extent: that he may remain outside his own tent for seven days.

9 And on the seventh day he shall shave the hair of his head, and his beard, and his eyebrows, as well as the hair of his entire body. And having washed his clothes again, and his body,

10 on the eighth day, he shall take two immaculate lambs, and a one-year-old female sheep without blemish, and three tenths of fine wheat flour, which has been sprinkled with oil, as a sacrifice, and separately, one twelfth hin of oil.

11 And when the priest purifying the man has presented him and all these things in the sight of the Lord at the door of the tabernacle of the testimony,

12 he shall take a lamb and offer it for transgression, with the twelfth hin of oil. And having offered all these before the Lord,

13 he shall immolate the lamb, where the victim for sin is usually immolated with the holocaust, that is, in the holy place. For just as with the one for sin, so also the victim for transgression belongs to the priest. It is the Holy of holies.

14 And taking some of the blood of the victim, which was immolated for transgression, the priest shall place it upon the tip of the right ear of him who is being cleansed, and upon the thumb of his right hand, and likewise the foot.

15 And he shall send some of the twelfth hin of oil into his own left hand,

16 and he shall dip his right finger in it, and he shall sprinkle it in the sight of the Lord seven times.

17 But the oil which remains in his left hand, he shall pour over the tip of the right ear of him who is being cleansed, and upon the thumb of his right hand as well as the foot, and upon the blood which was shed for transgression,

18 and upon his head.

19 And he shall pray for him in the sight of the Lord, and he shall accomplish the sacrifice on behalf of sin. Then he shall immolate the holocaust,

20 and place it upon the altar with its libations, and the man will be duly cleansed.

21 But if he is poor, and his hand is not able to find what has been said, he shall take a lamb as an offering for transgression, so that the priest may pray for him, and a tenth part of fine wheat flour sprinkled with oil, as a sacrifice, and a twelfth hin of oil,

22 and two turtledoves or two young pigeons, of which one may be for sin, and the other as a holocaust.

23 And he shall offer them on the eighth day of his purification to the priest at the door of the tabernacle of the testimony in the sight of the Lord.

24 And he, receiving the lamb for transgression, and the twelfth hin of oil, shall lift them up together.

25 And when the lamb has been immolated, he shall place some of its blood upon the tip of the right ear of him who is being cleansed, and upon the thumb of his right hand, as well as the foot.

26 Yet truly, he shall send part of the oil into his own left hand,

27 and dipping the finger of his right hand in it, he shall sprinkle it seven times before the Lord.

28 And he shall touch the tip of the right ear of him who is being cleansed, and the thumb of his right hand, as well as the foot, in the place of the blood which was shed for transgression.

29 But the remaining part of the oil which is in his left hand, he shall send upon the head of the one being purified, to appease the Lord on his behalf.

30 And he shall offer a turtledove or a young pigeon,

31 one for transgression, and the other as a holocaust, with their libations.

32 This is the sacrifice of a leper, who is not able to obtain all of the things concerning his cleansing.

33 And the Lord spoke to Moses and Aaron, saying:

34 When you will have entered into the land of Canaan, which I will give to you as a possession, if there is the mark of leprosy in a building,

35 he whose house it is shall go and report to the priest, saying: "It seems to me that the mark of leprosy is in my house."

36 And he shall instruct them to carry all things out of the house, before he would enter it and see whether it is leprosy, lest all that is in the house become unclean. And after this, he shall enter to examine the leprosy of the house.

37 And when he will have seen in its walls something like little hollows, deformed with paleness or redness, and lower than the remaining surface,

38 he shall exit by the door of the house, and immediately close it up for seven days.

39 And returning on the seventh day, he shall examine it. If he finds that the leprosy has spread,

40 he shall order the stones in which the leprosy is, to be dug out and cast outside the city in an unclean place,

41 and that the house be scraped on the inside all around, and that the dust of the scrapings be scattered outside the city in an unclean place,

42 and that other stones be put back, in place of those which had been taken away, and that the house be plastered with other mortar.

43 But if, after the stones have been dug out, and the dust wiped away, and it is plastered with other clay,

44 the priest, upon entering, will have seen that the leprosy has returned, and that the walls are sprinkled with spots, then it is a persistent leprosy and the house is unclean.

45 And so they shall promptly destroy it, and shall cast its stones and timber, and also all the dust, outside the town in an unclean place.

46 Whoever enters into the house when it is closed up shall be unclean until evening.

47 And whoever will have slept in it, or eaten anything, shall wash his clothes.

48 But if the priest, upon entering, will have seen that the leprosy has not spread in the house, after it had been newly plastered, he shall purify it, restoring it to health.

49 And for its purification, he shall take two sparrows, and cedar wood, and vermillion, as well as hyssop,

50 and, having immolated one sparrow in an earthen vessel over living waters,

51 he shall take the cedar wood, and the hyssop, and the scarlet, and the living sparrow, and he shall dip all these in the blood of the immolated sparrow, and also in the living water, and he shall sprinkle the house seven times.

52 And he shall purify it as much with the blood of the sparrow as with the living water, and with the living sparrow, and the cedar wood, and the hyssop, and the vermillion.

53 And when he has released the sparrow to fly freely away into the field, he shall pray for the house, and it shall be justly cleansed.

54 This is the law of every kind of leprosy and plague:

55 of the leprosy of garments and houses,

56 of scars and erupting pustules, of a shining spot, when the appearance is also variegated,

57 so that it can be known at what time a thing is clean or unclean.

Leviticus 15

1 And the Lord spoke to Moses and Aaron, saying:

2 Speak to the sons of Israel, and say to them: The man who undergoes a flow of seed shall be unclean.

3 And then he shall be judged subject to this fault, if a filthy fluid, at each moment, adheres to his flesh and gathers there.

4 Every bed on which he sleeps shall be unclean, and every place where he sits.

5 If any man has touched his couch, he shall wash his clothes, and having washed with water, he shall be unclean until evening.

6 If he will have sat where that man has sat, he shall also wash his clothes, and having washed with water, he shall be unclean until evening.

7 Whoever has touched his flesh shall wash his clothes, and having washed with water, he shall be unclean until evening.

8 If such a man has cast his spittle upon him who is clean, he shall wash his clothes, and having washed with water, he shall be unclean until evening.

9 The saddle on which he has sat shall be unclean.

10 And whatever has been under him who has undergone a flow of seed shall be polluted until evening. Whoever carries any of these things shall wash his clothes, and having washed with water, he shall be unclean until evening.

11 All whom such a one has touched, not having washed his hands before, shall wash his clothes, and having washed with water, he shall be unclean until evening.

12 If he has touched an earthen vessel, it shall be broken. But if it is a wooden vessel, it shall be washed with water.

13 If he who suffers from this affliction will have been healed, he shall number seven days after his cleansing, and having washed his clothes and his entire body in living water, he shall be clean.

14 Then, on the eighth day, he shall take two turtledoves or two young pigeons, and he shall advance, in the sight of the Lord, toward the door of the tabernacle of the testimony, and he shall give these to the priest,

15 who shall offer one for sin, and the other as a holocaust. And he shall pray for him before the Lord, so that he may be cleansed from the flow of his seed.

16 A man from whom the seed of sexual intercourse goes out shall wash his entire body with water, and he shall be unclean until evening.

17 The garment or skin which he will have, he shall wash with water, and it shall be unclean until evening.

18 The woman with whom he has had sexual intercourse shall be washed with water, and she shall be unclean until evening.

19 The woman who, at the return of the month, undergoes the flow of blood shall be separated for seven days.

20 All who will touch her shall be unclean until evening.

21 And everything on which she sleeps or sits, in the days of her separation, shall be polluted.

22 Whoever will have touched her bed shall wash his clothes, and having washed himself with water, he shall be unclean until evening.

23 Anyone who will have touched any item on which she has sat shall wash his clothes, and having washed himself with water, he shall be polluted until evening.

24 If a man has sexual intercourse with her in the time of her monthly flow of blood, he shall be unclean for seven days, and every bed on which he sleeps shall be polluted.

25 The woman who undergoes a flow of blood many days beyond her time of menstruation, or whose blood does not cease to flow after the menstrual blood, as long as she is subject to this affliction, she shall be unclean, just as if she were in her time of menstruation.

26 Every bed on which she sleeps, and every item on which she sits, shall be polluted.

27 Whoever will have touched these shall wash his clothes, and having washed himself with water, he shall be unclean until evening.

28 If the blood has stopped and has ceased to flow, she shall number seven days for her purification,

29 and on the eighth day she shall offer for herself, to the priest, two turtledoves or two young pigeons, at the door of the tabernacle of the testimony.

30 And he shall offer one for sin, and the other as a holocaust, and he shall pray for her before the Lord, and for the flow of her uncleanness.

31 Therefore, you shall teach the sons of Israel to be cautious of uncleanness, so that they may not die in their filth, when they will have polluted my tabernacle, which is among them.

32 This is the law of him who undergoes a flow of seed, or who is polluted by sexual intercourse,

33 and of her who is separated in the time of menstruation, or who has a continual flow of blood, and of the man who sleeps with her.

Leviticus 16

1 And the Lord spoke to Moses, after the death of the two sons of Aaron, when they were destroyed for offering strange fire.

2 And he instructed him, saying: Speak to your brother Aaron, so that he may not, at any time, enter into the Sanctuary, which is within the veil, before the propitiatory by which the ark is covered, so that he may not die, (for I will appear in a cloud above the oracle)

3 unless he will have done these things beforehand. He shall offer a calf for sin, and a ram as a holocaust.

4 He shall be vested with a linen tunic. He shall conceal his nakedness with linen undergarments. He shall be wrapped with a linen belt, and he shall impose a linen headdress on his head. For these are holy vestments. All of these he shall put on, after he has been washed.

5 And he shall receive, from the entire multitude of the sons of Israel, two he-goats for sin, and one ram as a holocaust.

6 And when he has presented the calf, and has prayed for himself and for his own house,

7 he shall cause the two he-goats to stand in the sight of the Lord at the entrance to the tabernacle of the testimony.

8 And casting lots over them both, one is to be offered to the Lord, and the other is to be the emissary goat.

9 The one whose lot fell out to be offered to the Lord, he shall offer for sin.

10 But the one who is to be the emissary goat shall stand before the Lord, so that he may pour the prayers upon him, and may send him away into the wilderness.

11 After these things have been duly celebrated, he shall offer the calf, and praying for himself and for his own house, he shall immolate it.

12 And taking up the censer, which he has filled from the burning coals of the altar, and drawing up with his hands the aromatic compound for incense, he shall enter within the veil, into the holy place,

13 so that when the aromatics are placed upon the fire, its cloud and vapor may cover the oracle, which is above the testimony, and he may not die.

14 Likewise, he shall take some of the blood of the calf, and sprinkle it with his finger seven times opposite the propitiatory, toward the east.

15 And when he has slain the he-goat for the sin of the people, he shall carry its blood within the veil, just as he was instructed to do with the blood of the calf, so that he may sprinkle it away from the area of the oracle,

16 and so that he may expiate the Sanctuary from the uncleanness of the sons of Israel, and from their prevarications and every one of their sins. According to this rite, he shall act toward the tabernacle of the testimony, which is fixed among them in the midst of the filth of their habitation.

17 Let no man be in the tabernacle when the high priest enters the Sanctuary in order to pray for himself, and for his house, and for the entire assembly of Israel, until he exits.

18 And when he has exited to the altar which is before the Lord, let him pray for himself, and taking the blood of the calf, and of the he-goat, let him pour it upon its horns all around.

19 And sprinkling with his finger seven times, let him expiate and sanctify it from the uncleanness of the sons of Israel.

20 After he has cleansed the Sanctuary, and the tabernacle, and the altar, then let him offer the living goat.

21 And placing both hands upon its head, let him confess all the iniquities of the sons of Israel, and all of their offenses and sins. And calling these down upon its head, he shall send it away, by means of a man prepared to do so, into the desert.

22 And when the goat has carried all their iniquities into a solitary land, and has been released into the desert,

23 Aaron shall return into the tabernacle of the testimony. And placing aside the vestments, which he had worn before when he entered into the Sanctuary, and leaving them there,

24 he shall wash his flesh in the holy place, and he shall be clothed in his own garments. And departing afterwards, he shall present his own holocaust and that of the people: he shall pray as much for himself as for the people.

25 And the fat which is offered for sins, he shall burn upon the altar.

26 Yet truly, he who has sent away the emissary goat shall wash his clothes and his body with water, and so he shall enter into the camp.

27 But the calf and the he-goat, which were immolated for sin, and whose blood was brought into the Sanctuary to complete the expiation, these shall be carried outside the camp and be burned with fire: as with their skins, so also with their flesh and dung.

28 And whoever will have burned them shall wash his clothes and flesh with water, and so he shall enter into the camp.

29 And this shall be to you an everlasting ordinance. In the seventh month, on the tenth day of the month, you shall afflict your souls, and you shall do no work, neither someone native born, nor the newcomer who sojourns among you.

30 On this day, there shall be atonement for you, and also a cleansing from all your sins. You shall be cleansed in the sight of the Lord.

31 For it is a Sabbath of rest, and you shall afflict your souls as a perpetual observance.

32 And the priest who has been anointed, and whose hands have been consecrated to exercise the priesthood in the place of his father, shall make atonement. And he shall be clothed with the linen robe and the holy vestments.

33 And he shall expiate the Sanctuary and the tabernacle of the testimony and the altar, likewise the priest and all the people.

34 And this shall be to you a perpetual law, that you pray for the sons of Israel, and for all their sins once a year. Therefore, he did just as the Lord had instructed Moses.

Leviticus 17

1 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

2 Speak to Aaron and his sons, and to all the sons of Israel, saying to them: This is the word, which the Lord has commanded, saying:

3 Any man at all of the house of Israel, if he will have killed an ox, or a sheep, or a goat in the camp or beyond the camp,

4 and not have presented it as an oblation to the Lord at the door of the tabernacle, he shall be guilty of blood. It is just as if he had shed blood; so then, he shall perish from the midst of his people.

5 Therefore, the sons of Israel must offer to the priest their victims, which they kill in the field, so that they may be sanctified to the Lord before the door of the tabernacle of the testimony, and so that they may immolate them as peace offerings to the Lord.

6 And the priest shall pour the blood upon the altar of the Lord, at the door of the tabernacle of the testimony, and he shall burn the fat as a sweet odor to the Lord.

7 And they shall no longer immolate their victims to demons, with whom they have committed fornication. It shall be an everlasting ordinance for them and for their posterity.

8 And you shall say to them: The man of the house of Israel, or of the newcomers who sojourn with you, who offers a holocaust or a victim,

9 and who does not bring it to the door of the tabernacle of the testimony, so that it may be offered to the Lord, shall pass away from his people.

10 Any man at all of the house of Israel, or of the newcomers who sojourn among them, if he has eaten blood, I will harden my face against his soul, and I will drive him from his people.

11 For the life of the flesh is in the blood, and I have given it to you, so that you may atone with it upon the altar for your souls, and so that the blood may be for an expiation of the soul.

12 For this reason, I have said to the sons of Israel: No soul among you shall eat blood, nor among the newcomers who sojourn with you.

13 Any man at all from the sons of Israel, or from the newcomers who sojourn with you, whether by hunting or bird-catching, if he seizes a wild beast or a bird, which is lawful to eat, let him pour out its blood and cover the earth with it.

14 For the life of all flesh is in the blood. Therefore, I said to the sons of Israel: You shall not eat the blood of any flesh at all, because the life of the flesh is in the blood, and whoever has eaten it shall perish.

15 The soul who eats what has died on its own, or what has been caught by a beast, whether he is native born or a newcomer, shall wash his clothes and himself with water, and he shall be contaminated until evening. And by this means he shall be made clean.

16 But if he will not wash his clothes and his body, he shall bear his iniquity.

Leviticus 18

1 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

2 Speak to the sons of Israel, and you shall say to them: I am the Lord your God.

3 You shall not act according to the custom of the land of Egypt, in which you have lived; nor shall you behave according to the habit of the region of Canaan, into which I will lead you; neither shall you walk in their ordinances.

4 You shall accomplish my judgments, and you shall observe my precepts, and you shall walk in them. I am the Lord your God.

5 Keep my laws and judgments; when a man does these, he shall live by them. I am the Lord.

6 No man shall approach her who is a close blood-relative to him, so as to uncover her nakedness. I am the Lord.

7 You shall not expose the nakedness of your father, or the nakedness of your mother. She is your mother; you shall not uncover her nakedness.

8 You shall not expose the nakedness of your father's wife; for it is the nakedness of your father.

9 You shall not uncover the nakedness of your sister, whether from father or from mother, whether she was born at home or abroad.

10 You shall not uncover the nakedness of your son's daughter, or your daughter's daughter; for it is your own nakedness.

11 You shall not uncover the nakedness of your father's wife's daughter, whom she bore to your father, and who is your sister.

12 You shall not expose the nakedness of your father's sister; for she is the flesh of your father.

13 You shall not uncover the nakedness of your mother's sister, because she is the flesh of your mother.

14 You shall not uncover the nakedness of your father's brother, nor shall you approach his wife, who is joined to you by affinity.

15 You shall not uncover the nakedness of your daughter-in-law, for she is your son's wife; neither shall you expose her dishonor.

16 You shall not uncover the nakedness of your brother's wife; for it is the nakedness of your brother.

17 You shall not uncover the nakedness of your wife and her daughter. You shall not take her son's daughter or her daughter's daughter, so as to uncover her dishonor; for they are her flesh, and such sexual intercourse is incest.

18 You shall not take your wife's sister as a rival mistress; nor shall you uncover her nakedness, while your wife is still living.

19 You shall not approach a woman who is undergoing menstruation, nor shall you uncover her foulness.

20 You shall not have sexual intercourse with your neighbor's wife, nor shall you be defiled by the mingling of seed.

21 You shall not give some of your seed to be consecrated to the idol Moloch, nor to pollute the name of your God. I am the Lord.

22 You shall not commit sexual acts with a male, in place of sexual intercourse with a female, for this is an abomination.

23 You shall not commit sexual acts with any animal, nor shall you be defiled by it. A woman shall not lie down with a beast, nor commit sexual acts with it; for this is wickedness.

24 Do not pollute yourselves with any of these things, by which all of the nations, which I will cast out in your sight, have been contaminated

25 and by which the land has been polluted. I will visit the wickedness of the land, so that it may vomit out its inhabitants.

26 Keep my ordinances and judgments, and do not do any of these abominations: the native born, as well as the settler, who sojourns among you.

27 For all these detestable things were done by the inhabitants of the land who were here before you, and they have polluted it.

28 Therefore, beware, lest in a similar manner, it may vomit you out as well, if you do these same things, just as it vomited out the people who were before you.

29 Every soul who shall commit any of these abominations shall perish from the midst of his people.

30 Keep my commandments. Do not be willing to do the things which have been done by those who were before you, and do not be polluted by these things. I am the Lord your God.

Leviticus 19

1 The Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

2 Speak to the entire assembly of the sons of Israel, and you shall say to them: Be holy, for I, the Lord your God, am holy.

3 Let each one fear his father and his mother. Observe my Sabbaths. I am the Lord your God.

4 Do not be willing to convert to idols, neither should you make molten gods for yourselves. I am the Lord your God.

5 If you immolate a victim of peace offerings to the Lord, so that he may be appeased,

6 you shall eat it on the same day as when it was immolated, and the next day. Then whatever will remain on the third day you shall burn with fire.

7 If anyone, after two days, will have eaten from it, he shall be profane and guilty of impiety.

8 And he shall bear his iniquity, for he has polluted what is holy to the Lord. And that soul shall perish from his people.

9 When you will have harvested the grain fields of your land, you shall not cut it down to the surface of the land, even to the ground, nor shall you gather the remaining ears of grain.

10 Neither shall you gather the clusters or individual grapes which fall down in your vineyard, but you shall leave them for paupers and travelers to take. I am the Lord your God.

11 You shall not steal. You shall not lie. Neither shall anyone deceive his neighbor.

12 You shall not commit perjury in my name, nor shall you pollute the name of your God. I am the Lord.

13 You shall not slander your neighbor, nor shall you oppress him by violence. The wages of a hired hand, you shall not delay with you until tomorrow.

14 You shall not speak evil of the deaf, nor shall you place a stumbling block before the blind, but you shall fear the Lord your God, for I am the Lord.

15 You shall not do what is unjust, nor shall you judge unjustly. You shall not consider the reputation of the poor, nor shall you honor the countenance of the powerful. Judge your neighbor justly.

16 You shall not be a detractor, nor a whisperer, among the people. You shall not stand against the blood of your neighbor. I am the Lord.

17 You shall not hate your brother in your heart, but reprove him openly, lest you have sin over him.

18 Do not seek revenge, neither should you be mindful of the injury of your fellow citizens. You shall love your friend as yourself. I am the Lord.

19 Observe my laws. You shall not cause your cattle to breed with other kinds of animals. You shall not sow your field with diverse seeds. You shall not be clothed with a garment which has been woven from two things.

20 If a man will have slept in sexual intercourse with a woman, who is a servant and who is also able to be married, and yet he has not redeemed her with a price, nor paid to set her free, they both shall be beaten, but they shall not die, for she was not a free woman.

21 But, for his offense, he shall offer a ram to the Lord at the door of the tabernacle of the testimony.

22 And the priest shall pray for him, and for his sin, before the Lord, and he shall win his favor again for him, and the sin shall be forgiven.

23 When you will have entered into the land, and will have planted in it fruit trees, you shall take away their first-fruits; the fruit that germinates shall be unclean to you, neither shall you eat from these.

24 But in the fourth year, all their fruit shall be sanctified for the praise of the Lord.

25 And in the fifth year you shall eat the produce, gathering the fruits which are brought forth. I am the Lord your God.

26 You shall not eat with blood. You shall not practice divination, nor the observation of dreams.

27 And you shall not cut the hair of your head circularly, nor shave your beard.

28 You shall not cut your flesh for the dead, and you shall not make other figures or marks on yourself. I am the Lord.

29 Do not prostitute your daughter, lest the land be contaminated and filled with crimes.

30 Observe my Sabbaths, and be apprehensive toward my Sanctuary. I am the Lord.

31 Do not turn aside to astrologers, nor consult with soothsayers, so as to be polluted through them. I am the Lord your God.

32 Rise up in the presence of a gray-haired head, and honor the reputation of an elder, and fear the Lord your God. I am the Lord.

33 If a newcomer lives in your land and abides among you, do not reproach him,

34 but let him be among you like one native born. And you shall love him as yourselves. For you were also newcomers in the land of Egypt. I am the Lord your God.

35 Do not be willing to accomplish iniquity in judgment, in lengths, in weights, in quantities.

36 Let the scales be just and the weights equal, let the dry measure be just and the liquid measure be equal. I am the Lord your God, who led you away from the land of Egypt.

37 Keep all my precepts, and all my judgments, and accomplish them. I am the Lord.

Leviticus 20

1 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

2 You shall speak these things to the sons of Israel: A man among the sons Israel, or among the newcomers who live in Israel, if he will have given from his seed to the idol Moloch, he shall be put to death: the people of the land shall stone him.

3 And I will set my face against him. And I will cut him down from the midst of his people, because he has given from his seed to Moloch, and he has contaminated my Sanctuary, and polluted my holy name.

4 But if the people of the land, having been neglectful and holding little regard for my authority, release the man who has given from his seed to Moloch, and they are not willing to kill him,

5 I will set my face over that man and over his kindred, and I will cut down both him and all who consented with him to fornicate with Moloch, from the midst of their people.

6 The soul who will have turned aside to astrologers and soothsayers, and who will have fornicated with them, I will set my face against him, and I will destroy him from the midst of his people.

7 Be sanctified and be holy, for I am the Lord your God.

8 Observe my precepts, and do them. I am the Lord, who sanctifies you.

9 Whoever curses his father or mother shall die a death; he has cursed his father and mother. So let his blood be upon him.

10 If anyone will have committed sexual acts with the wife of another, or will have perpetrated adultery with his neighbor's spouse, they shall die a death, both the adulterer and the adulteress.

11 Whoever will have slept with his stepmother, or will have uncovered the shame of his father, they shall both die a death. So let their blood be upon them.

12 If any man will have slept with his daughter-in-law, both shall die, for they have acted according to wickedness. So let their blood be upon them.

13 If any man has slept with a male in place of sexual intercourse with a female, both have committed a nefarious act, they shall die a death. So let their blood be upon them.

14 If any man, having taken the daughter as a wife, will have married her mother, he has acted according to wickedness. He shall be burnt alive with them. Neither shall so great a nefarious act persist in your midst.

15 Whoever will have committed sexual acts with any animal or cattle, he shall die a death. Likewise, you shall slay the beast.

16 The woman who will have lain under any animal at all shall be destroyed together with it. So let their blood be upon them.

17 Whoever will have taken his sister, the daughter of his father or the daughter of his mother, and will have seen her nakedness, and she will have looked upon her brother's shame, they have committed a nefarious act. They shall be slain in the sight of their people, because they have uncovered one another's nakedness. And they shall bear their iniquity.

18 Whoever has sexual intercourse with a woman in her menstrual flow, and has uncovered her nakedness, and she has opened the fountain of her blood, both shall be destroyed from the midst of their people.

19 You shall not expose the nakedness of your maternal or paternal aunt. Whoever does this has laid bare the shame of his own flesh; both shall bear their iniquity.

20 If any man has had sexual intercourse with the wife of his paternal or maternal uncle, and he has uncovered the shame of his close relative, both shall bear their sin. They shall die without children.

21 Whoever will have married his brother's wife has done an unlawful thing; he has uncovered his brother's nakedness. They shall be without children.

22 Observe my laws as well as my judgments, and act according to them, lest the land, into which you will enter and live, may vomit you out, too.

23 Do not be willing to walk by the ordinances of the nations, which I will expel before you. For they have done all these things, and so I abominate them.

24 But I say to you: Possess their land, which I will give to you as an inheritance, a land flowing with milk and honey. I am the Lord your God, who has separated you from the other peoples.

25 Therefore, you must also separate the clean animals from the unclean, and the clean birds from the unclean. Do not pollute your souls with cattle, or birds, or anything that moves upon the earth, and which I have shown you to be unclean.

26 You shall be holy unto me, because I, the Lord, am holy, and I have separated you from the other peoples, so that you would be mine.

27 A man or a woman, in whom there is an oracle-like or a divining spirit, shall be put to death. They shall stone them. So let their blood be upon them.

Leviticus 21

1 The Lord also said to Moses: Speak to the priests, the sons of Aaron, and you shall say to them: Do not allow a priest to be contaminated by the death of his citizens,

2 except only by his blood-relatives and near-relatives, that is, by a father or mother, or by a son or daughter, or also a brother,

3 or a virgin sister, who is not married to a husband.

4 But not even by the leader of his people shall he be contaminated.

5 Neither shall they shave their head or their beard, and they shall not make incisions in their flesh.

6 They shall be holy to their God, and they shall not pollute his name. For they offer the incense of the Lord and the bread of their God, and because of this they shall be holy.

7 They shall not take as a wife a promiscuous woman, or a prostitute, or her who has been repudiated by her husband. For they are consecrated to their God,

8 and they offer the bread of the presence. Therefore, let them be holy, for I also am holy: the Lord, who sanctifies them.

9 If the daughter of a priest will have been taken into prostitution, and will have violated the name of her father, she shall be consumed by fire.

10 The high priest, that is, the priest who is the greatest among his brothers, upon whose head the oil of anointing has been poured, and whose hands have been consecrated for the priesthood, and who has been vested with the holy vestments: he shall not expose his head; he shall not rend his vestments.

11 And he shall not enter to any dead body whatsoever; likewise, not even by his father or mother shall he be contaminated.

12 Neither shall he exit from the holy places, lest he pollute the Sanctuary of the Lord. For the oil of the holy anointing of his God is upon him. I am the Lord.

13 He shall take a virgin as his wife.

14 But a widow, or one who has been repudiated or defiled, or also a mistress, he shall not accept, but only a maiden from among his own people.

15 He shall not mingle the stock of his family with the common people of his nation. For I am the Lord, who sanctifies him.

16 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

17 Say to Aaron: A man from your offspring, throughout their families, who has a blemish, shall not offer the bread to his God.

18 Neither shall he approach to minister to him: if he is blind, if he is lame, if he is small, or large, or has a crooked nose,

19 if his foot or hand is broken,

20 if he has a bulging back or bleary eyes, or if he has a white spot in his eye, or a chronic scab, or a skin disease on his body, or a hernia.

21 Anyone from the offspring of Aaron, the priest, who has a blemish, shall not approach to offer sacrifices to the Lord, nor the bread to his God.

22 Nevertheless, he shall eat from the loaves which are offered in the Sanctuary.

23 But even so, he may not enter within the veil, nor approach to the altar. For he has a blemish, and he must not contaminate my Sanctuary. I am the Lord, who sanctifies them.

24 Therefore, Moses spoke to Aaron, and to his sons, and to all of Israel, everything that had been commanded to him.

Leviticus 22

1 The Lord also spoke to Moses saying:

2 Speak to Aaron and to his sons, so that they may be careful of those things which have been consecrated for the sons of Israel, and so that they may not contaminate the name of the things sanctified to me, which they offer. I am the Lord.

3 Say to them and to their posterity: Every man of your stock, who approaches toward those things which have been consecrated, and which the sons of Israel have brought forward to the Lord, in whom there is uncleanness, shall perish before the Lord. I am the Lord.

4 The man of the offspring of Aaron, who is a leper or who is suffering a flow of seed, shall not eat of those things which have been sanctified to me, until he is healed. Whoever will have touched what is unclean because of the dead, and he whose seed goes out from him, as if from sexual intercourse,

5 and whoever has touched a creeping thing, or any kind of unclean thing, the touching of which is filthy,

6 shall be unclean until evening, and shall not eat those things which have been sanctified. But when he has washed his flesh with water,

7 and the sun has set, then, having been purified, he shall eat from what has been sanctified, because it is his food.

8 Whatever dies on its own, and whatever has been seized by a wild beast, they shall not eat, nor shall they be polluted by these. I am the Lord.

9 Let them observe my precepts, so that they may not fall under sin, and die in the Sanctuary, when they will have defiled it. I am the Lord, who sanctifies them.

10 No foreigner shall eat from what has been sanctified; a guest of the priests and a hired servant shall not eat from them.

11 But whomever the priest has bought, and whoever has been born into his house, these shall eat from them.

12 If the daughter of a priest has been married to any of the people, she shall not eat from what has been sanctified, nor from the first-fruits.

13 But if she is a widow or divorced, and, being without children, she returns to her father's house, she shall be nourished by her father's foods, just as she was accustomed to do as a girl. No foreigner shall have the authority to eat from them.

14 Whoever, through ignorance, eats from what has been sanctified shall add a fifth part to that which he ate, and he shall give it to the priest at the Sanctuary.

15 And they shall not contaminate what has been sanctified from the sons of Israel, which they offer to the Lord,

16 lest perhaps they may suffer the iniquity of their offense, when they will have eaten what has been sanctified. I am the Lord, who sanctifies them.

17 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

18 Speak to Aaron, and to his sons, and to all the sons of Israel, and you shall say to them: The man from the house of Israel, or from the newcomers who live with you, who would bring forward his oblation, either fulfilling his vows or offering spontaneously, whatever he brings forward as a holocaust for the Lord,

19 in order to be offered through you, shall offer an immaculate male from the oxen, or from the sheep, or from the goats.

20 If it has a blemish, you shall not offer it, and it shall not be acceptable.

21 The man who will have offered a victim of peace offerings to the Lord, either fulfilling his vows or offering spontaneously, whether of oxen, or of sheep, shall offer what is immaculate, so that it may be acceptable. There shall be no blemish in it.

22 If it is blind, or if it is broken, or if it has a scar, or if it is has a boil, or a skin disease or infection, you shall not offer these to the Lord, nor shall you burn any of these upon the altar of the Lord.

23 An ox or a sheep, having an amputated ear or tail, you are able to offer voluntarily, but a vow is not able to be fulfilled by these.

24 You shall not offer to the Lord any animal which has the testicles bruised, or crushed, or cut and taken away, and you shall not cause any of these things in your land.

25 From the hand of a foreigner, you shall not offer bread to your God, nor anything else that he would choose to give; for all this has been corrupted and blemished. You shall not accept them.

26 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

27 An ox, a sheep, or a goat, when they have been born, shall be under the udder of their mother for seven days. But on the eighth day and thereafter, they are able to be offered to the Lord.

28 Whether it is an ox, or a sheep, they shall not be immolated on the same day with their newborns.

29 If you immolate a victim as an act of thanksgiving to the Lord, so that he may be pleased,

30 you shall eat it on the same day; none of it shall remain until morning on the next day. I am the Lord.

31 Observe my commandments, and do them. I am the Lord.

32 Do not pollute my holy name, so that I may be sanctified in the midst of the sons of Israel. I am the Lord, who sanctifies you,

33 and who led you away from the land of Egypt, so that I may be to you as God. I am the Lord.

Leviticus 23

1 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

2 Speak to the sons of Israel, and you shall say to them: These are the feasts of the Lord, which you shall call holy.

3 For six days you shall do work; the seventh day, because it is the rest of the Sabbath, shall be called holy. You shall do no work on that day; it is the Sabbath of the Lord in all your dwelling places.

4 Therefore, these are the feasts of the Lord, which you must celebrate in their times.

5 The first month, the fourteenth day of the month, at evening, is the Passover of the Lord.

6 And the fifteenth day of this month is the solemnity of the unleavened bread of the Lord. For seven days shall you eat unleavened bread.

7 The first day shall be greatly honored and holy to you; you shall do no servile work in it.

8 But you shall offer a sacrifice with fire, for seven days, to the Lord. Then the seventh day shall be more honored and more holy; and you shall do no servile work in it.

9 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

10 Speak to the sons of Israel, and you shall say to them: When you will have entered into the land which I will give to you, and you will have harvested your grain fields, you shall carry the sheaves of grain, the first-fruits of your harvest, to the priest.

11 He shall lift up a sheaf before the Lord, on the day after the Sabbath, so that it may be acceptable for you, and he shall sanctify it.

12 And on the same day that the sheaf is consecrated, a one-year-old immaculate lamb shall be slain as a holocaust of the Lord.

13 And the libations shall be offered with it: two-tenths of fine wheat flour sprinkled with oil, as an incense and a most sweet odor for the Lord; likewise, libations of wine, the fourth part of a hin.

14 Bread, and parched grain, and boiled grain, you shall not eat from the grain field, until the day when you shall offer from it to your God. It is an everlasting precept in your generations and in all of your dwelling places.

15 Therefore, you shall number from the day after the Sabbath, in which you offered a sheaf of the first-fruits, seven full weeks,

16 all the way to the day after the completion of the seventh week, that is, fifty days, and then you shall offer a new sacrifice to the Lord,

17 from all of your dwelling places: two loaves from the first-fruits, from two-tenths of leavened fine wheat flour, which you shall bake as the first-fruits of the Lord.

18 And you shall offer with the bread: seven immaculate one-year-old lambs, and one calf from the herd, and two rams, and these shall be a holocaust, with their libations, as a most sweet odor to the Lord.

19 You shall also offer a he-goat for sin, and two one-year-old lambs as victims of peace offerings.

20 And when the priest has lifted them up with the loaves of the first-fruits, in the sight of the Lord, they shall fall to his use.

21 And you shall call this day most honored and most holy; you shall do no servile work in it. It shall be an everlasting ordinance in all your dwelling places and generations.

22 And when you will have harvested the grain fields of your land, you shall not cut it down all the way to the ground; neither shall you gather the remnants of the ears of grain, but you shall leave these for paupers and strangers. I am the Lord your God.

23 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

24 Say to the sons of Israel: The seventh month, the first day of the month, shall be a Sabbath for you, a memorial, with the sounding of trumpets, and it shall be called holy.

25 You shall do no servile work in it, and you shall offer a holocaust to the Lord.

26 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

27 The tenth day of this seventh month shall be the day of atonement; it shall be most honored, and it shall be called holy. And you shall afflict your souls on that day, and you shall offer a holocaust to the Lord.

28 You shall do no servile work in the time of this day; for it is a day of propitiation, so that the Lord your God may be merciful to you.

29 Every soul that has not been afflicted on this day shall perish from his people,

30 and anyone who will have done work, I shall wipe him away from his people.

31 Therefore, you shall do no work on that day. This shall be an everlasting ordinance for you in all your generations and dwelling places.

32 It is a Sabbath of rest, and you shall afflict your souls beginning on the ninth day of the month: from evening until evening you shall celebrate your Sabbaths.

33 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

34 Say to the sons of Israel: From the fifteenth day of this seventh month, there shall be the Feast of Tabernacles: seven days for the Lord.

35 The first day shall be called most honored and most holy; you shall do no servile work in it.

36 And for seven days you shall offer holocausts to the Lord. Likewise, the eighth day shall be most honored and most holy, and you shall offer holocausts to the Lord. For it is the day of assembly and gathering. You shall do no servile work in it.

37 These are the feasts of the Lord, which you shall call most honored and most holy, and in them you shall offer oblations to the Lord: holocausts and libations according to the rite of each particular day,

38 aside from the Sabbaths of the Lord, and your donations, and that which you offer by a vow, or which you give to the Lord spontaneously.

39 Therefore, from the fifteenth day of the seventh month, when you will have gathered together all the fruits of your land, you shall celebrate the feast of the Lord for seven days. The first day and the eighth day shall be a Sabbath, that is, a day of rest.

40 And you shall take for yourselves, on the first day, the fruits of the most beautiful tree, and branches of palm trees, and branches of trees with thick foliage, and willows from the torrent. And you shall rejoice in the sight of the Lord your God.

41 And you shall celebrate its solemnity for seven days each year. This shall be an everlasting ordinance in your generations. In the seventh month, you shall celebrate the feast,

42 and you shall live under shelters for seven days. All who are of the family of Israel shall dwell in tabernacles,

43 so that your posterity may learn that I caused the sons of Israel to live in tabernacles, when I led them away from the land of Egypt. I am the Lord your God.

44 And Moses spoke about the solemnities of the Lord to the sons of Israel.

Leviticus 24

1 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

2 Instruct the sons of Israel, so that they may bring to you clear oil from the purest olives, in order to supply the lamps continuously

3 outside the veil of the testimony in the tabernacle of the covenant. And Aaron shall place these, from evening until morning, before the Lord, as a perpetual worship and ritual in your generations.

4 They shall be placed upon the most pure candlestick in the sight of the Lord always.

5 You shall also receive fine wheat flour, and you shall bake twelve loaves from it, each loaf of which shall have two-tenths.

6 And you shall arrange them, six on each side, upon the most pure table before the Lord.

7 And you shall place upon them the clearest frankincense, so that the bread may be a memorial of oblation for the Lord.

8 On each Sabbath, they shall be changed before the Lord, having been received from the sons of Israel as an everlasting covenant.

9 And they shall be for Aaron and his sons, so that they may eat these in the holy place; for it is the Holy of holies from the sacrifices of the Lord, as a perpetual right.

10 Then, behold, the son of an Israelite woman, whom she had born of an Egyptian man among the sons of Israel, going out, was quarreling in the camp with a man of Israel.

11 And when he had blasphemed the name, and had cursed it, he was led to Moses. (Now his mother was called Shelomith, the daughter of Dibri from the tribe of Dan.)

12 And they sent him to prison, until they might know what the Lord would command,

13 who spoke to Moses,

14 saying: Lead away the blasphemer beyond the camp, and let all who heard him place their hands upon his head, and let the entire people stone him.

15 And you shall say to the sons of Israel: The man who curses his God shall bear his sin,

16 and whoever will have blasphemed the name of the Lord shall be put to death. The entire multitude shall overwhelm him with stones, whether he be a citizen or a sojourner. Whoever blasphemes the name of the Lord shall be put to death.

17 Whoever will have struck and killed a man shall be put to death.

18 Whoever will have struck down an animal shall repay its equivalent, that is, a life for a life.

19 Whoever will have inflicted a blemish on any of his citizens, just as he has done, so shall it be done to him:

20 fracture for fracture, eye for eye, tooth for tooth, shall he repay. Whatever degree of blemish he has inflicted, so shall he be compelled to suffer.

21 Whoever strikes down a beast, shall repay another. Whoever strikes a man shall be punished.

22 Let there be equal judgment among you, whether it is a sojourner or a citizen who will have sinned. For I am the Lord your God.

23 And Moses spoke to the sons of Israel. And they led away him who had blasphemed, beyond the camp, and they overwhelmed him with stones. And the sons of Israel did just as the Lord had instructed Moses.

Leviticus 25

1 And the Lord spoke to Moses on mount Sinai, saying:

2 Speak to the sons of Israel, and you shall say to them: When you will have entered into the land which I will give to you, rest on the Sabbath of the Lord.

3 For six years you shall sow your field, and for six years you shall care for your vineyard, and you shall gather its fruits.

4 But in the seventh year, there shall be a Sabbath of the land, a resting of the Lord. You shall not sow your field, and you shall not care for your vineyard.

5 What the soil shall spontaneously produce, you shall not harvest. And you shall not gather the grapes of the first-fruits as a crop. For it is a year of rest for the land.

6 But these shall be yours for food, for you and for your men and women servants, and for your hired hands, and for the newcomers who sojourn with you:

7 all that grows on its own shall provide food for your beasts and cattle.

8 You shall also number for yourselves seven weeks of years, that is, seven times seven, which together makes forty-nine years.

9 And you shall sound the trumpet in the seventh month, on the tenth day of the month, at the time of the atonement, throughout all your land.

10 And you shall sanctify the fiftieth year, and you shall proclaim a remission for all the inhabitants of your land: for the same is the Jubilee. A man shall return to his possession, and each one shall go back to his original family,

11 for it is the Jubilee and the fiftieth year. You shall not sow, and you shall not reap what grows in the field of its own accord, and you shall not gather the first-fruits of the crop,

12 due to the sanctification of the Jubilee. But you shall eat them as they present themselves.

13 In the year of the Jubilee, all shall return to their possessions.

14 When you will sell anything to your fellow citizen, or buy anything from him, do not cause your brother grief, but buy from him according to the number of years from the Jubilee,

15 and he shall sell to you according to the computation of the produce.

16 The more years that will remain after the Jubilee, the more the price shall increase, and the less the time is numbered, so much less shall the purchase price be. For he will sell to you the time for the produce.

17 Do be willing to afflict your countrymen, but let each one fear his God. For I am the Lord your God.

18 Accomplish my precepts, and observe my judgments, and complete them, so that you may be able to live in the land without any fear,

19 and so that the soil may produce its fruits for you, from which you may eat, even to fullness, dreading violence by no one.

20 But if you will say: What shall we eat in the seventh year, if we do not sow and do not gather our produce?

21 I will give my blessing to you in the sixth year, and it shall yield the produce of three years.

22 And in the eighth year you shall sow, but you shall eat from the old produce, until the ninth year, until what is new matures, you shall eat what is old.

23 Also, the land shall not be sold in perpetuity, for it is mine, and you are newcomers and settlers to me.

24 Therefore, every region of your possession shall be sold under the condition of redemption.

25 If your brother, being in need, will have sold his little possession and his close relative is willing, he is able to redeem what he had sold.

26 But if he has no near relative, and he himself is able to find the price to redeem it,

27 the produce shall be calculated from that time when he sold it. And what is lacking, he shall repay to the buyer, and so he shall receive his possession.

28 But if his hand will not have discovered a way to repay the price, the buyer shall have what he bought, until the year of the Jubilee. For in that year all that has been sold shall return to the owner, and to the original possessor.

29 Whoever will have sold a house within the walls of a city shall have the freedom to redeem it, until one year has been completed.

30 If he has not redeemed it, and the year will have turned full circle, the buyer and his posterity shall possess it, in perpetuity, and it is not able to be redeemed, even in the Jubilee.

31 But if the house is in a village, which has no walls, it shall be sold by the law of the fields. If it has not been redeemed beforehand, then in the Jubilee it shall return to the owner.

32 The buildings of the Levites, which are in the cities, are always able to be redeemed.

33 If they have not been redeemed, then in the Jubilee they shall return to the owners, for the houses of the cities of the Levites are for their possession among the sons of Israel.

34 But let not their suburbs be sold, for it is an everlasting possession.

35 If your brother has become impoverished, or infirm of hand, and you take him in, like a newcomer or a sojourner, and he lives with you,

36 do not accept usury from him, nor anything more than what you gave. Fear your God, so that your brother may be able to live with you.

37 You shall not give him your money by usury, nor exact from him an overabundance of produce.

38 I am the Lord your God, who led you away from the land of Egypt, so that I might give to you the land of Canaan, and so that I may be your God.

39 If your brother, having been compelled by poverty, will have sold himself to you, you shall not oppress him with the servitude of indentured servants.

40 But he shall be like a hired hand or a settler; he shall work with you, until the year of the Jubilee.

41 And after that, he shall depart with his children, and he shall return to his kindred, to the possession of his fathers.

42 For these are my servants, and I led them away from the land of Egypt; let them not be sold into the condition of servitude.

43 Do not afflict him by power, but be fearful of your God.

44 Let your male and female servants be from the nations which are all around you,

45 and from the newcomers who sojourn with you, or who have been born from them in your land. These you shall have as servants,

46 and, by the right of inheritance, you shall transmit them to your posterity, and you shall possess them forever. But do not oppress your brothers, the sons of Israel, by power.

47 If the hand of a newcomer or a sojourner will have grown strong among you, and your brother, having become impoverished, will have sold himself to him, or to any of his stock,

48 after the sale, he is able to be redeemed. Whoever is willing among his brothers shall redeem him:

49 either the paternal uncle, or the paternal uncle's son, or his close relative, by blood or by affinity. But if he himself will be able also, he shall redeem himself,

50 considering only the years from the time of his selling until the year of the Jubilee, and calculating the money for which he was sold, according to the number of years and the accounting of a hired hand.

51 If there will have been many years which remain until the Jubilee, according to these shall he also repay the price.

52 If few, he shall determine the accounting with him according to the number of years, and he shall repay to the buyer by what is left remaining of the years;

53 his wages being charged by what served before. He shall not afflict him violently in your sight.

54 But if, by these means, he will not be able to be redeemed, then in the year of the Jubilee he shall depart with his children.

55 For they are my servants, the sons of Israel, whom I led away from the land of Egypt.

Leviticus 26

1 I am the Lord your God. You shall not make for yourselves an idol or a graven image. Neither shall you erect a monument, or set up a conspicuous stone in your land, in order that you may adore it. For I am the Lord your God.

2 Observe my Sabbaths, and be fearful toward my Sanctuary. I am the Lord.

3 If you will walk in my precepts, and observe my commandments, and accomplish them, I will give to you rain in its time,

4 and the ground shall bring forth its seedlings, and the trees shall be filled again with fruit.

5 The threshing of the harvest shall last until the vintage, and the vintage shall overtake the sowing. And you shall eat your bread to fullness, and you shall live in your land without fear.

6 I will give peace to your most distant regions. You will sleep, and there will be no one to strike you with terror. I will take away harmful wild beasts, and the sword will not cross your borders.

7 You will pursue your enemies, and they will fall down at the sight of you.

8 Five of yours will pursue a hundred foreigners, and a hundred of you will pursue ten thousand. Your enemies will fall by the sword in your sight.

9 I will look with favor upon you, and I will cause you to increase; you will be multiplied, and I will confirm my covenant with you.

10 You will eat the oldest of what is old, and, when what is new arrives, you will throw away what is old.

11 I will set my tabernacle in your midst, and my soul will not cast you out.

12 I will walk among you, and I will be your God, and you shall be my people.

13 I am the Lord your God, who led you away from the land of the Egyptians, lest you serve them, and who broke the chains around your necks, so that you would walk upright.

14 But if you will not listen to me, nor accomplish all of my commandments,

15 if you despise my laws, and disdain my judgments, so that you do not accomplish those things which have been established by me, and so that you lead my covenant away into nullification,

16 then I also will do these things to you. I will quickly visit you with destitution, and burning heat, which will waste away your eyes, and consume your lives. In vain will you sow your seed, which will be devoured by your enemies.

17 I will set my face against you, and you will fall down before your enemies, and you will be subjugated to those who hate you. You will flee, though no one pursues.

18 But if you will not be obedient to me in this way, then I will add sevenfold to your chastisement, because of your sins.

19 And I will crush the pride in your hardness, and I will give to you heaven above like iron, and the earth below like brass.

20 Your labor will be consumed to no purpose; the land will not bring forth seedlings, nor will the trees provide their fruit.

21 If you walk as an adversary to me, and if you are not willing to listen to me, I will add sevenfold to your plagues, because of your sins.

22 And I will send upon you the wild beasts of the field, which will consume you and your cattle, and which will reduce everything to paucity, and cause your roadways to become desolate.

23 But if you are not willing to receive discipline in this way, and you still walk as an adversary to me,

24 likewise, I will advance against you as an adversary, and I will strike you seven times, because of your sins.

25 And I will lead over you the sword that shall avenge my covenant. And when you will have fled into the cities, I will send a pestilence into your midst, and you will be delivered into the hands of your enemies.

26 After this, I will have broken the staff of your bread, so that ten women bake bread in one oven, and distribute it by weight. And you shall eat and not be filled.

27 Then, if you will not listen to me through these things, and you still walk against me,

28 then I also will advance against you, with an opposing fury, and I will chastise you with seven plagues, because of your sins:

29 so much so that you will eat the flesh of your sons and your daughters.

30 I will destroy your high places, and I will break apart your false images. You will fall among the ruins of your idols, and my soul will abominate you:

31 so much so that I will reduce your cities to a wilderness, and I will make your Sanctuaries desolate, and I will no longer accept the most sweet odors.

32 And I will utterly ruin your land, and your enemies shall be stupefied at it, when they will have become its inhabitants.

33 Then I will scatter you among the Gentiles, and I will unsheathe the sword after you. And your land will be deserted, and your cities will be demolished.

34 Then the land will be pleased by her Sabbaths, throughout all the days of her solitude. So, while you will be

35 in the land of the enemy, she will worship and rest in the Sabbath of her solitude, because she will not have rested in your Sabbaths, when you lived in her.

36 And whoever of you will remain, I will send terror into their hearts in the regions of their enemies. The sound of a flying leaf will terrify them, and so they will flee, as if from the sword. They will fall, though no one pursues.

37 And they will each fall upon their brothers, as if they were fleeing from wars; no one among you will dare to resist your foes.

38 You will perish among the Gentiles, and the land of the enemy will consume you.

39 But if some few of these still remain, they shall waste away in their iniquities, in the land of their enemies, and they will be afflicted, because of the sins of their fathers and their own sins,

40 until they confess their iniquities, and those of their ancestors, by which they have transgressed against me and walked as adversaries to me.

41 Therefore, I also will walk against them, and I will lead them into a hostile land, until their uncircumcised mind shall be ashamed. Then shall they pray on behalf of their impiety.

42 And I will remember my covenant, which I formed with Jacob, and Isaac, and Abraham. I will also remember the land,

43 which, when she will be left behind by them, shall be pleased by her Sabbaths, enduring solitude because of them. Yet truly, they shall pray for their sins, because they cast aside my judgments, and they despised my laws.

44 And even after so much, when they were in the land of their enemy, I did not cast them off entirely, and I did not so despise them that they would be consumed, nor so that I would nullify my covenant with them. For I am the Lord their God.

45 And I will remember my original covenant, when I led them away from the land of Egypt, in the sight of the Gentiles, so as to be their God. I am the Lord. These are the judgments, and precepts, and laws, which the Lord has granted between himself and the sons of Israel, on mount Sinai, by the hand of Moses.

Leviticus 27

1 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

2 Speak to the sons of Israel, and you shall say to them: The man who will have made a vow and espoused his soul to God shall give the price according to the estimation.

3 If it is a male from twenty years to sixty years, he shall give fifty shekels of silver, by the measure of the Sanctuary;

4 if it is a woman, thirty.

5 But from the fifth year until the twentieth, a male shall give twenty shekels; a female, ten.

6 From one month until the fifth year, for a male, five shekels shall be given; for a female, three.

7 At sixty years and beyond, a male shall give fifteen shekels; a female, ten.

8 If he is poor, and he does not have the means to pay the estimation, he shall stand before the priest, and however much he will value him and see that he is able to pay, so much shall he give.

9 But an animal which could be immolated to the Lord, if anyone has vowed it, shall be holy,

10 and it cannot be exchanged, that is, neither better for worse, nor worse for better. And if he has exchanged it, both that which was exchanged, and that for which it was exchanged shall be consecrated to the Lord.

11 An unclean animal which could not be sacrificed to the Lord, if anyone has vowed it, shall be led before the priest,

12 who, judging whether it is either good or bad, shall set the price.

13 But if he who offers it was willing to give, he shall add a fifth part above the estimation.

14 If a man has vowed his house, and he has sanctified it to the Lord, the priest shall examine it, whether it is good or bad, and it shall be sold according to the price which he will have established.

15 But if he who vowed it was willing to redeem it, he shall give a fifth part beyond the estimation, and he shall have the house.

16 But if he has vowed a field of his possession, and has consecrated it to the Lord, the price shall be estimated according to the measure of the seed. If the land would be sown with thirty measures of barley, then let it be sold for fifty shekels of silver.

17 If he has vowed his field beginning from the current year of Jubilee, as much as it may be worth, so shall it be estimated.

18 But if, after some amount of time, the priest shall evaluate the money according to the number of years that remain until the Jubilee, then the price shall be reduced.

19 But if he who had vowed it, was willing to redeem his field, he shall add a fifth part of the money to the estimation, and then he shall possess it.

20 But if he is not willing to redeem it, then it shall be sold to any other; he who vowed it is no longer able to redeem it.

21 For when the day of Jubilee arrives, it shall be sanctified to the Lord. And as a possession that has been consecrated, it rightfully belongs to the priest.

22 If a field has been bought, and it is not from the possession of ancestors, it shall be sanctified to the Lord.

23 The priest shall evaluate the price according to the number of years until the Jubilee; and the one who had vowed it shall give to the Lord.

24 Then, in the Jubilee, it shall be returned to the former owner, the one who had sold it and who had held it within the lot of his possession.

25 All estimation shall be weighed according to the shekel of the Sanctuary. A shekel has twenty obols.

26 The firstborn, which belong to the Lord, no one is able to sanctify or vow, whether it is an ox, or a sheep, they are for the Lord.

27 But if it is an unclean animal, whoever offers it shall redeem it, according to your estimation, and he shall add a fifth part to the price. If he is not willing to redeem it, it shall be sold to another for whatever amount it was estimated by you.

28 All that is consecrated to the Lord, whether it is a man, or an animal, or a field, shall not be sold; neither is it able to be redeemed. Anything, once it has been consecrated, shall be the Holy of holies to the Lord.

29 And all that has been consecrated, which is offered by man, shall not be redeemed, but shall surely die.

30 All the tithes of the land, whether from the grain, or from the fruits of trees, are for the Lord and are sanctified to him.

31 But if anyone is willing to redeem his tithes, he shall add a fifth part to them.

32 Out of all the tithes of oxen, and sheep, and goats, which cross under the rod of the shepherd, every tenth one that arrives shall be sanctified to the Lord.

33 It shall not be chosen by what is good or bad; neither shall it be exchanged for another. If anyone has exchanged it, both that which was exchanged, and that for which it was exchanged, shall be sanctified to the Lord and shall not be redeemed.

34 These are the precepts, which the Lord commanded Moses for the sons of Israel on mount Sinai.

Numbers 1

1 And the Lord spoke to Moses in the desert of Sinai, in the tabernacle of the covenant, on the first day of the second month, in the year after their departure from Egypt, saying:

2 "Take a total of the entire assembly of the sons of Israel, by their families and houses, and the names of each one, of whomever is of the male sex,

3 from twenty years and above, of all the able-bodied men out of Israel, and you shall number them by their companies, you and Aaron.

4 And there shall be with you the leaders of the tribes, as well as of the houses, in their kinships,

5 the names of whom are these: of Ruben, Elizur the son of Shedeur;

6 of Simeon, Shelumiel the son of Zurishaddai;

7 of Judah, Nahshon the son of Amminadab;

8 of Issachar, Nathanael the son of Zuar;

9 of Zebulon, Eliab the son of Helon.

10 And from the sons of Joseph: of Ephraim, Elishama the son of Ammihud; of Manasseh, Gamaliel the son of Pedahzur;

11 of Benjamin, Abidan the son of Gideoni;

12 of Dan, Ahiezer the son of Ammishaddai;

13 of Asher, Pagiel the son of Ochran;

14 of Gad, Eliasaph the son of Reuel;

15 of Naphtali, Ahira the son of Enan."

16 These are the very noble leaders of the multitude, by their tribes and kinships, and the heads of the army of Israel.

17 Moses and Aaron took these, with all the multitude of the common people,

18 and they gathered them together on the first day of the second month, taking a census of them by kinships, and houses, and families, and heads, and the names of each one from twenty years and above,

19 just as the Lord had instructed Moses. And they were numbered in the desert of Sinai.

20 Of Ruben, the firstborn of Israel, by their generations and families and houses, and the names of each head, of all who were of the male sex, from twenty years and above, capable of going to war,

21 there were forty-six thousand five hundred.

22 Of the sons of Simeon, by their generations and families, and the houses of their kinships, having been counted by the names and heads of each one, of all who were of the male sex, from twenty years and above, capable of going to war,

23 there were fifty-nine thousand three hundred.

24 Of the sons of Gad, by their generations and families, and the houses of their kinships, having been counted by the names of each one, from twenty years and above, of all who could go forth to war,

25 there were forty-five thousand six hundred fifty.

26 Of the sons of Judah, by their generations and families, and the houses of their kinships, by the names of each one, from twenty years and above, of all who were able to go forth to war,

27 there were counted seventy-four thousand six hundred.

28 Of the sons of Issachar, by their generations and families, and the houses of their kinships, by the names of each one, from twenty years and above, of all who could go forth to war,

29 there were counted fifty-four thousand four hundred.

30 Of the sons of Zebulon, by their generations and families, and the houses of their kinships, having been counted by the names of each one, from twenty years and above, of all who were able to go forth to war,

31 there were fifty-seven thousand four hundred.

32 From the sons of Joseph, of the sons of Ephraim, by their generations and families, and the houses of their kinships, having been counted by the names of each one, from twenty years and above, of all who were able to go forth to war,

33 there were forty thousand five hundred.

34 Furthermore, of the sons of Manasseh, by their generations and families, and the houses of their kinships, having been counted by the names of each one, from twenty years and above, of all who were able to go forth to war,

35 there were thirty-two thousand two hundred.

36 Of the sons of Benjamin, by their generations and families, and the houses of their kinships, having been counted by the names of each one, from twenty years and above, of all who were able to go forth to war,

37 there were thirty-five thousand four hundred.

38 Of the sons of Dan, by their generations and families, and the houses of their kinships, having been counted by the names of each one, from twenty years and above, of all who were able to go forth to war,

39 there were sixty-two thousand seven hundred.

40 Of the sons of Asher, by their generations and families, and the houses of their kinships, having been counted by the names of each one, from twenty years and above, of all who were able to go forth to war,

41 there were forty thousand and one thousand five hundred.

42 Of the sons of Naphtali, by their generations and families, and the houses of their kinships, having been counted by the names of each one, from twenty years and above, of all who were able to go forth to war,

43 there were fifty-three thousand four hundred.

44 These are the ones who were numbered by Moses and Aaron and the twelve leaders of Israel, each one by the houses of their kinships.

45 And the entire number of the sons of Israel by their houses and families, from twenty years and above, who were able to go forth to war, were

46 six hundred three thousand five hundred fifty men.

47 But the Levites in the tribes of their families were not numbered with them.

48 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

49 "Do not number the tribe of Levi, neither shall you take a total of them with the sons of Israel.

50 But appoint them over the tabernacle of the testimony, and all its vessels, and whatever pertains to the ceremonies. They shall carry the tabernacle and all its articles. And they shall be for the ministry, and they shall encamp all around the tabernacle.

51 When you would depart, the Levites shall take down the tabernacle. When you are to make camp, they shall set it up. Any outsider who will approach it shall be killed.

52 Now the sons of Israel shall make camp, each one by his companies and bands, as well as his army.

53 Moreover, the Levites shall fix their tents all around the tabernacle, lest there be an indignation over the multitude of the sons of Israel. And they shall stand watch as guardians over the tabernacle of the testimony."

54 Therefore, the sons of Israel acted according to everything that the Lord had instructed Moses.

Numbers 2

1 And the Lord spoke to Moses and Aaron, saying:

2 "Each one shall make camp, by their troops, as well as by their insignia and standards, and by the houses of their kinships, all around the tabernacle of the covenant."

3 To the east, Judah shall fix his tents, by the companies of his army. And the leader of his sons shall be Nahshon the son of Amminadab.

4 And the entire total of the fighting men from his stock was seventy-four thousand six hundred.

5 Beside him, those of the tribe of Issachar were encamped, whose leader was Nathanael the son of Zuar.

6 And the entire number of his fighting men was fifty-four thousand four hundred.

7 In the tribe of Zebulon, the leader was Eliab the son of Helon.

8 All the army of fighting men from his stock were fifty-seven thousand four hundred.

9 All who were numbered in the camp of Judah were one hundred eighty-six thousand four hundred. And these, by their companies, shall go forth first.

10 In the camp of the sons of Ruben, toward the south side, the leader shall be Elizur the son of Shedeur.

11 And the entire army of his fighting men, who were numbered, were forty-six thousand five hundred.

12 Beside him, those of the tribe of Simeon were encamped, whose leader was Shelumiel the son of Zurishaddai.

13 And the entire army of his fighting men, who were numbered, were fifty-nine thousand three hundred.

14 In the tribe of Gad, the leader was Eliasaph the son of Reuel.

15 And the entire army of his fighting men, who were numbered, were forty-five thousand six hundred fifty.

16 All who were counted in the camp of Ruben were one hundred fifty thousand and one thousand four hundred fifty, by their companies. These shall advance in the second place.

17 But the tabernacle of the testimony shall be lifted up by the officers of the Levites and their companies. In the manner in which it is set up, so also shall it be taken down. Each one shall advance according to their places and ranks.

18 On the west side, there shall be the camp of the sons of Ephraim, whose leader was Elishama the son of Ammihud.

19 The entire army of his fighting men, who were numbered, were forty thousand five hundred.

20 And with them was the tribe of the sons of Manasseh, whose leader was Gamaliel the son of Pedahzur.

21 And the entire army of his fighting men, who were numbered, were thirty-two thousand two hundred.

22 In the tribe of the sons of Benjamin, the leader was Abidan the son of Gideoni.

23 And the entire army of his fighting men, who were counted, were thirty-five thousand four hundred.

24 All who were numbered in the camp of Ephraim were one hundred eight thousand one hundred, by their companies. These shall advance third.

25 Toward the north side, the sons of Dan were encamped, whose leader was Ahiezer the son of Ammishaddai.

26 The entire army of his fighting men, who were numbered, were sixty-two thousand seven hundred.

27 Beside him, those of the tribe of Asher fixed their tents, whose leader was Pagiel the son of Ochran.

28 The entire army of his fighting men, who were numbered, were forty thousand and one thousand five hundred.

29 From the tribe of the sons of Naphtali, the leader was Ahira the son of Enan.

30 The entire army of his fighting men were fifty-three thousand four hundred.

31 All who were numbered in the camp of Dan were one hundred fifty-seven thousand six hundred; and these shall advance at the very end.

32 This is the number of the sons of Israel, of their army divided by the houses of their kinships and their companies: six hundred three thousand five hundred fifty.

33 But the Levites were not numbered among the sons of Israel. For so the Lord had instructed Moses.

34 And the sons of Israel acted according to all the things that the Lord had commanded. They were encamped by their companies, and they advanced by the families and houses of their fathers.

Numbers 3

1 These are the generations of Aaron and Moses, in the day when the Lord spoke to Moses on mount Sinai.

2 And these are the names of the sons of Aaron: his firstborn Nadab, then Abihu, and Eleazar, and Ithamar.

3 These the names of the sons of Aaron, the priests who were anointed and whose hands were filled and consecrated in order to exercise the priesthood.

4 For Nadab and Abihu died without children, when they offered, in the sight of the Lord, a strange fire, in the desert of Sinai. And so, Eleazar and Ithamar exercised the priesthood in the sight of Aaron, their father.

5 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

6 "Bring forward the tribe of Levi, and cause them to stand in the sight of Aaron the priest, in order to minister to him. And let them keep watch outside,

7 and let them observe whatever pertains to the ritual for the multitude, in front of the tabernacle of the testimony,

8 and let them take care of the vessels of the tabernacle, serving in its ministry.

9 And you shall give the Levites as a gift to Aaron and his sons; for they have been delivered to them by the sons of Israel.

10 But you shall appoint Aaron and his sons over the service of priesthood. The outsider who approaches to minister shall be put to death."

11 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

12 "I have taken the Levites from the sons of Israel. For the Levites, and all the firstborn who open the womb among the sons of Israel, shall be mine.

13 For every firstborn is mine. From the time that I struck the firstborn in the land of Egypt, I have sanctified for myself whatever is born first in Israel. From man, even to beast, they are mine. I am the Lord."

14 And the Lord spoke to Moses in the desert of Sinai, saying:

15 "Number the sons of Levi by the houses of their fathers and their families, every male from one month and above."

16 Moses numbered them, just as the Lord had instructed,

17 and there were found the sons of Levi by their names: Gershon and Kohath and Merari.

18 The sons of Gershon: Libni and Shimei.

19 The sons of Kohath: Amram, and Izhar, Hebron and Uzziel.

20 The sons of Merari: Mahli and Mushi.

21 From Gershon were two families: the Libnites, and the Shimeites.

22 The people of these were numbered, of the male sex, from one month and above: seven thousand five hundred.

23 These shall encamp behind the tabernacle, toward the west,

24 under the leader Eliasaph the son of Lael.

25 And they shall keep watch over the tabernacle of the covenant:

26 the tabernacle itself, and its covering; the tent that is drawn before the doors of the covering of the covenant; and the curtains of the atrium; likewise, the tent that is suspended at the entrance of the atrium of the tabernacle; and whatever pertains to the ritual of the altar; the cords of the tabernacle and all its implements.

27 The kinship of Kohath includes the peoples of the Amramites and Izharites and Hebronites and Uzzielites. These are the families of the Kohathites, having been counted by their names,

28 all those of the male gender, from one month and above: eight thousand six hundred. They shall keep watch over the Sanctuary,

29 and they shall encamp toward the south side.

30 And their leader shall be Elisaphan the son of Uzziel.

31 And they shall take care of the ark, and the table and the lampstand, the altars and the vessels of the Sanctuary, by which they minister, and the veil, and all the articles of this kind.

32 But the leader of the leaders of the Levites, Eleazar the son of Aaron the priest, shall be over those who watch over the care of the Sanctuary.

33 And truly, from Merari are the peoples of the Mahlites and Mushites, having been counted by their names,

34 all those of the male gender, from one month and above: six thousand two hundred.

35 Their leader is Suriel the son of Abihaiel. They shall make camp on the north side.

36 Under their care shall be the panels of the tabernacle, and the bars, and the columns with their bases, and all the things which pertain to service of this kind,

37 and the columns of the surrounding atrium with their bases, and the tent pegs with their cords.

38 Moses and Aaron, with their sons, shall make camp before the tabernacle of the covenant, that is, on the east side, holding the custody of the Sanctuary in the midst of the sons of Israel. Whatever foreigner approaches it shall die.

39 All the Levites, whom Moses and Aaron numbered by their families according to the precept of the Lord, of the male gender, from one month and above, were twenty-two thousand.

40 And the Lord said to Moses: "Number the firstborn of the male sex from the sons of Israel, from one month and above, and you shall take their total.

41 And you shall bring the Levites to me, in place of all the firstborn of the sons of Israel, and you shall bring their cattle to me, in place of all the firstborn of the cattle of the sons of Israel. I am the Lord."

42 Moses took a census, just as the Lord had instructed, of the firstborn of the sons of Israel.

43 And the males by their names, from one month and above, were twenty-two thousand two hundred seventy-three.

44 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

45 "Take the Levites, in place of the firstborn of the sons of Israel, and the cattle of the Levites, in place of their cattle, and so the Levites shall be mine. I am the Lord.

46 But for the price of the two hundred and seventy-three, which exceed the number of the Levites compared to the number of firstborn of the sons of Israel,

47 you shall take five shekels for each head, by the measure of the Sanctuary. A shekel has twenty obols.

48 And you shall give the money to Aaron and his sons as the price of those that are in excess."

49 Therefore, Moses took the money for those that were in excess, and whom they had redeemed from the Levites

50 in place of the firstborn of the sons of Israel: one thousand three hundred sixty-five shekels, according to the weight of the Sanctuary.

51 And he gave it to Aaron and his sons, according to the word by which the Lord had instructed him.

Numbers 4

1 And the Lord spoke to Moses and Aaron, saying:

2 "Take a total of the sons of Kohath from the midst of the Levites, by their houses and families,

3 from thirty years and above, even to the fiftieth year, of all who enter so as to stand and minister in the tabernacle of the covenant.

4 This is the service of the sons of Kohath: the tabernacle of the covenant and the Holy of holies.

5 Aaron and his sons shall enter, when the camp is going to move, and they shall take down the veil, which hangs before the entrance, and they shall wrap the ark of the testimony in it,

6 and they shall cover it further with a veil of violet skins, and they shall extend over it a cloth made entirely of hyacinth, and they shall draw in the bars.

7 Likewise, they shall wrap the table of the presence in a cloth of hyacinth, and they shall place with it the censers and little mortars, the cups and bowls for pouring out libations; the bread shall be always on it.

8 And they shall extend over it a cloth of scarlet, which they shall further cover with a veil of violet skins, and they shall draw in the bars.

9 They shall take also a cloth of hyacinth, with which they shall cover the lampstand with the lamps, and its tongs, and the candle snuffers, and all the vessels of oil, which are necessary for the preparation of the lamps.

10 And over all this they shall place a covering of violet skins, and they shall draw in the bars.

11 And certainly they shall wrap the golden altar in a hyacinth garment, and they shall extend over it a covering of violet skins, and they shall draw in the bars.

12 All the vessels with which they minister in the Sanctuary they shall wrap in a cloth of hyacinth, and they shall extend over it a covering of violet skins, and they shall draw in the bars.

13 Moreover, they shall cleanse the altar of ashes, and they shall wrap it in a purple garment,

14 and they shall place it with all the vessels which they use in its ministry, that is, receptacles for fire, small hooks as well as forks, larger hooks and shovels. They shall cover all the vessels of the altar together with a veil of violet skins, and they shall draw in the bars.

15 And when Aaron and his sons have wrapped the Sanctuary and its vessels at the dismantling of the camp, then the sons of Kohath shall enter, so as to carry what has been wrapped. And they shall not touch the vessels of the Sanctuary, lest they die. These are the burdens of the sons of Kohath concerning the tabernacle of the covenant.

16 Over them shall be Eleazar, the son of Aaron the priest, to whom belongs the care of the oil to prepare the lamps, and the incense compound, and the sacrifice, which is offered continually, and the oil of unction, and whatever pertains to the service of the tabernacle, and all the vessels that are in the Sanctuary."

17 And the Lord spoke to Moses and Aaron, saying:

18 "Do not be willing to lose the people of Kohath from the midst of the Levites.

19 But do this for them, so that they may live, and so that they may not die by touching the Holies of holies. Aaron and his sons shall enter, and they shall assign the work of each one, and they shall determine what each one ought to carry.

20 Let no others, out of curiosity, see the things that are in the Sanctuary before they are wrapped, otherwise they shall die."

21 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

22 "Now also take a total of the sons of Gershon, by their houses and families and kinships,

23 from thirty years and above, even to fifty years. Number all those who enter and minister in the tabernacle of the covenant.

24 This is the duty of the family of the Gershonites:

25 to carry the curtains of the tabernacle, and the roof of the covenant, the other covering, and the veil over everything, and the violet tent, which hangs at the entrance of the tabernacle of the covenant,

26 the curtains of the atrium, and the veil at the entrance, which is before tabernacle. Everything that pertains to the altar, the cords, and the vessels of the ministry

27 the sons of Gershon shall carry, under the orders of Aaron and his sons. And so shall each one know to which burden he ought to surrender.

28 This is the service of the family of the Gershonites, in the tabernacle of the covenant, and they shall be under the hand of Ithamar, the son of Aaron the priest.

29 Likewise, you shall take a census of the sons of Merari, by the families and houses of their fathers,

30 from thirty years and above, even to fifty years, of all who enter to the office of their ministry and to the service of the covenant of the testimony.

31 These are their burdens: They shall carry the panels of the tabernacle and its bars, the columns and their bases,

32 also the columns surrounding the atrium, with their bases and tent pegs and cords. They shall accept by number all the vessels and articles, and so shall they carry them.

33 This is the office of the family of the Merarites, and their ministry for the tabernacle of the covenant. And they shall be under the hand of Ithamar, the son of Aaron the priest."

34 Therefore, Moses and Aaron, and the leaders of the assembly, took a census of the sons of Kohath, by the kinships and houses of their fathers,

35 from thirty years and above, even to the fiftieth year, of all who enter to the ministry of the tabernacle of the covenant.

36 And there were found two thousand seven hundred fifty.

37 This is the number of the people of Kohath, who enter the tabernacle of the covenant. These Moses and Aaron numbered according to the word of the Lord by the hand of Moses.

38 The sons of Gershon also were numbered by the kinships and houses of their fathers,

39 from thirty years and above, even to the fiftieth year, all who enter so as to minister in the tabernacle of the covenant.

40 And there were found two thousand six hundred thirty.

41 This is the people of the Gershonites, whom Moses and Aaron numbered according to the word of the Lord.

42 The sons of Merari also were numbered by the kinships and houses of their fathers,

43 from thirty years and above, even to the fiftieth year, all who enter to fulfill the rituals of the tabernacle of the covenant.

44 And there were found three thousand two hundred.

45 This is the number of the sons of Merari, whom Moses and Aaron counted according to the command of the Lord by the hand of Moses.

46 All who were counted from the Levites, and whom, by name, Moses and Aaron, and the leaders of Israel, counted by the kinships and houses of their fathers,

47 from thirty years and above, until the fiftieth year, entering for the ministry of the tabernacle and carrying the burdens,

48 were together eight thousand five hundred eighty.

49 Moses took a census of them, according to the word of the Lord, each one according to their office and their burdens, just as the Lord had instructed him.

Numbers 5

1 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

2 "Instruct the sons of Israel to cast out of the camp every leper, and those who have a flow of seed, and those who have been polluted because of the dead;

3 cast out of the camp both male and female, lest they contaminate it while I am dwelling with you."

4 And the sons of Israel did so, and they cast them out, beyond the camp, just as the Lord had spoken to Moses.

5 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

6 "Say to the sons of Israel: A man or a woman, when they have done anything out of all the sins that often befall men, or if, by negligence, they have transgressed the commandment of the Lord, and so have committed an offense,

7 they shall confess their sin, and they shall restore the principle itself, plus a fifth part above it, to any against whom they have sinned.

8 But if there would be no one to receive it, they shall give it to the Lord, and it shall be for the priest, except for the ram, which is offered for expiation, in order to be a pleasing victim.

9 Likewise, all the first-fruits, which the sons of Israel offer, belong to the priest,

10 with whatever is offered by each one at the Sanctuary, and which is delivered into the hands of the priest; it shall be his."

11 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

12 "Speak to the sons of Israel, and you shall say to them: The man whose wife will have gone astray, and, disdaining her husband,

13 will have slept with another man, and if her husband cannot discover it, but the adultery is secret, and if it cannot be proved by witnesses, because she was not caught in the shameful act,

14 if the spirit of jealousy stirs up the husband against his wife, who either has been polluted or is being assailed with a false suspicion,

15 he shall bring her to the priest, and he shall offer an oblation for her, a tenth part of native barley meal. He shall not pour oil over it, nor shall he place frankincense on it, because it is a sacrifice for jealousy, or an oblation investigating adultery.

16 Therefore, the priest shall offer it, and he shall set it in the sight of the Lord.

17 And he shall take up holy water in an earthen vessel, and he shall cast a little earth from the pavement of the tabernacle into it.

18 And while the woman stands before the Lord, he shall uncover her head, and he shall place over her hands the sacrifice of recollection and oblation of jealousy. But he shall take hold of the most bitter waters, in which he has gathered curses with loathing.

19 And he shall bind her by an oath, and he shall say: 'If another man has not slept with you, and if you have not been polluted by forsaking the bed of your husband, these most bitter waters, into which I have gathered curses, shall not harm you.

20 But if you have turned away from your husband, and also have been defiled, and have lain together with another man,

21 these curses shall be thrown upon you: May the Lord turn you into a curse and an example among all his people. May he cause your thigh to rot, and may your abdomen swell up and burst out.

22 May the cursed waters enter into your stomach, and may your womb swell and your thigh rot.' And the woman shall respond: 'Amen, amen.'

23 And the priest shall write these curses in a little book, and then he shall erase them with the very bitter waters, into which he had gathered the curses,

24 and he shall give it to her to drink. And when she has emptied it,

25 the priest shall take from her hand the sacrifice of jealousy, and he shall elevate it before the Lord, and he shall impose it upon the altar. Yet only after he first

26 takes a handful of the sacrifice from that which is offered, and burns it upon the altar, and then he may give the most bitter waters to the woman as a drink.

27 And when she drinks it, if she has been defiled, and, having despised her husband, is guilty of adultery, the curse shall pass through her, and as her belly swells up, her thigh shall decay, and the woman shall become a curse and an example to all the people.

28 But if she has not been defiled, she shall be unharmed and she shall bear children.

29 This is the law for jealousy. If a woman has turned aside from her husband, and if she has been polluted,

30 and if the husband, being stirred up by the spirit of jealousy, has brought her before the sight of the Lord, and the priest has acted toward her according to all that has been written:

31 then the husband shall be without guilt, and she shall bear her iniquity."

Numbers 6

1 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

2 "Speak to the sons of Israel, and you shall say to them: A man or a woman, when they have made a vow so that they may be sanctified, and when they are willing to consecrate themselves to the Lord,

3 shall abstain from wine and from anything which is able to inebriate. They shall not drink vinegar made from wine or from any other drink, nor anything pressed from the grape. They shall not eat grapes, neither fresh nor dried.

4 During all the days that they are consecrated to the Lord by vow, they shall not eat whatever may be from the vineyard, from raisins, even to grape seeds.

5 During all the time of his separation, no razor shall pass over his head, even until the completion of the day when he is consecrated to the Lord. He shall be holy, letting the hair of his head grow long.

6 During all the time of his consecration, he shall not enter because of a death,

7 nor shall he contaminate himself, even over the funeral of his father, or his mother, or his brother, or his sister. For the consecration of his God is upon his head.

8 During all the days of his separation, he shall be holy to the Lord.

9 But if anyone will have died unexpectedly before him, the head of his consecration shall be polluted, and he shall shave it in that very place, on the same day of his purification, and again on the seventh day.

10 Then, on the eighth day, he shall offer two turtledoves or two young pigeons, to the priest at the entrance to the covenant of the testimony.

11 And the priest shall effect one for sin, and the other as a holocaust, and he shall pray for him, because he has sinned on account of the dead. And he shall sanctify his head on that day.

12 And he shall consecrate to the Lord the days of his separation, offering a one-year-old lamb for sin, yet in such a manner that the former days will be made null and void, because his sanctification was polluted.

13 This is the law of consecration. When the days that he had decreed by vow have been completed, he shall bring him to the door of the tabernacle of the covenant,

14 and he shall offer his oblation to the Lord: an immaculate one-year-old male lamb as a holocaust, and an immaculate one-year-old female lamb for sin, and an immaculate ram, a peace-offering victim,

15 also, a basket of unleavened bread, which has been sprinkled with oil, and cakes without leaven, anointed with oil, as well as the libations of each one.

16 And the priest shall offer them before the Lord, and he shall perform both the sin offering and the holocaust.

17 Yet truly, the ram he shall immolate as a peace-offering victim to the Lord, offering at the same time the basket of unleavened bread, and the libations which are required by custom.

18 Then the Nazarite shall be shaved of the long hair of his consecration, before the door of the tabernacle of the covenant. And he shall take his hair, and he shall place it upon the fire, which is under the sacrifice of the peace offerings.

19 And he shall take the cooked shoulder of the ram, and one twist of bread without leaven from the basket, and one unleavened cake, and he shall deliver them into the hands of the Nazarite, after his head has been shaven.

20 And receiving them again from him, he shall elevate them in the sight of the Lord. And having been sanctified, these shall be for the priest, as also the breast, which was ordered to be separated, and the leg. After this, the Nazarite is able to drink wine.

21 This is the law of the Nazarite, when he has vowed his oblation to the Lord in the time of his consecration, aside from those things which his hand shall find. According to what he had vowed in his mind, so shall he do, to the perfection of his sanctification."

22 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

23 "Say to Aaron and his sons: Thus shall you bless the sons of Israel, and you shall say to them:

24 'May the Lord bless you and keep you.

25 May the Lord reveal his face to you and take pity on you.

26 May the Lord turn his countenance toward you and grant peace to you.'

27 And they shall invoke my name over the sons of Israel, and I will bless them."

Numbers 7

1 Now it happened in the day when Moses completed the tabernacle, and he set it up, and he anointed and sanctified it with all of its vessels, and similarly the altar and all of its vessels,

2 that the leaders of Israel and the heads of the families, who were in each tribe and who were in charge of those who had been numbered, offered

3 their gifts in the sight of the Lord: six covered wagons with twelve oxen. Two leaders offered one wagon, and each offered one ox, and they offered these in the sight of the tabernacle.

4 Then the Lord said to Moses:

5 "Receive these things from them, in order to serve in the ministry of the tabernacle, and you shall deliver them to the Levites, according to the order of their ministry."

6 And so Moses, having received the wagons and the oxen, delivered them to the Levites.

7 Two wagons and four oxen he gave to the sons of Gershon, according to what they needed.

8 The other four wagons and eight oxen he gave to the sons of Merari, according to their offices and service, under the hand of Ithamar, the son of Aaron the priest.

9 But to the sons of Kohath he gave no wagons or oxen, because they serve in the Sanctuary and they carry their burdens on their shoulders.

10 Therefore, the leaders offered, at the dedication of the altar on the day when it was anointed, their oblation before the altar.

11 And the Lord said to Moses: "Let each of the leaders, on each of the days, offer their gifts for the dedication of the altar."

12 On the first day, Nahshon, the son of Amminadab of the tribe of Judah, offered his oblation.

13 And in it were these: a silver dish weighing one hundred thirty shekels, a silver bowl having seventy shekels, according to the weight of the Sanctuary, and both were filled with fine wheat flour sprinkled with oil as a sacrifice,

14 a little mortar made from ten shekels of gold, filled with incense,

15 an ox from the herd, and a ram, and a one-year-old lamb as a holocaust,

16 and a he-goat for sin;

17 and for the sacrifice of peace offerings: two oxen, five rams, five he-goats, and five one-year-old lambs. This was the oblation of Nahshon, the son of Amminadab.

18 On the second day, Nathanael, the son of Zuar, the leader of the tribe of Issachar, offered:

19 a silver dish weighing one hundred thirty shekels, a silver bowl having seventy shekels, according to the weight of the Sanctuary, and both were filled with fine wheat flour sprinkled with oil as a sacrifice,

20 a little mortar of gold having ten shekels, filled with incense,

21 an ox from the herd, and a ram, and one-year-old lamb as a holocaust,

22 and a he-goat for sin;

23 and for the sacrifice of peace offerings: two oxen, five rams, five he-goats, and five one-year-old lambs. This was the oblation of Nathanael, the son of Zuar.

24 On the third day, the leader of the sons of Zebulon, Eliab the son of Helon,

25 offered a silver dish weighing one hundred thirty shekels, a silver bowl having seventy shekels, by the weight of the Sanctuary, and both were filled with fine wheat flour sprinkled with oil as a sacrifice,

26 a little mortar of gold weighing ten shekels, filled with incense,

27 an ox from the herd, and a ram, and one-year-old lamb as a holocaust,

28 and a he-goat for sin;

29 and for the sacrifice of peace offerings: two oxen, five rams, five he-goats, and five one-year-old lambs. This is the oblation of Eliab the son of Helon.

30 On the fourth day, the leader of the sons of Ruben, Elizur the son of Shedeur,

31 offered a silver dish weighing one hundred thirty shekels, a silver bowl having seventy shekels, by the weight of the Sanctuary, and both were filled with fine wheat flour sprinkled with oil as a sacrifice,

32 a little mortar of gold weighing ten shekels, filled with incense,

33 an ox from the herd, and a ram, and a one-year-old lamb as a holocaust,

34 and a he-goat for sin;

35 and for victims of peace offerings: two oxen, five rams, five he-goats, and five one-year-old lambs. This was the oblation of Elizur, the son of Shedeur.

36 On the fifth day, the leader of the sons of Simeon, Shelumiel the son of Zurishaddai,

37 offered a silver dish weighing one hundred thirty shekels, a silver bowl having seventy shekels, by the weight of the Sanctuary, and both were filled with fine wheat flour sprinkled with oil as a sacrifice,

38 a little mortar of gold weighing ten shekels, filled with incense,

39 an ox from the herd, and a ram, and a one-year-old lamb as a holocaust,

40 and a he-goat for sin;

41 and for victims of peace offerings: two oxen, five rams, five he-goats, and five one-year-old lambs. This was the oblation of Shelumiel, the son of Zurishaddai.

42 On the sixth day, the leader of the sons of Gad, Eliasaph the son of Reuel,

43 offered a silver dish weighing one hundred thirty shekels, a silver bowl having seventy shekels, by the weight of the Sanctuary, and both were filled with fine wheat flour sprinkled with oil as a sacrifice,

44 a little mortar of gold weighing ten shekels, filled with incense,

45 an ox from the herd, and a ram, and one-year-old lamb as a holocaust,

46 and a he-goat for sin;

47 and for victims of peace offerings: two oxen, five rams, five he-goats, and five one-year-old lambs. This was the oblation of Eliasaph, the son of Reuel.

48 On the seventh day, the leader of the sons of Ephraim, Elishama the son of Ammihud,

49 offered a silver dish weighing one hundred thirty shekels, a silver bowl having seventy shekels, by the weight of the Sanctuary, and both were filled with fine wheat flour sprinkled with oil as a sacrifice,

50 a little mortar of gold weighing ten shekels, filled with incense,

51 an ox from the herd, and a ram, and one-year-old lamb as a holocaust,

52 and a he-goat for sin;

53 and for victims of peace offerings: two oxen, five rams, five he-goats, and five one-year-old lambs. This was the oblation of Elishama, the son of Ammihud.

54 On the eighth day, the leader of the sons of Manasseh, Gamaliel the son of Pedahzur,

55 offered a silver dish weighing one hundred thirty shekels, a silver bowl having seventy shekels, by the weight of the Sanctuary, and both were filled with fine wheat flour sprinkled with oil as a sacrifice,

56 a little mortar of gold weighing ten shekels, filled with incense,

57 an ox from the herd, and a ram, and a one-year-old lamb as a holocaust,

58 and a he-goat for sin;

59 and for victims of peace offerings: two oxen, five rams, five he-goats, and five one-year-old lambs. This was the oblation of Gamaliel, the son of Pedahzur.

60 On the ninth day, the leader of the sons of Benjamin, Abidan the son of Gideoni,

61 offered a silver dish weighing one hundred thirty shekels, a silver bowl having seventy shekels, by the weight of the Sanctuary, and both were filled with fine wheat flour sprinkled with oil as a sacrifice,

62 a little mortar of gold weighing ten shekels, filled with incense,

63 an ox from the herd, and a ram, and a one-year-old lamb as a holocaust,

64 and a he-goat for sin;

65 and for victims of peace offerings: two oxen, five rams, five he-goats, and five one-year-old lambs. This was the oblation of Abidan, the son of Gideoni.

66 On the tenth day, the leaders of the sons of Dan, Ahiezer the son of Ammishaddai,

67 offered a silver dish weighing one hundred thirty shekels, a silver bowl having seventy shekels, by the weight of the Sanctuary, and both were filled with fine wheat flour sprinkled with oil as a sacrifice,

68 a little mortar of gold weighing ten shekels, filled with incense,

69 an ox from the herd, and a ram, and a one-year-old lamb as a holocaust,

70 and a he-goat for sin;

71 and for victims of peace offerings: two oxen, five rams, five he-goats, and five one-year-old lambs. This was the oblation of Ahiezer, the son of Ammishaddai.

72 On the eleventh day, the leader of the sons of Asher, Pagiel the son of Ochran,

73 offered a silver dish weighing one hundred thirty shekels, a silver bowl having seventy shekels, by the weight of the Sanctuary, and both were filled with fine wheat flour sprinkled with oil as a sacrifice,

74 a little mortar of gold weighing ten shekels, filled with incense,

75 an ox from the herd, and a ram, and a one-year-old lamb as a holocaust,

76 and a he-goat for sin;

77 and for victims of peace offerings: two oxen, five rams, five he-goats, and five one-year-old lambs. This was the oblation of Pagiel, the son of Ochran.

78 On the twelfth day, the leader of the sons of Naphtali, Ahira the son of Enan,

79 offered a silver dish weighing one hundred thirty shekels, a silver bowl having seventy shekels, by the weight of the Sanctuary, and both were filled with fine wheat flour sprinkled with oil as a sacrifice,

80 a little mortar of gold weighing ten shekels, filled with incense,

81 an ox from the herd, and a ram, and a one-year-old lamb as a holocaust,

82 and a he-goat for sin;

83 and for victims of peace offerings: two oxen, five rams, five he-goats, and five one-year-old lambs. This was the oblation of Ahira, the son of Enan.

84 These were the oblations from the leaders of Israel for the dedication of the altar on the day when it was consecrated: twelve dishes of silver, twelve bowls of silver, twelve little mortars of gold,

85 such that each dish had one hundred thirty shekels of silver, and each bowl had seventy shekels, that is, putting all of the vessels from silver together, two thousand four hundred shekels, by the weight of the Sanctuary,

86 and twelve little mortars of gold, filled with incense, weighing ten shekels by the weight of the Sanctuary, that is, all together one hundred twenty shekels of gold,

87 and twelve oxen from the herd as a holocaust, twelve rams, twelve one-year-old lambs, with their libations, and twelve he-goats for sin;

88 and for victims of peace offerings: twenty-four oxen, sixty rams, sixty he-goats, and sixty one-year-old lambs. These were the oblations for the dedication of the altar, when it was anointed.

89 And when Moses entered into the tabernacle of the covenant, to consult the oracle, he heard the voice of One speaking to him from the propitiatory, which is over the ark of the testimony between the two cherubims, and there he also spoke to him.

Numbers 8

1 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

2 "Speak to Aaron, and you shall say to him: When you place the seven lamps, let the lampstand be set up on the south side. Therefore, give this instruction: that the lamps should look out from the region opposite the north, toward the table of the bread of the presence; they shall give light opposite that area, toward the area that the lampstand faces."

3 And Aaron did so, and he placed the lamps on the lampstand, just as the Lord had instructed Moses.

4 Now this was the workmanship of the lampstand: it was of ductile gold, both the main shaft and all that originated from both sides of the branches. According to the example that the Lord revealed to Moses, so did he make the lampstand.

5 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

6 "Take the Levites from the midst of the sons of Israel, and you shall purify them

7 according to this ritual: Let them be sprinkled with the water of illumination, and let them shave off all the hairs of their body. And when they have washed their garments and have been cleansed,

8 they shall take an ox from the herd, with its libation of fine wheat flour sprinkled with oil; then you shall receive another ox from the herd for sin.

9 And you shall bring forward the Levites before the tabernacle of the covenant, calling together all the multitude of the sons of Israel.

10 And when the Levites are before the Lord, the sons of Israel shall place their hands upon them.

11 And Aaron shall offer the Levites as a gift in the sight of the Lord, from the sons of Israel, so that they may serve in his ministry.

12 Likewise, the Levites shall place their hands upon the heads of the oxen; you shall make use of one of these for sin, and the other as a holocaust to the Lord, so that you may intercede for them.

13 And you shall set the Levites in the sight of Aaron and his sons, and you shall consecrate those being offered to the Lord,

14 and you shall separate them from the midst of the sons of Israel, so that they may be for me.

15 And after this, they shall enter the tabernacle of the covenant, in order to serve me. And so shall you purify and consecrate them as an oblation to the Lord. For they were given to me as a gift from the sons of Israel.

16 I have accepted them in place of the firstborn which open every womb in Israel.

17 For all the firstborn of the sons of Israel, as much from men as from beasts, are mine. From the day when I struck down all the firstborn in the land of Egypt, I have sanctified them to myself.

18 And I have taken the Levites in place of all the firstborn of the sons of Israel.

19 And I have delivered them as a gift to Aaron and his sons, from the midst of the people, in order to serve me, for Israel, in the tabernacle of the covenant, and in order to pray for them, lest there be a scourge among the people, if they were to dare to approach to my Sanctuary."

20 And Moses and Aaron, and all the multitude of the sons of Israel, accomplished all that the Lord had commanded Moses concerning the Levites.

21 And they were purified, and they washed their garments. And Aaron lifted them up in the sight of the Lord, and he prayed for them,

22 so that, having been purified, they might enter to their duties in the tabernacle of the covenant before Aaron and his sons. Just as the Lord had instructed Moses about the Levites, so was it done.

23 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

24 "This is the law of the Levites: From twenty-five years and above, they shall enter to minister in the tabernacle of the covenant.

25 And when they will have completed the fiftieth year of age, they shall cease to serve.

26 And they shall be the ministers of their brothers in the tabernacle of the covenant, in order to care for the things that have been commended to them, but not to perform the works themselves. So shall you assign the Levites in their duties."

Numbers 9

1 The Lord spoke to Moses in the desert of Sinai, in the second year after they departed from the land of Egypt, in the first month, saying:

2 "Let the sons of Israel observe the Passover at its proper time,

3 on the fourteenth day of this month, in the evening, according to all of its ceremonies and justifications."

4 And Moses instructed the sons of Israel, so that they would observe the Passover.

5 And they observed it at its proper time: on the fourteenth day of the month, in the evening, at mount Sinai. The sons of Israel acted according to all the things that the Lord had commanded Moses.

6 But behold, certain ones, who were not able to observe the Passover on that day, being unclean because of the life of a man, approaching Moses and Aaron,

7 said to them: "We are unclean because of the life of a man. Why have we been cheated, in that we are not permitted to offer, at its proper time, the oblation to the Lord among the sons of Israel?"

8 And Moses responded to them: "Remain, so that I may consult the Lord, as to what he will rule about you."

9 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

10 "Say to the sons of Israel: The man who becomes unclean because of a life, or if he is on a distant journey within your nation, let him observe the Passover to the Lord.

11 In the second month, on the fourteenth day of the month, in the evening, they shall eat it with unleavened bread and wild lettuce.

12 They shall not leave behind any of it until morning, and they shall not break a bone of it; they shall observe all the rituals of the Passover.

13 But if any man was both clean, and not on a journey, and yet he did not observe the Passover, that soul shall be exterminated from among his people, because he did not offer the sacrifice to the Lord in its time. He shall bear his sin.

14 Likewise, the sojourner and the newcomer, if they are among you, shall observe the Passover to the Lord according to its ceremonies and justifications. The same precept shall be with you, as much for the newcomer as for the native."

15 And so, on the day when the tabernacle was raised, a cloud covered it. But over the tabernacle, from evening until morning, there was, as it seemed, the appearance of fire.

16 This was so continually: throughout the day a cloud covered it, and throughout the night, the appearance of fire.

17 And when the cloud that was protecting the tabernacle had been taken up, then the sons of Israel advanced forward, and in the place where the cloud had remained standing, there they made camp.

18 Upon the order of the Lord they advanced, and upon his order they fixed the tabernacle. All the days during which the cloud was standing over the tabernacle, they remained in the same place.

19 And if it happened that it remained for a long time over it, the sons of Israel kept the night watches of the Lord, and they did not advance,

20 during as many days as the cloud remained over the tabernacle. At the command of the Lord they raised their tents, and at his command they took them down.

21 If the cloud remained from evening until morning, and immediately, at first light, it left the tabernacle, they set out. And if it withdrew after a day and a night, they dismantled their tents.

22 Yet truly, whether it remained over the tabernacle for two days, or one month, or a longer time, the sons of Israel remained in the same place, and they did not set out. Then, as soon as it withdrew, they moved the camp.

23 By the word of the Lord they fixed their tents, and by his word they advanced. And they kept the night watches of the Lord, according to his command by the hand of Moses.

Numbers 10

1 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

2 "Make for yourself two trumpets of ductile silver, with which you may be able to call together the multitude when the camp is to be moved.

3 And when you sound the trumpets, all the multitude shall gather to you at the door of the tabernacle of the covenant.

4 If you sound it only once, the leaders and the heads of the multitude of Israel shall come to you.

5 But if the sound of the trumpets is prolonged, but with interruptions, those who are toward the east side shall move the camp first.

6 Then, at the second sounding of the trumpet with the same cadence, those who live toward the south shall take up their tents. And the remainder shall act in like manner, when the trumpets shall reverberate for a departure.

7 But when the people are to be gathered together, the sound of the trumpets shall be simple, and the sounds shall not be separated.

8 Now it is the sons of Aaron the priest who shall sound the trumpets. And this shall be an everlasting ordinance, in your generations.

9 If you go forth to war from your land, against the enemies who set out against you, you shall sound the trumpets repeatedly, and there shall be a remembrance of you before the Lord your God, so that you may be rescued from the hands of your enemies.

10 If at any time you will have a banquet, and on feast days, and on the first days of the months, you shall sound the trumpets over the holocausts and the peace-offering victims, so that they may be for you as a remembrance by your God. I am the Lord your God."

11 In the second year, in the second month, on the twentieth day of the month, the cloud was lifted up from the tabernacle of the covenant.

12 And the sons of Israel set out by their companies from the desert of Sinai, and the cloud rested in the wilderness of Paran.

13 And the first to move their camp, according to the command of the Lord by the hand of Moses,

14 were the sons of Judah by their companies, whose leader was Nahshon the son of Amminadab.

15 In the tribe of the sons of Issachar, the leader was Nathanael the son of Zuar.

16 In the tribe of Zebulon, the leader was Eliab the son of Helon.

17 And the tabernacle was taken down, because the sons of Gershon and Merari, who carry it, were departing.

18 And the sons of Ruben also set out, by their companies and ranks, whose leader was Elizur the son of Shedeur.

19 And in the tribe of Simeon, the leader was Shelumiel the son of Zurishaddai.

20 And in the tribe of Gad, the leader was Eliasaph the son of Reuel.

21 Then the Kohathites also set out, carrying the Sanctuary. The tabernacle was carried, all the while, until they arrived at the place for setting it up.

22 The sons of Ephraim also moved their camp by their companies, and the leader of their army was Elishama the son of Ammihud.

23 And in the tribe of the sons of Manasseh, the leader was Gamaliel the son of Pedahzur.

24 And in the tribe of Benjamin, the leader was Abidan the son of Gideoni.

25 The last of all the camp to set out were the sons of Dan by their companies, and the leader of their army was Ahiezer the son of Ammishaddai.

26 And in the tribe of the sons of Asher, the leader was Pagiel the son of Ochran.

27 And in the tribe of the sons of Naphtali, the leader was Ahira the son of Enan.

28 These were the camps and departures of the sons of Israel by their companies, when they went forth.

29 And Moses said to Hobab the son of Raguel the Midianite, his kinsman: "We are setting out to the place which the Lord will give to us. Come with us, so that we may do good to you. For the Lord has promised good things to Israel."

30 And he answered him, "I will not go with you, but I will return to my own land, in which I was born."

31 And he said: "Do not choose to leave us. For you know in which places in the desert we ought to make camp, and so you shall be our guide.

32 And if you come with us, whatever will be best among the riches which the Lord will deliver to us, we will give to you."

33 Therefore, they set out from the Mountain of the Lord on a journey of three days. And the ark of the covenant of the Lord preceded them, for three days, in order to provide a place for the camp.

34 Likewise, the cloud of the Lord was over them, throughout the day, while they proceeded.

35 And when the ark was lifted up, Moses said, "Rise up, O Lord, and let your enemies be scattered, and let those who hate you flee from your face."

36 And when it was set down, he said: "Return, O Lord, to the multitude of the army of Israel."

Numbers 11

1 Meanwhile, there arose a murmur among the people against the Lord, as if they were grief-stricken because of their labors. And when the Lord had heard it, he was angry. And when the fire of the Lord was enflamed against them, it devoured those who were at the extreme end of the camp.

2 And when the people had cried out to Moses, Moses prayed to the Lord, and the fire was consumed.

3 And he called the name of that place, 'The Burning,' because the fire of the Lord had burned against them.

4 So then, the mix of common people, who had ascended with them, were enflamed with desire, and sitting and weeping, with the sons of Israel joining them, they said, "Who will give us flesh to eat?

5 We remember the fish that we ate freely in Egypt; we call to mind the cucumbers, and melons, and leeks, and onions, and garlic.

6 Our life is dry; our eyes look out to see nothing but manna."

7 Now the manna was like coriander seed, but with the color of bdellium.

8 And the people wandered about, gathering it, and they crushed it with a millstone, or ground it with a mortar; then they boiled it in a pot, and made biscuits out of it, with a taste like bread made with oil.

9 And when the dew descended in the night over the camp, the manna descended together with it.

10 And so, Moses heard the people weeping by their families, each one at the door of his tent. And the fury of the Lord was greatly enflamed. And to Moses also the matter seemed intolerable.

11 And so he said to the Lord: "Why have you afflicted your servant? Why do I not find favor before you? And why have you imposed the weight of this entire people upon me?

12 Could I have conceived this entire multitude, or have given birth to them, so that you might say to me: Carry them in your bosom, as a nursemaid usually carries a little infant, and bring them into the land, about which you have sworn to their fathers?

13 From where would I obtain the flesh to give to so great a multitude? They weep against me, saying, 'Give us flesh, so that we may eat.'

14 I alone am unable to sustain this entire people, because it is too heavy for me.

15 But if it seems to you otherwise, I beg you to put me to death, and so may I find grace in your eyes, lest I be afflicted with such evils."

16 And the Lord said to Moses: "Gather to me seventy men from the elders of Israel, whom you know to be elders, as well as teachers, of the people. And you shall lead them to the door of the tabernacle of the covenant, and you shall cause them to stand there with you,

17 so that I may descend and speak to you. And I will take from your spirit, and I will deliver it to them, so that, with you, they may sustain the burden of the people, and so that you will not be weighed down alone.

18 You shall also say to the people: Be sanctified. Tomorrow you will eat flesh. For I have heard you say: 'Who will give us flesh to eat? It was well with us in Egypt.' So then, may the Lord give you flesh. And you will eat,

19 not for one day, nor for two, nor for five, nor for ten, nor even for twenty,

20 but for up to a month of days, until it exits from your nostrils, and until it turns into nausea for you, because you have slipped away from the Lord, who is in your midst, and because you have wept before him, saying: 'Why did we go forth out of Egypt?' "

21 And Moses said: "There are six hundred thousand footmen of this people, and yet you say, 'I will give them flesh to eat for a whole month.'

22 Could a multitude of sheep and oxen be slain, so that there would be enough food? Or will the fishes of the sea be gathered together, in order to satisfy them?"

23 And the Lord answered him: "Can the hand of the Lord be ineffective? Soon now, you shall see whether my word will be fulfilled in this work."

24 And so, Moses went and explained the words of the Lord to the people. Gathering together seventy men from the elders of Israel, he caused them to stand around the tabernacle.

25 And the Lord descended in a cloud, and he spoke to him, taking from the Spirit which was in Moses, and giving to the seventy men. And when the Spirit had rested in them, they prophesied; nor did they cease afterwards.

26 Now there had remained in the camp two of the men, of whom one was called Eldad, and the other Medad, upon whom the Spirit rested; for they also had been enrolled, but they did not go forth to the tabernacle.

27 And when they were prophesying in the camp, a boy ran and reported to Moses, saying: "Eldad and Medad prophesy in the camp."

28 Promptly, Joshua the son of Nun, the minister of Moses and chosen from many, said: "My lord Moses, prohibit them."

29 But he said, "Why are you jealous on my behalf? Who decides that any of the people may prophesy and that God may give to them his Spirit?"

30 And Moses returned, with those greater by birth of Israel, into the camp.

31 Then a wind, going out from the Lord and moving forcefully across the sea, brought quails and cast them into the camp, across a distance of one day's journey, in every part of the camp all around, and they flew in the air two cubits high above the ground.

32 Therefore, the people, rising up, gathered quails all that day and night, and the next day; he who did least well gathered ten homers. And they dried them throughout the camp.

33 The flesh was still between their teeth, neither had this kind of food ceased, and behold, the fury of the Lord was provoked against the people, and he struck them with an exceedingly great scourge.

34 And that place was called, 'The Graves of Lust.' For there, they buried the people who had desired. Then, departing from the Graves of Lust, they arrived in Hazeroth, and they stayed there.

Numbers 12

1 And Miriam and Aaron spoke against Moses, because of his wife, an Ethiopian,

2 and they said: "Has the Lord spoken only through Moses? Has he not also spoken similarly to us?" And when the Lord had heard this,

3 (for Moses was a man exceedingly meek, beyond all the men who were living upon the earth)

4 immediately he spoke to him, and to Aaron and Miriam, "Go out, you three only, to the tabernacle of the covenant." And when they had gone out,

5 the Lord descended in a column of cloud, and he stood at the entrance of the tabernacle, calling to Aaron and Miriam. And when they had advanced,

6 he said to them: "Listen to my words. If there will be among you a prophet of the Lord, I will appear to him in a vision, or I will speak to him through a dream.

7 But it is not so with my servant Moses, who is the most faithful in all my house.

8 For I speak with him mouth to mouth, and plainly. And not through enigmas and figures does he perceive the Lord. Therefore, why were you not afraid to disparage my servant Moses?"

9 And being angry against them, he went away.

10 Likewise, the cloud which was over the tabernacle withdrew. And behold, Miriam appeared to be white with a leprosy, like snow. And when Aaron had looked upon her, and he had seen the spreading of the leprosy,

11 he said to Moses: "I beg you, my lord, not to impose upon us this sin, which we have committed foolishly.

12 Do not let this one be like one who is dead, or like an abortion that has been cast from the womb of her mother. Behold, half of her flesh is already consumed by leprosy."

13 And Moses cried out to the Lord, saying, "O God, I beg you: heal her."

14 And the Lord answered him: "If her father had spit on her face, should she not have been filled with shame for at least seven days? Let her be separated, outside the camp, for seven days, and after that, she will be called back."

15 And so Miriam was excluded from the camp for seven days. And the people did not move from that place, until Miriam was called back.

Numbers 13

1 And the people set out from Hazeroth, and they pitched their tents in the desert of Paran.

2 And there, the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

3 "Send men, who may examine the land of Canaan, which I will give to the sons of Israel, one from the rulers of each tribe."

4 Moses did what the Lord had commanded, sending, from the desert of Paran, leading men, whose names are these:

5 from the tribe of Ruben, Shammua the son of Zaccur;

6 from the tribe of Simeon, Shaphat the son of Hori;

7 from the tribe of Judah, Caleb the son of Jephunneh;

8 from the tribe of Issachar, Igal the son of Joseph;

9 from the tribe of Ephraim, Hosea the son of Nun;

10 from the tribe of Benjamin, Palti the son of Raphu;

11 from the tribe of Zebulon, Gaddiel the son of Sodi;

12 from the tribe of Joseph, of the scepter of Manasseh, Gaddi the son of Susi;

13 from the tribe of Dan, Ammiel the son of Gemalli;

14 from the tribe of Asher, Sethur the son of Michael;

15 from the tribe of Naphtali, Nahbi the son of Vophsi;

16 from the tribe of Gad, Guel the son of Machi.

17 These are the names of the men, whom Moses sent to examine the land. And he called Hosea, the son of Nun, Joshua.

18 And so, Moses sent them to examine the land of Canaan, and he said to them: "Ascend by the south side. And when you arrive at the mountains,

19 consider the land, as to what kind it may be, and the people, who are its inhabitants, whether they may be strong or weak, whether they may be few in number or many,

20 and the land itself, whether it is good or bad, what kind of cities, walled or without walls,

21 the soil, rich or barren, forested or without trees. Be strong, and bring us some of the fruits of the land." Now it was the time when the first ripe grapes were ready to be eaten.

22 And when they had ascended, they explored the land from the desert of Sin, all the way to Rehob, as one enters into Hamath.

23 And they ascended by the south side. And they arrived at Hebron, where there were Ahiman and Shishai and Talmai, the sons of Anak. For Hebron was founded seven years before Tanis, the city of Egypt.

24 And continuing on as far as the Torrent of the Cluster of Grapes, they cut off a vine with its grapes, which two men carried on a board. Likewise, they took from the pomegranates and the figs of that place,

25 which was called Nehel Eshcol, that is, the Torrent of the Cluster of Grapes, because the sons of Israel had carried a cluster of grapes from there.

26 And those exploring the land returned after forty days, having circulated through the entire region.

27 And they went to Moses and Aaron, and to the entire assembly of the sons of Israel in the desert of Paran, which is in Kadesh. And speaking to them, and to the entire multitude, they showed them the fruits of the land.

28 And they explained, saying: "We went into the land, to which you sent us, which, it is true, flows with milk and honey, as one can know by these fruits.

29 But it has very strong occupants, and the cities are great and also walled. We saw the race of Anak there.

30 Amalek lives in the south. The Hethite, and the Jebusite, and the Amorite live in the mountains. And truly, the Canaanite stays near the sea and around the streams of the Jordan."

31 During these events, Caleb, to restrain the murmuring of the people who rose up against Moses, said, "Let us ascend and possess the land, for we will be able to obtain it."

32 Yet truly, the others, who had been with him, were saying, "By no means are we able to ascend to this people, because they are stronger than we are."

33 And before the sons of Israel they disparaged the land, which they had inspected, saying: "The land, which we viewed, devours its inhabitants. The people, upon whom we gazed, were of lofty stature.

34 There, we saw some monsters among the sons of Anak, of the race of giants; by comparison with them, we seemed like locusts."

Numbers 14

1 And so, crying out, the entire crowd wept throughout that night.

2 And all the sons of Israel were murmuring against Moses and Aaron, saying:

3 "If only we had died in Egypt," and, "If only we would perish in this vast wilderness," and, "May the Lord not lead us into this land, lest we fall by the sword, and our wives, as well as our children, be led away as captives. Is it not better to return to Egypt?"

4 And they said to one another, "Let us appoint our leader, and so return to Egypt."

5 And when Moses and Aaron heard this, they fell prone on the ground in the sight of the multitude of the sons of Israel.

6 Yet truly, Joshua the son of Nun, and Caleb the son of Jephunneh, who themselves had also viewed the land, tore their garments,

7 and they said to the entire multitude of the sons of Israel: "The land that we circled through is very good.

8 If the Lord will be gracious to us, he will lead us into it, and he will give us the land flowing with milk and honey.

9 Do not choose to be rebellious against the Lord. And do not fear the people of this land, for, like bread, so are we able to devour them. All protection has withdrawn from them. The Lord is with us. Do not be afraid."

10 And when the entire multitude cried out, and they wanted to crush them with stones, the glory of the Lord appeared, over the roof of the covenant, to all the sons of Israel.

11 And the Lord said to Moses: "How long will this people disparage me? How long will they refuse to believe me, despite all the signs that I have wrought before them?

12 Therefore, I will strike them with a pestilence, and so I will consume them. But you I will make the ruler over a great nation, and one which is mightier than this one."

13 And Moses said to the Lord: "But then the Egyptians, from whose midst you led out this people,

14 and the inhabitants of this land, who have heard that you, O Lord, are among this people, and that you are seen face to face, and that your cloud protects them, and that you go before them with a column of cloud by day, and a column of fire by night,

15 may hear that you have killed so great a multitude, as if they were one man, and they may say:

16 'He was not able to lead the people into the land about which he had sworn. Therefore, he slew them in the wilderness.'

17 Therefore, may the strength of the Lord be magnified, just as you swore, saying:

18 'The Lord is patient and full of mercy, taking away iniquity and wickedness, and forsaking no one who is harmless. He visits the sins of the fathers upon the sons, to the third and fourth generation.'

19 Forgive, I beg you, the sins of this people, according to the greatness of your mercy, just as you have been gracious to them in their journey from Egypt to this place."

20 And the Lord said: "I have forgiven them according to your word.

21 Also, as I live, the entire world shall be filled with the glory of the Lord.

22 And yet, all the men who have seen my majesty, and the signs that I have wrought in Egypt and in the wilderness, and who have tested me ten times already, and yet have not obeyed my voice,

23 these shall not see the land, about which I swore to their fathers, neither shall any of those who detracted me gaze upon it.

24 My servant Caleb, who, being full of another spirit, has followed me, I will lead into this land, through which he has wandered, and his offspring shall possess it.

25 For the Amalekites and the Canaanites live in the valleys. Tomorrow, move the camp and return into the wilderness, by the way of the Red Sea."

26 And the Lord spoke to Moses and Aaron, saying:

27 "How long will this very wicked multitude murmur against me? I have heard the complaints of the sons of Israel.

28 Therefore, say to them: As I live, says the Lord, as you spoke in my hearing, so will I do to you.

29 In the wilderness, here shall your carcasses lie. All you who were numbered from twenty years and above, and who have murmured against me,

30 you shall not enter into the land, over which I lifted up my hand to cause you to live there, except Caleb the son of Jephunneh, and Joshua the son of Nun.

31 But your little ones, about whom you said that they would be a prey to the enemies, I will lead them in, so that they may see the land that has displeased you.

32 Your carcasses shall lie in the wilderness.

33 Your sons shall wander in the desert for forty years, and they shall bear your fornication, until the carcasses of their fathers are consumed in the desert.

34 According to the number of the forty days, during which you examined the land, one year shall be charged for each day. And so, for forty years you shall take back your iniquities, and you shall know my retribution.

35 For just as I have spoken, so shall I do, to this entire most wicked multitude, which has risen up together against me. In the wilderness, here shall it fade away and die."

36 Therefore, all the men, whom Moses had sent to contemplate the land, and who, having returned, had caused the entire multitude to murmur against him, disparaging the land as if it were evil,

37 suffered death and were struck down in the sight of the Lord.

38 But only Joshua the son of Nun, and Caleb the son of Jephunneh remained alive, out of all those who had journeyed to examine the land.

39 And Moses spoke all these words to all the sons of Israel, and the people mourned exceedingly.

40 And behold, rising up at first light, they climbed to the top of the mountain, and they said, "We are prepared to ascend to the place, about which the Lord has spoken, for we have sinned."

41 And Moses said to them: "Why do you transgress the word of the Lord, merely because it will not result in prosperity for you?

42 Do not ascend, for the Lord is not with you, lest you be overthrown before your enemies.

43 The Amalekite and the Canaanite are before you, by whose sword you shall be ruined, for you were not willing to consent to the Lord, and so the Lord is not with you."

44 But they, having been darkened, ascended to the top of the mountain. But the ark of the testament of the Lord, and Moses, did not withdraw from the camp.

45 And the Amalekites descended, along with those Canaanites who were living in the mountains. And so, striking and cutting them down, they pursued them all the way to Hormah.

Numbers 15

1 The Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

2 "Speak to the sons of Israel, and you shall say to them: When you will have entered into the land of your habitation, which I will give you,

3 and you make an offering to the Lord, as a holocaust or as a victim, paying your vows, or as a voluntary offering of gifts, or in your solemnities, burning a sweet odor to the Lord, whether from the oxen or from the sheep:

4 whoever immolates the victim shall offer a sacrifice of fine wheat flour, the tenth part of an ephah, sprinkled with oil, which shall have the measure of the fourth part of a hin,

5 and he shall give the same measure of wine, poured out as libations, whether as a holocaust or as a victim.

6 With each lamb and each ram, there shall be a sacrifice of fine wheat flour, of two tenths, which shall be sprinkled with one third part of a hin of oil.

7 And he shall offer the same measure, one third part of wine, for the libation, as a sweet odor to the Lord.

8 Yet truly, when you will offer, from the oxen, a holocaust or a victim, in order to fulfill your vow or for peace-offering victims,

9 you shall give, for each ox, three tenths of fine wheat flour, sprinkled with oil, which has the measure of one half of one hin,

10 and the wine, poured out as libations, shall be of the same measure, as an oblation of most sweet odor to the Lord.

11 So shall you do

12 for each ox, and ram, and lamb, and young goat.

13 Both natives and sojourners

14 shall offer sacrifices by the same rituals.

15 There shall be one precept and one judgment, as much for yourselves as for newcomers to the land."

16 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

17 "Speak to the sons of Israel, and you shall say to them:

18 When you will arrive in the land which I will give to you,

19 and when you will eat from the bread of that region, you shall separate the first-fruits to the Lord

20 from the foods that you eat. Just as you separate the first-fruits of your threshing floors,

21 so also shall you give the first-fruits of your cooked grains to the Lord.

22 And if, through ignorance, you neglect any of these things, which the Lord has spoken to Moses,

23 and which he has commanded through him for you, from the day that he began to command and thereafter,

24 and if the multitude will have forgotten to do it, then they shall offer a calf from the herd, a holocaust as a most sweet odor to the Lord, and its sacrifice and libations, just as the ceremonies ask, and a he-goat for sin.

25 And the priest shall pray for the entire multitude of the sons of Israel, and it shall be forgiven them, because they did not sin willfully. Nevertheless, they shall offer incense to the Lord for themselves, and for sin, as well as for their error.

26 And it shall be forgiven all the people of the sons of Israel, as well as the newcomers who sojourn among them, for it is the culpability of all the people through neglect.

27 But if one soul will have sinned by not knowing, he shall offer a one-year-old she-goat for his sin.

28 And the priest shall pray for him, because he sinned unknowingly before the Lord. And he shall obtain pardon for him, and it will be forgiven him.

29 One law shall be for all who sin by ignorance, as much for natives as for newcomers.

30 Yet truly, the soul who commits any of these acts through arrogance, whether he is a citizen or a sojourner, because he has rebelled against the Lord, shall perish from among his people.

31 For he has despised the word of the Lord, and he has nullified his precept. For this reason, he shall be destroyed, and he shall bear his iniquity."

32 And it happened that, when the sons of Israel were in the wilderness, and they had found a man collecting wood on the day of the Sabbath,

33 they brought him to Moses and Aaron, and to the whole multitude.

34 And they enclosed him in a prison, not knowing what they should do with him.

35 And the Lord said to Moses, "Let that man be put to death; let the entire crowd crush him with stones, outside the camp."

36 And when they had led him out, they overwhelmed him with stones, and he died, just as the Lord had instructed.

37 The Lord also said to Moses:

38 "Speak to the sons of Israel, and you shall tell them to make for themselves hems at the corners of their cloaks, placing in them ribbons of hyacinth,

39 so that, when they see these, they may remember all the commandments of the Lord, and they may not follow their own thoughts and eyes, fornicating in various ways,

40 but instead, they, being more mindful of the precepts of the Lord, may do them and may be holy to their God.

41 I am the Lord your God, who led you away from the land of Egypt, so that I may be your God."

Numbers 16

1 Then, behold, Korah the son of Izhar, the son of Kohath, the son of Levi, with Dathan and Abiram, the sons of Eliab, and also On the son of Peleth, of the sons of Ruben,

2 rose up against Moses, with two hundred fifty others of the sons of Israel, leading men of the assembly, and who, at the time of a council, would be called by name.

3 And when they had stood against Moses and Aaron, they said: "Let it be sufficient for you that the entire multitude is of holy ones, and that the Lord is among them. Why do you elevate yourselves above the people of the Lord?"

4 When Moses had heard this, he fell prone on his face.

5 And speaking to Korah, and to the entire multitude, he said: "In the morning, the Lord will cause it to be known who belongs to him, and which holy ones he will join to himself. And whomever he will choose, they shall be close to him.

6 Therefore, do this: Each one of you, Korah and all your associates, take your censer,

7 and drawing fire into it tomorrow, place incense upon it before the Lord. And whomever he will choose, the same shall be holy. You sons of Levi have been raised up greatly."

8 And he said again to Korah: "Listen, sons of Levi.

9 Is it a small thing to you, that the God of Israel has separated you from all the people, and has joined you to himself, so that you would serve him in the rituals of the tabernacle, and stand before gatherings of the people, and minister to him?

10 Was the reason that he caused you and all your brothers, the sons of Levi, to approach him, so that you would even claim for yourselves the priesthood too,

11 and so that your entire group would stand against the Lord? For what is Aaron that you should murmur against him?"

12 Therefore, Moses sent to call for Dathan and Abiram, the sons of Eliab, who responded: "We will not come.

13 Is it a small matter to you, that you have led us away from a land that was flowing with milk and honey, so as to kill us in the desert, unless you could also be a ruler over us?

14 You have led us, it is true, to a land that flows with streams of milk and honey, and you have given us possession of fields and vineyards. But will you also tear out our eyes? We will not come."

15 And Moses, being very angry, said to the Lord: "Do not look with favor on their sacrifices. You know that I have not accepted from them, at any time, so much as a young donkey, nor have I afflicted any of them."

16 And he said to Korah: "You and your congregation, stand alone before the Lord, and apart from Aaron, tomorrow.

17 Let each one of you take censers, and place incense in them, offering to the Lord two hundred fifty censers. Let Aaron also hold his censer."

18 When they had done this, Moses and Aaron stood up,

19 and, having crowded the entire multitude close to them at the door of the tabernacle, the glory of the Lord appeared to them all.

20 And the Lord, speaking to Moses and Aaron, said:

21 "Separate yourselves from the midst of this congregation, so that I may suddenly destroy them."

22 But they fell prone on their faces, and they said, "O most strong One, the God of the spirits of all flesh, should your anger rage against all, for the sin of one?"

23 And the Lord said to Moses:

24 "Instruct the entire people to separate from the tents of Korah, and Dathan, and Abiram."

25 And Moses rose up and went to Dathan and Abiram. And the elders of Israel followed him,

26 and he said to the crowd, "Withdraw from the tabernacles of these impious men, and touch nothing which pertains to them, lest you become involved in their sins."

27 And when they had withdrawn from their tents all around, Dathan and Abiram came out and stood at the entrance of their pavilions, with their wives and children, and with all their associates.

28 And Moses said: "By this shall you know that the Lord has sent me to do all that you discern, and that I have not brought these things out of my own heart:

29 If these men pass away by the common death of men, or if they will be visited by a scourge, of a kind by which others are often visited, then the Lord did not send me.

30 But if the Lord accomplishes something new, so that the earth opens its mouth and swallows them whole, along with everything that belongs to them, and they descend alive into the underworld, then you shall know that they have blasphemed the Lord."

31 Therefore, as soon as he had ceased to speak, the earth broke open under their feet.

32 And opening its mouth, it devoured them with their tabernacles and their entire substance.

33 And they descended alive, the ground closing around them, into the underworld, and they perished from the midst of the mulititude.

34 Yet truly, all of Israel, which was standing all around, took flight at the clamor of those who were perishing, saying, "Lest perhaps the earth may swallow us whole also."

35 Then, too, a fire, going forth from the Lord, put to death the two hundred fifty men who were offering the incense.

36 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

37 "Instruct Eleazar, the son of Aaron the priest, to take up the censers which lie in the burning, and to scatter the fire to one side and another, because they were sanctified

38 in the deaths of these sinners. And let him form them into plates, and affix them to the altar, because incense had been offered in them to the Lord, and they were sanctified, and so that the sons of Israel may discern in them a sign and a memorial."

39 Therefore, Eleazar the priest took the bronze censers, by which those whom the burning devoured had made an offering, and he formed them into plates, affixing them to the altar,

40 so that the sons of Israel would have, thereafter, something to admonish them, lest any stranger, or anyone who is not of the offspring of Aaron, might approach to offer incense to the Lord, and lest he endure what happened to Korah, and to all his congregation, when the Lord spoke to Moses.

41 Then, the following day, the entire multitude of the sons of Israel murmured against Moses and Aaron, saying: "You have put to death the people of the Lord."

42 And when there arose a sedition, and the tumult increased,

43 Moses and Aaron fled to the tabernacle of the covenant. But after they had entered it, the cloud covered it, and the glory of the Lord appeared.

44 And the Lord said to Moses:

45 "Withdraw from the midst of this multitude, and I will destroy them immediately." And while they were lying on the ground,

46 Moses said to Aaron: "Take the censer, and draw fire into it from the altar; place incense upon it, and continue on, quickly, to the people, to pray for them. For already wrath has gone forth from the Lord, and the scourge rages."

47 When Aaron had done this, and he ran into the midst of the multitude, which the burning fire was now destroying, and he offered the incense.

48 And standing between the dead and the living, he prayed for the people, and the scourge ceased.

49 But the number of those who were struck down was fourteen thousand men, and seven hundred, aside from those who had perished in the sedition of Korah.

50 And Aaron returned to Moses at the door of the tabernacle of the covenant, after the destruction quieted.

Numbers 17

1 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

2 "Speak to the sons of Israel, and receive from each of them a rod by their kinships, from all the leaders of the tribes, twelve rods, and write the name of each one on his rod.

3 But the name of Aaron shall be for the tribe of Levi, and one rod separately shall contain all their families.

4 And you shall place these in the tabernacle of the covenant before the testimony, where I will speak to you.

5 Whomever of these I will choose, his rod will germinate, and so shall I restrain the complaints of the sons of Israel before me, by which they murmur against you."

6 And Moses spoke to the sons of Israel. And all the leaders gave him rods, one for each tribe. And there were twelve rods, aside from the rod of Aaron.

7 And when Moses had placed these before the Lord, in the tabernacle of the testimony,

8 returning on the following day, he found that the rod of Aaron for the house of Levi, had germinated, and that the swelling buds had opened into flowers, which, spreading their petals, were formed into those of an almond tree.

9 Therefore, Moses brought out all the rods, from the sight of the Lord, to all the sons of Israel. And they saw, and each one received their rods.

10 And the Lord said to Moses: "Carry back the rod of Aaron into the tabernacle of the testimony, so that it may be kept there as a sign of the rebellion of the sons of Israel, and so that their complaints may be quieted before me, lest they die."

11 And Moses did just as the Lord had instructed.

12 Then the sons of Israel said to Moses: "Behold, we have been consumed; we have been ruined.

13 Whoever approaches to the tabernacle of the Lord dies. Will we all be wiped away, even to total annihilation?"

Numbers 18

1 And the Lord said to Aaron: "You, and your sons, and the house of your father with you, shall carry the iniquity of the Sanctuary. And you and your sons together shall bear the sins of your priesthood.

2 But take to yourselves also your brothers from the tribe of Levi, and the scepter of your father, and may they be prepared, and may they minister to you. Then you and your sons shall minister in the tabernacle of the testimony.

3 And the Levites shall stand watch by your precepts, and for all the works of the tabernacle; yet in such a manner that they shall not approach the vessels of the Sanctuary and of the altar, lest both they die, and you perish, at the same time.

4 But they may be with you, and they may watch over the care of the tabernacle and all its ceremonies. A foreigner shall not be mixed with you.

5 Watch over the care of the Sanctuary, and over the ministry of the altar, lest an indignation may rise over the sons of Israel.

6 I have given your brothers, the Levites, to you from the midst of the sons of Israel, and I have delivered them as a gift to the Lord, in order to serve in the ministries of his tabernacle.

7 But as for you and your sons: guard the priesthood. For all that pertains to the service of the altar and of what is beyond the veil shall be exercised by the priests. If any outsider will approach, he shall be killed."

8 And the Lord said to Aaron: "Behold, I have given you custody of my first-fruits. Everything that is sanctified by the sons of Israel I have delivered to you and your sons, for the office of the priesthood, by everlasting ordinances.

9 Therefore, you shall receive these, from the things that are sanctified and offered to the Lord. Every offering, and sacrifice, and whatever is repaid to me, on behalf of sin and also for offenses, and which becomes the Holy of holies, shall be for you and for your sons.

10 You shall eat it in the Sanctuary. Only the males shall eat from it, because it has been consecrated for you.

11 But the first-fruits, which the sons of Israel shall vow and offer, I have given to you, and to your sons, as well as to your daughters, by a perpetual right. Whoever is clean in your house shall eat them.

12 All the innermost of the oil, and of the wine, and of the grain, whatever first-fruits they offer to the Lord, I have given to you.

13 All the first of the crops, which the soil produces and which are carried to the Lord, shall fall to your use. Whoever is clean in your house shall eat them.

14 All that the sons of Israel shall repay by vow shall be yours.

15 Whatever goes out first from the womb, of all flesh, which they offer to the Lord, whether from men or from cattle, shall be your right; yet only in so far as, for the firstborn of man, you shall accept a price. And every animal that is unclean you shall cause to be redeemed.

16 And its redemption shall be, after one month, five shekels of silver, by the weight of the Sanctuary. A shekel has twenty obols.

17 But the firstborn of a cow, or of a sheep, or of a goat, you shall not cause to be redeemed, because they have been sanctified to the Lord. Thus, their blood you shall pour out upon the altar, and their fat you shall burn as a most sweet odor to the Lord.

18 Yet truly, the flesh shall fall to your use, just as the consecrated breast and the right shoulder shall be yours.

19 All the first-fruits of the Sanctuary, which the sons of Israel offer to the Lord, I have given to you and to your sons as well as to your daughters, as a perpetual right. It is an everlasting covenant of salt before the Lord, for you and for your sons."

20 And the Lord said to Aaron: "In their land, you shall possess nothing; neither shall you have a portion among them. I am your portion and your inheritance in the midst of the sons of Israel.

21 But I have given, to the sons of Levi, all the tithes of Israel as a possession, for the ministry by which they serve me in the tabernacle of the covenant,

22 so that the sons of Israel may no longer approach to the tabernacle, nor commit deadly sin.

23 Only the sons of Levi may serve me in the tabernacle and may carry the sins of the people. It shall be an everlasting ordinance in your generations. They shall possess nothing else;

24 being content with the oblation of tithes, which I have separated for their uses and necessities."

25 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

26 "Instruct the Levites, and also declare to them: When you will receive, from the sons of Israel, the tithes, which I have given to you, offer their first-fruits to the Lord, that is, the tenth part of a tenth,

27 so that it may be accounted to you as an oblation of the first-fruits, as much from the threshing floors as from the oil and wine presses.

28 And offer the first-fruits of everything, from which you receive tithes, to the Lord, and give them to Aaron the priest.

29 Everything which you shall offer from the tithes, and which you shall separate as gifts to the Lord, shall be the finest and most select.

30 And you shall say to them: 'If you offer the noble and the better of the tithes, it shall be accounted to you as if you had given from the first-fruits of the threshing floor and of the oil and wine presses.'

31 And you shall eat these in all your places, both you and your families, because it is your price for the ministry, by which you serve in the tabernacle of the testimony.

32 And you shall not sin in this way: by reserving the excellent and fat things for yourselves, lest you pollute the oblations of the sons of Israel, and lest you die."

Numbers 19

1 And the Lord spoke to Moses and Aaron, saying:

2 "This is the ritual that the Lord has appointed for a victim. Instruct the sons of Israel, so that they may bring to you a red cow of full maturity, in which there is no blemish, and which has not carried a yoke.

3 And you shall deliver it to Eleazar the priest, who, having led it out beyond the camp, shall immolate it in the sight of all.

4 And dipping his finger in its blood, he shall sprinkle it seven times, opposite the door of the tabernacle.

5 And he shall burn it, while all are watching, delivering into the flame, not only its skin and flesh, but also the blood and dung.

6 Likewise, cedar wood, and hyssop, and twice-dyed scarlet he shall cast into the flame, by which the cow is consumed.

7 And then finally, having washed his garments and his body, he shall enter into the camp, and he shall be deeply stained until evening.

8 Then he also who had burned it shall wash his garments and his body, and he shall be unclean until evening.

9 Then a clean man shall gather the ashes of the cow, and he shall pour them out beyond the camp, in a very pure place, so that they may be preserved for the multitude of the sons of Israel, and for the water of aspersion, because the cow was burned for sin.

10 And when he who had carried the ashes of the cow will have washed his garments, he shall be unclean until evening. The sons of Israel, and the newcomers who live among them, shall have this as a holy and perpetual right.

11 Whoever touches the corpse of a man, and is, because of this, unclean for seven days,

12 shall be sprinkled from this water on the third and seventh days, and so shall he be cleansed. But if he was not sprinkled on the third day, he is not able to be cleansed on the seventh.

13 Anyone who will have touched the dead body of a human life, and who has not been sprinkled with this mixture, pollutes the tabernacle of the Lord, and he shall perish out of Israel. For not having been sprinkled with the water of expiation, he shall be unclean, and his filth shall remain upon him.

14 This is the law of a man who dies in a tent. All who enter into his tent, and all the vessels which are there, shall be polluted for seven days.

15 The vessel that has no cover or binding over it shall be unclean.

16 If anyone in the field will have touched the corpse of a man, who was killed or who died on his own, or his bone, or his grave, he shall be unclean for seven days.

17 And they shall take some of the ashes from the burning and the sin offering, and they shall pour living waters over them into a vessel.

18 And into it a man who is clean shall dip hyssop, and he shall sprinkle from it the entire tent, and all its articles, and the men who were polluted by means of contact.

19 And so, in this manner, what is clean shall purify what is unclean, on the third and seventh days. And have been expiated on the seventh day, he shall wash both himself and his garments, and he shall be unclean until evening.

20 If anyone has not been expiated by this ritual, his soul shall perish from the midst of the Church. For he has polluted the Sanctuary of the Lord, and he has not been sprinkled with purifying waters.

21 This precept shall be an everlasting ordinance. Likewise, the one who has sprinkled the waters shall wash his garments. All who will have touched the waters of expiation shall be unclean until evening.

22 Whatever has been touched by something unclean will itself be made unclean. And the soul who touches any of these things shall become unclean until evening."

Numbers 20

1 And the sons of Israel, and the entire multitude, went into the desert of Sin, in the first month. And the people stayed at Kadesh. And Miriam died there, and she was buried in the same place.

2 And when the people were in need of water, they came together against Moses and Aaron.

3 And as it turned into sedition, they said: "If only we had perished among our brothers in the sight of the Lord.

4 Why have you led away the Church of the Lord, into the wilderness, so that both we and our cattle would die?

5 Why did you cause us to ascend from Egypt, and why have you led us into this most wretched place, which is not able to be sown, which does not produce figs, or vines, or pomegranates, and which, moreover, does not even have water to drink?"

6 And Moses and Aaron, dismissing the multitude, entered the tabernacle of the covenant, and they fell prone on the ground, and they cried out to the Lord, and they said: "O Lord God, listen to the outcry of this people, and open for them, from your storehouse, a fountain of living water, so that, being satisfied, their murmuring may cease." And the glory of the Lord appeared over them.

7 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

8 "Take the rod, and gather the people, you and your brother Aaron, and speak to the rock before them, and it shall bestow waters. And when you have brought forth water from the rock, the entire multitude and their cattle shall drink."

9 Therefore, Moses took the rod, which was in the sight of the Lord, just as he had instructed him.

10 And having gathered the multitude before the rock, he said to them: "Listen, you who are rebellious and unbelieving. Would we be able to cast out water from this rock?"

11 And when Moses had lifted up his hand, striking the stone twice with the rod, very great waters went forth, so much so that the people and their cattle were able to drink.

12 And the Lord said to Moses and Aaron, "Because you did not believe me, so as to sanctify me before the sons of Israel, you shall not lead this people into the land, which I will give to them."

13 This is the Water of Contradiction, where the sons of Israel were quarreling against the Lord, and he was sanctified in them.

14 Meanwhile, Moses sent messengers from Kadesh to the king of Edom. They said: "Your brother Israel says this: You know of all the hardships which have overtaken us,

15 how our fathers descended into Egypt, and we lived there for a long time, and the Egyptians afflicted both us and our fathers,

16 and how we cried out to the Lord, and he heeded us and sent an Angel, who led us away from Egypt. Behold, we are situated in the city of Kadesh, which is at the extremity of your borders.

17 And we beg you to permit us to cross through your land. We will not go through the fields, nor through the vineyards; we will not drink the waters of your wells, but we will travel by the public ways, neither turning aside to the right, nor to the left, until we have passed your borders."

18 Edom responded to them: "You shall not cross through me, otherwise, I will meet you armed."

19 And the sons of Israel said: "We will travel by the well-trodden path. And if we or our cattle drink from your waters, we will give you what is just. There shall be no difficulty in the price, only let us cross through quickly."

20 But he answered, "You shall not cross." And immediately he went out to meet them with a countless multitude and a strong hand;

21 neither was he willing to agree to their petition to concede passage through his borders. For this reason, Israel diverted away from him.

22 And when they had moved the camp from Kadesh, they arrived at mount Hor, which is at the borders of the land of Edom,

23 where the Lord spoke to Moses:

24 "Let Aaron," he said, "go to his people. For he shall not enter into the land which I have given to the sons of Israel, because he did not believe my mouth at the Waters of Contradiction.

25 Take Aaron, and his son with him, and lead them on to mount Hor.

26 And when you have stripped the father of his vestments, you shall put them on Eleazar, his son. Aaron shall be gathered and shall die there."

27 Moses did just as the Lord had instructed. And they ascended mount Hor, in the sight of the entire multitude.

28 And when he had despoiled Aaron of his vestments, he clothed his son Eleazar with them.

29 And when Aaron had died at the top of the mountain, Moses came down with Eleazar.

30 And the entire multitude, seeing that Aaron lay dead, wept over him for thirty days, throughout all their families.

Numbers 21

1 And when king Arad the Canaanite, who was living toward the south, had heard this, namely, that Israel had arrived by the way of spies, he fought against them. And proving to be the victor, he led away prey from them.

2 But Israel, obliging himself by a vow to the Lord, said: "If you deliver this people into my hand, I will wipe away their cities."

3 And the Lord heard the prayers of Israel, and he delivered the Canaanite, who they put to death, overthrowing his cities. And they called the name of that place Hormah, that is, Anathema.

4 Then they set out from mount Hor, by the way that leads to the Red Sea, to circle around the land of Edom. And the people began to tire of their journey and hardships.

5 And speaking against God and Moses, they said: "Why did you lead us away from Egypt, so as to die in the wilderness? Bread is lacking; there are no waters. Our soul is now nauseous over this very light food."

6 For this reason, the Lord sent fiery serpents among the people, which wounded or killed many of them.

7 And so they went to Moses, and they said: "We have sinned, because we have spoken against the Lord and against you. Pray, so that he may take away these serpents from us." And Moses prayed for the people.

8 And the Lord said to him: "Make a bronze serpent, and place it as a sign. Whoever, having been struck, gazes upon it, shall live."

9 Therefore, Moses made a bronze serpent, and he placed it as a sign. When those who had been struck gazed upon it, they were healed.

10 And the sons of Israel, setting out, made camp at Oboth.

11 Having departed from there, they pitched their tents at Iye-abarim, in the wilderness, which looks out toward Moab, opposite the eastern region.

12 And moving from there, they arrived at the Torrent of Zared.

13 Having left that place behind, they then made camp opposite Arnon, which is in the desert, and which juts out at the borders of the Amorite. For certainly Arnon is at the limit of Moab, dividing the Moabites and the Amorites.

14 About this place, it is said in the book of the wars of the Lord: "As he did at the Red Sea, so will he do at the Torrents of Arnon."

15 The stones of the torrents were bent, so that they might rest in Ar and lie back within the borders of the Moabites.

16 Beyond that place appeared a well, about which the Lord said to Moses: "Gather the people together, and I will give them water."

17 Then Israel sang this verse: "Let the well rise up." They sang:

18 "The well, the leaders dug it, and the commanders of the multitude prepared it, at the direction of the lawgiver, and with their staffs."

19 They went from the wilderness to Mattanah, from Mattanah to Nahaliel, from Nahaliel to Bamoth,

20 from Bamoth, a valley in the region of Moab, to the top of Pisgah, which looks out opposite the desert.

21 Then Israel sent messengers to Sihon, the king of the Amorites, saying:

22 "I beg you to permit me to cross through your land. We will not turn aside into the fields or the vineyards. We will not drink waters from the wells. We will travel by the royal way, until we have passed your borders."

23 And he was not willing to allow Israel to cross through his borders. But instead, gathering an army, he went out to meet them in the desert, and he arrived at Jahaz and fought against them.

24 And he was struck down by them with the edge of the sword, and they possessed his land from Arnon, even to Jabbok and the sons of Ammon. For the borders of the Ammonites were held by a strong fortress.

25 Therefore, Israel took all his cities and lived in the cities of the Amorite, namely, in Heshbon and its villages.

26 Heshbon was the city of Sihon, the king of the Amorites, who fought against the king of Moab. And he took all the land, which had been under his sovereignty, as far as Arnon.

27 About this, it is said in the proverb: "Enter into Heshbon. Let the city of Sihon be established and built.

28 A fire has gone forth from Heshbon, a flame from the town of Sihon, and it has devoured Ar of the Moabites, and the inhabitants of the heights of Arnon.

29 Woe to you, Moab! You are perishing, O people of Chemosh. He gave flight to his sons, and he gave the daughters into captivity, to the king of the Amorites, Sihon.

30 Their yoke has been scattered from Heshbon even to Dibon. They have passed through, wearily, into Nophah, and as far as Medeba."

31 And so Israel lived in the land of the Amorite.

32 And Moses sent some to explore Jazer. These captured its villages and possessed its inhabitants.

33 And they turned themselves and ascended, along the way of Bashan. And Og, the king of Bashan, met them with all his people, to fight at Edrei.

34 And the Lord said to Moses: "Do not be afraid of him. For I have delivered him, and all his people, as well as his land, into your hand. And you shall do to him just as you did to Sihon, the king of the Amorites, the inhabitant of Heshbon."

35 Therefore, they struck him down also, with his sons, and all his people, even to utter destruction, and they possessed his land.

Numbers 22

1 And they set out and made camp in the plains of Moab, across the Jordan, where Jericho is situated.

2 Then Balak, the son of Zippor, seeing all that Israel had done to the Amorite,

3 and that the Moabites had great fear of him, and that they were not able to bear his assault,

4 said to those greater by birth of Midian: "So will this people wipe away all those who are dwelling within our borders, in the same way that the ox is accustomed to tear out grass, all the way to the roots." At that time, he was king of Moab.

5 Therefore, he sent messengers to Balaam, the son of Beor, a seer who lived above the river of the land of the sons of Ammon, to call him, and to say: "Behold, a people has gone forth from Egypt, which has covered the face of the earth. They are encamped opposite me.

6 Therefore, come and curse this people, for they are stronger than I am. If only, in some way, I might be able to strike them and to drive them from my land. For I know that he whom you bless shall be blessed, and he whom you curse shall be cursed."

7 And the elders of Moab, and those greater by birth of Midian, continued on, holding the price of divination in their hands. And when they had come to Balaam, and had explained to him all the words of Balak,

8 he responded, "Remain for this night, and I will answer with whatever the Lord will say to me." And while they stayed with Balaam, God came and said to him,

9 "What do these men want with you?"

10 He responded, "Balak, the son of Zippor, the king of the Moabites has sent to me,

11 saying: 'Behold, a people, which has gone forth from Egypt, has covered the face of the earth. Come and curse them, so that, in some way, I may be able to fight them and drive them away.' "

12 And God said to Balaam, "Do not go with them, and do not curse the people, for they are blessed."

13 And he, rising up in the morning, said to the leaders, "Go into your own land, for the Lord has prohibited me from going with you."

14 Returning, the leaders said to Balak, "Balaam was not willing to come with us."

15 Again, he sent many more persons, and these were more noble than those he had sent before.

16 And when these had come to Balaam, they said: "So says Balak, the son of Zippor. Do not hesitate to come to me.

17 For I am ready to honor you, and whatever you would want, I shall give to you. Come and curse this people."

18 Balaam responded: "Even if Balak were to give to me his own house, filled with silver and gold, I still would not be able to change the word of the Lord my God, neither to say more, nor to say less.

19 I beg you to remain for this night also, so that I may know what the Lord will answer me again."

20 Therefore, God came to Balaam in the night, and said to him: "If these men have arrived to call you, then rise up and go with them; yet only in so far as you shall do what I will command you."

21 Balaam rose up in the morning, and saddling his donkey, he set out with them.

22 And God was angry. And an Angel of the Lord stood in the way opposite Balaam, who was sitting on the donkey, and he had two servants with him.

23 The donkey, discerning that the Angel was standing in the way with a drawn sword, turned herself from the road and went through a field. And when Balaam beat her and intended to return her to the path,

24 the Angel stood in a narrow place between the two walls, with which the vineyards were enclosed.

25 And the donkey, seeing this, drew herself close to the wall and scraped the foot of the rider. So he beat her again.

26 And, nevertheless, the Angel passing on to a narrow place, where one would not be able to deviate either to the right or to the left, stood to meet him.

27 And when the donkey had seen the Angel standing there, she fell under the feet of the rider, who, being angry, struck her sides more vehemently with a club.

28 And the Lord opened the mouth of the donkey, and she said: "What have I done to you? Why do strike you me, behold now, for the third time?"

29 Balaam responded, "Because you have deserved it, and you have mistreated me. If only I had a sword, so that I might pierce you."

30 The donkey said: "Am not I your animal, on which you have always been accustomed to sit, even until this present day? Tell me, when did I ever do the same thing to you." But he said, "Never."

31 Immediately, the Lord opened the eyes of Balaam, and he saw the Angel standing in the way with a drawn sword, and he reverenced him prone on the ground.

32 And the Angel said to him: "Why did you beat your donkey three times? I have come to be an adversary to you, because your way is perverse and contrary to me.

33 And unless the donkey had turned aside from the way, allowing a place for my opposition, I would have killed you, and she would have lived."

34 Balaam said: "I have sinned, not knowing that you stood against me. And now, if it displeases you for me to continue on, I will return."

35 The Angel said, "Go with them, but be careful not to speak anything other than what I shall instruct you." And so, he went with the leaders.

36 And when Balak had heard it, he went out to meet him in a town of the Moabites, which is situated at the furthest borders of Arnon.

37 And he said to Balaam: "I sent messengers to call you. Why did you not come to me immediately? Was it because I am not able to pay the cost for your arrival?"

38 He answered him: "Behold, here I am. Am I able to speak anything other than what God will put into my mouth?"

39 Therefore, they continued on together, and they arrived at a city, which was at the furthest borders of his kingdom.

40 And after Balak had killed oxen and sheep, he sent the gifts to Balaam, and to the leaders who were with him.

41 Then, when morning arrived, he led him to the heights of Baal, and he gazed upon the most distant portions of the population.

Numbers 23

1 And Balaam said to Balak, "Build seven altars here for me, and prepare as many calves, and the same number of rams."

2 And when he had acted according to the words of Balaam, they placed a calf and a ram together on each altar.

3 And Balaam said to Balak: "Stand for a little while next to your holocaust, until I go, to see if perhaps the Lord will meet with me. And whatever he will command, I shall speak to you."

4 And after he had quickly departed, God met with him. And Balaam, speaking to him, said: "I have set up seven altars, and I have placed a calf and a ram on each."

5 Then the Lord placed the word in his mouth, and he said: "Return to Balak, and you shall say this."

6 Returning, he found Balak standing next to his holocaust, with all the leaders of the Moabites.

7 And taking up his parable, he said: "Balak, king of the Moabites, has led me from Aram, from the mountains of the east. 'Come forth,' he said, 'and curse Jacob. Hurry and condemn Israel.'

8 How shall I curse him, whom God has not cursed? For what reason would I condemn him, whom the Lord does not condemn?

9 I will look upon him from the tops of the stones, and I will consider him from the hills. This people shall dwell alone, and they shall not be counted among the nations.

10 Who can number the dust that is Jacob, and who can know the number of the stock of Israel? May my soul die a just death, and may my end be like theirs."

11 And Balak said to Balaam: "What is this that you are doing? I called for you, in order to curse my enemies, and to the contrary, you bless them."

12 He answered him, "How can I say anything other than what the Lord orders?"

13 Therefore, Balak said: "Come with me to another place, from where you may see a portion of Israel, though you cannot see them all. Curse them from there."

14 And when he had led him to a lofty place, on the top of mount Pisgah, Balaam built seven altars, and placing upon each a calf and a ram,

15 he said to Balak, "Stand here next to your holocaust, while I continue on to meet him."

16 And when the Lord had met him, and had put the word in his mouth, he said, "Return to Balak, and you shall say this to him."

17 Returning, he found him standing next to his holocaust, and the leaders of the Moabites were with him. And Balak said to him, "What has the Lord spoken?"

18 But, taking up his parable, he said: "Stand, Balak, and pay attention. Listen, you son of Zippor.

19 God is not like a man, so that he would lie, nor is he like a son of man, so that he would be changed. Therefore, having spoken, will he not act? Has he ever spoken, and not fulfilled?

20 I was led here to bless, and I have no strength to hinder the blessing.

21 There is no idol in Jacob; neither is there a false image to be seen in Israel. The Lord his God is with him, and the resound of royal victory is in him.

22 God has led him away from Egypt; his strength is like that of the rhinoceros.

23 There is no soothsaying in Jacob, nor any divination in Israel. In their times, it shall be told to Jacob and to Israel what God has wrought.

24 Behold, the people will rise up like a lioness, and lie down like a lion. But they will not lie down until they devour the prey and drink the blood of the slain."

25 And Balak said to Balaam, "Neither curse him, nor bless him."

26 And he said, "Have I not told you that whatever God would command of me, I would do?"

27 And Balak said to him: "Come and I will lead you to another place. If perhaps it may please God, then you may curse them from there."

28 And when he had led him on to the top of mount Peor, which looks out toward the wilderness,

29 Balaam said to him, "Build seven altars here for me, and prepare as many calves, and the same number of rams."

30 Balak did as Balaam had said, and he placed on each altar a calf and a ram.

Numbers 24

1 And when Balaam had seen that it was pleasing to the Lord that he should bless Israel, he by no means went out as he had gone before, to seek divination. But directing his face opposite the desert,

2 and lifting up his eyes, he saw Israel dwelling in tents by their tribes. And with the Spirit of God rushing into him,

3 taking up his parable, he said: "Balaam, the son of Beor, the man whose eye has been obstructed,

4 the hearer of the sermon of God, he who has gazed upon a vision of the Almighty, he who falls down and so his eyes are opened, has declared:

5 'How beautiful are your tabernacles, O Jacob, and your tents, O Israel!

6 They are like forested valleys, like gardens irrigated next to rivers, like tabernacles which the Lord has fixed, like cedars close to waters.

7 Water shall flow from his jar, and his offspring shall be amid many waters, because Agag, his king, shall be taken, and his kingdom shall be removed.

8 Away from Egypt, God has led him, whose strength is like the rhinoceros. They shall devour the nations that are his enemies, and break their bones, and pierce them with arrows.

9 Lying down, he has slept like a lion, and like a lioness, whom no one would dare to awaken. He who blesses you, shall himself also be blessed. He who curses you, shall be considered cursed."

10 And Balak, being angry against Balaam, clapped his hands together and said: "I called you to curse my enemies, and, to the contrary, you have blessed them three times.

11 Return to your place. I had decided, indeed, to honor you greatly, but the Lord has deprived you of the designated honor."

12 Balaam responded to Balak: "Did I not say to your messengers, whom you sent to me:

13 Even if Balak would give me his house, filled with silver and gold, I still could not go away from the word of the Lord my God, so as to offer anything, either good or evil, from my own heart; but whatever the Lord will speak, this, too, I shall speak.

14 Yet truly, as I continue on to my own people, I will give you counsel as to what this people shall do to your people in the end times."

15 Therefore, taking up his parable, he again spoke: "Balaam the son of Beor, the man whose eye has been obstructed,

16 the hearer of the sermon of God, he who knows the doctrine of the Most High, and who sees the visions of the Almighty, who, falling down, has his eyes opened, has declared:

17 I shall see him, but not presently. I shall gaze upon him, but not soon. A star shall rise out of Jacob, and a rod shall spring up from Israel. And he shall strike down the commanders of Moab, and he shall devastate all the sons of Seth.

18 And he shall possess Idumea; the inheritance of Seir shall fall to their enemies. Yet truly, Israel shall act with strength.

19 From Jacob will be he who shall be ruler. And he shall perish the remnants of the city."

20 And when he saw Amalek, taking up his parable, he said: "Amalek, first among the Gentiles, whose very end shall be perdition."

21 Likewise, he saw the Kainites, and taking up his parable, he said: "Robust, indeed, is your habitation. But though you will set your nest in a rock,

22 and you will be elect among the stock of Kain, how long will you be able to remain? For Assur shall take you captive."

23 And taking up his parable once more he said: "Alas! Who will be able to survive, when God will do these things?

24 They shall arrive in Greek warships from Italy. They shall overcome the Assyrians, and they shall devastate the Hebrews, and yet, at the very end, even they themselves shall perish."

25 And Balaam rose up, and he returned to his place. Likewise, Balak went back, along the way by which he had arrived.

Numbers 25

1 Now Israel, at that time, dwelt in Shittim, and the people were fornicating with the daughters of Moab,

2 who called them to their sacrifices. And they ate, and they adored their gods.

3 And Israel was initiated into Baal of Peor. And so the Lord, being angry,

4 said to Moses, "Take all the leaders of the people, and hang them on gallows against the sun, so that my fury may be averted from Israel."

5 And Moses said to the judges of Israel, "Let each one kill his neighbors, who have been initiated into Baal of Peor."

6 And behold, one of the sons of Israel entered, in the sight of his brothers, to a prostitute of Midian, within view of Moses and of all the crowd of the sons of Israel, who were weeping before the door of the tabernacle.

7 And when Phinehas the son of Eleazar, the son of Aaron the priest, had seen it, he rose up from the midst of the multitude, and, seizing a dagger,

8 he entered after the Israelite man, into the brothel, and he pierced both of them at the same time, specifically, the man and the woman at the location of their genitals. And the scourge ceased from among the sons of Israel.

9 And there were slain twenty-four thousand men.

10 And the Lord said to Moses:

11 "Phinehas the son of Eleazar, the son of Aaron the priest, has averted my wrath from the sons of Israel. For he was moved against them by my zeal, so that I myself, in my zeal, might not wipe away the sons of Israel.

12 Because of this, say to him: Behold, I give to him the peace of my covenant.

13 And the covenant of the everlasting priesthood shall be as much for him as for his offspring. For he was zealous on behalf of his God, and he has made expiation for the wickedness of the sons of Israel."

14 Now the name of the Israelite man, who was killed with the Midianite woman, was Zimri the son of Salu, a leader from the kinship and tribe of Simeon.

15 Moreover, the Midianite woman, who was put to death together with him, was called Cozbi the daughter of Zur, a most noble leader among the Midianites.

16 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

17 "Let the Midianites perceive you as enemies, and strike them down,

18 for they, too, have behaved with hostility against you, and they have deceived you insidiously by means of the idol Peor, and by Cozbi, the daughter of a commander of Midian, their sister, who was struck down in the day of the scourge because of the sacrilege of Peor."

Numbers 26

1 After the blood of the guilty was shed, the Lord said to Moses, and to Eleazar the son of Aaron the priest:

2 "Number the entire sum of the sons of Israel, from twenty years and above, by their houses and kinships, all who are able to go forth to war."

3 And so, Moses and Eleazar the priest, who were in the plains of Moab, above the Jordan, opposite Jericho, spoke to those who were

4 from twenty years and above, just as the Lord had commanded. And this is their number:

5 Ruben, the firstborn of Israel; his son, Hanoch, from whom is the family of the Hanochites; and Pallu, from whom is the family of the Palluites;

6 and Hezron, from whom is the family of the Hezronites; and Carmi, from whom is the family of the Carmites.

7 These are the families of the stock of Ruben, whose number was found to be forty-three thousand and seven hundred thirty.

8 The son of Phallu: Eliab;

9 his sons, Nemuel and Dathan and Abiram. These are Dathan and Abiram, the leaders of the people, who rose up against Moses and Aaron in the sedition at Korah, when they rebelled against the Lord.

10 And the earth, opening its mouth, devoured Korah, with many others dying, when the fire burned two hundred fifty men. And a great miracle was wrought,

11 so that, when Korah perished, his sons did not perish.

12 The sons of Simeon, by their kinships: Nemuel, from him is the family of the Nemuelites; Jamin, from him is the family of the Jaminites; Jachin, from him is the family of the Jachinites;

13 Sohar, from him is the family of the Soharites; Shaul, from him is the family of the Shaulites.

14 These are the families of the stock of Simeon, whose entire number was twenty-two thousand two hundred.

15 The sons of Gad, by their kinships: Zephon, from him is the family of the Zephonites; Haggi, from him is the family of the Haggites; Shuni, from him is the family of the Shunites;

16 Ozni, from him is the family of the Oznites; Eri, from him is the family of the Erites;

17 Arod, from him is the family of the Arodites; Areli, from him is the family of the Arelites.

18 These are the families of Gad, whose entire number was forty thousand five hundred.

19 The sons of Judah: Er and Onan, who both died in the land of Canaan.

20 And these were the sons of Judah, by their kinships: Shelah, from whom is the family of the Shelahites; Perez, from whom is the family of the Perezites; Zerah, from whom is the family of the Zerahites.

21 Moreover, the sons of Phares were: Hezron, from whom is the family of the Hezronites; and Hamul, from whom is the family of the Hamulites.

22 These are the families of Judah, whose entire number was seventy-six thousand five hundred.

23 The sons of Issachar, by their kinships: Tola from whom is the family of the Tolaites; Puvah, from whom is the family of the Puvahites;

24 Jashub, from whom is the family of the Jashubites; Shimron, from whom is the family of the Shimronites.

25 These are the kinships of Issachar, whose number was sixty-four thousand three hundred.

26 The sons of Zebulon by their kinships: Sered, from whom is the family of the Seredites; Elon, from whom is the family of the Elonites; Jahleel, from whom is the family of the Jahleelites.

27 These are the kinships of Zebulun, whose number was sixty thousand five hundred.

28 The sons of Joseph by their kinships: Manasseh and Ephraim.

29 From Manasseh was born Machir, from whom is the family of the Machirites. Machir conceived Gilead, from whom is the family of the Gileadites.

30 Gilead had sons: Jezer, from whom is the family of the Jezerites; and Helek, from whom is the family of the Helekites;

31 and Asriel, from whom is the family of the Asrielites; and Shechem, from whom is the family of the Shechemites;

32 and Shemida, from whom is the family of the Shemidaites; and Hepher, from whom is the family of the Hepherites.

33 Now Hepher was the father of Zelophehad, who had no sons, but only daughters, whose names are these: Mahlah, and Noa, and Hoglah, and Milcah, and Tirzah.

34 These are the families of Manasseh, and their number was fifty-two thousand seven hundred.

35 Now the sons of Ephraim by their kinships were these: Shuthelah, from whom is the family of the Shuthelahites; Becher, from whom is the family of the Becherites; Tahan, from whom is the family of the Tahanites.

36 Furthermore, the son of Shuthelah was Eran, from whom is the family of the Eranites.

37 These are the kinships of the sons of Ephraim, whose number was thirty-two thousand five hundred.

38 These are the sons of Joseph by their families: the sons of Benjamin in their kinships: Bela, from whom is the family of the Belaites; Ashbel, from whom is the family of the Ashbelites; Ahiram, from whom is the family of the Ahiramites;

39 Shupham, from whom is the family of the Shuphamites; Hupham, from whom is the family of the Huphamites.

40 The sons of Bela: Arad and Naaman. From Arad, the family of the Aradites; from Naaman, the family of the Naamanites.

41 These are the sons of Benjamin by their kinships, whose number was forty-five thousand six hundred.

42 The sons of Dan by their kinships: Shuham, from whom is the family of the Shuhamites. These are the kinships of Dan by their families.

43 All these were Shuhamites, whose number was sixty-four thousand four hundred.

44 The sons of Asher by their kinships: Imnah, from whom is the family of the Imnahites; Ishvi, from whom is the family of the Ishvites; Beriah, from whom is the family of the Beriahites.

45 The sons of Beriah: Heber, from whom is the family of the Heberites; and Malchiel, from whom is the family of the Malchielites.

46 Now the name of the daughter of Asher was Serah.

47 These are the kinships of the sons of Asher, and their number was fifty-three thousand four hundred.

48 The sons of Naphtali by their kinships: Jahzeel, from whom is the family of the Jahzeelites; Guni, from whom is the family of the Gunites;

49 Jezer, from whom is the family of the Jezerites; Shillem, from whom is the family of the Shillemites.

50 These are the kinships of the sons of Naphtali by their families, whose number was forty-five thousand four hundred.

51 This is the sum of the sons of Israel, who were counted: six hundred thousand and one thousand seven hundred thirty.

52 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

53 "The land shall be divided to these, as their possessions, according to the number of their names.

54 To the greater number you shall give a greater portion, and to the lesser number, a lesser portion. To each one, just as they have now been counted, a possession shall be delivered.

55 Yet only in so far as the land is divided by lot to a tribe and to families.

56 Whatever the lot will happen to be, it shall be accepted, either by the greater, or by the lesser.

57 Likewise, this is the number of the sons of Levi by their families: Gershon, from whom is the family of the Gershonites; Kohath, from whom is the family of the Kohathites; Merari, from whom is the family of the Merarites.

58 These are the families of Levi: The family of Libni, the family of Hebroni, the family of Mahli, the family of Mushi, the family of Korah. Yet truly, Kohath conceived Amram,

59 who had a wife, Jochebed, the daughter of Levi, who was born to him in Egypt. She bore, to her husband Amram: sons, Aaron and Moses, as well as their sister, Miriam.

60 From Aaron were born Nadab and Abihu, and Eleazar and Ithamar.

61 Of these, Nadab and Abihu died, when they had offered strange fire before the Lord.

62 And these were all who were numbered: twenty-three thousand of the male gender, from one month and above. For they were not counted among the sons of Israel, neither was a possession given to them with the others.

63 This is the number of the sons of Israel, who were enrolled by Moses and by Eleazar the priest, in the plains of Moab, above the Jordan, opposite Jericho.

64 Among these, not one of them was numbered before, by Moses and Aaron in the desert of Sinai.

65 For the Lord had foretold that all would die in the wilderness. And not one of them remained, except Caleb the son of Jephunneh, and Joshua the son of Nun.

Numbers 27

1 Then there approached the daughters of Zelophehad, the son of Hepher, the son of Gilead, the son of Machir, the son of Manasseh, who was the son of Joseph: and their names are Mahlah, and Noa, and Hoglah, and Milcah, and Tirzah.

2 And they stood before Moses and Eleazar the priest, and all the leaders of the people, at the door of the tabernacle of the covenant, and they said:

3 "Our father died in the desert, and was not with the sedition, which was stirred up against the Lord under Korah, but he died in his own sin; he had no male sons. Why is his name taken away from his family, because he had no son? Give us a possession among the kinsmen of our father."

4 And Moses referred their case to the judgment of the Lord.

5 And the Lord said to him:

6 "The daughters of Zelophehad are asking for something just. So give them a possession among the kinsmen of their father, and let them succeed him in his inheritance.

7 And to the sons of Israel, you shall speak these things:

8 When a man dies without a son, his inheritance shall be transferred to his daughter.

9 If he has no daughter, his brothers shall succeed him.

10 But if there were also no brothers, you shall give the inheritance to the brothers of his father.

11 But if he has no paternal uncles, the inheritance shall be given to those who are closest to him. And this shall be, for the sons of Israel, consecrated as a perpetual law, just as the Lord has instructed Moses."

12 The Lord also said to Moses: "Ascend onto this mountain, Abarim, and contemplate from there the land, which I will give to the sons of Israel.

13 And when you have seen it, you shall then go to your people, just as your brother Aaron went.

14 For you offended me in the desert of Sin at the Contradiction of the multitude; neither were you willing to sanctify me in their sight over the waters. These are the Waters of Contradiction at Kadesh in the desert of Sin."

15 Moses answered him:

16 "May the Lord, the God of the spirits of all flesh, provide a man, who may be over this multitude,

17 and who may be able to exit and enter before them, and who may lead them out or lead them in: lest the people of the Lord be like sheep without a shepherd."

18 And the Lord said to him: "Take Joshua, the son of Nun, a man in whom the Spirit is, and place your hand upon him.

19 And he shall stand before Eleazar the priest and the entire multitude.

20 And you shall give him the precepts in the sight of all, and a portion of your glory, so that the entire congregation of the sons of Israel may listen to him.

21 On his behalf, if anything is to be done, Eleazar the priest shall consult the Lord. He, and all the sons of Israel with him, and the rest of the multitude, shall go out and enter in at his word."

22 Moses did just as the Lord had instructed. And when he had brought Joshua, he set him before Eleazar the priest, and before the entire gathering of the people.

23 And imposing his hands upon his head, he repeated all that the Lord had commanded.

Numbers 28

1 The Lord also said to Moses:

2 "Instruct the sons of Israel, and you shall say to them: Offer my oblation and bread, and the incense of most sweet odor, at their proper times.

3 These are the sacrifices which you must offer: Two immaculate one-year-old lambs each day as a perpetual holocaust.

4 You shall offer one in morning, and the other in the evening,

5 and the tenth part of an ephah of fine wheat flour, which has been sprinkled with the purest oil, and which has the measure of the fourth part of a hin.

6 It is the continual holocaust which you offered at mount Sinai as a most sweet odor of incense to the Lord.

7 And you shall offer a libation of wine, of the fourth part of a hin for each lamb, in the Sanctuary of the Lord.

8 And you shall offer the other lamb similarly, in the evening, according to all the rites of the morning sacrifice and its libations, as an oblation of most sweet odor to the Lord.

9 Then, on the Sabbath day, you shall offer two immaculate one-year-old lambs, and two tenths of fine wheat flour sprinkled with oil, as sacrifice, as well as the libations

10 that are usually poured out on each Sabbath as a perpetual holocaust.

11 Then, on the first day of the month, you shall offer a holocaust to the Lord: two calves from the herd, one ram, seven immaculate one-year-old lambs,

12 and three tenths of fine wheat flour sprinkled with oil, as sacrifice, for each calf, and two tenths of fine wheat flour sprinkled with oil, for each ram,

13 and one tenth of fine wheat flour with oil, as a sacrifice, for each lamb. It is a holocaust of most sweet odor and also an incense to the Lord.

14 Now these shall be the libations of wine, which are to be poured out for each victim: one half portion of a hin for each calf, one third for a ram, and one fourth for a lamb. This shall be the holocaust for all the months, as they succeed one another in the turning of the year.

15 Likewise, a he-goat shall be offered to the Lord for sin, with the perpetual holocaust and its libations.

16 Then, in the first month, the fourteenth day of the month shall be the Passover of the Lord.

17 And the fifteenth day shall be a solemnity. For seven days, they shall eat unleavened bread.

18 And the first day of these days shall be venerable and holy; you shall not do any servile work in it.

19 And you shall offer the incense of a holocaust to the Lord, two calves from the herd, one ram, seven immaculate one-year-old lambs;

20 and with each sacrifice, from fine wheat flour which has been sprinkled with oil, three tenths for each calf, and two tenths for each ram,

21 and one tenth for each lamb, that is, for the seven lambs;

22 and one he-goat for sin, as an expiation for you,

23 aside from the morning holocaust, which you shall always offer.

24 You shall do this on each day of the seven days, as fuel for the fire, and as a most sweet odor to the Lord, which shall rise up from the holocaust and from each of the libations.

25 Likewise, the seventh day shall be very honored and holy for you. Any servile work, you shall not do in it.

26 And also the day of the first-fruits, after the weeks have been fulfilled, when you shall offer new fruits to the Lord, shall be venerable and holy. You shall not do any servile work in it.

27 And you shall offer a holocaust as a most sweet odor to the Lord: two calves from the herd, one ram, and seven immaculate one-year-old lambs,

28 and also, as their sacrifices, fine wheat flour sprinkled with oil, three tenths for each calf, two for each ram,

29 one tenth for each lamb, which all together are seven lambs; likewise, a he-goat,

30 which is slain for expiation, aside from the perpetual holocaust and its libations.

31 You shall offer only what is immaculate, with their libations."

Numbers 29

1 "Now the first day of the seventh month also shall be venerable and holy to you. In it, you shall not do any servile work, because it is the day of the sounding of the trumpets.

2 And you shall offer a holocaust, as a most sweet odor to the Lord: one calf from the herd, one ram, and seven immaculate one-year-old lambs;

3 and, as their sacrifices, fine wheat flour sprinkled with oil: three tenths for each calf, two tenths for a ram,

4 one tenth for a lamb, which all together are seven lambs;

5 and a he-goat for sin, which is offered as an expiation for the people,

6 aside from the holocaust of the first day of the month with its sacrifices, and the perpetual holocaust with the usual libations. By these same ceremonies, you shall offer incense as a most sweet odor to the Lord.

7 Likewise, the tenth day of this seventh month shall be for you holy and venerable, and you shall afflict your souls. You shall do no servile work in it.

8 And you shall offer a holocaust to the Lord, as a most sweet odor: one calf from the herd, one ram, seven immaculate one-year-old lambs;

9 and for their sacrifices, fine wheat flour sprinkled with oil: three tenths for each calf, two tenths for a ram,

10 one tenth for each lamb, which are all together seven lambs;

11 and a he-goat for sin, apart from those things which are usually offered for offenses as an expiation, and as a perpetual holocaust, with their sacrifice and libations.

12 Yet truly, on the fifteenth day of the seventh month, which shall be for you holy and venerable, you shall not do any servile work in it, but you shall celebrate a solemnity to the Lord for seven days.

13 And you shall offer a holocaust, as a most sweet odor to the Lord: thirteen calves from the herd, two rams, fourteen immaculate one-year-old lambs;

14 and as their libations, fine wheat flour sprinkled with oil: three tenths for each calf, which is all together thirteen calves, and two tenths for each ram, that is, all together two rams,

15 and one tenth for each lamb, which is all together fourteen lambs;

16 and a he-goat for sin, apart from the perpetual holocaust, and the sacrifice and its libation.

17 On the next day, you shall offer twelve calves from the herd, two rams, and fourteen immaculate one-year-old lambs.

18 And the sacrifices and libations for each of the calves and the rams and the lambs, you shall celebrate according to the rite,

19 with a he-goat for sin, apart from the perpetual holocaust, and the sacrifice and its libation.

20 On the third day, you shall offer eleven calves, two rams, and fourteen immaculate one-year-old lambs.

21 And the sacrifices and libations for each of the calves and the rams and the lambs, you shall celebrate according to the rite,

22 with a he-goat for sin, apart from the perpetual holocaust, and the sacrifice and its libation.

23 On the fourth day, you shall offer ten calves, two rams, and fourteen immaculate one-year-old lambs.

24 And the sacrifices and the libations for each of the calves and the rams and the lambs, you shall celebrate according to the rite,

25 with a he-goat for sin, apart from the perpetual holocaust, and its sacrifice and libation.

26 On the fifth day, you shall offer nine calves, two rams, and fourteen immaculate one-year-old lambs.

27 And the sacrifices and libations for each of the calves and the rams and the lambs, you shall celebrate according to the rite,

28 with a he-goat for sin, apart from the perpetual holocaust, and its sacrifice and libation.

29 On the sixth day, you shall offer eight calves, two rams, and fourteen immaculate one-year-old lambs.

30 And the sacrifices and libations for each of the calves and the rams and the lambs, you shall celebrate according to the rite,

31 with a he-goat for sin, apart from the perpetual holocaust, and its sacrifice and libation.

32 On the seventh day, you shall offer seven calves, and two rams, and fourteen immaculate one-year-old lambs.

33 And the sacrifices and libations for each of the calves and the rams and the lambs, you shall celebrate according to the rite,

34 with a he-goat for sin, apart from the perpetual holocaust, and its sacrifice and libation.

35 On the eighth day, which is most honored, you shall not do any servile work,

36 offering a holocaust as a most sweet odor to the Lord: one calf, one ram, and seven immaculate one-year-old lambs.

37 And the sacrifices and libations for each of the calves and the rams and the lambs, you shall celebrate according to the rite,

38 with a he-goat for sin, apart from the perpetual holocaust, and its sacrifice and libation.

39 These things you shall offer to the Lord in your solemnities, aside from the vowed and voluntary oblations, as a holocaust, as a sacrifice, as a libation, or as peace-offering victims."

Numbers 30

1 And Moses explained to the sons of Israel all that the Lord had commanded him.

2 And he said to the leaders of the tribes of the sons of Israel: "This is the word, which the Lord has instructed:

3 If any man makes a vow to the Lord, or binds himself by an oath, he shall not make his word null and void, but all that he has promised, he shall fulfill.

4 If a woman, who is in her father's house, vows anything, or binds herself by an oath, and she is still in a state of childhood, if her father knew of the vow which she has promised or of the oath by which she has obligated her soul, and he kept silent, she shall be liable to the vow:

5 whatever she has promised or swore, she shall complete in deed.

6 But if her father, as soon as he had heard it, had contradicted it, both her vows and her oaths shall be nullified, neither shall she be held liable to the promise, because her father had contradicted it.

7 If she has a husband, and she has vowed anything, then, once the word has gone out of her mouth, she will have obligated her soul by an oath.

8 On the day that her husband will hear of it, and yet not contradict it, she shall be liable to the vow, and she shall repay whatever she has promised.

9 But if, as soon as he hears it, he contradicts it, then he will have caused her promises, and the words by which she had bound her soul, to be null and void. The Lord will be favorable to her.

10 Widows and divorced women shall repay whatever they have vowed.

11 If a wife in the house of her husband has bound herself by a vow or an oath,

12 if her husband heard it and remained silent, and he did not contradict the promise, she shall repay what she had promised.

13 But if he promptly contradicts it, she shall not be held liable to the promise. For her husband has contradicted it. And the Lord will be favorable to her.

14 If she has vowed or bound herself by oath, in order to afflict her soul by fasting, or by abstaining from other things, it shall be for the arbitration of her husband, as to whether or not she may do it.

15 But if the husband, upon hearing it, remains silent, and he delays judgment until another day, whatever she had vowed or promised, she shall repay, because when he first heard it, he remained silent.

16 And if he contradicted it only sometime after he had known about it, he shall bear his iniquity."

17 These are the laws which the Lord has appointed to Moses, between a husband and a wife, between a father and a daughter, who is still in the state of childhood or who remains in her father's house.

Numbers 31

1 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

2 "First, avenge the sons of Israel from the Midianites, and then you shall be gathered to your people."

3 And immediately Moses said: "Arm the men among you for a battle, so that they may be able to fulfill the retribution of the Lord on the Midianites.

4 Let one thousand men be chosen from each tribe of Israel, who shall be sent to war."

5 And they gave one thousand from each tribe, that is, twelve thousand foot soldiers for battle.

6 And Moses sent them with Phinehas, the son of Eleazar the priest; also, he delivered to him the holy vessels, and the trumpets to sound.

7 And when they had fought against the Midianites and had prevailed, they killed all the men.

8 And they put to death by the sword their kings: Evi, and Rekem, and Zur, and Hur, and Reba, the five leaders of the nation, and also Balaam the son of Beor.

9 And they seized their women and little ones, and all their cattle, and all their goods; whatever they were able to have, they despoiled.

10 Both their cities and their villages, as well as their fortresses, they burned.

11 And they carried away prey from everything that they had seized, both of men and of beasts.

12 And they led these to Moses and Eleazar the priest, and to all the multitude of the sons of Israel. But the remainder of the articles they carried to the camp on the plains of Moab, next to the Jordan, opposite Jericho.

13 Then Moses, and Eleazar the priest, and all the leaders of the assembly went out to meet them beyond the camp.

14 And Moses, being angry with the leaders of the army, and the tribunes, and the centurions, who had arrived from the battle,

15 said: "Why have you spared the females?

16 Are not these the ones who deceived the sons of Israel at the suggestion of Balaam, and who caused you betray the Lord by the sin of Peor, because of which the people also were struck down?

17 Therefore, put to death all of them: whatever is of the male sex, even among the little ones, and cut the throats of those women who have known men by sexual relations.

18 But the young girls, and all female virgins, reserve for yourselves.

19 And remain beyond the camp for seven days. Whoever has killed a man, or who has touched one that was killed, shall be purified on the third day and on the seventh day.

20 And all of the spoils, whether it is a garment, or a vessel, or another useful thing, made from the pelts or hair of goats, or from wood, shall be expiated."

21 Likewise, Eleazar the priest spoke in this manner to the men of the army who had fought: "This is the precept of the law, which the Lord has commanded Moses:

22 Gold, and silver, and brass, and iron, and lead, and tin,

23 and all that may be able to pass through fire, shall be purified by fire. But whatever is not able to sustain fire shall be sanctified with the waters of expiation.

24 And you shall wash your garments on the seventh day, and, after having been purified, you shall enter the camp."

25 And the Lord also said to Moses:

26 "Take the sum of those things which were captured, from man even to beast, you and Eleazar the priest, and the leaders of the common people.

27 And you shall divide the prey equally, among those who went out to war and fought, and among the remainder of the multitude.

28 And you shall separate a portion for the Lord from the portion of those who fought and were in the battle: one soul out of five hundred, as much from humans, as from oxen and donkeys and sheep.

29 And you shall give it to Eleazar the priest, because these are the first-fruits of the Lord.

30 Likewise, from the half of the portion belonging to the sons of Israel, you shall receive the fiftieth head of humans, and of oxen, and donkeys, and sheep, and of all living things, and you shall give these to the Levites who stand watch over the care of the tabernacle of the Lord."

31 And Moses and Eleazar did just as the Lord had instructed.

32 Now the prey which the army had seized was six hundred seventy-five thousand sheep,

33 seventy-two thousand oxen,

34 sixty-one thousand donkeys,

35 and thirty-two thousand human lives, of the female sex, who had not known men.

36 And one half of the portion was given to those who had been in the battle: three hundred thirty-seven thousand five hundred sheep.

37 From these, for the portion of the Lord, there were accounted: six hundred seventy-five sheep;

38 and from the thirty-six thousand oxen, seventy-two oxen;

39 from the thirty thousand five hundred donkeys, sixty-one donkeys.

40 From the sixteen thousand human souls, there fell to the portion of the Lord thirty-two souls.

41 And Moses delivered the number of the first-fruits of the Lord to Eleazar the priest, just as had been commanded of him,

42 from the one half portion belonging to the sons of Israel, which he had separated from the portion of those who had been in the battle.

43 Yet truly, from the one half portion which fell to the remainder of the multitude, that is, from the three hundred thirty-seven thousand five hundred sheep,

44 and from the thirty-six thousand oxen,

45 and from the thirty thousand five hundred donkeys,

46 and from the sixteen thousand persons,

47 Moses took the fiftieth head, and gave it to the Levites who stand watch at the tabernacle of the Lord, just as the Lord had instructed.

48 And when the leaders of the army, and the tribunes, and the centurions had approached Moses, they said:

49 "We, your servants, have taken a census of the number of the fighting men, whom we had under our hand, and indeed not one was lacking.

50 For this reason, we offer as gifts to the Lord whatever gold each one was able to find amid the spoils, in anklets and arm bands, rings and bracelets, and little chains, so that you may intercede for us to the Lord."

51 And Moses and Eleazar the priest received all the gold in its various kinds,

52 weighing sixteen thousand seven hundred fifty shekels, from the tribunes and the centurions.

53 For whatever each one had taken away in the spoils was his own.

54 And having been accepted, they took it into the tabernacle of the testimony, as a memorial of the sons of Israel before the Lord.

Numbers 32

1 Now the sons of Ruben and of Gad had many herds, and their substance in cattle was inestimable. And when they had seen that the lands of Jazer and Gilead were suitable for feeding animals,

2 they went to Moses, and to Eleazar the priest and the leaders of the multitude, and they said:

3 "Ataroth, and Dibon, and Jazer, and Nimrah, Heshbon, and Elealeh, and Sebam, and Nebo, and Beon,

4 the land, which the Lord has struck in the sight of the sons of Israel, is a very fertile region for pasturing animals. And we, your servants, have very many cattle.

5 And so we beseech you, if we have found favor before you, that you give it to us, your subjects, as a possession, and that you not cause us cross the Jordan."

6 And Moses answered them: "Should your brothers go to battle, while you sit here?

7 Why do you subvert the minds of the sons of Israel, so that they might not dare to cross into the place which the Lord will give to them?

8 Did not your fathers act in the same way, when I sent them from Kadesh-Barnea to explore the land?

9 And when they had gone all the way to the Valley of the Cluster of Grapes, having viewed the entire region, they subverted the hearts of the sons of Israel, so that they would not enter into the parts that the Lord gave to them.

10 And being angry, the Lord swore an oath, saying:

11 'These men, who ascended out of Egypt, from twenty years and above, will not see the land, which I have promised under an oath to Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob. For they were not willing to follow me,

12 except Caleb, the son of Jephunneh the Kenizzite, and Joshua the son of Nun; these have fulfilled my will.'

13 And the Lord, being angry against Israel, led them in a course through the desert for forty years, until the entire generation, which had done evil in his sight, was consumed.

14 And behold," he said, "you have risen up in the place of your fathers, the offshoots and the nurslings of sinful men, in order to augment the fury of the Lord against Israel.

15 But if you are not willing to follow him, he will leave the people behind in the wilderness, and you will have been the cause of all our deaths."

16 But approaching closer, they said: "We will manufacture sheep pens and cattle stalls, as well as fortified cities, for our little ones.

17 But we ourselves will continue on, armed and girded for battle, before the sons of Israel, until we lead them to their places. Our little ones, and whatever we may be able to have, shall be in walled cities, because of the treachery of the inhabitants.

18 We will not return to our houses, even until the sons of Israel may possess their inheritance.

19 Neither will we seek anything across the Jordan, because we already have our possession on its eastern side."

20 And Moses said to them: "If you accomplish what you have promised, you may go out, equipped for battle, before the Lord.

21 And let every fighting man cross over the Jordan, until the Lord overthrows his enemies,

22 and all the land is subjected to him. Then you will be guiltless with the Lord and with Israel, and you will obtain the regions which you desire before the Lord.

23 But if you do not do what you have said, no one could doubt that you will have sinned against God. And know this: your sin shall overtake you.

24 Therefore, build cities for your little ones, and pens and stables for your sheep and cattle; and fulfill what you have promised."

25 And the sons of Gad and of Ruben said to Moses: "We are your servants, we shall do what you, our ruler, orders.

26 We will leave behind our little ones, and our wives, and the sheep and cattle, in the cities of Gilead.

27 And we, your servants, all well-equipped, will go forth to battle, just as you, our ruler, has spoken."

28 Therefore, Moses instructed Eleazar the priest, and Joshua the son of Nun, and the princes of the families throughout the tribes of Israel, and he said to them:

29 "If the sons of Gad and the sons of Ruben cross over the Jordan with you, all armed for war before the Lord, and if the land becomes subject to you, give them Gilead as a possession.

30 But if they are not willing to cross with you, armed, into the land of Canaan, then let them receive places among you for their dwellings."

31 And the sons of Gad and the sons of Ruben responded: "Just as the Lord has spoken to his servants, so shall we do.

32 We will go forth, armed, before the Lord into the land of Canaan; and we acknowledge that we have already received our possession across the Jordan."

33 And so, Moses gave to the sons of Gad and of Ruben, and to half the tribe of Manasseh, the son of Joseph, the kingdom of Sihon, king of the Amorites, and the kingdom of Og, king of Bashan, and their land with its surrounding cities.

34 Therefore, the sons of Gad built up Dibon, and Ataroth, and Aroer,

35 and Atroth and Shophan, and Jazer, and Jogbehah,

36 and Beth-Nimrah, and Beth-Haran, as fortified cities with pens for their cattle.

37 Yet truly, the sons of Ruben built up Heshbon, and Elealeh, and Kiriathaim,

38 and Nebo, and Baal-meon (their names having been changed) and Sibmah, appointing names for the cities which they had built.

39 Moreover, the sons of Machir, the son of Manasseh, continued on within Gilead, and they devastated it, putting to death its inhabitant, the Amorite.

40 Therefore, Moses gave the land of Gilead to Machir, the son of Manasseh, and he lived in it.

41 But Jair, the son of Manasseh, went out and occupied its villages, which he called Havoth Jair, that is, the Villages of Jair.

42 Likewise, Nobah went forth and captured Kenath with its villages. And he called it by his own name, Nobah.

Numbers 33

1 These are the lodging places of the sons of Israel, who departed from Egypt by their companies under the hand of Moses and Aaron,

2 which Moses wrote down according to the places of the encampments, which they changed upon the order of the Lord.

3 Thus the sons of Israel set out from Rameses in the first month, on the fifteenth day of the first month, on the day after the Passover, with an exalted hand, being seen by all the Egyptians.

4 And these were burying their firstborn, whom the Lord had struck down (for so, too, did he carry out retribution against their gods).

5 And they made camp at Soccoth.

6 And from Soccoth they went to Etham, which is at the furthest limits of the wilderness.

7 Departing from there, they arrived opposite Pi-hahiroth, which looks out toward Baal-zephon, and they were encamped before Migdol.

8 And setting out from Pi-hahiroth, they crossed through the middle of the Sea into the wilderness. And having walked for three days through the desert of Etham, they made camp at Marah.

9 And setting out from Marah, they arrived at Elim, where there were twelve fountains of water and seventy palm trees. And they set up camp there.

10 But departing from there also, they fixed their tents above the Red Sea. And setting out from the Red Sea,

11 they were encamped in the desert of Sin.

12 Departing from there, they went to Dophkah.

13 And setting out from Dophkah, they made camp at Alush.

14 And departing from Alush, they fixed their tents at Rephidim, where the people lacked water to drink.

15 And setting out from Rephidim, they camped in the desert of Sinai.

16 But departing also from the wilderness of the Sinai, they arrived at the Graves of Lust.

17 And setting out from the Graves of Lust, they were encamped at Hazeroth.

18 And from Hazeroth, they went to Rithmah.

19 And setting out from Rithmah, they made camp at Rimmon-perez.

20 And departing from there, they arrived at Libnah.

21 From Libnah, they made camp at Rissah.

22 And departing from Rissah, they went to Kehelathah.

23 Setting out from there, they were encamped at mount Shepher.

24 Departing from mount Shepher, they went to Haradah.

25 Continuing on from there, they made camp at Makheloth.

26 And setting out from Makheloth, they went to Tahath.

27 From Tahath, they made camp at Terah.

28 Departing from there, they pitched their tents at Mithkah.

29 And from Mithkah, they were encamped at Hashmonah.

30 And setting out from Hashmonah, they went to Moseroth.

31 And from Moseroth, they made camp at Bene-jaakan.

32 And setting out from Bene-jaakan, they went to mount Gidgad.

33 Setting out from there, they were encamped at Jotbathah.

34 And from Jotbathah, they went to Abronah.

35 And departing from Abronah, they made camp at Eziongeber.

36 Setting out from there, they went into the desert of Sin, which is Kadesh.

37 And departing from Kadesh, they encamped at mount Hor, at the furthermost limits of the land of Edom.

38 And Aaron the priest ascended onto mount Hor, by the order of the Lord. And there he died, in the fortieth year of the departure of the sons of Israel from Egypt, in the fifth month, on the first day of the month,

39 when he was one hundred twenty-three years old.

40 And king Arad the Canaanite, who lived toward the south, heard that the sons of Israel had arrived in the land of Canaan.

41 And setting out from mount Hor, they made camp at Zalmonah.

42 Departing from there, they went to Punon.

43 And setting out from Punon, they were encamped at Oboth.

44 And from Oboth, they went to Iye-abarim, which is at the borders of the Moabites.

45 And setting out from Iye-abarim, they fixed their tents at Dibon-gad.

46 Departing from there, they made camp at Almon-diblathaim.

47 And departing from Almon-diblathaim, they went to the mountains of Abarim, opposite Nebo.

48 And setting out from the mountains of Abarim, they crossed over to the plains of Moab, above the Jordan, opposite Jericho.

49 And they made camp there, from Beth-jeshimoth all the way to Abel-shittim, in the level places of the Moabites,

50 where the Lord said to Moses:

51 "Instruct the sons of Israel, and say to them: When you will have crossed over the Jordan, entering into the land of Canaan,

52 destroy all the inhabitants of that land. Break their monuments, and shatter their statues, and lay waste to every exalted thing,

53 cleansing the land and living in it. For I have given it you as a possession,

54 which you shall divide among you by lot. To the greater number you shall give more, and to the lesser number, less. To each one, just as the lot shall fall, so shall the inheritance be distributed. The possession shall be divided by the tribes and families.

55 But if you are not willing to put to death the inhabitants of the land, those who remain shall be to you like spikes in your eyes and lances in your sides, and they shall be adversaries to you in the land of your habitation.

56 And whatever I had decided to do to them, I will do to you."

Numbers 34

1 And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying:

2 "Instruct the sons of Israel, and you shall say to them: When you will have entered into the land of Canaan, and it has fallen into your possession by lot, it shall be bound by these limits:

3 The southern part shall begin from the wilderness of Sin, which is next to Edom, and it shall have the Sea of Salt as a limit to the east.

4 It shall circle on the south side along the ascent of the Scorpion, by this way crossing into Senna, and passing through, from the south, as far as Kadesh-barnea, from which its confines shall go out to the town called Adar, and extend even to Azmon.

5 And its limits shall go around from Azmon to the Torrent of Egypt, and shall end at the shore of the Great Sea.

6 Then the western region shall begin from the Great Sea, and the same shall be its end.

7 Furthermore, toward the northern region, its limits shall begin from the Great Sea, passing through even to the highest mountain.

8 From there, it limits shall advance into Hamath, as far as the limits of Zedad.

9 And its confines shall go all the way to Ziphron, and to the village of Enan. These shall be the limits on the northern side.

10 From there, its limits shall be measured, facing the east side, from the village of Enan as far as Shepham.

11 And from Shepham, the boundaries shall descend into Riblah, opposite the fountain of Daphnis. From there, the boundaries shall pass through, opposite the east, to the Sea of Chinnereth,

12 and shall extend as far as the Jordan, and, at the furthest extent, shall be enclosed by the Sea of Salt. You shall have this land, with its borders all around."

13 And Moses instructed the sons of Israel, saying: "This shall be the land which you shall possess by lot, and which the Lord has ordered to be given to the nine tribes, and to the half tribe.

14 For the tribe of the sons of Ruben, by their families, and the tribe of the sons of Gad, according to the number of their kinships, and also one half of the tribe of Manasseh,

15 that is, two and a half tribes, have received their portion across the Jordan, opposite Jericho, toward the eastern side."

16 And the Lord said to Moses:

17 "These are the names of the men, who shall divide the land for you: Eleazar the priest, and Joshua the son of Nun,

18 and one leader from each tribe,

19 whose names are these: from the tribe of Judah, Caleb the son of Jephunneh;

20 from the tribe of Simeon, Samuel the son of Ammihud;

21 from the tribe of Benjamin, Elidad the son of Chislon;

22 from the tribe of the sons of Dan, Bukki the son of Jogli;

23 of the sons of Joseph, from the tribe of Manasseh, Hanniel the son of Ephod;

24 from the tribe of Ephraim, Kemuel the son of Shiphtan;

25 from the tribe of Zebulon, Elizaphan the son of Parnach;

26 from the tribe of Issachar, Paltiel the leader, the son of Azzan;

27 from the tribe of Asher, Ahihud the son of Shelomi;

28 from the tribe of Naphtali, Pedahel the son of Ammihud."

29 These are the ones that the Lord has ordered to divide the land of Canaan to the sons of Israel.

Numbers 35

1 And the Lord also spoke these things to Moses in the plains of Moab, above the Jordan, opposite Jericho:

2 "Instruct the sons of Israel, so that they may give to the Levites, from their possessions,

3 cities as dwelling places, with their surrounding suburbs, so that they may lodge in the towns, and so that the suburbs may be for cattle and beasts of burden.

4 The suburbs shall extend from the outer walls of the cities, all around, for the space of one thousand steps.

5 Facing the east, there shall be two thousand cubits, and facing the south, similarly, there shall be two thousand cubits. Toward the sea, also, which looks out toward the west, there shall be the same measure, and the northern region shall be bounded by equal limits. And the cities shall be in the center, and the suburbs shall be outside.

6 Now, from the towns which you shall give to the Levites, six shall be separated for the assistance of fugitives, so that he who has shed blood may flee to them. And, aside from these, there shall be forty-two other towns,

7 that is, all together forty-eight with their suburbs.

8 And concerning these cities, which shall be given from the possessions of the sons of Israel: from those who have more, more shall be taken, and from those who have less, less shall be taken. Each shall give towns to the Levites according to the measure of their inheritance."

9 The Lord said to Moses:

10 "Speak to the sons of Israel, and you shall say to them: When you will have crossed the Jordan into the land of Canaan,

11 discern which cities ought to be for the protection of fugitives who have shed blood unwillingly.

12 And when a fugitive is in these, the kinsman of the deceased shall not be able to kill him, until he stands in the sight of the multitude and his case is judged.

13 Then, among those cities which are separated for relief to fugitives,

14 three shall be across the Jordan, and three in the land of Canaan,

15 as much for the sons of Israel as for newcomers and sojourners, so that anyone who has shed blood unwillingly may flee to these places.

16 If anyone will have struck someone with iron, and he who was struck will have died, then he shall be guilty of homicide, and he himself shall die.

17 If he will have thrown a stone, and he who has been struck lies dead, then he shall be punished similarly.

18 If he who has been struck with wood passes away, he shall be avenged by the blood of the one who struck him.

19 The close relative of the deceased shall put to death the murderer; as soon as he apprehends him, he shall put him to death.

20 If, out of hatred, anyone assaults a man, or throws anything at him with ill intent,

21 or, while being his enemy, strikes him with his hand, and so he has died, the attacker shall be guilty of murder. The kinsman of the deceased, as soon as he finds him, shall cut his throat.

22 But if by chance, and without hatred

23 or animosity, he will have done any of these things,

24 and this has been proven in the hearing of the people, and the questions have been aired, between the one who struck and the close relative,

25 then the innocent one shall be freed from the hand of the revenger, and he shall be returned by this judgment into the city to which he had fled, and he shall stay there until the high priest, who has been anointed with the holy oil, dies.

26 If the one who has killed has been found beyond the limits of the cities which have been assigned to the exiled,

27 and he has been struck by him who is avenging blood, he who killed him shall not be harmed.

28 For the fugitive ought to have resided in the city, until the death of the high priest. Then, after he is dead, the one who has killed shall be returned to his own land.

29 These things shall be a perpetual ordinance in all your habitations.

30 The punishment of a murderer shall be based upon testimony; but no one shall be condemned upon the testimony of only one person.

31 You shall not accept money from him who is guilty of blood, and he shall be put to death promptly.

32 Exiles and fugitives, prior to the death of the high priest, are by no means able to be returned to their own cities.

33 Do not pollute the land of your habitation, so as to stain it with the blood of the innocent; neither is it able to be expiated in any way other than by the blood of him who has shed the blood of another.

34 And so shall your possession be cleansed, while I myself am abiding with you. For I am the Lord, who lives among the sons of Israel."

Numbers 36

1 Then the leaders of the families of Gilead, the son of Machir, the son of Manasseh, from the stock of the sons of Joseph, approached and spoke to Moses before the leaders of Israel, and they said:

2 "The Lord has instructed you, our ruler, so that you would divide the land by lot to the sons of Israel, and so that you would give to the daughters of Zelophehad, our brother, the possession owed to their father.

3 But if men of another tribe receive them as wives, their possession will follow them, and having been transferred to another tribe, there will be a reduction in our inheritance.

4 And so it may be that, when the Jubilee of remission, that is, the fiftieth year, has arrived, the distribution by lots shall be confounded, and the possession of the one shall be transferred to others."

5 Moses answered the sons of Israel, and, at the instruction of the Lord, he said: "The tribe of the sons of Joseph has spoken correctly.

6 And so, this is the law which has been promulgated by the Lord about the daughters of Zelophehad: Let them marry whomever they may wish, but only among the men of their own tribe,

7 lest the possession of the sons of Israel become commingled, from tribe to tribe. For all men shall take wives from their own tribe and kinship;

8 and all women shall take husbands from their same tribe, so that the inheritance may remain within the families,

9 and so that the tribes may not be mingled together, but may remain such as they were separated by the Lord."

10 And the daughters of Zelophehad acted according to what was ordered.

11 And Mahlah, and Tirzah, and Hoglah, and Milcah, and Noa were wed to the sons of their paternal uncle,

12 from the family of Manasseh, who was a son of Joseph. And the possession which had been distributed to them remained in the tribe and family of their father.

13 These are the commandments and judgments which the Lord ordered by the hand of Moses to the sons of Israel, in the plains of Moab, above the Jordan, opposite Jericho.

Deuteronomy 1

1 These are the words which Moses spoke to all of Israel, across the Jordan, in the plain of the wilderness opposite the Red Sea, between Paran and Tophel and Laban and Hazeroth, where gold is very plentiful,

2 eleven days from Horeb, by way of Mount Seir as far as Kadesh-barnea.

3 In the fortieth year, on the eleventh month, on the first day of the month, Moses told the sons of Israel all that the Lord had instructed him. And so he spoke to them,

4 after he had struck down Sihon, the king of the Amorites, who lived at Heshbon, and Og, the king of Bashan, who resided at Ashtaroth and at Edrei,

5 across the Jordan in the land of Moab. And so, Moses began to explain the law, and to say:

6 "The Lord our God spoke to us at Horeb, saying: 'You have remained long enough on this mountain.

7 Turn back and go to the mountain of the Amorites, and to the other places which are near it: the plains as well as the mountainous regions, and the low-lying places opposite the south and along the shore of the sea, the land of the Canaanites, and Lebanon, as far as the great river Euphrates.'

8 'Lo,' he said, 'I have delivered it to you. Enter and possess that which the Lord swore to your fathers, Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, that he would give it to them, and to their offspring after them.'

9 And I said to you, at that time:

10 'I alone am not able to sustain you. For the Lord, your God, has multiplied you, and you are today like the stars of heaven, very many.

11 May the Lord, the God of your fathers, add to this number many thousands more, and may he bless you, just as he has said.

12 Alone, I do not have the strength to endure your arbitrations and judgments and disputes.

13 Offer, from among you, wise and experienced men, those whose conversation has been proven within your tribes, so that I may appoint them as your rulers.'

14 Then you responded to me: 'What you intend to do is a good thing.'

15 And so, I took from your tribes men, wise and noble, and I appointed them as rulers, as tribunes and centurions, and as leaders over fifty and over ten, who would teach you each thing.

16 And I instructed them, saying: 'Listen to them, and judge what is just, whether he is one of your citizens or a sojourner.

17 There shall be no favoritism to any persons. So you shall listen to the little as well as to the great. And you shall not accept anyone's reputation, for this is the judgment of God. But if anything seems difficult to you, then refer it to me, and I will hear it.'

18 And I instructed you in all that you were obliged to do.

19 Then, setting out from Horeb, we crossed through a terrible and great wasteland, which you saw along the way of the mountain of the Amorite, just as the Lord our God had instructed us. And when we had arrived at Kadesh-barnea,

20 I said to you: 'You have arrived at the mountain of the Amorite, which the Lord our God will give to us.

21 Gaze upon the land that the Lord your God gives to you. Ascend and possess it, just as the Lord our God has spoken to your fathers. Do not be afraid, and do not become terrified by anything.'

22 And you all approached me and said: 'Let us send men who may consider the land, and who may report as to the way by which we ought to ascend, and as to which cities we ought to travel.'

23 And since the word was pleasing to me, I sent from among you twelve men, one from each tribe.

24 These, when they had set out and had ascended the mountains, arrived as far as the valley of the cluster of grapes. And having considered the land,

25 having taken from its fruits in order to show its fertility, they brought these to us, and they said: 'The land that the Lord our God will give to us is good.'

26 Yet you were not willing to go there. Instead, being incredulous to the word of the Lord our God,

27 you murmured in your tents, and you said: 'The Lord hates us, and therefore he has led us away from the land of Egypt, so that he might deliver us into the hand of the Amorite and destroy us.

28 To where should we ascend? The messengers have terrified our heart by saying: "The multitude is very great, and taller than us. And the cities are great, and the walls extend even to the sky. We have seen the sons of the Anakim there." '

29 And I said to you: 'Do not be apprehensive, nor should you fear them.

30 The Lord God himself, who is your leader, will fight on your behalf, just as he did in Egypt in the sight of all.

31 And in the wilderness (as you yourselves saw), the Lord your God carried you, like a man who is accustomed to carrying his little son, along all the way that you walked, until you arrived at this place.'

32 And yet, despite all of this, you did not believe the Lord your God,

33 who went before you on the way, and who marked out the place where you should pitch your tents, showing you the way by fire in the night, and by a pillar of cloud in the day.

34 And when the Lord had heard the voice of your words, becoming angry, he swore and said:

35 'None of the men of this wicked generation will see the good land, which I have promised by oath to your fathers,

36 except Caleb the son of Jephuneh. For he himself will see it, and I will give the land on which he has walked to him and to his sons, because he has followed the Lord.'

37 Neither is his indignation with the people a wonder, since the Lord also became angry with me because of you, and so he said: 'Neither will you enter into that place.

38 But Joshua, the son of Nun, your minister, shall himself enter on your behalf. Exhort and strengthen this man, and he himself shall divide the land by lot to Israel.

39 Your little ones, about whom you said that they would be led away as captives, and your sons, who to this day are ignorant of the difference between good and evil, they shall enter. And I will give the land to them, and they will possess it.

40 But as for you, turn back and go out to the wilderness, by way of the Red Sea.'

41 And you responded to me: 'We have sinned against the Lord. We will ascend and fight, just as the Lord our God has instructed.' And having been equipped with weapons, when you were setting out for the mountain,

42 the Lord said to me: 'Say to them: Do not ascend and do not fight. For I am not with you. Otherwise, you may fall in the sight of your enemies.'

43 I spoke, and you did not listen. But, opposing the order of the Lord, and swelling with pride, you ascended onto the mountain.

44 And so, having gone forth, the Amorite, who was living in the mountains, came against you and pursued you, just as a swarm of bees would do. And he struck you down from Seir all the way to Hormah.

45 And when you returned and were weeping in the sight of the Lord, he would not hear you, nor was he willing to agree to your voice.

46 Therefore, you camped at Kadesh-barnea for a long time."

Deuteronomy 2

1 "And setting out from there, we arrived at the wilderness which leads to the Red Sea, just as the Lord had spoken to me. And we encompassed Mount Seir for a long time.

2 And the Lord said to me:

3 'You have encompassed this mountain for long enough. Go forth, toward the north.

4 And instruct the people, saying: You shall cross through the borders of your brothers, the sons of Esau, who live at Seir, and they will fear you.

5 Therefore, take care diligently, lest you be moved against them. For I will not give to you from their land even as much as the step that one foot can tread upon, because I have given Mount Seir to Esau as a possession.

6 You shall buy food from them for money, and you shall eat. You shall draw water for money, and you shall drink.

7 The Lord your God has blessed you in every work of your hands. The Lord your God, dwelling with you, knows your journey, how you crossed through this great wilderness over forty years, and how you have been lacking in nothing.'

8 And when we had passed through our brothers, the sons of Esau, who were living at Seir by the way of the plain from Elath and from Eziongeber, we arrived at the way which leads to the desert of Moab.

9 And the Lord said to me: 'You should not fight against the Moabites, nor should you go to battle against them. For I will not give to you anything from their land, because I have given Ar to the sons of Lot as a possession.'

10 The Emim were the first of its inhabitants, a people great and strong, and of such great height, like the race of the Anakim.

11 They were considered to be like giants, and they were like the sons of the Anakim. And, indeed, the Moabites call them: the Emim.

12 The Horites also formerly lived at Seir. When these had been driven out and destroyed, the sons of Esau lived there, just as Israel did in the land of his possession, which the Lord gave to him.

13 Then, rising up so as to cross over the torrent Zered, we arrived at the place.

14 Then, from the time that we advanced from Kadesh-barnea until we crossed over the torrent Zered, there were thirty-eight years, until the entire generation of the men who were fit for war had been consumed out of the camp, just as the Lord had sworn.

15 For his hand was against them, so that they would pass away from the midst of the camp.

16 Then, after all the fighting men had fallen,

17 the Lord spoke to me, saying:

18 'Today, you shall cross the borders of Moab, at the city named Ar.

19 And when you have arrived in the vicinity of the sons of Ammon, be careful that you do not fight against them, nor should you be moved to battle. For I will not give to you from the land of the sons of Ammon, because I have given it to the sons of Lot as a possession.'

20 It was reputed to be a land of giants. And giants lived there in times past, those whom the Ammonites call the Zamzummim.

21 They are a people, great and numerous, and of lofty stature, like the Anakim, whom the Lord wiped away before their face. And he caused them to live there in place of them,

22 just as he had done for the sons of Esau, who live at Seir, wiping out the Horites and delivering their land to them, which they possess even to the present time.

23 Likewise the Hevites, who were living in small villages as far as Gaza, were expelled by the Cappadocians, who went forth from Cappadocia, and they wiped them out and lived in their place.

24 'Rise up and cross the torrent Arnon! Behold, I have delivered Sihon, the king of Heshbon, the Amorite, into your hand, and so, begin to possess his land and to engage in battle against him.

25 Today I will begin to send the terror and dread of you among the peoples who are living under all of heaven, so that, when they hear your name, they may be afraid, and may tremble in the manner of a woman giving birth, and may be gripped by anguish.'

26 Therefore, I sent messengers from the wilderness of Kedemoth to Sihon, the king of Heshbon, with peaceful words, saying:

27 'We will cross through your land. We will advance by the public way. We will not turn aside, neither to the right, nor to the left.

28 Sell us food for a price, so that we may eat. Provide us with water for money, and so we will drink. We only ask that you allow us to pass through,

29 just as the sons of Esau have done, who live at Seir, and the Moabites, who abide in Ar, until we arrive at the Jordan, and we cross to the land which the Lord our God will give to us.'

30 And Sihon, the king of Heshbon, was not willing to grant passage to us. For the Lord your God had hardened his spirit, and had fastened his heart, so that he would be delivered into your hands, just as you now see.

31 And the Lord said to me: 'Behold, I have begun to deliver Sihon and his land to you. Begin to possess it.'

32 And Sihon went out to meet us with all his people, to battle at Jahaz.

33 And the Lord our God delivered him to us. And we struck him down, with his sons and all his people.

34 And we seized all his cities at that time, putting to death their inhabitants: men as well as women and children. We left nothing of them,

35 except the cattle, which went to the share of those who plundered them. And we seized the spoils of the cities,

36 from Aroer, which is above the bank of the torrent Arnon, a town which is situated in a valley, all the way to Gilead. There was not a village or city which escaped from our hands. The Lord our God delivered everything to us,

37 except the land of the sons of Ammon, which we did not approach, and all that is adjacent to the torrent Jabbok, and the cities in the mountains, and all the places which the Lord our God prohibited to us."

Deuteronomy 3

1 "And so, having turned back, we ascended by the way of Bashan. And Og, the king of Bashan, went forth with his people to meet us in warfare at Edrei.

2 And the Lord said to me: 'You should not fear him. For he has been delivered into your hand, with all his people as well as his land. And you shall do to him just as you have done to Sihon, the king of the Amorites, who lived at Heshbon.'

3 Therefore, the Lord our God delivered into our hands, now Og, the king of Bashan, and all his people. And we struck them down unto utter annihilation,

4 laying waste to all his cities at one time. There was not a village which escaped from us: sixty cities, the entire region of Argob, the kingdom of Og, in Bashan.

5 All the cities were fortified with very high walls, and with gates and bars, in addition to innumerable villages which had no walls.

6 And we wiped them out, just as we had done to Sihon, the king of Heshbon, destroying every city, and its men, as well as women and children.

7 But the cattle and the spoils of the cities, we plundered.

8 And at that time, we took the land from the hand of the two kings of the Amorites, who were across the Jordan: from the torrent Arnon as far as Mount Hermon,

9 which the Sidonians call Sirion, and the Amorites call Senir,

10 all the cities that are situated in the plain, and the entire land of Gilead and Bashan, all the way to Salecah and Edrei, cities of the kingdom of Og in Bashan.

11 For only Og, the king of Bashan, was left behind out of the race of the giants. His bed of iron is on display, (it is in Rabbah, among the sons of Ammon) being nine cubits in length, and four in width, according to the measure of the cubit of a man's hand.

12 And we possessed the land, at that time, from Aroer, which is above the bank of the torrent Arnon, as far as the middle of Mount Gilead. And I gave its cities to Ruben and Gad.

13 Then I delivered the remaining part of Gilead, and all of Bashan, the kingdom of Og, which is the entire region of Argob, to one half of the tribe of Manasseh. And all of Bashan is called the land of the giants.

14 Jair, the son of Manasseh, possessed all the region of Argob, as far as the borders of Geshur and Maacath. And he called Bashan by his own name, Havvoth Jair, that is, the villages of Jair, even to the present day.

15 Likewise, to Machir, I gave Gilead.

16 And to the tribes of Ruben and Gad, I gave from the land of Gilead as far as the torrent Arnon, one half of the torrent and its confines, even to the torrent Jabbok, which is along the border of the sons of Ammon,

17 and the plain of the wilderness, as well as the Jordan, and the borders of Chinnereth, all the way to the sea of the desert, which is very salty, to the base of Mount Pisgah toward the east.

18 And I instructed you at that time, saying: 'The Lord your God gives to you this land as an inheritance. Having armed yourselves, go before your brothers, the sons of Israel, all you strong men.

19 Leave behind your wives and little ones, as well as the cattle. For I know that you have many cattle, and they should remain in the cities which I have delivered to you,

20 until the Lord provides rest to your brothers, just as he has provided for you. And they, too, shall possess the land, which he will give to them beyond the Jordan. Then each one shall return to his possession, which I have allotted to you.'

21 Likewise, I instructed Joshua at that time, saying: 'Your eyes have seen what the Lord your God has done to these two kings. So also will he do to all the kingdoms through which you shall pass.

22 You should not fear them. For the Lord your God will fight on your behalf.'

23 And I beseeched the Lord at that time, saying:

24 'Lord God, you have begun to reveal your greatness and your very strong hand to your servant. For there is no other god, either in heaven or on earth, who is able to accomplish your works, or to be compared to your strength.

25 Therefore, I will cross over, and I will view this excellent land beyond the Jordan, and this singular mountain, and Lebanon.'

26 And the Lord became angry with me because of you, and he would not heed me. But he said to me: 'It is enough for you. You shall no longer speak to me at all about this matter.

27 Ascend to the summit of Pisgah, and look around with your eyes to the west, and to the north, and to the south, and to the east, and behold it. For you shall not cross this Jordan.

28 Instruct Joshua, and encourage and strengthen him. For he shall go before this people, and he shall distribute to them the land that you will see.'

29 And we remained in the valley, opposite the shrine of Peor."

Deuteronomy 4

1 "And now, O Israel, listen to the precepts and judgments which I am teaching to you, so that, by doing these, you may live, and you may enter and possess the land, which the Lord, the God of your fathers, will give to you.

2 You shall not add to the word which I speak to you, neither shall you take away from it. Preserve the commandments of the Lord your God which I am teaching to you.

3 Your eyes have seen all that the Lord has done against Baal-peor, in what manner he has crushed all of his worshippers from among you.

4 But you who adhere to the Lord your God are all still alive, to the present day.

5 You know that I have taught you precepts as well as justices, just as the Lord my God has commanded me. And so shall you do in the land that you will possess.

6 And you shall observe and fulfill these in practice. For this is your wisdom and understanding in the sight of the peoples, so that, upon hearing all these precepts, they may say: 'Lo, a wise and understanding people, a great nation.'

7 Neither is there any other nation so great, which has its gods so near to them, as our God is present to all our petitions.

8 For what other nation is there so renowned as to have ceremonies, and just judgments, and the entire law that I will set forth today before your eyes?

9 And so, guard yourself and your soul carefully. You should not forget the words that your eyes have seen, and do not let them be cut away from your heart, throughout all the days of your life. You shall teach them to your sons and to your grandsons,

10 from the day on which you stood before the Lord your God at Horeb, when the Lord spoke to me, saying: 'Gather the people to me, so that they may listen to my words, and may learn to fear me, throughout all the time that they are alive on earth, and so that they may teach their children.'

11 And you approached the base of the mountain, which was burning even toward heaven. And there was a darkness upon it, and a cloud, and a mist.

12 And the Lord spoke to you from the midst of fire. You heard the voice of his words, but you did not see any form at all.

13 And he revealed his covenant to you, which he instructed you to carry out, and the ten words which he wrote on two tablets of stone.

14 And he commanded me, at that time, that I should teach you the ceremonies and judgments which you must carry out, in the land that you shall possess.

15 And so, guard your souls carefully. You saw no likeness on the day that the Lord God spoke to you on Horeb from the midst of fire.

16 Otherwise, perhaps being deceived, you might have made a graven image, or an image of male or female,

17 a likeness of any of the beasts, which are upon the earth, or of birds, which fly under heaven,

18 or of reptiles, which move across the earth, or of fish, which abide in the waters under the earth.

19 Otherwise, perhaps lifting up your eyes to heaven, you might look upon the sun and the moon and all the stars of heaven, and being deceived by error, you might adore and worship these things, which the Lord your God created for the service of all the nations, which are under heaven.

20 But the Lord has taken you up, and led you away from the iron furnaces of Egypt, in order to have a people of inheritance, just as it is to the present day.

21 And the Lord became angry against me because of your words, and he swore that I would not cross over the Jordan, nor enter into the excellent land, which he will give to you.

22 Behold, I shall die on this soil. I shall not cross over the Jordan. You shall cross it, and you shall possess the singular land.

23 Be careful, lest you at sometime forget the covenant of the Lord your God, which he has formed with you, and lest you make for yourselves a graven likeness of those things which the Lord has prohibited to be made.

24 For the Lord your God is a consuming fire, a jealous God.

25 When you will have conceived sons and grandsons while abiding in the land, and if, having been deceived, you make for yourselves any likeness, accomplishing evil in the sight of the Lord your God, so as to provoke him to wrath,

26 I call heaven and earth as witnesses this day, that you shall quickly perish from the land, which, when you have crossed over the Jordan, you will possess. You will not live in it for a long time; instead, the Lord will destroy you.

27 And he will scatter you among all the nations, and few of you will remain among those nations, to which the Lord will lead you.

28 And there, you will serve gods which were fabricated by the hands of men: gods of wood and of stone, who neither see, nor hear, nor eat, nor smell.

29 And when you will seek the Lord your God in that place, you shall find him, if only you seek him with all your heart, and in all the tribulation of your soul.

30 After all these things which have been foretold have found you, in the end time, you shall return to the Lord your God, and you will hear his voice.

31 For the Lord your God is a merciful God. He will not abandon you, nor will he entirely destroy you, nor will he forget the covenant, which he swore to your fathers.

32 Inquire concerning the days of antiquity, which were before you, from the day when God created man upon the earth, from one end of heaven to another, if anything similar has ever occurred, or whether any such thing has ever been known,

33 that a people would hear the voice of God, speaking from the midst of fire, just as you have heard it, and live,

34 whether God has acted so as to enter and take for himself a nation from the midst of the nations, by means of tests, signs, and wonders, by means of fighting, and a strong hand, and an outstretched arm, and terrible visions, in accord with all the things which the Lord your God has accomplished for you in Egypt, in the sight of your eyes.

35 So may you know that the Lord himself is God, and there is no other beside him.

36 He has caused you to hear his voice from heaven, so that he might teach you. And he showed you his exceedingly great fire on earth, and you heard his words from the midst of the fire.

37 For he loved your fathers, and he chose their offspring after them. And he led you away from Egypt, advancing before you with his great power,

38 so as to wipe away, upon your arrival, nations, very great and stronger than you, and so as to lead you in, and to present to you their land as a possession, just as you discern in the present day.

39 Therefore, know on this day and consider in your heart, that the Lord himself is God in heaven above, and on earth below, and there is no other.

40 Keep his precepts and commandments, which I am teaching to you, so that it may be well with you, and with your sons after you, and so that you may remain for a long time upon the land, which the Lord your God will give to you."

41 Then Moses set aside three cities, across the Jordan toward the eastern region,

42 so that anyone might flee to these if he has killed his neighbor unwillingly, who was not his enemy a day or two earlier, and so that he would be able to escape to one of these cities:

43 Bezer in the wilderness, which is situated in the plains of the tribe of Ruben; and Ramoth in Gilead, which is in the tribe of Gad; and Golan in Bashan, which is in the tribe of Manasseh.

44 This is the law, which Moses set forth before the sons of Israel.

45 And these are the testimonies and ceremonies as well as judgments, which he spoke to the sons of Israel, when they departed from Egypt,

46 across the Jordan, in the valley opposite the shrine of Peor, in the land of Sihon, the king of the Amorites, who lived at Heshbon, whom Moses struck down. Accordingly, the sons of Israel, having departed from Egypt,

47 possessed his land, and the land of Og, the king of Bashan, the land of the two kings of the Amorites, who were beyond the Jordan, toward the rising of the sun:

48 from Aroer, which is situated above the bank of the torrent Arnon, as far as Mount Zion, which is also called Hermon,

49 the entire plain across the Jordan, from its eastern region, as far as the sea of the wilderness, and even to the base of Mount Pisgah.

Deuteronomy 5

1 And Moses summoned all of Israel, and he said to them: "Listen, O Israel, to the ceremonies and judgments, which I am speaking to your ears on this day. Learn them, and fulfill them in deed.

2 The Lord our God formed a covenant with us at Horeb.

3 He did not make the covenant with our fathers, but with us, who are alive and in the present time.

4 He spoke to us face to face on the mountain, from the midst of fire.

5 I was the mediator, for I was in the middle between the Lord and you, at that time, to announce his words to you. For you were afraid of the fire, and so you did not ascend to the mountain. And he said:

6 'I am the Lord your God, who led you away from the land of Egypt, from the house of servitude.

7 You shall not have strange gods in my sight.

8 You shall not make for yourself a graven image, nor the likeness of anything, which is in heaven above, or on earth below, or which abides in the waters under the earth.

9 You shall not adore and you shall not worship these things. For I am the Lord your God, a jealous God, repaying the iniquity of the fathers upon the sons to the third and fourth generation to those who hate me,

10 and acting with mercy in thousands of ways to those who love me and keep my precepts.

11 You shall not use the name of the Lord your God in vain. For he will not go unpunished who takes up his name over an unimportant matter.

12 Observe the day of the Sabbath, so that you may sanctify it, just as the Lord your God has instructed you.

13 For six days, you shall labor and do all your work.

14 The seventh is the day of the Sabbath, that is, the rest of the Lord your God. You shall not do any work in it, nor shall your son, nor daughter, nor man servant, nor woman servant, nor ox, nor donkey, nor any of your cattle, nor the sojourner who is within your gates, so that your men and woman servants may rest, just as you do.

15 Remember that you also were servants in Egypt, and the Lord your God led you away from that place with a strong hand and an outstretched arm. Because of this, he has instructed you so that you would observe the Sabbath day.

16 Honor your father and mother, just as the Lord your God has instructed you, so that you may live a long time, and so that it may be well with you in the land, which the Lord your God will give to you.

17 You shall not murder.

18 And you shall not commit adultery.

19 And you shall not commit theft.

20 Neither shall you speak false testimony against your neighbor.

21 You shall not covet your neighbor's wife, nor his house, nor his field, nor his man servant, nor his woman servant, nor his ox, nor his donkey, nor anything out of all that is his.'

22 The Lord spoke these words to the entire multitude of you on the mountain, from the midst of the fire and the cloud and the darkness, with a loud voice, adding nothing more. And he wrote them on two tablets of stone, which he delivered to me.

23 Then, after you heard the voice from the midst of the darkness, and you saw the mountain burning, you approached me, all you leaders of the tribes and those greater by birth. And you said:

24 'Behold, the Lord our God has revealed to us his majesty and his greatness. We have heard his voice from the midst of fire, and we have proven today that, though God is speaking with man, man has lived.

25 Therefore, why should we die, and why should this very great fire devour us? For if we hear the voice of the Lord our God any longer, we will die.

26 What is all flesh, that it would hear the voice of the living God, who speaks from the midst of fire, just as we have heard it, and be able to live?

27 Instead, you should approach and listen to all the things that the Lord our God will say to you. And you will speak to us, and we will listen and do these things.'

28 But when the Lord had heard this, he said to me: 'I have heard the voice of the words of this people, which they spoke to you. All this, they have spoken well.

29 Who will grant to them to have such a mind, so that they may fear me, and may keep all my commandments at all times, so that it may be well with them and with their sons forever?

30 Go and say to them: Return to your tents.

31 But as for you, stand here with me, and I will speak to you all my commandments and ceremonies, as well as judgments. These, you shall teach them, so that they may do them in the land, which I will give to them as a possession.

32 And so, keep and do the things which the Lord God has commanded you. You shall not turn aside, neither to the right, nor to the left.

33 For you shall walk in the way that the Lord your God has instructed, so that you may live, and it may be well with you, and your days may be extended in the land of your possession.' "

Deuteronomy 6

1 "These are the precepts and ceremonies, as well as the judgments, which the Lord your God has commanded that I teach to you, which you shall do in the land to which you will travel in order to possess it.

2 So may you fear the Lord your God, and keep all his commandments and precepts, which I am entrusting to you, and to your sons and grandsons, all the days of your life, so that your days may be prolonged.

3 Listen and observe, O Israel, so that you may do just as the Lord has instructed you, and it may be well with you, and you may be multiplied all the more, for the Lord, the God of your fathers, has promised you a land flowing with milk and honey.

4 Listen, O Israel: the Lord our God is one Lord.

5 You shall love the Lord your God with all your heart, and with all your soul, and with all your strength.

6 And these words, which I instruct to you this day, shall be in your heart.

7 And you shall explain them to your sons. And you shall meditate upon them sitting in your house, and walking on a journey, when lying down and when rising up.

8 And you shall bind them like a sign on your hand, and they shall be placed and shall move between your eyes.

9 And you shall write them at the threshold and on the doors of your house.

10 And when the Lord your God will have led you into the land, about which he swore to your fathers, Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, and when he will have given to you great and excellent cities, which you did not build;

11 houses full of goods, which you did not amass; cisterns, which you did not dig; vineyards and olive groves, which you did not plant;

12 and when you will have eaten and been satisfied:

13 take care diligently, lest you forget the Lord, who led you away from the land of Egypt, from the house of servitude. You shall fear the Lord your God, and you shall serve him alone, and you shall swear by his name.

14 You shall not go after the strange gods of all the Gentiles, who are around you.

15 For the Lord your God is a jealous God in your midst. Otherwise, at sometime, the fury of the Lord your God may be enraged against you, and he may take you away from the face of the earth.

16 You shall not tempt the Lord your God, as you tempted him in the place of temptation.

17 Keep the precepts of the Lord your God, as well as the testimonies and ceremonies, which he has instructed to you.

18 And do what is pleasing and good in the sight of the Lord, so that it may be well with you, and so that, when you enter, you may possess the excellent land, about which the Lord swore to your fathers

19 that he would wipe away all your enemies before you, just as he has spoken.

20 And when your son will ask you tomorrow, saying: 'What do these testimonies and ceremonies and judgments mean, which the Lord our God has entrusted to us?'

21 You shall say to him: 'We were servants of Pharaoh in Egypt, and the Lord led us away from Egypt with a strong hand.

22 And he wrought signs and wonders, great and very grievous, in Egypt, against Pharaoh and all his house, in our sight.

23 And he led us away from that place, so that he might lead us in and give us the land, about which he swore to our fathers.

24 And the Lord instructed us that we should do all these ordinances, and that we should fear the Lord our God, so that it may be well with us all the days of our life, just as it is today.

25 And he will be merciful to us, if we keep and perform all his precepts, in the sight of the Lord our God, just as he has commanded us.' "

Deuteronomy 7

1 "When the Lord your God will have led you to the land, which you will enter so as to possess it, and when he will have destroyed many nations before you, the Hittite, and the Girgashite, and the Amorite, and the Canaanite, and the Perizzite, and the Hivite, and the Jebusite, seven nations much more numerous than you, and more robust than you,

2 and when the Lord your God will have delivered them to you, you shall strike them down unto utter annihilation. You shall not enter into a pact with them, nor shall you show any pity to them.

3 And you shall not associate with them in marriage. You shall not give your daughter to his son, nor accept his daughter for your son.

4 For she will seduce your son, so that he will not follow me, and so that he will instead serve foreign gods. And the fury of the Lord will be enraged, and he will quickly destroy you.

5 So instead, you shall do this to them: overturn their altars, and break their statues, and cut down their sacred groves, and burn up their graven images.

6 For you are a holy people to the Lord your God. The Lord your God has chosen you so that you would be his particular people out of all the peoples who are upon the earth.

7 It is not because you surpass all the nations in number that the Lord has joined with you and has chosen you, for you are the least numerous of any people.

8 But it is because the Lord has loved you, and has kept his oath, which he swore to your fathers. And he has led you away with a strong hand, and he has redeemed you from the house of servitude, from the hand of Pharaoh, the king of Egypt.

9 And you shall know that the Lord your God himself is a strong and faithful God, preserving his covenant and his mercy for those who love him and those who keep his precepts for a thousand generations,

10 and promptly repaying those who hate him, so as to utterly ruin them, without further delay, quickly rendering to them what they deserve.

11 Therefore, keep the precepts and ceremonies as well as the judgments, which I command to you this day, so that you may do them.

12 If, after you have heard these judgments, you keep and do them, the Lord your God will also keep his covenant with you and the mercy that he swore to your fathers.

13 And he will love you and multiply you. And he will bless the fruit of your womb, and the fruit of your land: your grain as well as your vintage, oil, and herds, and the flocks of your sheep, upon the land about which he swore to your fathers that he would give it to you.

14 Blessed shall you be among all peoples. No one will be barren among you of either gender, as much among men as among your herds.

15 The Lord will take all sickness away from you. And the very grievous infirmities of Egypt, which you have known, he will not bring upon you, but upon your enemies.

16 You shall devour all the peoples, which the Lord your God will deliver to you. Your eye shall not spare them, neither shall you serve their gods, lest they be your ruin.

17 If you say in your heart, 'These nations are more than I am, so how will I be able to destroy them?'

18 do not be apprehensive. Instead, recall what the Lord your God did to Pharaoh and to all the Egyptians:

19 the very great plagues, which your eyes saw, and the signs and wonders, and the powerful hand and outstretched arm, by which the Lord your God led you away. So will he do to all the peoples, whom you dread.

20 Moreover, the Lord your God will also send hornets among them, until he destroys and scatters all who have escaped from you, or who have been able to hide.

21 You shall not fear them, for the Lord your God is in your midst: a great and terrible God.

22 He himself will consume these nations in your sight, a little at a time, by degrees. You will not be able to destroy them all at once. Otherwise, the wild beasts of the earth might increase against you.

23 And so, the Lord your God will present them in your sight, and you shall slay them until they are thoroughly wiped away.

24 And he shall deliver their kings into your hands, and you shall abolish their names from under heaven. No one will be able to withstand you, until you crush them.

25 Their graven images, you shall burn with fire. You shall not covet the silver or gold from which they have been made. And you shall not take for yourself anything from these, lest you offend, because this is an abomination to the Lord your God.

26 Neither shall you carry anything of the idol into your house, lest you become accursed, just as it also is. You shall detest it like dung, and you shall abominate it like defilement and filth, because it is an accursed thing."

Deuteronomy 8

1 "All the commandments which I am entrusting to you this day, take care to observe them diligently, so that you may live and be multiplied, and so that, upon entering, you may possess the land, about which the Lord swore to your fathers.

2 And you shall remember the entire journey along which the Lord your God led you, for forty years through the desert, to afflict you, and to test you, and to make known the things that were turning in your soul, whether or not you would keep his commandments.

3 He afflicted you with need, and he gave you Manna as your food, which neither you nor your fathers knew, so as to reveal to you that it is not by bread alone that man lives, but by every word that goes forth from the mouth of God.

4 Your garment, with which you were covered, has by no means decayed due to age, and your foot has not been worn down, even to this fortieth year,

5 so that you would recognize in your heart that, just as a man educates his son, so has the Lord your God educated you.

6 So may you keep the commandments of the Lord your God, and walk in his ways, and fear him.

7 For the Lord your God will lead you into a good land: a land of brooks and waters and fountains, in which deep rivers burst forth from its plains and mountains,

8 a land of crops, barley, and vineyards, in which fig and pomegranate and olive trees spring up, a land of oil and honey.

9 In that place, without any need, you shall eat your bread and enjoy an abundance of all things: where the stones are like iron, and where ore for brass is dug out of its mountains.

10 So then, when you have eaten and been satisfied, you should bless the Lord your God for the excellent land which he has given to you.

11 Be observant and cautious, lest at sometime you may forget the Lord your God, and neglect his commandments, as well as the judgments and ceremonies, which I instruct to you this day.

12 Otherwise, after you have eaten and been satisfied, and have built beautiful houses and have lived in them,

13 and have obtained herds of oxen, and flocks of sheep, and a plentitude of gold and silver and all things,

14 your heart might be lifted up, and you might not remember the Lord your God, who led you away from the land of Egypt, from the house of servitude,

15 and who was your leader in the great and terrible wilderness, in which there was the serpent with a burning breath, and the scorpion, and the snake of thirst, and no waters at all. He led streams out of the hardest rock,

16 and he nourished you in the wilderness with Manna, which your fathers had not known. And after he had afflicted and tested you, in the very end, he took pity on you.

17 Otherwise, you might say in your heart: 'My own strength, and the power of my own hand, have brought forth all these things for me.'

18 But remember the Lord your God, that he himself has provided you with strength, so that he may fulfill his covenant, about which he swore to your fathers, just as the present day reveals.

19 But if you forget the Lord your God, so that you follow foreign gods, and serve and adore them: behold, I now foretell to you that you shall utterly perish.

20 Just like the nations, which the Lord destroyed upon your arrival, so shall you also perish, if you have been disobedient to the voice of the Lord your God."

Deuteronomy 9

1 "Listen, O Israel: You shall cross over the Jordan today, in order to possess nations, very great and stronger than yourself, cities vast and walled even to the sky,

2 a people great and lofty, the sons of the Anakim, whom you yourselves have seen and heard, against whom no one is able to stand.

3 Therefore, you shall know today that the Lord your God himself will pass over before you, like a devouring and consuming fire, to crush and to wipe away and to utterly ruin them before your face, quickly, just as he has spoken to you.

4 You should not say in your heart, when the Lord your God will have destroyed them in your sight: 'It is because of my justice that the Lord led me in, so that I might possess this land, while these nations have been destroyed because of their impiety.'

5 For it is not because of your justices or the uprightness of your heart that you will enter, so that you may possess their lands. Instead, it is because they have acted wickedly that they are destroyed upon your arrival, and so that the Lord may accomplish his word, which he promised under oath to your fathers, Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob.

6 Therefore, know that the Lord your God will not give you this excellent land as a possession due to your justices, for you are a very stiff-necked people.

7 Remember, and never forget, how you provoked the Lord your God to anger in the wilderness. You have always contended against the Lord, from the day that you went forth from Egypt, even to this place.

8 For at Horeb also, you provoked him, and, becoming angry, he was willing to destroy you,

9 when I ascended onto the mountain, so that I might receive the tablets of stone, the tablets of the covenant which the Lord formed with you. And I persevered on the mountain for forty days and nights, neither eating bread, nor drinking water.

10 And the Lord gave me two tablets of stone, written with the finger of God and containing all the words that he spoke to you on the mountain from the midst of fire, while the people, being stirred up, were assembled together.

11 And when forty days, and as many nights, had passed, the Lord gave me the two tablets of stone, the tablets of the covenant.

12 And he said to me: 'Rise up, and descend quickly from here. For your people, whom you led away from Egypt, have quickly abandoned the way that you have shown to them, and they have made a molten idol for themselves.'

13 And again, the Lord said to me: 'I discern that this people is stiff-necked.

14 Depart from me, so that I may crush them, and abolish their name from under heaven, and appoint you over a nation, which will be greater and stronger than this one.'

15 And as I was descending from the burning mountain, and I held the two tablets of the covenant with both hands,

16 and I had seen that you had sinned against the Lord your God, and had made a molten calf for yourselves, and had quickly abandoned his way, which he had revealed to you,

17 I threw down the tablets from my hands, and I broke them in your sight.

18 And I fell prostrate before the Lord, just as before, for forty days and nights, not eating bread, and not drinking water, because of all your sins, which you had committed against the Lord, and because you provoked him to anger.

19 For I feared his indignation and wrath, which had been stirred up against you, so that he was willing to destroy you. And the Lord heeded me at this time also.

20 Likewise, he became vehemently angry against Aaron, and he was willing to destroy him, and I prayed for him similarly.

21 But as for your sin which you committed, that is, the calf, taking hold of it, I burned it with fire. And breaking it into pieces, and reducing it entirely to dust, I threw it into the torrent that descends from the mountain.

22 Likewise, at the Burning, and at the Temptation, and at the Graves of Lust, you provoked the Lord.

23 And when he sent you from Kadesh-barnea, saying, 'Ascend and possess the land, which I have given to you,' even so, you spurned the command of the Lord your God, and you did not believe him, nor were you willing to listen to his voice.

24 Instead, you were ever rebellious, from the day when I first began to know you.

25 And so, I lay prostrate before the Lord for forty days and nights, as I humbly begged him, lest he destroy you, just as he had threatened to do.

26 And praying, I said: 'O Lord God, do not destroy your people and your inheritance, whom you have redeemed in your greatness, whom you have led away from Egypt with a strong hand.

27 Remember your servants, Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob. Do not look upon the stubbornness of this people, nor upon their wickedness and sinfulness.

28 Otherwise, perhaps the inhabitants of the land, out of which you have led us, may say: "The Lord was not able to lead them into the land, which he promised to them. And he hated them; therefore, he led them out, so that he might put them to death in the wilderness."

29 These are your people and your inheritance, whom you have led out by your great strength, and with your outstretched arm.' "

Deuteronomy 10

1 "At that time, the Lord said to me: 'Hew for yourself two tablets of stone, like those that were before, and ascend to me on the mountain. And you shall make an ark of wood.

2 And I will write on the tablets the words which were on those that you broke before, and you shall place them in the ark.'

3 And so, I made an ark of setim wood. And when I had hewn two tablets of stone like the former, I ascended onto the mountain, having them in my hands.

4 And he wrote on the tablets, according to that which he had written before, the ten words, which the Lord spoke to you on the mountain from the midst of fire, when the people were assembled. And he gave them to me.

5 And returning from the mountain, I descended and placed the tablets in the ark, which I had made, and they are still there even now, just as the Lord instructed me.

6 Then the sons of Israel moved their camp, from Beeroth among the sons of Jaakan, into Moserah, where Aaron died and was buried, and where his son Eleazar was installed in the priesthood in his place.

7 From there, they went into Gudgodah. From that place, they set out and camped at Jotbathah, in a land of waters and torrents.

8 At that time, he separated the tribe of Levi, so that he would carry the ark of the covenant of the Lord, and stand before him in the ministry, and speak blessings in his name, even to the present day.

9 As a result, Levi has no portion or possession with his brothers. For the Lord himself is his possession, just as the Lord your God promised him.

10 Then I stood on the mountain, as before, for forty days and nights. And the Lord heeded me at this time also, and he was not willing to destroy you.

11 And he said to me: 'Go forth and walk before the people, so that they may enter and possess the land, which I swore to their fathers that I would deliver to them.'

12 And now, O Israel, what does the Lord your God require of you? Only that you fear the Lord your God, and walk in his ways, and love him, and serve the Lord your God with your whole heart and with your whole soul,

13 and that you keep the commandments of the Lord, and his ceremonies, which I am instructing to you this day, so that it may be well with you.

14 Lo, heaven belongs to the Lord your God, and the heaven of heaven, and the earth, and all the things that are within these.

15 Now the Lord was closely joined to your fathers, and he loved them, and he chose their offspring after them, that is, you yourselves, out of all the nations, just as is being proven today.

16 Therefore, circumcise the foreskin of your heart, and no longer stiffen your neck.

17 For the Lord your God himself is the God of gods, and the Lord of lords, a God great and powerful and terrible, who favors no person and accepts no bribe.

18 He accomplishes judgment for the orphan and the widow. He loves the sojourner, and he gives him food as well as clothing.

19 Therefore, you also should love sojourners, for you also were new arrivals in the land of Egypt.

20 You shall fear the Lord your God, and him alone shall you serve. You shall cling to him, and you shall swear by his name.

21 He is your praise and your God. He has done for you these great and terrible things, which your eyes have seen.

22 As seventy souls, your fathers descended into Egypt. And now, behold, the Lord your God has multiplied you to be like the stars of heaven."

Deuteronomy 11

1 "And so, love the Lord your God, and observe his precepts and ceremonies, his judgments and commandments, at all times.

2 Acknowledge, on this day, the things that your sons did not know. For they did not see the chastisements of the Lord your God, his great acts, and powerful hand, and outstretched arm,

3 the signs and works that he did in the midst of Egypt, to Pharaoh, the king, and to his entire land,

4 and to the entire army of the Egyptians, and to their horses and chariots: how the waters of the Red Sea covered them as they were pursuing you, and how the Lord wiped them away, even to the present day;

5 and the things that he accomplished for you in the wilderness, until you arrived at this place;

6 and to Dathan and Abiram, sons of Eliab, who was the son of Reuben, those whom the earth, opening its mouth, engulfed with their households and tents, and with their entire substance which they had in the midst of Israel.

7 Your eyes have seen all the great works of the Lord, which he has accomplished,

8 so that you would keep all his commandments, which I entrust to you this day, and so that you would be able to enter and possess the land, toward which you are advancing,

9 and so that you may live, for a long time, in the land which the Lord promised under oath to your fathers, and to their offspring, a land flowing with milk and honey.

10 For the land, which you shall enter and possess, is not like the land of Egypt, from which you departed, where, when seed has been sown, waters are brought in by irrigation, in the manner of gardens.

11 Rather, it has mountainous regions and plains, which lay waiting for rain from heaven.

12 And the Lord your God always visits it, and his eyes are upon it, from the beginning of the year, all the way to its end.

13 So then, if you obey my commandments, which I am instructing to you this day, so that you love the Lord your God, and serve him with your whole heart and your whole soul,

14 he will give to your land the early rain and the late rain, so that you may gather your grain, and your wine, and your oil,

15 and your hay from the fields in order to feed your cattle, and so that you yourselves may eat and be satisfied.

16 Be careful, lest perhaps your heart may be deceived, and you might withdraw from the Lord, and serve strange gods, and adore them.

17 And the Lord, becoming angry, might close up heaven, so that the rain would not descend, nor would the earth produce her seedlings, and then you would quickly perish from the excellent land, which the Lord will give to you.

18 Place these words of mine in your hearts and minds, and hang them as a sign on your hands, and arrange them between your eyes.

19 Teach your sons to meditate on them, when you sit in your house, and when you walk along the way, and when you lie down or rise up.

20 You shall write them upon the doorposts and the gates of your house,

21 so that your days may be multiplied, and the days of your sons, in the land which the Lord swore to your fathers, that he would give it to them for as long as heaven is suspended above the earth.

22 For if you keep the commandments which I am entrusting to you, and if you do them, so that you love the Lord your God, and walk in all his ways, clinging to him,

23 the Lord will scatter all these nations before your face, and you shall possess them, though they are greater and stronger than you.

24 Every place upon which your foot shall tread will be yours. From the desert, and from Lebanon, from the great river Euphrates, as far as the western sea, shall be your borders.

25 No one will stand against you. The Lord your God will spread the terror and dread of you over all the land upon which you shall tread, just as he has spoken to you.

26 Behold, I am setting forth in your sight today a blessing and a curse.

27 It will be a blessing, if you obey the commandments of the Lord your God, which I am instructing to you this day.

28 It will be a curse, if you do not obey the commandments of the Lord your God, but instead you withdraw from the way, which I am revealing to you now, and you walk after foreign gods that you have not known.

29 Yet truly, when the Lord your God will have led you into the land, to which you are traveling for a habitation, you shall place the blessing upon Mount Gerizim, the curse upon Mount Ebal,

30 which are across the Jordan, behind the way which slopes toward the setting of the sun, in the land of the Canaanite, who lives in the plains opposite Gilgal, which is near the valley extending toward and entering a distant place.

31 For you shall cross over the Jordan, so that you may possess the land which the Lord your God will give you, so that you may have it and possess it.

32 Therefore, see to it that you fulfill the ceremonies and judgments, which I am placing in your sight this day."

Deuteronomy 12

1 "These are the precepts and judgments which you must do in the land which the Lord, the God of your fathers, will give to you, so that you may possess it during all the days that you shall walk upon the soil.

2 Overturn all the places where the nations, which you will possess, worshipped their gods on lofty mountains, and on hills, and under every leafy tree.

3 Scatter their altars and break their statues. Burn their sacred groves with fire and crush their idols. Abolish their names from those places.

4 But you shall not do the same to the Lord your God.

5 Instead, you shall approach the place which the Lord your God will choose among all your tribes, so that he may set his name there, and may dwell in that place.

6 And you shall offer, in that place, your holocausts and victims, the tithes and first-fruits of your hands, and your vows and gifts, the firstborn of the cattle and of the sheep.

7 And you shall eat it there, in the sight of the Lord your God. And you shall rejoice in all the things to which you shall set your hand: you and your household, which the Lord your God has blessed for you.

8 You shall not do there the things that we are doing here today: each one doing what seems good to himself.

9 For even until the present time, you did not arrive at the rest and the possession, which the Lord your God will give to you.

10 You shall cross over the Jordan, and you shall live in the land which the Lord your God will give to you, so that you may have rest from all the surrounding enemies, and so that you may live without any fear,

11 in the place which the Lord your God will choose, so that his name may be in it. To that place, you shall bring all the things that I instruct you: holocausts, and victims, and tithes, and the first-fruits of your hands, and whatever is best among the gifts that you shall vow to the Lord.

12 In that place, you shall feast before the Lord your God: you, and your sons and daughters, your men and women servants, as well as the Levite who dwells in your cities. For he has no other portion or possession among you.

13 Take care that you do not offer your holocausts in any place that you see.

14 Instead, you shall offer sacrifices in the place which the Lord will choose within one of your tribes, and you shall do whatsoever I instruct you.

15 So, if you wish to eat, and if the eating of flesh pleases you, then kill and eat according to the blessing of the Lord your God, which he has given to you, in your cities: you may eat it whether it is unclean, that is, having blemish or defect, or whether it is clean, that is, whole and without blemish, of the kind which is permitted to be offered, such as the roe deer and the stag.

16 Only the blood you shall not eat. Instead, you shall pour it upon the ground like water.

17 You may not eat in your towns the tithes of your crops, and your wine and oil, the firstborn of your herds and your flocks, nor anything which you will vow, or which you will offer spontaneously, nor the first-fruits of your hands.

18 But you shall eat these before the Lord your God, in the place which the Lord your God will choose: you, and your son, and your daughter, and your man servant and woman servant, and the Levite who dwells in your cities. And you shall rejoice and be refreshed in the sight of the Lord your God by all the things to which you will extend your hand.

19 Be careful, lest you abandon the Levite, at anytime while you are living in the land.

20 When the Lord your God will have enlarged your borders, just as he has spoken to you, and when you would eat the flesh that your soul desires,

21 but if the place which the Lord your God will choose, so that his name may be there, is far away, you may kill, from your herds and your flocks which you will have, in the manner I have instructed to you, and you may eat in your towns, as it pleases you.

22 Just as the roe deer and the stag may be eaten, so also may you eat these: you may eat both the clean and the unclean alike.

23 Only beware of this: you may not eat the blood. For their blood is for the soul. And because of this, you must not eat the soul with the flesh.

24 Instead, you shall pour it upon the ground like water,

25 so that it may be well with you, and with your sons after you, when you will do what is pleasing in the sight of the Lord.

26 But the things that you have sanctified and vowed to the Lord, you shall take up and bring to the place which the Lord will choose.

27 And you shall offer your oblations of flesh and of blood upon the altar of the Lord your God. You shall poor out the blood of your victims upon the altar. And you yourself shall eat the flesh.

28 Observe and heed all the things that I instruct to you, so that it may be well with you, and with your sons after you, continually, when you will do what is good and pleasing in the sight of the Lord your God.

29 When the Lord your God will have abolished before your face the nations, which you shall enter so as to possess them, and when you will possess them and live in their land,

30 be careful that you do not imitate them, after they have been overturned at your arrival, and that you do not seek their ceremonies, saying: 'Just as these nations have worshipped their gods, so also will I worship.'

31 You shall not act in like manner toward the Lord your God. For they have done to their gods all the abominations that the Lord spurns, offering their sons and daughters, and burning them with fire.

32 What I command to you, this only shall you do, for the Lord. You may neither add nor subtract anything."

Deuteronomy 13

1 "If there will have arisen in your midst a prophet, or someone who claims that he had seen a dream, and if he will have predicted sign and portent,

2 and if what he has spoken happens, and he says to you, 'Let us go and follow strange gods,' which you have not known, 'and let us serve them,'

3 you shall not listen to the words of that prophet or dreamer. For the Lord your God is testing you, so that it may become clear whether or not you love him with all your heart and with all your soul.

4 Follow the Lord your God, and fear him, and keep his commandments, and listen to his voice. Him shall you serve, and to him shall you cling.

5 But that prophet or forger of dreams shall be put to death. For he has spoken so as to turn you away from the Lord your God, who led you away from the land of Egypt and who redeemed you from the house of servitude, and so as to cause you to wander from the way that the Lord your God has entrusted to you. And so shall you remove the evil from your midst.

6 If your brother, the son of your mother, or your own son or daughter, or your wife who is in your bosom, or your friend, whom you love like your own soul, were willing to persuade you secretly, saying: 'Let us go, and serve foreign gods,' which neither you nor your fathers have known,

7 gods from any of the surrounding nations, whether these are near or far away, from the beginning even to the end of the earth,

8 you should neither agree with him, nor listen to him. And your eye should not spare him so that you take pity on him and conceal him.

9 Instead, you shall put him to death promptly. Let your hand be upon him first, and after that, let the hands of all the people be sent forth.

10 He shall be killed by being overwhelmed with stones. For he was willing to draw you away from the Lord your God, who led you away from the land of Egypt, from the house of servitude.

11 So may all of Israel, upon hearing this, be afraid, so that nothing like this will ever be done again.

12 If, in one of your cities which the Lord your God will give to you as a habitation, you hear someone say:

13 'The sons of Belial have departed from your midst, and they have persuaded the inhabitants of their city, and they have said: "Let us go, and serve strange gods," ' which you have not known:

14 inquire carefully and diligently, seeking the truth of the matter. And if you find that what was said is certain, and that this abomination is a work which has been perpetrated,

15 you shall promptly strike down the inhabitants of that city with the edge of the sword. And you shall destroy it, along with all the things that are in it, even the flocks.

16 Then all the household goods which are there, you shall gather together in the midst of its streets, and you shall set fire to these, along with the city itself, so that you may consume everything for the Lord your God, and so that it may be an everlasting tomb. It shall no longer be built up.

17 And there shall remain nothing of that anathema in your hand, so that the Lord may turn from the wrath of his fury, and may take pity on you, and may multiply you, just as he swore to your fathers,

18 when you will heed the voice of the Lord your God, keeping all his precepts, which I am entrusting to you this day, so that you may do what is pleasing in the sight of the Lord your God."

Deuteronomy 14

1 "Be sons of the Lord your God. You shall not cut yourselves, nor make yourselves bald, because of the dead.

2 For you are a holy people, for the Lord your God. And he chose you, so that you may be a people particularly his, out of all the nations on earth.

3 You shall not eat the things that are unclean.

4 These are the animals which you ought to eat: the ox, and the sheep, and the goat,

5 the stag and the roe deer, the gazelle, the wild goat, the addax, the antelope, the giraffe.

6 Every beast which has a hoof divided into two parts and which also chews the cud, you shall eat.

7 But those which chew over again, but do not have a divided hoof, you must not eat, such as the camel, the hare, and the hyrax. Since these chew the cud, but do not have a divided the hoof, they shall be unclean to you.

8 The pig also, since it has a divided hoof, but does not chew over again, shall be unclean. Their flesh shall not be eaten, and you shall not touch their carcasses.

9 These you shall eat out of all that dwells in the waters: whatever has fins and scales, you shall eat.

10 Whatever is without fins and scales, you shall not eat, for these are unclean.

11 All the clean birds, you shall eat.

12 You shall not eat those that are unclean: such as the eagle, and the griffin, and the osprey,

13 the crane, and the vulture, and the kite, according to their kind,

14 and any kind of raven,

15 and the ostrich, and the owl, and the gull, and the hawk, according to their kind,

16 the heron, and the swan, and the ibis,

17 and the sea bird, the marsh hen, and the night raven,

18 the pelican and the plover, each in their kind, likewise the crested hoopoe and the bat.

19 And anything which crawls and also has little wings shall be unclean, and shall not be eaten.

20 All that is clean, you shall eat.

21 But whatever has died of itself, you shall not eat from it. Give it to the sojourner, who is within your gates, so that he may eat, or sell it to him. For you are the holy people of the Lord your God. You shall not boil a young goat in the milk of his mother.

22 Each year, you shall separate the tithes out of all your crops which spring forth from the earth.

23 And you shall eat these in the sight of the Lord your God, in the place which he will choose, so that his name may be invoked there: the tenth part of your grain and wine and oil, and the firstborn from the herds and your sheep. So may you learn to fear the Lord your God at all times.

24 But when the way and the place which the Lord your God will have chosen is further away, and he will have blessed you, so that you are not able to carry all these things to it,

25 you shall sell them all, so as to turn them into money, and you shall carry it in your hand, and you shall set out for the place which the Lord will choose.

26 And you shall buy with the same money whatever pleases you, either from the herds or from the sheep, and also wine and liquor, and all that your soul desires. And you shall eat in the sight of the Lord your God, and you shall feast: you and your household.

27 As for the Levite, who is within your gates, take care that you do not abandon him, for he has no other portion within your possession.

28 In the third year, you shall separate another tenth part of all the things which spring forth for you at that time, and you shall store it within your gates.

29 And the Levite, who has no other portion or possession with you, and the sojourner as well as the orphan and the widow who are within your gates, shall approach and eat and be satisfied, so that the Lord your God may bless you in all the works of your hands which you shall do."

Deuteronomy 15

1 "In the seventh year, you shall perform a remission,

2 which shall be celebrated according to this order. Anyone to whom anything is owed, by his friend or neighbor or brother, will not be able to request its return, because it is the year of remission of the Lord.

3 From the sojourner and the new arrival, you may require its return. From your fellow countryman and neighbor, you will not have the power to request its return.

4 And there shall not be anyone indigent or begging among you, so that the Lord your God may bless you in the land which he will deliver to you as a possession.

5 But only if you heed the voice of the Lord your God, and keep to all that he has ordered, that which I am entrusting to you this day, will he bless you, just as he has promised.

6 You shall lend money to many nations, and you yourselves shall borrow in return from no one. You shall rule over very many nations, and no one shall rule over you.

7 If one of your brothers, who dwells within the gates of your city, in the land which the Lord your God will give to you, falls into poverty, you shall not harden your heart, nor tighten your hand.

8 Instead, you shall open your hand to the poor, and you shall lend to him whatever you perceive him to need.

9 Take care, lest perhaps an impious thought might creep within you, and you might say in your heart: 'The seventh year of remission approaches.' And so you might turn your eyes away from your poor brother, unwilling to lend to him what he has asked. If so, then he may cry out against you to the Lord, and it will be a sin for you.

10 Instead, you shall give to him. Neither shall you do anything craftily while assisting him in his needs, so that the Lord your God may bless you, at all times and in all things to which you will put your hand.

11 The poor will not be absent from the land of your habitation. For this reason, I instruct you to open your hand to your indigent and poor brother, who lives among you in the land.

12 When your brother, a Hebrew man or a Hebrew woman, has been sold to you, and has served you for six years, in the seventh year you shall set him free.

13 And when you grant his freedom, you shall by no means permit him to go away empty.

14 Instead, you shall give to him, for his journey, from your flocks and threshing floor and winepress, with which the Lord your God has blessed you.

15 Remember that you yourself also served in the land of Egypt, and the Lord your God set you free. And therefore, I now command this of you.

16 But if he will say, 'I am not willing to depart,' because he loves you and your household, and because he feels that it would be good for him to stay with you,

17 then you shall take an awl and pierce his ear, at the door of your house. And he shall serve you even forever. You shall also act similarly toward your woman servant.

18 You should not avert your eyes from them when you set them free, because he has served you for six years, in a manner deserving of the pay of a hired hand. So may the Lord your God bless you in all the works that you do.

19 Of the firstborn, those born from your herds and sheep, you shall sanctify to the Lord your God whatever is of the male sex. You shall not put the firstborn of the oxen to work, nor shall you shear the firstborn of the sheep.

20 In the sight of the Lord your God, you shall eat these, each year, in the place which the Lord will choose, you and your household.

21 But if it has a blemish, or is lame, or is blind, or if it is in any part deformed or debilitated, it shall not be immolated to the Lord your God.

22 Instead, you shall eat it within the gates of your city. The clean as well as the unclean alike shall feed on these, such as the roe deer and the stag.

23 This alone shall you observe: that you do not eat their blood, but pour it upon the ground like water."

Deuteronomy 16

1 "Observe the month of new grain, at the beginning of springtime, so that you may accomplish the Passover to the Lord your God. For in this month, the Lord your God led you away from Egypt in the night.

2 And you shall immolate the Passover to the Lord your God, from sheep and from oxen, in the place which the Lord your God will choose, so that his name may dwell there.

3 You shall not eat it with leavened bread. For seven days you shall eat, without leaven, the bread of affliction. For you departed from Egypt in fear. So may you remember the day of your departure from Egypt, throughout all the days of your life.

4 No leaven shall be present in all your confines for seven days. And by morning, there shall not remain any of the flesh which was immolated on the first day in the evening.

5 You cannot immolate the Passover in any of your cities, which the Lord your God will give to you, that you wish,

6 but only in the place which the Lord your God will choose, so that his name may dwell there. You shall immolate the Passover in the evening, upon the setting of the sun, which is the time when you departed from Egypt.

7 And you shall cook and eat it in the place which the Lord your God will choose, and, rising up in the morning, you shall go into your tent.

8 For six days, you shall eat unleavened bread. And on the seventh day, because it is the assembly of the Lord your God, you shall do no work.

9 You shall number for yourself seven weeks from that day, the day on which you put the sickle to the grain field.

10 And you shall celebrate the Feast of Weeks, to the Lord your God, with a voluntary oblation from your hand, which you shall offer according to the blessing of the Lord your God.

11 And you shall feast in the sight of the Lord your God: you, your son and your daughter, your man servant and your woman servant, and the Levite who is within your gates, and the new arrival as well as the orphan and the widow, who abide with you, in the place which the Lord your God will choose, so that his name may dwell there.

12 And you shall recall that you were a servant in Egypt. And you shall preserve and carry out the things that have been instructed.

13 Likewise, you shall celebrate the Feast of Tabernacles for seven days, when you will have gathered your fruits from the orchard and the winepress.

14 And you shall feast at the time of your festival: you, your son and daughter, your man servant and woman servant, likewise the Levite and the new arrival, the orphan and the widow, who are within your gates.

15 For seven days you shall celebrate feasts to the Lord your God in the place which the Lord will choose. And the Lord your God will bless you in all your crops, and in every work of your hands. And you shall be joyful.

16 Three times a year, all your males shall appear in the sight the Lord your God in the place which he will choose: at the Feast of Unleavened Bread, at the Feast of Weeks, and at the Feast of Tabernacles. No one shall appear before the Lord empty.

17 But each one shall offer according to what he will have, according to the blessing of the Lord his God, which he will give to him.

18 You shall appoint judges and magistrates at all your gates, which the Lord your God will give to you, throughout each of your tribes, so that they may judge the people with a just judgment,

19 and not so as to show favoritism to either side. You shall not accept a person's reputation, nor gifts. For gifts blind the eyes of the wise and alter the words of the just.

20 You shall justly pursue what is just, so that you may live and possess the land, which the Lord your God will give to you.

21 You shall not plant a sacred grove, nor shall you plant any tree near the altar of the Lord your God;

22 you shall neither make nor set up for yourself a statue. These things the Lord your God hates."

Deuteronomy 17

1 "You shall not immolate to the Lord your God a sheep or an ox, in which there is a blemish or any defect at all; for this is an abomination to the Lord your God.

2 When there will have been found among you, within one of your gates which the Lord your God will give to you, a man or a woman who is doing evil in the sight of the Lord your God, and who is transgressing his covenant,

3 so as to go and serve foreign gods and adore them, such as the sun and the moon, or any of the host of heaven, which I have not instructed,

4 and when this will have been reported to you, and, upon hearing it, if you have inquired diligently and have found it to be true, that the abomination is being done in Israel:

5 you shall lead forward the man or the woman who has perpetrated this most wicked thing to the gates of your city, and they shall be stoned to death.

6 By the mouth of two or three witnesses, he who is to be put to death shall perish. Let no one be killed with only one person speaking testimony against him.

7 First, the hands of the witnesses shall be upon him who will be put to death, and lastly, the hands of the remainder of the people shall be sent forth. So may you take away the evil from your midst.

8 If you have perceived that there is among you a difficult and doubtful matter of judgment, between blood and blood, cause and cause, leprosy and leprosy, and if you will have seen that the words of the judges within your gates vary: rise up and ascend to the place which the Lord your God will choose.

9 And you shall approach the priests of the Levitical stock, and the judge, who shall be among them at that time, and you shall inquire of them, and they will reveal to you the truth of the judgment.

10 And you shall accept whatever they will say, those who preside in the place which the Lord will choose, and whatever they will teach you,

11 in accord with his law, and you shall follow their sentence. Neither shall you turn aside to the right or to the left.

12 But whoever will be arrogant, unwilling to obey the order of the priest who ministers at that time to the Lord your God, and the decree of the judge, that man shall die. And so shall you take away the evil from Israel.

13 And when the people hear about this, they shall be afraid, so that no one, from that time on, will swell with pride.

14 When you will have entered into the land which the Lord your God will give to you, and you possess it, and you live in it, and you say, 'I will appoint a king over me, just as all the surrounding nations have done,'

15 you shall appoint him whom the Lord your God will choose from among the number of your brothers. You cannot make a man of another people king, one who is not your brother.

16 And when he will have been appointed king, he shall not multiply horses for himself, nor lead the people back into Egypt, having been exalted by the number of his horsemen, especially since the Lord has instructed you never to return along the same way.

17 He shall not have many wives, who might allure his mind, and he shall not have immense weights of silver and gold.

18 Then, after he has been seated upon the throne of his kingdom, he shall write for himself the Deuteronomy of this law in a volume, using a copy from the priests of the Levitical tribe.

19 And he shall have it with him, and he shall read it all the days of his life, so that he may learn to fear the Lord his God, and to keep his words and ceremonies, which are instructed in the law.

20 And so may his heart not become exalted with arrogance over his brothers, nor turn aside to the right or to the left, so that he and his sons may reign for a long time over Israel."

Deuteronomy 18

1 "The priests and the Levites, and all who are from the same tribe, shall have no portion or inheritance with the rest of Israel. For they shall eat the sacrifices of the Lord and his oblations.

2 And they shall receive nothing else from the possession of their brothers. For the Lord himself is their inheritance, just as he said to them.

3 This shall be the recompense for the priests from the people, and from those who offer victims, whether they will immolate an ox or a sheep. They shall give to the priest the shoulder and the breast,

4 the first-fruits of grain, wine, and oil, and a portion of the wool from the shearing of the sheep.

5 For the Lord your God himself has chosen him out of all your tribes, so that he may stand and minister to the name of the Lord, him and his sons, forever.

6 If a Levite departs from one of the cities, throughout all of Israel, in which he lives, and if he wills and desires to go to the place which the Lord will choose,

7 he shall minister in the name of the Lord his God, as do all his brothers, the Levites, who will be standing at that time in the sight of the Lord.

8 He shall receive the same portion of food as the rest also receive, besides that which is due to him in his own city, by succession from his fathers.

9 When you will have entered into the land which the Lord your God will give to you, be careful that you are not willing to imitate the abominations of those nations.

10 Do not let there be found among you one who would purify his son or daughter by leading them through fire, nor one who consults seers, nor one who observes dreams or omens. Do not let there be found among you one who practices the occult,

11 nor one who uses spells, nor one who consults demonic spirits, nor a diviner, nor one who seeks the truth from the dead.

12 For the Lord abominates all these things. And, because of these wicked ways, he will destroy them at your arrival.

13 You shall be perfect and without blemish with the Lord your God.

14 These nations, whose land you shall possess, they listen to soothsayers and diviners. But you have been otherwise instructed by the Lord your God.

15 The Lord your God will raise up for you a PROPHET from your nation and from your brothers, similar to me. You shall listen to him,

16 just as you petitioned of the Lord your God at Horeb, when the assembly was gathered together, and you said: 'Let me no longer hear the voice of the Lord my God, and let me no longer see this very great fire, lest I die.'

17 And the Lord said to me: 'They have spoken all these things well.

18 I will raise up a prophet for them, from the midst of their brothers, similar to you. And I will place my words in his mouth, and he will speak to them all the things that I will instruct him.

19 But against anyone who is not willing to listen to his words, which he will speak in my name, I will stand forth as the avenger.

20 But if a prophet, having been corrupted by arrogance, chooses to speak, in my name, things which I did not instruct him to say, or to speak in the name of foreign gods, he shall be put to death.

21 But if, in silent thought, you respond: "How will I be able to recognize a word which the Lord has not spoken?"

22 you shall have this sign. If whatever that prophet predicts in the name of the Lord does not happen, then the Lord has not spoken it. Instead, the prophet has formed it through the swelling of his own mind. And for this reason, you shall not fear him.' "

Deuteronomy 19

1 "When the Lord your God will have destroyed the nations, whose land he will deliver to you, and when you possess it and live in its cities and buildings,

2 you shall separate for yourselves three cities in the midst of the land, which the Lord will give to you as a possession,

3 paving the road carefully. And you shall divide the entire province of your land equally into three parts, so that he who is forced to flee because of manslaughter may have a place nearby to which he may be able to escape.

4 This shall be the law of the killer who flees, whose life is to be saved. Whoever strikes down his neighbor unwillingly, and who has been proven to have had no hatred against him yesterday and the day before,

5 such that he had gone with him into the forest simply to cut wood, and in cutting down the tree, the axe slipped from his hand, or the iron slipped from the handle, and it struck his friend and killed him: he shall flee to one of the cities stated above, and he shall live.

6 Otherwise, perhaps the near relative of him whose blood was shed, impelled by his grief, might pursue and apprehend him, unless the way is too long, and he might strike down the life of him who is not guilty unto death, since he had demonstrated that he had no prior hatred against him who was slain.

7 For this reason, I instruct you to separate three cities at equal distance from one another.

8 And when the Lord your God will have enlarged your borders, just as he swore to your fathers, and when he will have given to you all the land that he has promised to them,

9 (but this is only so if you will keep his commandments and do the things which I instruct to you this day, so that you love the Lord your God, and walk in his ways at all times) you shall add for yourselves three other cities, and so you shall double the number of the three cities stated above.

10 So may innocent blood not be shed in the midst of the land which the Lord your God will give you to possess, lest you be guilty of blood.

11 But if anyone, having hatred for his neighbor, will have lain in ambush for his life, and, rising up, will have struck him, and he will have died, and if he will have fled to one of the cities stated above,

12 the elders of his city shall send, and they shall take him from the place of refuge, and they shall deliver him into the hand of the relative of him whose blood was shed, and he shall die.

13 You shall not take pity on him, and so shall you take away the blood of the innocent from Israel, so that it may be well with you.

14 You shall not take up or move the landmark of your neighbor, which those before you have placed, in your possession that the Lord your God will give to you, in the land you will receive to possess.

15 One witness shall not stand against another, no matter what the sin or outrage may be. For every word shall stand by the mouth of two or three witnesses.

16 If a lying witness will have stood against a man, accusing him of a transgression,

17 both of those whose case it is shall stand before the Lord in the sight of the priests and the judges who shall be in those days.

18 And when, after a very diligent examination, they will have found that the false witness had told a lie against his brother,

19 they shall render to him just as he intended to do to his brother. And so shall you take away the evil from your midst.

20 Then the others, upon hearing this, will be afraid, and they will by no means dare to do such things.

21 You shall not take pity on him. Instead, you shall require a life for a life, an eye for an eye, a tooth for a tooth, a hand for a hand, a foot for a foot."

Deuteronomy 20

1 "If you go out to battle against your enemies, and you see horsemen and chariots, and that the multitude of your adversary's army is greater than your own, you shall not fear them. For the Lord your God, who led you away from the land of Egypt, is with you.

2 Then, as the battle now draws near, the priest shall stand before the front ranks, and he shall speak to the people in this manner:

3 'Listen, O Israel! Today you engage in a battle against your enemies. Do not let your heart be overwhelmed with fear. Do not be apprehensive. Do not yield. You should have no dread of them.

4 For the Lord your God is in your midst, and he will contend against your enemies on your behalf, so that he may rescue you from peril.'

5 Likewise, the officers shall proclaim, throughout every company, in the hearing of the soldiers: 'What man is there who has built a new house, and has not dedicated it? Let him go and return to his house, lest perhaps he may die in the battle, and another man may dedicate it.

6 What man is there who has planted a vineyard, and has not yet caused it to be common, so that all may eat from it? Let him go, and return to his house, lest perhaps he may die in the battle, and another man may carry out his office.

7 What man is there, who has betrothed a wife, and has not taken her? Let him go, and return to his house, lest perhaps he may die in battle, and another man may take her.'

8 After these things have been declared, they shall add the remainder, and shall say to the people: 'What man is there who is overwhelmed by fear and is fainthearted? Let him go, and return to his house, lest he cause the hearts of his brothers to fear, just as he himself has been thoroughly stricken with fear.'

9 And when the officers of the army have become silent, and have completed their speech, each one shall prepare his unit to wage war.

10 When, at any time, you approach a city to fight against it, you shall first offer peace to it.

11 If they receive it, and open the gates to you, then all the people who are in it shall be saved, and they shall serve you by paying tribute.

12 But if they are not willing to enter into an agreement, and they begin to act against you in warfare, then you shall besiege it.

13 And when the Lord your God will have delivered it into your hands, you shall strike down anyone who is in it, of the male gender, with the edge of the sword,

14 but not the women and young children, nor the cattle and the other things that are within the city. And you shall divide all the plunder to the soldiers, and you shall eat the spoils from your enemies, which the Lord your God will give to you.

15 So shall you do to all the cities which are at a great distance from you, those which are not among the cities that you shall receive as a possession.

16 But among those cities which shall be given to you, you shall not permit anyone at all to live.

17 Instead, you shall put them to death with the edge of the sword, specifically: the Hittite and the Amorite and the Canaanite, the Perizzite and the Hivite and the Jebusite, just as the Lord your God has commanded you.

18 Otherwise, they may teach you to do all the abominations which they have committed for their own gods. And then you would sin against the Lord your God.

19 When you will have besieged a city for a long time, and you will have encircled it with fortifications, so that you may fight against it, you shall not cut down trees from which one is able to eat, neither shall you cause devastation with axes to the surrounding region. For it is a tree, and not a man. It is not able to increase the number of those who are fighting against you.

20 But if there are any trees which are not fruitful, but are wild, and if these are fit for other uses, then cut them down, and make machines, until you have captured the city that is contending against you."

Deuteronomy 21

1 "When there will have been found in the land, which the Lord your God will give to you, the corpse of a man who has been killed, and it is not known who is guilty of the murder,

2 your judges and those greater by birth shall go out and measure, from the place of the corpse, the distance to each of the surrounding cities.

3 And in whichever one they perceive to be closer than the others, the elders shall take a calf from the herd, one which has not pulled with a yoke, nor tilled with a plow.

4 And they shall lead it into a rough and stony valley, one which has never been tilled or sown. And in that place, they shall cut the neck of the calf.

5 And the priests the sons of Levi shall approach, those whom the Lord your God has chosen to minister to him, and to bless in his name, and to decide every controversy by their word, and to judge which things are clean and which are unclean.

6 And those greater by birth of that city, nearest to the one who was slain, shall go and shall wash their hands over the calf that was killed in the valley.

7 And they shall say: 'Our hands did not shed this blood, nor did our eyes see it.

8 Be merciful to your people Israel, whom you have redeemed, O Lord, and do not charge them with innocent blood in the midst of your people Israel.' And so the guilt of the blood will be taken away from them.

9 Then you will be free from the blood that was shed against the innocent, when you will have done as the Lord has instructed you.

10 If you have gone out to fight against your enemies, and the Lord your God has delivered them into your hand, and if, as you are leading away the captives,

11 you see among the number of the captives a beautiful woman, and you love her, and you are willing to have her as a wife:

12 then you shall lead her into your house. And she shall shave off her hair, and cut her nails short,

13 and remove the garment in which she was captured. And she shall sit in your house and weep for her father and mother, for one month. And after that, you shall enter to her and sleep with her, and she shall be your wife.

14 But if afterwards she does not sit well in your mind, you shall set her free. You cannot sell her for money, nor can you oppress her by force. For you have humiliated her.

15 If a man has two wives, one beloved and the other hated, and they have produced children by him, and if the son of the hated wife is the firstborn,

16 and if he wishes to divide his substance among his sons: he cannot make the son of the beloved wife the firstborn, and so prefer him before the son of the hated wife.

17 Instead, he shall acknowledge the son of the hated wife as the firstborn, and he shall give to him a double portion of all that he has. For he is the first among his children, and the rights of the firstborn are owed to him.

18 If a man produces a disobedient and reckless son, who will not listen to the orders of his father or mother, and, having been corrected, shows contempt for obedience:

19 they shall take him and lead him to the elders of the city and to the gate of judgment.

20 And they shall say to them: 'This our son is reckless and disobedient. He shows contempt when listening to our admonitions. He occupies himself with carousing, and self-indulgence, and feasting.'

21 Then the people of the city shall stone him to death. And he shall die, so that you may take away the evil from your midst. And so may all of Israel, upon hearing it, be very afraid.

22 When a man will have sinned in a matter which is punished by death, and, having been judged unto death, he has been hanged on a gallows:

23 his corpse shall not remain on the tree. Instead, he shall be buried on the same day. For he who hangs from a tree has been cursed by God, and you shall not defile your land, which the Lord your God will give to you as a possession."

Deuteronomy 22

1 "If you see your brother's ox or sheep wander astray, you shall not pass by. Instead, you shall lead them back to your brother.

2 But if your brother is not near, or you do not know him, you shall lead them to your house, and they shall be with you until your brother seeks them and receives them.

3 You shall act in a similar manner with his donkey, and his clothing, and all the belongings of your brother that have been lost. If you find it, you shall not neglect it, as if it belonged to a stranger.

4 If you see that your brother's donkey or ox has fallen along the way, you shall not disregard it. Instead, you shall lift it up with him.

5 A woman shall not be clothed with manly apparel, nor shall a man make use of feminine apparel. For whoever does these things is abominable with God.

6 If, as you are walking along the way, you find a bird's nest, in a tree or on the ground, and the mother is nurturing the young or the eggs, you shall not take her with her young.

7 Instead, you shall permit her to go, retaining the young that you have caught, so that it may be well with you, and you may live for a long time.

8 When you build a new house, you shall make a wall around the roof. Otherwise, someone may slip and fall down violently, and so blood would be shed at your house, and you would be guilty.

9 You shall not sow your vineyard with another seed, lest both the seed that you have sown and what springs forth from the vineyard be sanctified together.

10 You shall not till with an ox and a donkey at the same time.

11 You shall not wear a vestment which has been woven from both wool and linen.

12 You shall make strings along the hem, at the four corners of your cloak, which covers you.

13 If a man takes a wife, and afterwards he has hatred for her,

14 and so he seeks opportunities to dismiss her, imputing a very wicked name to her by saying, 'I received this woman as a wife, and upon entering to her, I found her not to be a virgin,'

15 then her father and mother shall take her, and they shall bring with them the signs of her virginity, to the elders of the city who are at the gate.

16 And the father shall say: 'I gave my daughter to this man as a wife. And because he hates her,

17 he accuses her with a very wicked name, by saying: "I did not find your daughter to be a virgin." But behold, these are the signs of my daughter's virginity.' And they shall spread the clothing before the elders of the city.

18 And the elders of that city shall apprehend that man and beat him.

19 Moreover, they shall fine him one hundred shekels of silver, which he will give to the father of the girl, because he has committed slander, with a very wicked name, against a virgin of Israel. And he shall have her as a wife, and he cannot dismiss her throughout all the days of his life.

20 But if what he has claimed is true and virginity is not found in the girl,

21 then they shall throw her down, outside the doors of her father's house, and the men of that city shall stone her to death, and she shall die. For she has acted wickedly in Israel, in that she fornicated in her father's house. And so shall you take away the evil from your midst.

22 If a man sleeps with the wife of another, then they shall both die, that is, the adulterer and the adulteress. And so shall you take away the evil from Israel.

23 If a man has betrothed a girl who is a virgin, and if someone finds her in the city and he lies with her,

24 then you shall lead them both out to the gate of that city, and they shall be stoned to death: the girl, because she did not cry out though she was in the city; the man, because he has humiliated the wife of his neighbor. And so shall you take away the evil from your midst.

25 But if a man discovers, in the countryside, a girl who has been betrothed, and, apprehending her, he lies with her, then he alone shall die.

26 The girl shall suffer nothing, nor is she guilty unto death. For just as a robber rises up against his brother and slays his life, so also did the girl suffer greatly.

27 She was alone in the field. She cried out, and there was no one nearby, who might deliver her.

28 If a man find a girl who is a virgin, who does not have a betrothal, and, taking her, he lies with her, and the matter is brought to judgment,

29 then he who slept with her shall give to the father of the girl fifty shekels of silver, and he shall have her as a wife, because he has humiliated her. He cannot dismiss her, throughout all the days of his life.

30 No man shall take his father's wife, nor remove her covering."

Deuteronomy 23

1 "A eunuch, one whose testicles have been debilitated or cut off, or whose penis has been cut off, shall not enter into the church of the Lord.

2 The offspring of a harlot, that is, one born of a prostitute, shall not enter into the church of the Lord, until the tenth generation.

3 The Ammonite and the Moabite, even after the tenth generation, shall not enter into the church of the Lord forever,

4 because they were not willing to meet you with bread and water along the way, when you had departed from Egypt, and because they hired against you Balaam, the son of Beor, from Mesopotamia in Syria, in order to curse you.

5 But the Lord your God was not willing to listen to Balaam, and he turned his cursing into your blessing, because he loves you.

6 You shall not make peace with them, nor shall you seek their prosperity, throughout all the days of your life forever.

7 You shall not abhor anyone from Idumea, for he is your brother, nor the Egyptian, for you were a new arrival in his land.

8 Those who have been born of them, in the third generation, shall enter into the church of the Lord.

9 When you have gone out to war against your enemies, you shall keep yourself from everything that is evil.

10 If there is a man among you who has been defiled by a dream in the night, he shall depart from the camp.

11 And he shall not return before the evening, after he has washed with water, and then, after the sun sets, he shall return to the camp.

12 You shall have a place beyond the camp to which you may go for the necessities of nature,

13 carrying a small shovel at your belt. And when you would sit down, you shall dig around, and then, with the soil that was dug up, you shall cover

14 that from which you were relieved. For the Lord your God walks in the midst of your camp, in order to rescue you, and to deliver your enemies to you. And so, let your camp be holy, and let nothing filthy appear within it, lest he abandon you.

15 You shall not deliver a servant who has fled to you to his master.

16 He shall live with you in a place that pleases him, and he shall rest in one of your cities. You shall not grieve him.

17 There shall be no prostitutes among the daughters of Israel, nor anyone among the sons of Israel who visits a prostitute.

18 You shall not offer money from a prostitute, nor the price of a dog, in the house of the Lord your God, no matter what you may have vowed. For both of these are an abomination with the Lord your God.

19 You shall not lend money, or grain, or anything else at all, to your brother at interest,

20 but only to a foreigner. For you shall lend to your brother whatever he needs without interest, so that the Lord your God may bless you in all your works in the land, which you shall enter so as to possess it.

21 When you have made a vow to the Lord your God, you shall not be late in paying it. For the Lord your God demands it. And if you delay, it shall be imputed to you as a sin.

22 If you are not willing to make a promise, then it shall be without sin.

23 But as soon as it has departed from your lips, you shall observe and do just as you have promised to the Lord your God and just as you have spoken by your own free will and with your own mouth.

24 Upon entering your neighbor's vineyard, you may eat as many grapes as you please. But you may not carry any out with you.

25 If you enter into your friend's grain field, you may break off the ears, and rub them in your hand, but you may not reap them with a sickle."

Deuteronomy 24

1 "If a man takes a wife, and he has her, and she does not find favor before his eyes because of some vileness, then he shall write a bill of divorce, and he shall give it to her hand, and he shall dismiss her from his house.

2 And when, having departed, she has married another,

3 and if he likewise hates her, and has given her a bill of divorce, and has dismissed her from his house, or if indeed he has died,

4 then the former husband cannot take her back as a wife. For she has been polluted and has become abominable in the sight of the Lord. Otherwise, you may cause your land, which the Lord your God will deliver to you as a possession, to sin.

5 When a man has recently taken a wife, he shall not go out to war, nor shall any public office be enjoined upon him. Instead, he shall be free at home without guilt, so that for one year he may rejoice with his wife.

6 You shall not accept an upper or lower millstone as collateral. For then he will have placed his life with you.

7 If a man has been caught soliciting his brother among the sons of Israel, and selling him in order to receive a price, then he shall be put to death. And so shall you take away the evil from your midst.

8 Observe diligently, lest you incur the wound of leprosy. But you shall do whatever the priests of the Levitical stock shall teach you to do, according to what I have instructed them. And you shall fulfill it carefully.

9 Remember what the Lord your God did to Miriam, along the way, as you were departing from Egypt.

10 When you require from your neighbor anything that he owes to you, you shall not enter into his house in order to take away the collateral.

11 Instead, you shall stand outside, and he will carry out to you what he has.

12 But if he is poor, then the collateral shall not remain with you through the night.

13 Instead, you shall return it to him promptly, before the setting of the sun, so that, sleeping in his own garment, he may bless you, and you may have justice in the presence of the Lord your God.

14 You shall not refuse the pay of the indigent and the poor, whether he is your brother, or he is a new arrival who dwells with you in the land and is within your gates.

15 Instead, you shall pay him the price of his labor on the same day, before the setting of the sun. For he is poor, and with it he sustains his life. Otherwise, he may cry out against you to the Lord, and it would be charged to you as a sin.

16 The fathers shall not be put to death on behalf of the sons, nor the sons on behalf of the fathers, but each one shall die for his own sin.

17 You shall not pervert the judgment of the new arrival or the orphan, nor shall you take away the widow's garment as collateral.

18 Remember that you served in Egypt, and that the Lord your God rescued you from there. Therefore, I am instructing you to act in this way.

19 When you have reaped the grain in your field, and, having forgotten, you leave behind a sheaf, you shall not return to take it away. Instead, you shall permit the new arrival, and the orphan, and the widow to take it away, so that the Lord your God may bless you in all the works of your hands.

20 If you have gathered the fruit of your olive trees, you shall not return in order to gather whatever may remain on the trees. Instead, you shall leave it behind for the new arrival, the orphan, and the widow.

21 If you harvest the vintage of your vineyard, you shall not gather the remaining clusters. Instead, they shall fall to the use of the stranger, the orphan, and the widow.

22 Remember that you also served in Egypt, and so, for this reason, I am instructing you to act in this way."

Deuteronomy 25

1 "If there is a case between persons, and they apply to the judges, they shall give the palm of justice to the one whom they perceive to be just, and they shall condemn of impiety the one who is impious.

2 But if they see that the one who has sinned is worthy of stripes, they shall prostrate him and cause him to be beaten before them. According to the measure of the sin, so shall the measure of the stripes be.

3 Even so, these shall not exceed the number of forty. Otherwise, your brother may depart, having been wounded shamefully before your eyes.

4 You shall not muzzle an ox as it is treading out your crops in the field.

5 When brothers are living together, and one of them dies without children, the wife of the deceased shall not marry another. Instead, his brother shall take her, and he shall raise up offspring for his brother.

6 And the first son from her, he shall call by his brother's name, so that his name will not be abolished from Israel.

7 But if he is not willing to take his brother's wife, who by law must go to him, the woman shall go to the gate of the city, and she shall call upon those greater by birth, and she shall say: 'The brother of my husband is not willing to raise up his brother's name in Israel; nor will he join with me.'

8 And immediately, they shall summon him to be sent, and they shall question him. If he responds, 'I am not willing to accept her as a wife,'

9 then the woman shall approach him in the sight of the elders, and she shall remove his shoe from his foot, and she shall spit in his face, and she shall say: 'So shall it be done to the man who was not willing to build up his brother's house.'

10 And his name shall be called in Israel: The House of the Unshod.

11 If two men have a conflict between themselves, and one begins to do violence to the other, and if the other's wife, wanting to rescue her husband from the hand of the stronger one, extends her hand and grasps him by his private parts,

12 then you shall cut off her hand. Neither shall you weep over her with any mercy.

13 You shall not have differing weights, greater and lesser, in your bag.

14 Neither shall there be in your house a greater and a lesser measure.

15 You shall have a just and a true weight, and your measure shall be equal and true, so that you may live for a long time upon the land, which the Lord your God will give to you.

16 For the Lord your God abominates him who does these things, and he loathes all injustice.

17 Remember what Amalek did to you, along the way, when you were departing from Egypt:

18 how he met you and cut down the stragglers of the troops, who were sitting down, exhausted, when you were consumed by hunger and hardship, and how he did not fear God.

19 Therefore, when the Lord your God will give you rest, and you will have subdued all the surrounding nations, in the land which he has promised to you, you shall delete his name from under heaven. Take care not to forget this."

Deuteronomy 26

1 "And when you will have entered into the land which the Lord your God will give to you to possess, and when you will have obtained it and are living within it:

2 you shall take the first of all your crops, and place them in a basket, and you shall travel to the place which the Lord your God will choose, so that his name may be invoked there.

3 And you shall approach the priest who will be in those days, and you shall say to him: 'I profess this day, before the Lord your God, that I have entered into the land about which he swore to our fathers that he would give it to us.'

4 And the priest, taking up the basket from your hand, shall place it before the altar of the Lord your God.

5 And you shall say, in the sight of the Lord your God: 'The Syrian pursued my father, who descended into Egypt, and he sojourned there in a very small number, and he increased into a great and strong nation and into an innumerable multitude.

6 And the Egyptians afflicted us, and they persecuted us, imposing upon us the most grievous burdens.

7 And we cried out to the Lord, the God of our fathers. He heard us, and he looked with favor upon our humiliation, and hardship, and distress.

8 And he led us away from Egypt, with a strong hand and an outstretched arm, with a mighty terror, with signs and wonders.

9 And he led us into this place, and he delivered to us the land flowing with milk and honey.

10 And because of this, I now offer the first fruits of the land which the Lord has given to me.' And you shall leave them in the sight of the Lord your God, and you shall adore the Lord your God.

11 And you shall feast on all the good things which the Lord your God will give to you and to your house: you, and the Levite, and the new arrival who is with you.

12 When you will have completed the tithing of all your crops, in the third year of tithes, you shall give it to the Levite, and to the new arrival, and to the orphan, and to the widow, so that they may eat within your gates and be satisfied.

13 And you shall say, in the sight of the Lord your God: 'I have taken what was sanctified from my house, and I have given it to the Levite, and to the new arrival, and to the orphan and the widow, just as you have commanded me. I have not transgressed your commandments, nor have I forgotten your precepts.

14 I have not eaten from these things in my grief, nor have I separated them due to any kind of uncleanness, nor have I expended any of these things in funerals. I have obeyed the voice of the Lord my God, and I have done all things just as you have instructed me.

15 Look with favor from your sanctuary and from your lofty habitation amid the heavens, and bless your people Israel and the land which you have given to us, just as you swore to our fathers, a land flowing with milk and honey.'

16 Today the Lord your God has instructed you to carry out these commandments and judgments, and to keep and fulfill them, with all your heart and with all your soul.

17 Today, you have chosen the Lord to be your God, so that you may walk in his ways, and keep his ceremonies and commandments and judgments, and obey his command.

18 Today, the Lord has chosen you, so that you may be his particular people, just as he has spoken to you, and so that you may keep all his precepts,

19 and so that he may cause you to be more exalted than all the nations which he has created, for the sake of his own praise and name and glory, in order that you may be a holy people for the Lord your God, just as he has spoken."

Deuteronomy 27

1 Then Moses and the elders of Israel instructed the people, saying: "Keep each commandment that I instruct to you this day.

2 And when you have crossed over the Jordan, into the land which the Lord your God will give to you, you shall erect immense stones, and you shall coat them with plaster,

3 so that you may be able to write upon them all the words of this law, when you have crossed the Jordan so as to enter into the land which the Lord your God will give to you, a land flowing with milk and honey, just as he swore to your fathers.

4 Therefore, when you have crossed over the Jordan, erect the stones, just as I instruct you to do this day, on Mount Ebal. And you shall coat them with plaster,

5 and you shall build, in that place, an altar to the Lord your God out of stones which have not been touched by iron,

6 out of stones which have not been hewn or polished. And you shall offer holocausts on it to the Lord your God.

7 And you shall immolate peace victims. And you shall eat and feast in that place, in the sight of the Lord your God.

8 And you shall write upon the stones all the words of this law, plainly and clearly."

9 And Moses and the priests of Levitical stock said to all of Israel: "Attend and listen, O Israel! Today you have become the people of the Lord your God.

10 You shall listen to his voice, and you shall do the commandments and justices, which I am entrusting to you."

11 And Moses instructed the people in that day, saying:

12 "These shall stand upon Mount Gerizim, as a blessing to the people, when you will have crossed the Jordan: Simeon, Levi, Judah, Issachar, Joseph, and Benjamin.

13 And in the opposite region, there shall stand upon Mount Ebal, as a curse: Reuben, Gad, and Asher, and Zebulun, Dan, and Naphtali.

14 And the Levites shall pronounce and declare to all the men of Israel, with an exalted voice:

15 Cursed be the man who makes a graven or molten idol, an abomination to the Lord, a work of the hands of its maker, and who puts it in a secret place. And all the people shall respond by saying: Amen.

16 Cursed be he who does not honor his father and mother. And all the people shall say: Amen.

17 Cursed be he who removes his neighbor's landmarks. And all the people shall say: Amen.

18 Cursed be he who causes the blind to go astray on a journey. And all the people shall say: Amen.

19 Cursed be he who subverts the judgment of the new arrival, the orphan, or the widow. And all the people shall say: Amen.

20 Cursed be he who lies with his father's wife, and so exposes the covering of his bed. And all the people shall say: Amen.

21 Cursed be he who lies with any beast. And all the people shall say: Amen.

22 Cursed be he who lies with his sister, the daughter of his father, or of his mother. And all the people shall say: Amen.

23 Cursed be he who lies with his mother-in-law. And all the people shall say: Amen.

24 Cursed be he who secretly strikes down his neighbor. And all the people shall say: Amen.

25 Cursed be he who accepts gifts in order to strike down the life of innocent blood. And all the people shall say: Amen.

26 Cursed be he who does not remain in the words of this law, and does not carry them out in deed. And all the people shall say: Amen."

Deuteronomy 28

1 "So then, if you will listen to the voice of the Lord your God, so as to keep and do all of his commandments, which I instruct to you this day, the Lord your God will cause you to be more exalted than all the nations which exist upon the earth.

2 And all these blessings shall come to you and take hold of you, but only if you listen to his precepts.

3 Blessed shall you be in the city, and blessed in the field.

4 Blessed shall be the fruit of your loins, and the fruit of your land, and the fruit of your cattle, the droves of your herds, and the folds of your sheep.

5 Blessed shall be your barns, and blessed your storehouses.

6 Blessed shall you be entering and departing.

7 The Lord will grant that your enemies, who rise up against you, will fall down in your sight. They will come against you by one way, and they will flee from your face by seven ways.

8 The Lord will send forth a blessing upon your cellars, and upon all the works of your hands. And he will bless you in the land that you shall receive.

9 The Lord will raise you up as a holy people for himself, just as he swore to you, if you will keep the commandments of the Lord your God, and walk in his ways.

10 And all the peoples of the earth shall see that the name of the Lord has been invoked over you, and they shall fear you.

11 The Lord will cause you be abundant in every good thing: in the fruit of your womb, and in the fruit of your cattle, and in the fruit of your land, which the Lord swore to your fathers that he would give to you.

12 The Lord will open his excellent treasury, the heavens, so that it may distribute rain in due time. And he will bless all the works of your hands. And you shall lend to many nations, but you yourself will borrow nothing from anyone.

13 And the Lord will appoint you as the head, and not as the tail. And you shall be always above, and not beneath. But only if you will listen to the commandments of the Lord your God, which I entrust to you this day, and will keep and do them,

14 and will not turn aside from them, neither to the right, nor to the left, nor follow strange gods, nor worship them.

15 But if you are not willing to listen to the voice of the Lord your God, so as to keep and do all his commandments and ceremonies, which I instruct to you this day, all these curses shall come to you, and take hold of you.

16 Cursed shall you be in the city, cursed in the field.

17 Cursed shall be your barn, and cursed your storehouses.

18 Cursed shall be the fruit of your loins, and the fruit of your land, the herds of your oxen, and the flocks of your sheep.

19 Cursed shall you be entering, and cursed departing.

20 The Lord will send famine and hunger upon you, and a rebuke upon all the works that you do, until he quickly crushes and perishes you, because of your very wicked innovations, by which you have forsaken me.

21 May the Lord join a pestilence to you, until he consumes you from the land, which you shall enter so as to possess.

22 May the Lord strike you with destitution, with fever and cold, with burning and heat, and with polluted air and rot, and may he pursue you until you perish.

23 May the heavens which are above you be of brass, and may the ground upon which you tread be of iron.

24 May the Lord give you dust instead of rain upon your land, and may ashes descend from heaven over you, until you have been wiped away.

25 May the Lord hand you over to fall before your enemies. May you go forth against them by one way, and flee by seven ways, and may you be scattered across all the kingdoms of the earth.

26 And may your carcass be food for all the flying things of the air and the wild beasts of the land, and may there be no one to drive them away.

27 May the Lord strike you with the ulcer of Egypt, and may he strike the part of your body, through which the dung goes out, with disease as well as itch, so much so that you are unable to be cured.

28 May the Lord strike you with frenzy and blindness and a madness of the mind.

29 And may you grope at midday, just as a blind man is accustomed to grope in darkness, and may your paths not be straight. And at all times may you suffer slander and be oppressed with violence, and may you have no one who may free you.

30 May you take a wife, though another sleeps with her. May you build a house, but not live within it. May you plant a vineyard, and not gather its vintage.

31 May your ox be immolated before you, though you do not eat from it. May your donkey be seized in your sight, and not restored to you. May your sheep be given to your enemies, and may there be no one who may help you.

32 May your sons and your daughters be handed over to another people, as your eyes watch and languish at the sight of them throughout the day, and may there be no strength in your hand.

33 May a people you do not know eat the fruits of your land and of all your labors. And may you continually suffer from slander and oppression every day.

34 And may you be stupefied at the terror of the things your eyes will see.

35 May the Lord strike you with a very grievous ulcer in the knees and in the legs, and may you be unable to attain health, from the sole of the foot to the top of the head.

36 May the Lord lead you and your king, whom you will have appointed over yourself, into a nation which you and your fathers have not known. And there you will serve foreign gods, of wood and of stone.

37 And you will become nothing but a proverb and a fable to all the peoples to whom the Lord will lead you.

38 You will sow much seed upon the ground, but you will harvest little. For the locusts will devour everything.

39 You will dig and plant a vineyard, but you will not drink the wine, nor gather anything at all from it. For it will be devastated by worms.

40 You will have olive trees in all your borders, but you will not be anointed with the oil. For the olives will fall off and perish.

41 You will conceive sons and daughters, and you will not enjoy them. For they will be led into captivity.

42 Rot will consume all the trees, as well as the fruits of your land.

43 The new arrival who lives with you in the land will ascend over you, and be higher. But you will descend, and be lower.

44 He will lend to you, and you will not lend to him. He will be as the head, and you will be as the tail.

45 And all these curses shall come to you, and shall pursue you, and shall take hold of you, until you pass away, because you would not listen to the voice of the Lord your God, and you would not serve his commandments and ceremonies, which he has instructed to you.

46 And there will be the signs and portents with you, and with your offspring, forever.

47 Because you did not serve the Lord your God, with gladness and a joyful heart, over the abundance of all things.

48 You will serve your enemy, whom the Lord will send to you, in hunger and thirst and nakedness, and in destitution of all things. And he will place an iron yoke upon your neck, until he has crushed you.

49 The Lord will lead over you a nation from far away, even from the furthest parts of the earth, like an eagle flying with great force, whose language you are not able to understand:

50 a very insolent nation, which will show no deference to elders, nor take pity on little ones.

51 And he will devour the fruit of your cattle, and the fruits of your land, until you have passed away, without leaving behind you wheat, or wine, or oil, or herds of oxen, or flocks of sheep: until he utterly destroys you.

52 And he will crush you in all your cities. And your strong and lofty walls, in which you trusted, will be destroyed throughout all your land. You will be besieged within your gates throughout all your land, which the Lord your God will give to you.

53 And you will eat the fruit of your womb, and the flesh of your sons and of your daughters, which the Lord your God will give to you, due to the anguish and devastation with which your enemy will oppress you.

54 The man who is pampered and very self-indulgent among you will vie with his own brother, and with the wife who lies at his bosom,

55 lest he give to them from the flesh of his sons, which he will eat. For he has nothing else due to the siege and the destitution, with which your enemies will devastate you within all your gates.

56 The tender and pampered woman, who would not walk upon the soil, nor step firmly with her foot due to her very great softness and tenderness, will vie with her husband, who lies at her bosom, over the flesh of son and of daughter,

57 and over the filth of the afterbirth, which goes forth from between her thighs, and over the children who are born in the same hour. For they will eat them secretly, due to the scarcity of all things during the siege and the devastation, with which your enemy will oppress you within your gates.

58 If you will not keep and do all the words of this law, which have been written in this volume, and fear his glorious and terrible name, that is, the Lord your God,

59 then the Lord will increase your plagues, and the plagues of your offspring, plagues great and long-lasting, infirmities very grievous and continuous.

60 And he will turn back upon you all the afflictions of Egypt, which you fear, and these will cling to you.

61 In addition, the Lord will lead over you all the diseases and plagues that are not written in the volume of this law, until he crushes you.

62 And you will remain few in number, though you were before like the stars of heaven in multitude, because you would not listen to the voice of the Lord your God.

63 And just as before, when the Lord rejoiced over you, doing good for you and multiplying you, so shall he rejoice, scattering and overturning you, so as to take you away from the land, which you shall enter in order to possess.

64 The Lord will disperse you among all the peoples, from the heights of the earth to its furthest limits. And there you will serve foreign gods of wood and of stone, which you and your fathers did not know.

65 Similarly, you will not have tranquility, even within those nations, nor will there be any rest for the steps of your feet. For the Lord will give to you in that place a fearful heart, and failing eyes, and a life consumed with grieving.

66 And your life will be as if it were hanging before you. You will be afraid night and day, and you will not have confidence in your own life.

67 In the morning you will say, 'Who will grant evening to me?' and at evening, 'Who will grant morning to me?' because of the dread of your heart, with which you will be terrified, and because of those things that you will see with your eyes.

68 The Lord will lead you back into Egypt with a fleet of ships, along the way, about which he said to you that you would not see it again. In that place, you will be put up for sale as men and women servants to your enemies, but there will be no one willing to buy you."

Deuteronomy 29

1 These are the words of the covenant which the Lord instructed Moses to form with the sons of Israel in the land of Moab, beside that covenant which he struck with them at Horeb.

2 And Moses called all of Israel, and he said to them: "You have seen all the things that the Lord has done in your sight in the land of Egypt to Pharaoh, and to all his servants, and to his entire land:

3 the great trials, which your eyes have seen, those immense signs and wonders.

4 But the Lord has not given you an understanding heart, and seeing eyes, and ears that are able to hear, even to this present day.

5 He led you for forty years through the desert. Your garments have not been worn out, nor have the shoes on your feet been consumed by age.

6 You did not eat bread, nor did you drink wine or liquor, so that you would know that I am the Lord your God.

7 And you arrived at this place. And Sihon, the king of Heshbon, and Og, the king of Bashan, went out to meet us in battle. And we struck them down.

8 And we took their land and delivered it as a possession to Ruben and to Gad, and to half of the tribe of Manasseh.

9 Therefore, keep the words of this covenant, and fulfill them, so that you may understand all that you are doing.

10 Today, you all stand in the sight of the Lord your God: your leaders, and tribes, and those greater by birth, and teachers, all the people of Israel,

11 your children and wives, and the new arrival who dwells with you in the camp, aside from those who cut wood, and those who bring water,

12 so that you may cross into the covenant of the Lord your God, and into the oath which the Lord your God strikes with you today.

13 So shall he raise you up as a people to himself, and so shall he be your God, just as he has spoken to you, and just as he swore to your fathers: Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob.

14 And I am not forming this covenant and confirm these oaths with you alone,

15 but with all those who are present as well as those who are absent.

16 For you know how we lived in the land of Egypt, and how we passed through the midst of nations. And when passing through them,

17 you saw their abominations and filth, that is, their idols of wood and of stone, of silver and of gold, which they worshipped,

18 so that there would not be among you man or woman, family or tribe, whose heart has been turned away this day from the Lord our God, so as to go and serve the gods of those nations. For then there would be among you a root springing forth gall and bitterness.

19 And if he were to hear the words of this oath, he would bless himself in his own heart saying: 'There will be peace for me, and I will walk in the depravity of my heart.' And so, the one who is inebriated would consume the one who is thirsty.

20 But the Lord would not ignore him. Instead, at that time, his fury and zealousness would be very greatly enflamed against that man, and all the curses which have been written in this volume would settle upon him. And the Lord would abolish his name from under heaven,

21 and consume him unto perdition out of all the tribes of Israel, according to the curses which are contained in the book of this law and in the covenant.

22 And the subsequent generation would speak out, along with the sons who will be born afterward. And the sojourners, who will arrive from far away, will see the plagues of that land and the infirmities with which the Lord will have afflicted it,

23 having burned it with sulphur and molten salt, so that it can no longer be sown. And certainly no greenery would spring up, as in the example of the destruction of Sodom and Gomorrah, Admah and Zeboiim, which the Lord overturned with his wrath and fury.

24 And so, all the nations would say: 'Why has the Lord acted this way toward this land? What is this immense wrath of his fury?'

25 And they will respond: 'Because they abandoned the covenant of the Lord, which he formed with their fathers, when he led them away from the land of Egypt.

26 And they have served foreign gods, and adored them, though they did not know them, and though they had not been allotted to them.

27 For this reason, the fury of the Lord was enraged against this land, so as to lead over it all the curses which have been written in this volume.

28 And he has cast them out of their own land, with anger and fury, and with a very great indignation, and he has thrown them into a strange land, just as has been proven this day.'

29 These hidden things of the Lord our God have been revealed to us and to our sons in perpetuity, so that we may accomplish all the words of this law."

Deuteronomy 30

1 "Now when all these things will have fallen over you, the blessing or the curse that I have set forth in your sight, and you will have been led to repentance in your heart among all the nations to which the Lord your God will have dispersed you,

2 and when you will have returned to him, so as to obey his commandments, just as I have instructed you this day, with your sons, with your whole heart and with your whole soul,

3 then the Lord your God will lead you away from your captivity, and he will take pity on you, and he will gather you again from all the nations to which he had dispersed you before.

4 Even if you will have been scattered as far as the poles of the heavens, the Lord your God will retrieve you from there.

5 And he will take you up and lead you into the land which your fathers had possessed, and you shall obtain it. And in blessing you, he will make you greater in number than your fathers ever were.

6 The Lord your God will circumcise your heart, and the heart of your offspring, so that you may love the Lord your God with your entire heart and with your entire soul, so that you may be able to live.

7 And he will turn all these curses upon your enemies, and upon those who hate and persecute you.

8 But you shall return, and you shall listen to the voice of the Lord your God. And you shall carry out all the commandments which I am entrusting to you this day.

9 And the Lord your God will cause you to abound in all the works of your hands, in the progeny of your womb, and in the fruit of your cattle, in the fertility of your land, and with an abundance of all things. For the Lord will return, so that he may rejoice over you in all good things, just as he rejoiced in your fathers:

10 but only if you will listen to the voice of the Lord your God, and keep his precepts and ceremonies, which have been written in this law, and only if you return to the Lord your God with all your heart and with all your soul.

11 This commandment, which I entrust to you today, is not high above you, nor has it been placed far away.

12 Nor is it in heaven, so that you would be able to say, 'Which of us can ascend to heaven, so as to carry it back to us, and so that we may hear it and fulfill it in deed?'

13 Nor is it beyond the sea, so that you would excuse yourself by saying, 'Which of us is able to cross the sea, and to carry it back to us, so that we may be able to hear and to do what has been instructed?'

14 Instead, the word is near to you, in your mouth and in your heart, so that you may do it.

15 Consider what I have set forth in your sight this day, life and good, or, on the opposite side, death and evil,

16 so that you may love the Lord your God, and walk in his ways, and keep his commandments and ceremonies and judgments, and so that you may live, and he may multiply you and bless you in the land, which you shall enter in order to possess.

17 But if your heart will have been turned aside, so that you are not willing to listen, and, having been deceived by error, you adore strange gods and serve them,

18 then I predict to you this day that you will perish, and you will remain for only a short time in the land, for which you shall cross the Jordan, and which you shall enter in order to possess.

19 I call heaven and earth as witnesses this day, that I have set before you life and death, blessing and curse. Therefore, choose life, so that both you and your offspring may live,

20 and so that you may love the Lord your God, and obey his voice, and cling to him, (for he is your life and the length of your days) and so that you may live in the land, about which the Lord swore to your fathers, Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, that he would give it to them."

Deuteronomy 31

1 And so, Moses went out, and he spoke all these words to all of Israel.

2 And he said to them: "Today, I am one hundred and twenty years old. I am no longer able to go out and return, especially since the Lord has also said to me, 'You shall not cross this Jordan.'

3 Therefore, the Lord your God will go across before you. He himself will abolish all these nations in your sight, and you shall possess them. And this man Joshua shall go across before you, just as the Lord has spoken.

4 And the Lord will do to them just as he did to Sihon and Og, the kings of the Amorites, and to their land, and he will wipe them away.

5 Therefore, when the Lord will have delivered these to you also, you shall act similarly toward them, just as I have instructed you.

6 Act manfully and be strengthened. Do not be afraid, and do not dread at the sight of them. For the Lord your God himself is your commander, and he will neither dismiss nor abandon you."

7 And Moses called Joshua, and, before all of Israel, he said to him: 'Be strong and valiant. For you shall lead this people into the land which the Lord swore that he would give to their fathers, and you shall divide it by lot.

8 And the Lord, who is your commander, will himself be with you. He will neither renounce nor abandon you. Do not be afraid, and do not dread."

9 And so, Moses wrote this law, and he handed it to the priests, the sons of Levi, who carried the ark of the covenant of the Lord, and to all the elders of Israel.

10 And he instructed them, saying: "After seven years, in the year of remission, at the solemnity of the Feast of Tabernacles,

11 when all of Israel has convened in order to appear in the sight of the Lord your God, in the place which the Lord will choose, you shall read the words of this law before all of Israel, in their hearing.

12 And when the people have gathered together, men as well as women and little children, and the new arrivals who are within your gates, they shall listen so that they may learn, and may fear the Lord your God, and may keep and fulfill all the words of this law,

13 and also so that their sons, who are now ignorant, may be able to listen, and may fear the Lord their God all the days that they live in the land to which you will travel, crossing the Jordan in order to obtain it."

14 And the Lord said to Moses: "Behold, the days of your death draw near. Call Joshua, and stand in the tabernacle of the testimony, so that I may instruct him." Therefore, Moses and Joshua went and stood in the tabernacle of the testimony.

15 And the Lord appeared there, in a pillar of cloud, which stood at the entrance of the tabernacle.

16 And the Lord said to Moses: "Behold, you shall sleep with your fathers, and this people will rise up and will fornicate after foreign gods, in the land which they will enter so that they may live in it. In that place, they will forsake me, and they will make void the covenant that I have formed with them.

17 And my fury will be enraged against them in that day. And I will abandon them, and I will hide my face from them, and they shall be devoured. Every evil and affliction will find them, so much so that they will say in that day: 'Truly, it is because God is not with me that these evils have found me.'

18 But I will hide myself, and I will conceal my face in that day, because of all the evils that they have done, because they have followed strange gods.

19 And so, write this canticle now, and teach it to the sons of Israel, so that they may retain it in memory, and may chant it by mouth, and so that this verse may be a testimony to me among the sons of Israel.

20 For I will lead them into the land, about which I swore to their fathers, a land flowing with milk and honey. And when they have eaten, and have been satiated and fattened, they will turn aside to foreign gods, and they will serve them. And they will disparage me, and they will nullify my covenant.

21 And after many evils and afflictions have overwhelmed them, this canticle will answer them as a testimony; it shall never pass into oblivion, away from the mouths of their offspring. For I know their thoughts and what they are about to do today, even before I lead them into the land which I have promised to them."

22 Therefore, Moses wrote the canticle, and he taught it to the sons of Israel.

23 And the Lord instructed Joshua, the son of Nun, and he said: "Be strong and valiant. For you shall lead the sons of Israel into the land which I have promised, and I will be with you."

24 Therefore, after Moses had written the words of this law in a volume, and had finished it,

25 he instructed the Levites, who carried the ark of the covenant of the Lord, saying:

26 "Take this book, and place it inside the ark of the covenant of the Lord your God, so that it may be there as a testimony against you.

27 For I know your contentiousness and your very stiff neck. Even while I am still living and entering with you, you have always acted with contention against the Lord. How much more so when I will be dead?

28 Gather to me all those greater by birth throughout your tribes, as well as your teachers, and I will speak these words in their hearing, and I will call heaven and earth as witnesses against them.

29 For I know that, after my death, you will act with iniquity, and you will quickly depart from the way that I have instructed to you. And so, evils will meet you in the end time, when you will have done evil in the sight of the Lord so as to provoke him through the works of your hands."

30 Thus did Moses speak, in the hearing of the entire assembly of Israel, the words of this canticle, and he completed it to its very end.

Deuteronomy 32

1 "Listen, O heavens, to what I am saying. Let the earth hear the words of my mouth.

2 Let my doctrine accumulate like the rain. Let my eloquence form like the dew, like a mist upon the plants, and like water droplets upon the grass.

3 For I will invoke the name of the Lord. Acknowledge the magnificence of our God!

4 The works of God are perfect, and all his ways are judgments. God is faithful and without any iniquity. He is just and upright.

5 They have sinned against him, and in their filth they are not his sons. They are a depraved and perverse generation.

6 How can this be the return you would offer to the Lord, O foolish and senseless people? Is he himself not your Father, who has possessed you, and made you, and created you?

7 Remember the days of antiquity. Consider each generation. Question your father, and he will declare it to you. Question your elders, and they will tell it to you.

8 When the Most High divided the nations, when he separated the sons of Adam, he appointed the limits of the peoples according to the number of the sons of Israel.

9 But the Lord's portion is his people: Jacob, the lot of his inheritance.

10 He discovered him in a desert land, in a place of horror and a vast wilderness. He led him around and taught him, and he guarded him like the pupil of his eye,

11 just as an eagle encourages its young to fly, and, flying above them, stretches out its wings, and takes them up, and carries them on its shoulders.

12 The Lord alone was his leader, and there was no strange god with him.

13 He stood him upon an exalted land, so that he might eat the fruits of the fields, so that he might eat honey from the rock, and oil from the hardest stone,

14 butter from the herd, and milk from the sheep, with fat from the lambs, and with rams and goats from the sons of Bashan, with the kernel of the wheat, and so that he might drink the undiluted blood of the grape.

15 The beloved grew fat, and he kicked. Having grown fat and thick and wide, he abandoned God, his Maker, and he withdrew from God, his Savior.

16 They provoked him with strange gods, and they stirred him to anger by their abominations.

17 They immolated to demons and not to God, to gods whom they did not know, who were new and recent arrivals, whom their fathers did not worship.

18 You have forsaken the God who conceived you, and you have forgotten the Lord who created you.

19 The Lord saw, and he was stirred to anger. For his own sons and daughters provoked him.

20 And he said: 'I will hide my face from them, and I will consider their very end. For this is a perverse generation, and they are unfaithful sons.

21 They have provoked me with that which was not God, and they have angered me with their emptiness. And so, I will provoke them with that which is not a people, and I will anger them with a foolish nation.

22 A fire has been kindled in my fury, and it will burn even to the deepest Hell, and it will devour the earth with its produce, and it will burn the foundations of the mountains.

23 I will heap evils upon them, and I will expend my arrows among them.

24 They will be consumed by famine, and birds with a very bitter bite will devour them. I will send forth the teeth of wild beasts among them, along with the fury of creatures that scurry across the ground, and of serpents.

25 Outside, the sword will devastate them; and inside, there will be dread, as much for the young man as for the maiden, and as much for the newborn as for the old man.

26 I said: Where are they? I will cause their memory to cease from among men.

27 But because of the wrath of the enemies, I have delayed it. Otherwise, perhaps their enemies would be arrogant and would say: "Our exalted hand, and not the Lord, has done all these things."

28 They are a nation without counsel and without prudence.

29 I wish that they would be wise and understanding, and would provide for the very end.'

30 How is it that one pursues a thousand, and two chases ten thousand? Is it not because their God has sold them, and because the Lord has enclosed them?

31 For our God is not like their gods. And our enemies are judges.

32 Their vines are of the vines of Sodom, but from the suburbs of Gomorrah. Their grapes are the grapes of gall, and their grape clusters are most bitter.

33 Their wine is the gall of snakes, and it is the incurable venom of asps.

34 'Have not these things been stored up with me, and sealed up amid my treasures?

35 Vengeance is mine, and I will repay them in due time, so that their foot may slip and fall. The day of perdition is near, and the time rushes to appear.'

36 The Lord will judge his people, and he will take pity on his servants. He will see that their hand has been weakened, and that those who have been enclosed have likewise failed, and that those who have been left behind have been consumed.

37 And he shall say: 'Where are their gods, in whom they had confidence?

38 They ate the fat of their victims, and they drank the wine of their libations. So let these rise up, and bring relief to you, and protect you in your distress.

39 See that I am alone, and there is no other god beside me. I will kill, and I will cause to live. I will strike, and I will heal. And there is no one who is able to rescue from my hand.

40 I will lift up my hand to heaven, and I will say: I live in eternity.

41 When I sharpen my sword like lightning, and my hand takes hold of judgment, then I will render vengeance to my enemies, and I will repay those who hate me.

42 I will inebriate my arrows with blood, and my sword will devour flesh: from the blood of the slain and from the captive, from the exposed head of the enemies.'

43 You nations, praise his people! For he will avenge the blood of his servants. And he will distribute vengeance to their enemies. And he will be merciful to the land of his people."

44 Therefore, Moses went and spoke all the words of this canticle to the ears of the people, both he and Joshua, the son of Nun.

45 And he completed all these words, speaking to all of Israel.

46 And he said to them: "Set your hearts upon all the words which I am testifying to you this day. So shall you command your sons, to keep, and to do, and to fulfill all the things that have been written in this law.

47 For these things have not been entrusted to you to no purpose, but so that each one would live by them, and so that, in doing these, you may continue for a long time in the land, which you will enter upon crossing the Jordan in order to possess it."

48 And the Lord spoke to Moses on the same day, saying:

49 "Ascend this mountain, Abarim, (that is, of crossings) onto Mount Nebo, which is in the land of Moab, opposite Jericho, and look upon the land of Canaan, which I will deliver to the sons of Israel to obtain it. And you shall die upon the mountain.

50 After climbing it, you will be joined to your people, just as your brother Aaron died on Mount Hor, and was placed with his people.

51 For you trespassed against me in the midst of the sons of Israel, at the Waters of Contradiction, in Kadesh, in the desert of Sin. And you did not sanctify me among the sons of Israel.

52 You shall see the land opposite you, which I will give to the sons of Israel, but you shall not enter into it."

Deuteronomy 33

1 This is the blessing, with which Moses, the man of God, blessed the sons of Israel before his death.

2 And he said: "The Lord went forth from Sinai, and he arose for us from Seir. He appeared from Mount Paran, and thousands of holy ones were with him. The fiery law was in his right hand.

3 He loved the people; all the holy ones are in his hand. And those who approach his feet shall receive from his doctrine.

4 Moses instructed us in the law, the inheritance of the multitude of Jacob.

5 The king shall have great righteousness, at the gathering of the princes of the people with the tribes of Israel.

6 Let Ruben live, and not die, and may he be small in number."

7 This is the blessing of Judah. "Hear, O Lord, the voice of Judah, and lead him to his people. His hands shall fight for him, and he shall be his helper against his adversaries."

8 Likewise, to Levi he said: "Your perfection and your doctrine are for your holy man, whom you have proven by temptation, and whom you have judged at the Waters of Contradiction.

9 He has said to his father and to his mother, 'I do not know you,' and to his brothers, 'I will disregard you.' And they have not known their own sons. Such as these have kept your word and have observed your covenant:

10 your judgments, O Jacob, and your law, O Israel. They shall place incense before your fury and a holocaust upon your altar.

11 O Lord, bless his strength, and receive the works of his hands. Strike the backs of his enemies, and do not let those who hate him rise up."

12 And to Benjamin he said: "The most beloved of the Lord will live confidently in him. He shall remain all day long, as if in a bridal chamber, and he shall rest amid her arms."

13 Likewise, to Joseph he said: "His land shall be from the blessing of the Lord, from the fruits of heaven, and from the dew, and from the abyss which lies below,

14 from the fruits of the crops under the sun and the moon,

15 from the heights of the ancient mountains, from the fruits of the everlasting hills,

16 and from the fruits of the earth with all its plenitude. May the blessing of him who appeared in the bush, settle upon the head of Joseph, and upon the top of the head of the Nazarite among his brothers.

17 His excellence is like that of a first-born bull. His horns are like the horns of a rhinoceros; he shall brandish these against the Gentiles, even to the ends of the earth. These are the multitudes of Ephraim, and these the thousands of Manasseh."

18 And to Zebulun he said: "Rejoice, O Zebulun, in your departure, and Issachar, in your tabernacles.

19 They shall summon the peoples to the mountain. There, they shall immolate the victims of justice, who feed on the flood of the sea, as if on milk, and on the hidden treasures of the sands."

20 And to Gad he said: "Blessed is Gad in his breadth. He has rested like a lion, and he has seized the arm and the top of the head.

21 And he has seen his own pre-eminence, which his teacher has stored up as his portion. He was with the princes of the people, and he accomplished the justices of the Lord, and his judgment with Israel."

22 Likewise, to Dan he said: "Dan is a young lion. He shall flow plentifully from Bashan."

23 And to Naphtali he said: "Naphtali shall enjoy abundance, and he shall be full of the blessings of the Lord. He shall possess the sea and the Meridian."

24 Likewise, to Asher he said: "Let Asher be blessed with sons. Let him be pleasing to his brothers, and let him dip his foot in oil.

25 His shoe shall be of iron and of brass. As were the days of your youth, so also shall be your old age.

26 There is no other god like the God of the most righteous one. He who rides upon the heavens is your helper. His magnificence scatters the clouds.

27 His habitation is above, and the everlasting arms are below. He shall cast out the enemy before your face, and he shall say: 'Be utterly broken!'

28 Israel shall live in confidence and alone, as the eye of Jacob in a land of grain and of wine; and the heavens shall be misty with dew.

29 Blessed are you, O Israel. Who is like you, the people who are saved by the Lord? He is the shield of your assistance and the sword of your glory. Your enemies will refuse to acknowledge you, and so you shall tread upon their necks."

Deuteronomy 34

1 Therefore, Moses ascended from the plains of Moab onto Mount Nebo, to the top of Pisgah, opposite Jericho. And the Lord revealed to him the entire land of Gilead, as far as Dan,

2 and all of Naphtali, and the land of Ephraim and Manasseh, and the entire land of Judah, even to the furthest sea,

3 and the southern region, and the breadth of the plain of Jericho, the city of palms, as far as Zoar.

4 And the Lord said to him: "This is the land, about which I swore to Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, saying: I will give it to your offspring. You have seen it with your eyes, but you shall not cross over to it."

5 And Moses, the servant of the Lord, died in that place, in the land of Moab, by order of the Lord.

6 And he buried him in the valley of the land of Moab, opposite Peor. And no man knows where his sepulcher is, even to the present day.

7 Moses was one hundred and twenty years old when he died. His eye was not dimmed, nor were his teeth displaced.

8 And the sons of Israel wept for him in the plains of Moab for thirty days. And then the days of their wailing, during which they mourned Moses, were completed.

9 Truly, Joshua, the son of Nun, was filled with the spirit of wisdom, for Moses had laid his hands upon him. And the sons of Israel were obedient to him, and they did as the Lord instructed Moses.

10 And no other prophet rose up in Israel like Moses, one whom the Lord knew face to face,

11 one with all the signs and wonders, which he sent through him, to perform in the land of Egypt, against Pharaoh, and all his servants, and his entire land,

12 nor one with such a powerful hand and such great miracles as Moses did in the sight of all Israel.

Joshua 1

1 And after the death of Moses, the servant of the Lord, it happened that the Lord spoke to Joshua, the son of Nun, the minister of Moses, and he said to him:

2 "Moses, my servant, has died. Rise up, and cross this Jordan, you and all the people with you, into the land which I will give to the sons of Israel.

3 I will deliver to you every place that the step of your foot will tread upon, just as I said to Moses.

4 From the desert and from Lebanon, even to the great river Euphrates, all the land of the Hittites, as far as the great sea opposite the setting of the sun, shall be your border.

5 No one will be able to resist you during all the days of your life. Just as I was with Moses, so will I be with you. I will not leave you, nor will I forsake you.

6 Be strengthened and be steadfast. For you shall divide by lot, to this people, the land about which I swore to their fathers that I would deliver it to them.

7 Therefore, be strengthened and be very steadfast, so that you may observe and accomplish the entire law, which Moses, my servant, instructed to you. You may not turn aside from it to the right, nor to the left. So may you understand all that you should do.

8 The book of this law shall not depart from your mouth. Instead, you shall meditate upon it, day and night, so that you may observe and do all the things that are written in it. Then you shall direct your way and understand it.

9 Behold, I am instructing you. Be strengthened, and be steadfast. Do not dread, and do not fear. For the Lord your God is with you in all things, wherever you may go."

10 And Joshua instructed the leaders of the people, saying: "Cross through the midst of the camp, and command the people, and say:

11 'Prepare your food supplies. For after the third day, you shall cross the Jordan, and you shall enter so as to possess the land, which the Lord your God will give to you.' "

12 Likewise, he said to the Reubenites and to the Gadites, and to the one half tribe of Manasseh:

13 "Remember the words, which Moses, the servant of the Lord, instructed to you, saying: 'The Lord your God has given you rest, and has given you all the land.'

14 Your wives and sons, as well as the cattle, shall remain in the land which Moses delivered to you beyond the Jordan. But as for you, pass over with weapons, before your brothers, all you who are strong of hand, and fight on their behalf,

15 until the Lord gives rest to your brothers, just as he has given to you, and until they also possess the land, which the Lord your God will give to them. And so shall you be returned to the land of your possession. And you shall live in the land, which Moses, the servant of the Lord, gave to you beyond the Jordan, opposite the rising of the sun."

16 And they responded to Joshua, and they said: "All that you have instructed to us, we shall do. And wherever you will send us, we shall go.

17 Just as we obeyed Moses in all things, so shall we obey you also. But may the Lord your God be with you, just as he was with Moses.

18 Whoever will contradict your mouth, and whoever will not obey all of your words, which you will instruct to him, let him die. But may you be strengthened, and may you act manfully."

Joshua 2

1 And so Joshua, the son of Nun, sent two men from Shittim to explore in secret. And he said to them, "Go and consider the land and the city of Jericho." And while traveling, they entered into the house of a harlot woman named Rahab, and they rested with her.

2 And it was reported to the king of Jericho, and it was said: "Behold, men have entered to this place in the night, from the sons of Israel, so that they might explore the land."

3 And the king of Jericho sent to Rahab, saying: "Bring out the men who came to you, and who entered into your house. For certainly they are spies, and they have arrived to consider the entire land."

4 And the woman, taking the men, hid them. And she said: "I admit that they came to me, but I did not know where they were from.

5 And when the gate was closed, they went out together in the darkness. I do not know where they have gone. Pursue them quickly, and you will overtake them."

6 But she caused the men to ascend to the roof of her house, and she covered them with the stalks of flax that were there.

7 But those who had been sent pursued after them along the way that leads to the ford of the Jordan. And as soon as they went out, the gate was closed.

8 Those who were hiding had not yet fallen asleep, and behold, the woman went up to them, and she said:

9 "I know that the Lord has given this land to you. For the terror of you has fallen upon us, and all the inhabitants of the land have languished.

10 We have heard that the Lord dried up the water of the Red Sea upon your arrival, when you were departing from Egypt, and we heard of the things that you did to the two kings of the Amorites, who were beyond the Jordan, Sihon and Og, whom you put to death.

11 And upon hearing these things, we were very afraid, and our heart languished. Neither did there remain in us any spirit at your arrival. For the Lord your God is the very God in heaven above and on earth below.

12 Now, therefore, swear to me by the Lord that in the same way that I have acted with mercy toward you, so also shall you act toward the house of my father. And may you give me a true sign

13 that you will save my father and mother, my brothers and sisters, and all that is theirs, and that you may rescue our souls from death."

14 They responded to her: "May our lives be yours unto death, if only you do not betray us. And when the Lord will have delivered the land to us, we will act toward you with mercy and truth."

15 Therefore, she sent them down from a window with a rope. For her house was joined to the wall.

16 And she said to them: "Climb up to the mountains; otherwise, they may meet you as they are returning. And lay hidden there for three days, until they return. And then you will go on your way."

17 And they said to her: "We shall be innocent of this oath, to which you have sworn us,

18 if, when we enter into the land, this scarlet cord has been placed as a sign, and you have tied it at the window by which you let us down. And so, gather your father, and mother, and brothers, and all your family into your house.

19 Whoever will have exited from the door of your house, his blood will be on his own head, and we will be uninvolved. But the blood of all who will be with you in the house shall fall back upon our own head, if anyone touches them.

20 But if you will have betrayed us, so that you spread this word in their midst, we will be free from this oath, to which you have sworn us."

21 And she responded, "Just as you have spoken, so let it be done." And sending them to travel on, she hung the scarlet cord at the window.

22 And truly, walking on, they arrived at the mountains, and they stayed there for three days, until those who had been pursuing them returned. For having sought them along the entire way, they did not find them.

23 And when they returned and entered the city, the explorers descended from the mountain. And crossing the Jordan, they went to Joshua, the son of Nun, and they reported to him all that had happened to them.

24 And they said, "The Lord has delivered this entire land into our hands, and all its inhabitants have been struck down by fear."

Joshua 3

1 And so, Joshua arose in the night, and he moved the camp. And they departed from Shittim, and they went to the Jordan: he, and all the sons of Israel, and they remained there for three days.

2 After these things unfolded, announcers passed through the midst of the camp,

3 and they began to proclaim: "When you will see the ark of the covenant of the Lord your God, and the priests of the stock of Levi carrying it, you also shall rise up and follow those who are going before you.

4 And let there be, between you and the ark, the space of two thousand cubits, so that you may be able to see it from far away, and to know along which way you should advance. For you have not walked this way before. And be careful that you do not approach the ark."

5 And Joshua said to the people: "Be sanctified. For tomorrow the Lord will accomplish miracles among you."

6 And he said to the priests: "Take up the ark of the covenant, and go before the people." And they fulfilled the orders, and they took it and walked before them.

7 And the Lord said to Joshua: "Today I will begin to exalt you in the sight of all Israel, so that they may know that, just as I was with Moses, so also am I with you.

8 Now instruct the priests, who are carrying the ark of the covenant, and say to them, 'When you will have entered into a part of the water of the Jordan, stand still in it.' "

9 And Joshua said to the sons of Israel, "Approach to here, and listen to the word of the Lord your God."

10 And again, he said: "By this shall you know that the Lord, the living God, is in your midst, and that he shall scatter in your sight, the Canaanite and the Hittite, the Hivite and the Perizzite, likewise the Girgashite, and the Jebusite, and the Amorite.

11 Behold, the ark of the covenant of the Lord of all the earth shall go before you through the Jordan.

12 Prepare twelve men from the tribes of Israel, one from each tribe.

13 And when the priests who are carrying the ark of the Lord, the God of the entire earth, will have placed the steps of their feet in the waters of the Jordan, the waters that are lower will run down and pass away, and those that are approaching above will stand together in a mass."

14 And the people departed from their tents, so that they might cross the Jordan. And the priests who were carrying the ark of the covenant were advancing before them.

15 And as soon as they entered into the Jordan, and their feet were dipped in a portion of the water, (now the Jordan, since it was the time of the harvest, had filled the banks of its channel,)

16 the descending waters stood still in one place, and, swelling up like a mountain, they were seen from far away, from the city that is called Adam, even as far as the place of Zarethan. But those that were lower ran down into the Sea of the Wilderness, (which is now called the Dead Sea,) until they entirely passed away.

17 Then the people advanced opposite Jericho. And the priests who were carrying the ark of the covenant of the Lord were standing, fully-dressed, upon dry soil in the midst of the Jordan, and all the people passed over, through the channel that was dried up.

Joshua 4

1 And when they had crossed over, the Lord said to Joshua:

2 "Choose twelve men, one from each tribe,

3 and instruct them so that they may take from the midst of the channel of the Jordan, where the feet of the priests stood still, twelve very hard stones, which you shall station in the place of the camp, where you will pitch your tents this night."

4 And Joshua called twelve men, whom he had chosen from the sons of Israel, one from each tribe,

5 and he said to them: "Go before the ark of the Lord your God into the middle of the Jordan, and let each one carry from there one stone on your shoulders, according to the number of the sons of Israel,

6 so that it may be a sign among you. And when your sons will ask you, tomorrow, saying, 'What do these stones mean to you?'

7 you shall respond to them: 'The waters of the Jordan failed before the ark of the covenant of the Lord, when the ark crossed over it. For this reason, these stones were placed as a monument for the sons of Israel, even forever.' "

8 Therefore, the sons of Israel did as Joshua instructed them, carrying twelve stones from the midst of the channel of the Jordan, just as the Lord had ordered him, according to the number of the sons of Israel, as far as the place where they made camp, and there they stationed them.

9 Similarly, Joshua positioned another twelve stones in the middle of the channel of the Jordan, where the priests stood who were carrying the ark of the covenant; and they are there, even to the present day.

10 Now the priests who were carrying the ark stood in the midst of the Jordan, until everything was accomplished which the Lord had instructed Joshua to speak to the people and which Moses had said to him. And the people hurried, and they passed over.

11 And when they had all crossed, the ark of the Lord also crossed, and the priests advanced before the people.

12 Likewise, the sons of Reuben, and of Gad, and of the one half tribe of Manasseh advanced with weapons before the sons of Israel, just as Moses had instructed them.

13 And forty thousand fighters, by companies and divisions, advanced through the plains and fields of the city of Jericho.

14 In that day, the Lord magnified Joshua in the sight of all Israel, so that they would fear him, just as they had feared Moses while he lived.

15 And he said to him,

16 "Command the priests who are carrying the ark of the covenant to ascend from the Jordan."

17 And he commanded them, saying, "Ascend from the Jordan."

18 And when those who were carrying the ark of the covenant of the Lord had ascended, and they began to step on dry soil, the waters returned to their channel, and they flowed as they usually did before.

19 Now the people ascended from the Jordan on the tenth day of the first month, and they encamped at Gilgal, opposite the eastern portion of the city of Jericho.

20 Likewise, the twelve stones that they had taken up from the channel of the Jordan, Joshua stationed at Gilgal.

21 And he said to the sons of Israel: "When your sons will question their fathers, tomorrow, and they will say to them, 'What do these stones mean to you?'

22 you shall teach them, and you shall say: 'Israel passed over this Jordan, through the dry channel.'

23 For the Lord your God dried up its waters in your sight, until you crossed over,

24 just as he had done before, at the Red Sea, which he dried up until we crossed over.

25 So may all the peoples of the earth learn of the very powerful hand of the Lord. So may you also fear the Lord your God for all time."

Joshua 5

1 Therefore, after all the kings of the Amorites, who were living across the Jordan toward the western region, and all the kings of Canaan, who possessed the places beside the great sea, had heard that the Lord had dried up the waters of the Jordan before the sons of Israel, until they crossed over it, their heart was broken, and there remained in them no spirit, out of fear at the entrance of the sons of Israel.

2 So at that time, the Lord said to Joshua: "Make for yourself knives of stone, and circumcise the sons of Israel a second time."

3 He did what the Lord had commanded, and he circumcised the sons of Israel at the hill of the foreskins.

4 Now this is the reason for the second circumcision: All the people who departed from Egypt of the male gender, all the men fit for war, died in the desert during the very long wandering way;

5 all these had been circumcised. But the people who were born in the desert,

6 throughout the forty years of the journey in the very broad wilderness, were uncircumcised, until the ones who had not listened to the voice of the Lord were consumed. For he had sworn to them before, that he would not reveal to them the land flowing with milk and honey.

7 The sons of these ones succeeded to the place of their fathers, and they were circumcised by Joshua. For they were uncircumcised, just as they had been born, and no one had circumcised them along the way.

8 Then, after they were all circumcised, they remained in the same place of the camp until they were healed.

9 And the Lord said to Joshua, "Today I have taken away from you the disgrace of Egypt." And the name of that place was called Gilgal, even to the present day.

10 And the sons of Israel stayed at Gilgal, and they kept the Passover, on the fourteenth day of the month at evening, in the plains of Jericho.

11 And on the following day, they ate unleavened bread from the grain of the land, and cooked grain, of the same year.

12 And the manna ceased after they ate from the grain of the land. And the sons of Israel no longer made use of that food. Instead, they ate from the grain of the present year, from the land of Canaan.

13 And when Joshua was in the field of the city of Jericho, he lifted up his eyes, and he saw a man standing opposite him, holding a drawn sword. And he went to him and said, "Are you one of ours, or one of our adversaries?"

14 And he responded: "Not at all. Instead, I am a prince of the host of the Lord, and now I have arrived."

15 Joshua fell prone on the ground. And reverencing, he said, "What does my lord say to his servant?"

16 He said: "Remove your shoes from your feet. For the place on which you stand is holy." And Joshua did just as he had been commanded.

Joshua 6

1 Now Jericho was closed as well as fortified, out of fear of the sons of Israel, and no one dared to depart or to enter.

2 And the Lord said to Joshua: "Behold, I have given Jericho into your hand, with its king and all the strong men.

3 Have all the warriors circle the city once each day; you shall do so for six days.

4 Then, on the seventh day, the priests shall take the seven trumpets, which are used on the jubilee, and they shall precede the ark of the covenant. And you shall circle the city seven times, and the priests shall sound the trumpets.

5 And when the voice of the trumpet sounds longer and with interruptions, and it increases in your ears, then all the people shall cry out together with a very great shout, and the walls of the city shall fall to the foundation, and they shall enter it, each from a place opposite where they are standing."

6 Then Joshua, the son of Nun, called the priests, and he said to them, "Take the ark of the covenant, and let seven other priests take the seven trumpets of the jubilee, and advance before the ark of the Lord."

7 He also said to the people, "Go, and circle the city, armed, preceding the ark of the Lord."

8 And when Joshua had finished his words, and the seven priests sounded the seven trumpets before the ark of the covenant of the Lord,

9 and all the armed soldiers went ahead, the remainder of the common people followed the ark, and the sound of the trumpets grew louder everywhere.

10 But Joshua had instructed the people, saying, "You shall not cry out, nor shall your voice be heard, and no word at all shall proceed from your mouth, until the day arrives on which I will say to you, 'Cry out, and shout.' "

11 Thus, the ark of the Lord circled the city once each day, and returning to the camp, it remained there.

12 And so, with Joshua, arising in the night, the priests took the ark of the Lord,

13 and seven of them took the seven trumpets, which are used in the jubilee, and they preceded the ark of the Lord, walking and sounding the trumpets. And the armed men went before them, and the remainder of the common people followed the ark, and they were blaring the trumpets.

14 And they circled the city on the second day, once, and they returned to the camp. They did so for six days.

15 Then, on the seventh day, rising at first light, they circled the city, just as had been ordered, seven times.

16 And at the seventh circling, when the priests sounded the trumpets, Joshua said to all of Israel: "Shout! For the Lord has delivered the city to you.

17 And let this city be anathema, with all the things that are within it, before the Lord. May only Rahab the harlot live, with all who are with her in the house. For she hid the messengers whom we sent.

18 But you must be careful that you do not touch any of those things, as you have been instructed, for then you would be guilty of transgression, and all the camp of Israel would be under sin and would be troubled.

19 But whatever gold and silver there will be, and vessels of brass or of iron, let these be consecrated to the Lord and be stored in his treasuries."

20 Therefore, with all the people shouting, and the trumpets blaring, after the voice and the sound increased in the ears of the multitude, the walls promptly fell to ruin. And each one climbed up at the place which was opposite where he was. And they seized the city.

21 And they put to death all who were in it, from man even to woman, from infant even to elder. Likewise, the oxen and sheep and donkeys, they struck down with the edge of the sword.

22 But Joshua said to the two men who had been sent to explore, "Enter the house of the harlot woman, and bring her out, and all the things that are hers, just as you assured her by oath."

23 And the youths entered, and they led out Rahab, and her parents, also her brothers, and all her goods and kindred, and they caused them to dwell outside the camp.

24 Then they set fire to the city and all the things that were within it, except the gold and silver, and the vessels of brass or of iron, which they consecrated into the treasury of the Lord.

25 Yet truly, Joshua caused Rahab the harlot, and her father's household, and all she had, to survive. And they lived in the midst of Israel, even to the present day. For she hid the messengers, whom he had sent to explore Jericho. At that time, Joshua made an invocation, saying:

26 "Cursed before the Lord is the man who will raise up and rebuild the city of Jericho! With his firstborn, may he lay its foundation, and with the last of his children, may he set up its gates."

27 And so the Lord was with Joshua, and his name was made known throughout all the land.

Joshua 7

1 But the sons of Israel transgressed the commandment, and they usurped what was anathema. For Achan, the son of Carmi, the son of Zabdi, the son of Zerah, from the tribe of Judah, took something from what was anathema. And the Lord became angry against the sons of Israel.

2 And when Joshua sent men from Jericho against Ai, which is beside Bethaven, toward the eastern region of the town of Bethel, he said to them, "Go up and explore the land." And they fulfilled his instruction, and they explored Ai.

3 And returning, they said to him: "Let not the entire people go up. Instead, let two or three thousand men go out and destroy the city. Why should all the people be troubled without cause against enemies that are so very few?"

4 Therefore, they went up with three thousand fighters. And they promptly turned their backs,

5 and were struck down by the men of the city of Ai. And thirty-six men of them fell. And the adversaries pursued them from the gate, even as far as Shebarim. And they felled them as they were fleeing downward. And the heart of the people was struck with fear, and it melted like water.

6 And truly, Joshua tore his garments, and he fell prone on the ground before the ark of the Lord, even until evening, both he and all the elders of Israel. And they cast dust upon their heads.

7 And Joshua said: "Alas, O Lord God! Why would you want to lead this people over the river Jordan, so that you might deliver us into the hand of the Amorite and destroy us? I wish that we had remained beyond the Jordan, as when we began.

8 My Lord God, what shall I say, seeing Israel turning their backs to their enemies?

9 The Canaanites and all the inhabitants of the land will hear of it, and coming together as one, they will surround us, and they will wipe our name from the earth. And what will you do concerning your great name?"

10 And the Lord said to Joshua: "Rise up. Why are you lying flat on the ground?

11 Israel has sinned and transgressed my covenant. And they have taken from what is anathema. And they have stolen and lied, and they have hidden it among their goods.

12 Israel is not able to stand before his enemies, and he will flee from them. For he has been defiled by what is anathema. I will be no longer be with you, until you destroy him who is guilty of this wickedness.

13 Rise up. Sanctify the people. And you shall say to them: 'Be sanctified tomorrow. For thus says the Lord, the God of Israel: That which is anathema is in your midst, O Israel! You are not able to stand before your enemies, until he who has been contaminated by this wickedness is taken away from you.'

14 And you shall draw near in the morning, each one by your tribes. And whichever tribe will be found by lot shall come forward by its families, and the families by houses, and the house by the men.

15 And whoever he may be that will be found guilty of this deed, he shall be burnt with fire with all his substance. For he transgressed the covenant of the Lord, and he committed a wicked act in Israel."

16 And so Joshua, rising in the morning, brought forth Israel by their tribes, and the tribe of Judah was found.

17 And when its families had been presented, the family of Zerah was found. Likewise, bringing that one forward by the houses, he discovered Zabdi.

18 And dividing his house by each man, he found Achan, the son of Carmi, the son of Zabdi, the son of Zerah, from the tribe of Judah.

19 And Joshua said to Achan: "My son, give glory to the Lord, the God of Israel, and confess, and reveal to me what you have done. You may not conceal it."

20 And Achan responded to Joshua, and he said to him: "Truly, I have sinned against the Lord, the God of Israel, and I have done one thing and another.

21 For I saw among the spoils a very fine scarlet cloak, and two hundred shekels of silver, and a gold bar of fifty shekels. And coveting these, I took and hid them in the ground near the middle of my tent, and I covered the silver with the soil that I had dug."

22 Therefore, Joshua sent ministers, who, running to his tent, discovered everything hidden in the same place, together with the silver.

23 And taking these from the tent, they brought them to Joshua, and to all the sons of Israel, and they cast them down before the Lord.

24 And so Joshua took Achan, the son of Zerah, and the silver, and the cloak, and the gold bar, also his sons and daughters, the oxen and donkeys and sheep, and even the tent and all his goods, (and all of Israel went with him,) and he brought these to the valley of Achor.

25 There, Joshua said: "Because you have troubled us, the Lord troubles you, on this day." And all of Israel stoned him. And all the things that were his were consumed by fire.

26 And they gathered upon him a great pile of stones, which remains even to the present day. And the fury of the Lord was averted from them. And the name of that place was called the Valley of Achor, even to this day.

Joshua 8

1 Then the Lord said to Joshua: "You should not fear, and you should not dread. Take with you the entire multitude of fighters, and rising up, ascend to the town of Ai. Behold, I have delivered into your hand its king and people, and the city and the land.

2 And you shall do to the city of Ai, and to its king, just as you did to Jericho, and to its king. Yet truly, the spoils, and all the living things, you shall plunder for yourselves. Set an ambush against the city behind it."

3 And Joshua rose up, and the entire army of warriors with him, so that they might ascend against Ai. And he sent thirty thousand elect strong men in the night.

4 And he instructed them, saying: "Set an ambush behind the city. You shall withdraw not far away, and let everyone be prepared.

5 But I and the remainder of the multitude that is with me will approach from the opposite side of the city. And when they come out against us, we will flee and turn our backs, just as we did before,

6 until, pursuing us, they are drawn away from the city. For they will think that we are fleeing as before.

7 Then, while we are fleeing and they are pursuing, you shall rise up from the ambush, and you shall lay waste to the city. And the Lord your God will deliver it into your hands.

8 And when you have seized it, set it on fire. And you shall do all that I have ordered."

9 And he sent them away, and they traveled to the place of the ambush, and they settled between Bethel and Ai, toward the western region of the city of Ai. But Joshua remained for that night in the midst of the people.

10 And rising at first light, he reviewed his troops, and he went up, with the elders at the front of the army, surrounded by an auxiliary of fighters.

11 And when they had arrived, and had ascended from the opposite side of the city, they stood toward the northern region of the city. And there was a valley in the middle, between them and the city.

12 Now he had chosen five thousand men, and he had positioned them in ambush between Bethel and Ai, at the western part of the same city.

13 Yet truly, all the remainder of the army was arranged in a line to the north, so that the very end of that multitude reached to the western region of the city. Then Joshua went out that night, and he stood in the middle of the valley.

14 And when the king of Ai had seen this, he hurried in the morning, and he went out with the entire army of the city. And he arranged them in a line opposite the desert, not knowing that an ambush lay hidden behind his back.

15 Yet truly, Joshua, and all of Israel, withdrew from the place, pretending to be afraid, and fleeing along the way of the wilderness.

16 And they pursued them, shouting together and encouraging one another. And when they had withdrawn from the city,

17 and indeed not one remained in the city of Ai and of Bethel who did not pursue after Israel, (leaving the towns open after they had rushed out,)

18 the Lord said to Joshua: "Lift up the shield that is in your hand, toward the city of Ai. For I will deliver it to you."

19 And when he had lifted up the shield toward the city, the ambush, which lay hidden, rose up quickly. And advancing to the city, they seized it, and set it on fire.

20 Now the men of the city who were pursuing Joshua, looking back and seeing the smoke of the city rising up even to heaven, were no longer able to flee in one direction or another, especially since those who had pretended to flee, and who were heading toward the wilderness, had turned back very strongly against those who were pursuing them.

21 And Joshua, and all of Israel, seeing that the city had been captured, and that the smoke of the city was ascending, returned and struck down the men of Ai.

22 Then too, those who had seized and set the city on fire, departing from the city toward their own men, began to strike the enemies in the middle. Therefore, since the adversaries were cut off from both sides, none of so great a multitude was saved.

23 Also, they apprehended the king of the city of Ai, alive, and they brought him before Joshua.

24 And so, after all were slain who had pursued Israel fleeing toward the wilderness, and after they fell by the sword in the same place, the sons of Israel returned and struck the city.

25 Now there were twelve thousand persons who had fallen on the same day, from man even to woman, the entire city of Ai.

26 Truly Joshua did not draw back his hand, which he had stretched out on high, keeping hold of the shield until all the inhabitants of Ai were put to death.

27 Then the sons of Israel divided among themselves the cattle and the plunder of the city, just as the Lord had instructed Joshua.

28 And he set fire to the city, and he caused it to be a perpetual tomb.

29 Also, he suspended the king on a gallows, until evening and the setting of the sun. And Joshua instructed, and they took down his dead body from the hanging tree. And they cast it at the very entrance of the city, gathering a great pile of stones upon it, which remains even to the present day.

30 Then Joshua built an altar to the Lord, the God of Israel, on Mount Ebal,

31 just as Moses, the servant of the Lord, had instructed to the sons of Israel, and this was written in the book of the law of Moses: truly, an altar of uncut stones, which iron has not touched. And he offered holocausts upon it to the Lord, and he immolated victims as peace-offerings.

32 And he wrote on the stones, the Deuteronomy of the law of Moses, which he had set in order before the sons of Israel.

33 Then all the people, and those greater by birth, and the commanders and judges were standing on both sides of the ark, in the sight of the priests who were carrying the ark of the covenant of the Lord, with both the new arrival and the native born, one half part of them beside Mount Gerizim, and one half beside Mount Ebal, just as Moses, the servant of the Lord, had instructed. And first, certainly, he blessed the people of Israel.

34 After this, he read all the words of the blessing and the cursing, and all the things that were written in the book of the law.

35 He left nothing untouched out of those things that Moses had ordered, and he repeated everything before the entire multitude of Israel, with the women and the little ones, and the new arrivals who were staying among them.

Joshua 9

1 And when these things were heard, all the kings across the Jordan, who lived among the mountains and plains, along the coastline and shores of the great sea, also those who were living near Lebanon, the Hittite, and the Amorite, the Canaanite, the Perizzite, and the Hivite, and the Jebusite,

2 gathered themselves together, so that they might fight against Joshua and Israel, with one mind and with the same resolve.

3 But those who were living in Gibeon, hearing all that Joshua had done to Jericho and Ai,

4 planning cleverly, took for themselves provisions, placing old sacks upon their donkeys, and wineskins that had torn and been sewed up,

5 and having very old shoes, which had been sewn with patches indicating their age, and being clothed in old garments, having also loaves, which they carried as food for the journey, which were hard and broken into pieces.

6 And they traveled to Joshua, who at that time was staying in the camp at Gilgal. And they said to him, and to all of Israel with him, "We have come from a far away land, desiring to make peace with you." And the sons of Israel responded to them, and said,

7 "Perhaps instead, you live in the land which ought to be ours by lot, and we would be unable to form a pact with you."

8 But they said to Joshua, "We are your servants." And Joshua said to them: "But who are you? And where are you from?"

9 They responded: "Your servants have arrived, from a very far away land, in the name of the Lord, your God. For we have heard about the fame of his power, all the things that he has done in Egypt,

10 and to the two kings of the Amorites, who were beyond the Jordan: Sihon, the king of Heshbon, and Og, the king of Bashan, who was at Ashtaroth.

11 And our elders, and all the inhabitants of our land, have said to us: 'Take in hand provisions for the very long journey, and meet with them, and say: We are your servants; form a pact with us.'

12 Lo, the loaves were taken up warm when we departed from our houses, so that we might come to you. Now they have become dry and broken, due to age.

13 These wineskins were new when we filled them, now they are torn and broken. The garments we are wearing, and the shoes we have on our feet, due to the great length of the distance, have become worn and are nearly consumed."

14 And so they accepted this, because of their provisions, and they did not consult the mouth of the Lord.

15 And Joshua made peace with them, and entering into a pact, he promised that they would not be put to death. The leaders of the multitude also swore to them.

16 Then, three days after the pact was formed, they heard that they lived in the vicinity, and that they would soon be among them.

17 And so the sons of Israel moved the camp, and they arrived at their cities on the third day, those which are called: Gibeon, and Chephirah, and Beeroth, and Kiriath-jearim.

18 And they did not strike them, because the leaders of the multitude had sworn to them in the name of the Lord, the God of Israel. And so all of the common people murmured against the leaders.

19 And they responded to them: "We have sworn to them in the name of the Lord, the God of Israel, and for that reason, we are not able to touch them.

20 But we shall do this to them: Certainly, let them be preserved so that they may live, lest the wrath of the Lord be stirred up against us, since we would have sworn falsely.

21 But though they live, let them serve the entire multitude by cutting wood and carrying water." And while they were discussing these things,

22 Joshua called the Gibeonites, and he said to them: "Why would you be willing to deceive us by fraud, saying, 'We live very far away from you,' when you are in our midst?

23 Therefore, you shall be under a curse, and your stock shall not cease to be cutters of wood and carriers of water, into the house of my God."

24 And they responded: "It was reported to us, your servants, that the Lord your God had promised his servant Moses that he would give you the entire land, and that he would destroy all its inhabitants. Therefore, we were very afraid, and we made a provision for our lives, compelled by the dread of you, and we undertook this counsel.

25 And now we are in your hand. Act toward us as it seems good and right to you."

26 Therefore, Joshua did just as he had said, and he freed them from the hand of the sons of Israel, so that they would not be killed.

27 And he decreed on that day, that they would be in the ministry of all the people and of the altar of the Lord, cutting wood and carrying water, even until this present time, in the place which the Lord had chosen.

Joshua 10

1 When Adonizedek, the king of Jerusalem, had heard these things, specifically, that Joshua had seized Ai, and had overthrown it, (for just as he had done to Jericho and its king, so did he do to Ai and its king,) and that the Gibeonites had fled over to Israel, and were now their confederates,

2 he was very afraid. For Gibeon was a great city, and was one of the royal cities, and was greater than the town of Ai, and all its warriors were very strong.

3 Therefore, Adonizedek, the king of Jerusalem, sent to Hoham, the king of Hebron, and to Piram, the king of Jarmuth, and also to Japhia, the king of Lachish, and to Debir, the king of Eglon, saying:

4 "Ascend to me, and bring troops, so that we may fight against Gibeon. For it has fled over to Joshua and the sons of Israel."

5 And so, having assembled, the five kings of the Amorites, the king of Jerusalem, the king of Hebron, the king of Jarmuth, the king of Lachish, the king of Eglon, together with their armies, went up and encamped around Gibeon, laying siege to it.

6 But the inhabitants of the city of Gibeon, when it was besieged, sent to Joshua, who was then staying in the camp at Gilgal. And they said to him: "May you not draw back your hands from helping your servants. Come quickly, and free us, and bring troops. For all the kings of the Amorites, who live in the mountains, have gathered together against us."

7 And Joshua ascended from Gilgal, and the entire army of warriors with him, very strong men.

8 And the Lord said to Joshua: "You should not fear them. For I have delivered them into your hands. None of them will be able to withstand you."

9 And so Joshua, ascending from Gilgal throughout the night, rushed upon them suddenly.

10 And the Lord set them in disarray before the face of Israel. And he crushed them in a great defeat at Gibeon, and he pursued them along the way of the ascent to Beth-horon, and he struck them down, even as far as Azekah and Makkedah.

11 And while they were fleeing from the sons of Israel, and were on the descent of Beth-horon, the Lord cast great stones from heaven upon them, as far as Azekah. And many more were killed by the hailstones, than were struck down by the swords of the sons of Israel.

12 Then Joshua spoke to the Lord, on the day that he handed over the Amorite in the sight of the sons of Israel, and he said before them: "O sun, you shall not move toward Gibeon! O moon, you shall not move toward the valley of Aijalon!"

13 And the sun and the moon stood still, until the people had avenged themselves of their enemies. Has this not been written in the book of the just? And so the sun stood still in the midst of heaven, and it did not hurry to its rest for the space of one day.

14 Never before and never after was there so long a day, as when the Lord obeyed the voice of a man, and fought for Israel.

15 And Joshua returned, with all of Israel, into the camp of Gilgal.

16 For the five kings had fled, and had hidden themselves in a cave, near the city of Makkedah.

17 And it was reported to Joshua that the five kings had been found hidden in a cave, near the city of Makkedah.

18 And he instructed his companions and said: "Roll vast stones to the mouth of the cave, and station attentive men who will keep them closed.

19 But as for you, do not stay here; instead, pursue the enemies, and cut down the lattermost of those who are fleeing. You shall not permit those whom the Lord God has delivered into your hands to enter into the protection of their cities."

20 Thus, the adversaries were struck down in a great defeat, and having been nearly consumed, even to utter annihilation, those who were able to escape from Israel entered into fortified cities.

21 And the entire army returned to Joshua at Makkedah, where they were then encamped, in good health and in their full numbers. And no one dared to move his tongue against the sons of Israel.

22 And Joshua instructed, saying, "Open the mouth of the cave, and bring forward to me the five kings, who are hidden within it."

23 And the ministers did just as they had been ordered. And they led out to him the five kings from the cave: the king of Jerusalem, the king of Hebron, the king of Jarmuth, the king of Lachish, the king of Eglon.

24 And when they had been led out to him, he called all the men of Israel, and he said to the leaders of the army who were with him, "Go, and place your feet upon the necks of these kings." And when they had gone and had tread their feet upon the necks of those who were thrown down,

25 he spoke to them again: "Do not be afraid, and do not dread. Be strengthened and be steadfast. For so will the Lord do to all your enemies, against whom you fight."

26 And Joshua struck them down and killed them, and he suspended them on five gallows. And they hung there until evening.

27 And when the sun had set, he instructed his assistants that they should take them down from the gallows. And having been taken down, they cast them into the cave, where they had lain hidden, and they set vast stones at its mouth, which remain, even to the present.

28 Also on the same day, Joshua seized Makkedah, and he struck it with the edge of the sword, and he put to death its king and all its inhabitants. He did not leave in it even the smallest remains. And he did to the king of Makkedah, just as he had done to the king of Jericho.

29 Then he went on, with all of Israel, from Makkedah to Libnah, and he fought against it.

30 And the Lord delivered it, with its king, into the hands of Israel. And they struck the city with the edge of the sword, and all its inhabitants. They did not leave in it any remains. And they did to the king of Libnah, just as they had done to the king of Jericho.

31 From Libnah, with all of Israel, he went on to Lachish. And taking positions around it with his army, he besieged it.

32 And the Lord delivered Lachish into the hands of Israel, and he seized it on the following day, and he struck it with the edge of the sword, and every soul that was in it, just as he had done to Libnah.

33 At that time, Horam, the king of Gezer, went up so that he might assist Lachish. And Joshua struck him with all his people, even unto utter annihilation.

34 And he went on from Lachish to Eglon, and he surrounded it.

35 And he also defeated it on the same day. And he struck all the souls that were in it with the edge of the sword, in accord with all that he had done to Lachish.

36 He also ascended, with all of Israel, from Eglon into Hebron, and he fought against it.

37 He seized it and struck it with the edge of the sword, likewise with its king, and all the towns of that region, and all the souls that were staying in it. He did not leave any remains in it. Just as he had done to Eglon, so also did he do to Hebron, consuming with the sword all that he found within it.

38 Returning from there to Debir,

39 he seized it and laid waste to it, likewise with its king. And all the surrounding towns, he struck with the edge of the sword. He did not leave in it any remains. Just as he had done to Hebron and Libnah, and to their kings, so did he do to Debir and to its king.

40 And so Joshua struck the entire land, the mountains, and the south, and the plains, and the descending slopes, with their kings. He did not leave in it any remains, but he put to death all that was able to breathe, just as the Lord, the God of Israel, had instructed him,

41 from Kadesh-barnea, as far as Gaza, with all the land of Goshen, as far as Gibeon.

42 And all their kings and their regions, he seized and destroyed with a single attack. For the Lord, the God of Israel, fought on his behalf.

43 And he returned, with all of Israel, to the place of the encampment at Gilgal.

Joshua 11

1 And when Jabin, the king of Hazor, had heard these things, he sent to Jobab, the king of Madon, and to the king of Shimron, and to the king of Achshaph,

2 also to the kings of the north, who were living in the mountains, and in the plains opposite the southern region of Chinneroth, and also in the plains and the regions of Dor, beside the sea,

3 also to the Canaanites, from east to west, and to the Amorite, and the Hittite, and the Perizzite, and the Jebusite in the mountains, also to the Hivite who was living at the base of Hermon, in the land of Mizpah.

4 And they all went forth with their troops, a people exceedingly numerous, like the sand that is on the shore of the sea. And their horses and chariots were an immense multitude.

5 And all these kings assembled at the waters of Merom, so that they might fight against Israel.

6 And the Lord said to Joshua: "You should not fear them. For tomorrow, at this same hour, I will deliver all these to be wounded in the sight of Israel. You will hamstring their horses, and you will burn their chariots with fire."

7 And Joshua, and the entire army with him, came against them suddenly, at the waters of Merom, and they rushed upon them.

8 And the Lord delivered them into the hands of Israel. And they struck them, and they pursued them as far as the great Sidon, and the waters of Misrephoth, and the field of Mizpeh, which is toward the eastern region. He struck them all, so that nothing was left of them to remain.

9 And he did just as the Lord had instructed him. He hamstrung their horses, and he burned their chariots with fire.

10 And turning back, he immediately seized Hazor. And he struck down its king with the sword. For Hazor, from antiquity, held the first position among all these kingdoms.

11 And he struck down all the souls that were staying there. He did not leave in it any remains, but he destroyed everything unto utter annihilation, and he destroyed the city itself with fire.

12 And he seized, struck, and destroyed all the surrounding cities and their kings, just as Moses, the servant of God, had instructed him.

13 And except for the cities that were on hills and in elevated places, the rest Israel burned. One only, highly-fortified Hazor, was consumed with fire.

14 And the sons of Israel divided among themselves all the plunder of these cities, and the cattle, putting to death all persons.

15 Just as the Lord had instructed his servant Moses, so did Moses instruct Joshua, and he fulfilled everything. He did not omit even one word out of all the commandments, which the Lord had commanded Moses.

16 And so Joshua seized the entire land of the mountains, and of the south, and the land of Goshen, and the plains, and the western region, and the mountain of Israel, and its plains.

17 As for the part of the mountain that ascends to Seir, as far as Baalgad, along the plain of Lebanon under mount Hermon, all their kings he seized, struck down, and killed.

18 For a long time, Joshua fought against these kings.

19 There was not a city that delivered itself to the sons of Israel, except the Hivites who were living at Gibeon. For he seized it all in warfare.

20 For it was the sentence of the Lord that their hearts would be hardened, and that they would fight against Israel and fall, and that they did not deserve any clemency, and that they should perish, just as the Lord had commanded Moses.

21 In that time, Joshua went and put to death the Anakim from the mountains, from Hebron and Debir and Anab, and from all the mountains of Judah and Israel. And he destroyed their cities.

22 He did not leave any from the stock of the Anakim in the land of the sons of Israel, except the cities of Gaza, and Gath, and Ashdod, which alone were left behind.

23 Thus, Joshua seized all the land, just as the Lord spoke to Moses, and he delivered it as a possession to the sons of Israel, according to their divisions and tribes. And the land rested from battles.

Joshua 13

1 Joshua was old and advanced in age, and the Lord said to him: "You have grown old, and are aged, and a very wide land remains, which has not yet been divided by lot,

2 specifically, all of Galilee, Philistia, and all of Geshur;

3 from the muddy river, which irrigates Egypt, as far as the border of Ekron toward the north, the land of Canaan, which is divided among the rulers of Philistia: the Gazites, and the Ashdodites, the Ashkelonites, the Gathites, and the Ekronites;

4 truly, to the south are the Hivites, all the land of Canaan, and Mearah of the Sidonians, as far as Aphek and the borders of the Amorite

5 and his confines; also, the region of Lebanon toward the east, from Baalgad, under mount Hermon, until you enter into Hamath;

6 all who live in the mountains from Lebanon, as far as the waters of Misrephoth, and all the Sidonians. I am the One who will wipe them out, before the face of the sons of Israel. Therefore, let their land become a part of the inheritance of Israel, just as I have instructed you.

7 And now, divide the land as a possession to the nine tribes, and to the one half tribe of Manasseh."

8 With them, Reuben and Gad have possessed the land, which Moses, the servant of the Lord, delivered to them beyond the river Jordan, on the eastern side:

9 from Aroer, which is situated on the bank of the torrent Arnon and in the midst of the valley, and all the plains of Medeba, as far as Dibon;

10 and all the cities of Sihon, the king of the Amorites, who reigned in Heshbon, even to the borders of the sons of Ammon;

11 and Gilead, as well as the borders of Geshur and Maacati, and all of mount Hermon, and all of Bashan, as far as Salecah;

12 the entire kingdom of Og in Bashan, who reigned at Ashtaroth and Edrei, (he was among the last of the Rephaim). And Moses struck and destroyed them.

13 And the sons of Israel were not willing to destroy Geshur and Maacati, and so they have lived in the midst of Israel, even to the present day.

14 But to the tribe of Levi, he did not give a possession. Instead, the sacrifices and victims of the Lord, the God of Israel, these are his inheritance, just as he spoke to him.

15 Therefore, Moses gave a possession to the tribe of the sons of Reuben, according to their families.

16 And their border was from Aroer, which is situated on the bank of the torrent Arnon, and in the midst of the valley of the same torrent, with all the flatlands that lead to Medeba;

17 and Heshbon, and all their villages, which are in the plains; also Dibon, and Bamothbaal, and the town of Baalmeon,

18 and Jahaz, and Kedemoth, and Mephaath,

19 and Kiriathaim, and Sibmah, and Zereth-shahar on the mountain of the steep valley;

20 Bethpeor, and the descending slopes of Pisgah, and Beth-jeshimoth;

21 and all the cities of the plain, and all the kingdoms of Sihon, the king of the Amorites, who reigned at Heshbon, whom Moses struck down with the leaders of Midian: Evi, and Rekem, and Zur, and Hur, and Reba, the commanders of Sihon, inhabitants of the land.

22 And the sons of Israel killed Balaam, the son of Beor, the seer, with the sword, along with the others who were slain.

23 And the river Jordan was made the border of the sons of Reuben; this is the possession of the Reubenites, by their families, in cities and villages.

24 And Moses gave to the tribe of Gad and his sons, by their families, a possession, of which this is the division:

25 the border of Jazer, and all the cities of Gilead, and one half part of the land of the sons of Ammon, as far as Aroer, which is opposite Rabbah;

26 and from Heshbon as far as Ramath, Mizpeh, and Betonim; and from Mahanaim as far as the borders of Debir;

27 also, in the valley Beth-haram and Beth-nimrah, and Succoth, and Zaphon, the remaining part of the kingdom of Sihon, the king of Heshbon; the limit of this also is the Jordan, as far as the furthest part of the sea of Chinnereth, beyond the Jordan on the eastern side.

28 This is the possession of the sons of Gad, by their families, in their cities and villages.

29 He also gave, to the one half tribe of Manasseh and to his sons, a possession according to their families,

30 the beginning of which is this: from Mahanaim, all of Bashan, and all the kingdoms of Og, the king of Bashan, and all the villages of Jair, which are in Bashan, sixty towns;

31 and one half part of Gilead, and Ashtaroth, and Edrei, the cities of the kingdom of Og in Bashan, to the sons of Machir, the son of Manasseh, to one half part of the sons of Machir, according to their families.

32 Moses divided this possession, in the plains of Moab, beyond the Jordan, opposite Jericho on the eastern side.

33 But to the tribe of Levi he did not give a possession. For the Lord, the God of Israel, is himself their possession, just as he spoke to him.

Joshua 14

1 This is what the sons of Israel possessed in the land of Canaan, which Eleazar, the priest, and Joshua, the son of Nun, and the leaders of the families, by the tribes of Israel, gave to them,

2 dividing all by lot, just as the Lord had instructed by the hand of Moses, to the nine tribes and to the one half tribe.

3 For to the two and one half tribes, Moses had given a possession beyond the Jordan, aside from the Levites, who received no land among their brothers.

4 For by succession, the sons of Joseph, in their place, were divided into two tribes, Manasseh and Ephraim. But the Levites did not receive another portion of land, except cities in which to live, and their suburbs, so as to feed their beasts of burden and cattle.

5 Just as the Lord had commanded Moses, so the sons of Israel did, and they divided the land.

6 And so, the sons of Judah approached Joshua at Gilgal. And Caleb, the son of Jephone, the Kenizzite, spoke to him: "You know what the Lord said to Moses, the man of God, at Kadesh-barnea, about me and you.

7 I was forty years old when Moses, the servant of the Lord, sent me from Kadesh-barnea, so that I might consider the land. And I reported to him what seemed to me to be true.

8 But my brothers, who had ascended with me, broke the heart of the people. And I nevertheless followed the Lord my God.

9 And Moses swore, on that day, saying: 'The land that your foot has tread upon shall be your possession, and that of your sons, unto eternity. For you have followed the Lord my God.'

10 Therefore, the Lord has granted life to me, just as he promised, even to the present day. It has been forty-five years since the Lord spoke this word to Moses, when Israel was wandering through the wilderness. Today, I am eighty-five years old,

11 being just as strong as I was at that time, when I was sent to explore the land. The fortitude in me at that time continues even until today, as much to fight as to march.

12 Therefore, grant to me this mountain, which the Lord has promised in your hearing also, on which are the Anakim, and cities, great and fortified. Perhaps it may be that the Lord will be with me, and I will be able to destroy them, just as he promised to me."

13 And Joshua blessed him, and he delivered Hebron to him as a possession.

14 And from then on, Hebron was for Caleb, the son of Jephunneh, the Kenizzite, even to the present day. For he followed the Lord, the God of Israel.

15 Previously, the name Hebron was called Kiriath-Arba. Adam, the greatest among the Anakim, was laid there. And the land ceased from battles.

Joshua 15

1 And so, the lot of the sons of Judah, by their families, was this: from the border of Edom, to the desert of Sin toward the south, and even to the furthest part of the southern region.

2 Its beginning was from the summit of the very salty sea, and from its bay, which looks toward the south.

3 And it extends toward the ascent of the Scorpion, and it passes on to Sinai. And it ascends into Kadesh-barnea, and it passes through to Hezron, ascending to Addar, and encompassing Karka.

4 And from there, it passes on to Azmon, and reaches to the torrent of Egypt. And its boundary shall be the great sea; this shall be the limit of the southern region.

5 Yet truly, toward the east, the beginning shall be the very salty sea, even to the limit of the Jordan, and that which looks toward the north, from the bay of the sea, even to the same river Jordan.

6 And the border ascends into Beth-hoglah, and it crosses from the north into Beth-Arabah, ascending to the stone of Bohan, the son of Reuben.

7 And it reaches as far as the borders of Debara, from the Valley of Achor, to the north, looking toward Gilgal, which is opposite the Ascent of Adummim, on the southern part of the torrent. And it crosses the waters that are called the Fountain of the Sun. And its exit shall be at the Fountain of Rogel.

8 And it ascends by the steep valley of the son of Hinnom, from the side of the Jebusite, toward the south; this is Jerusalem. And from there, it raises itself to the top of the mountain, which is opposite Geennom to the west, at the top of the Valley of the Rephaim, to the north.

9 And it passes through, from the top of the mountain, even to the fountain of the Water of Nephtoah. And it continues on, as far as the villages of mount Ephron. And it inclines toward Baalah, which is Kiriath-jearim, that is, the City of Forests.

10 And it circles from Baalah, to the west, as far as mount Seir. And it passes by the side of mount Jearim, to the north, into Chesalon. And it descends into Beth-shemesh, and it passes through to Timnah.

11 And it continues on, toward the north, to a region beside Ekron. And it inclines toward Shikkeron, and it crosses to mount Baalah. And it extends into Jabneel, and the last part closes at the west with the great sea.

12 These are the borders of the sons of Judah, in their families, on all sides.

13 Yet truly, to Caleb, the son of Jephunneh, he gave a portion in the midst of the sons of Judah, just as the Lord had instructed him: the City of Arba, the father of Anak, which is Hebron.

14 And Caleb destroyed from it the three sons of Anak, Sheshai, and Ahiman, and Talmai, of the stock of Anak.

15 And ascending further from there, he came to the inhabitants of Debir, which before was called Kiriath-Sepher, that is, the City of Letters.

16 And Caleb said, "Whoever will have struck down Kiriath-Sepher, and will have seized it, I will give to him Achsah, my daughter, as wife."

17 And Othniel, the son of Kenaz, the younger brother of Caleb, seized it. And he gave him Achsah, his daughter, as wife.

18 And as they were traveling together, she was urged by her husband that she ask her father for a field. And she sighed, as she was sitting on her donkey. And Caleb said to her, "What is it?"

19 But she answered: "Give a blessing to me. You have given to me a southern and dry land; join to it also a watered land." And so Caleb gave to her the watered land above and below it.

20 This is the possession of the tribe of the sons of Judah, by their families.

21 And the cities, from the furthest parts of the sons of Judah, beside the borders of Edom to the south, were: Kabzeel and Eder and Jagur,

22 and Kinah and Dimonah and Adadah,

23 and Kadesh and Hazor and Ithnan,

24 Ziph and Telem and Bealoth,

25 new Hazor and Kerioth-Hezron, which is Hazor,

26 Amam, Shema, and Moladah,

27 and Hazar-gaddah and Heshmon and Bethpelet,

28 and Hazar-shual and Beersheba and Biziothiah,

29 and Baalah and Iim and Ezem,

30 and Eltolad and Chesil and Hormah,

31 and Ziklag and Madmannah and Sansannah,

32 Lebaoth and Shilhim, and Ain and Rimmon. All the cities were twenty-nine, and their villages.

33 Truly, in the plains, there were: Eshtaol and Zorah and Ashnah,

34 and Zanoah and Engannim, and Tappuah and Enam,

35 and Jarmuth and Adullam, Socoh and Azekah,

36 and Shaaraim and Adithaim, and Gederah and Gederothaim: fourteen cities, and their villages.

37 Zenan and Hadashah and Middalgad,

38 Dilean and Mizpeh and Joktheel,

39 Lachish and Bozkath and Eglon,

40 Cabbon and Lahmam and Chitlish,

41 and Gederoth and Bethdagon, and Naamah and Makkedah: sixteen cities, and their villages.

42 Libnah and Ether and Ashan,

43 Iphtah and Ashnah and Nezib,

44 and Keilah and Achzib and Mareshah: nine cities, and their villages.

45 Ekron, with its towns and villages:

46 from Ekron, as far as the sea, all that inclines toward Ashdod, and its villages.

47 Ashdod, with its towns and villages. Gaza, with its towns and villages, as far as the torrent of Egypt, with the great sea as its border.

48 And on the mountain, Shamir and Jattir and Socoh,

49 and Dannah, and Kiriath-Sannah, which is Debir,

50 Anab and Eshtemoh and Anim,

51 Goshen and Holon and Giloh: eleven cities, and their villages.

52 Arab and Dumah and Eshan,

53 and Janim and Beth-Tappuah and Aphekah,

54 Humtah and Kiriath-Arba, which is Hebron, and Zior: nine cities, and their villages.

55 Maon and Carmel, and Ziph and Juttah,

56 Jezreel and Jokdeam and Zanoah,

57 Kain, Gibeah, and Timnah: ten cities, and their villages.

58 Halhul and Bethzur and Gedor,

59 Maarath and Bethanoth and Eltekon: six cities, and their villages.

60 Kiriath-baal, which is Kiriath-jearim, the City of Forests, and Rabbah: two cities, and their villages.

61 In the desert: Beth-Arabah, Middin, and Secacah,

62 and Nibshan, and the City of Salt, and Engedi: six cities, and their villages.

63 But the sons of Judah were not able to destroy the Jebusite inhabitants of Jerusalem. And so the Jebusite lived with the sons of Judah in Jerusalem, even to the present day.

Joshua 16

1 Similarly, the lot of the sons of Joseph fell from the Jordan, opposite Jericho and its waters, to the east, to the wilderness that ascends from Jericho to the mountain of Bethel.

2 And it goes out from Bethel to Luz. And it crosses the border of Archi to Ataroth.

3 And it descends to the west, beside the border of Japhleti, as far as the borders of lower Beth-horon, and to Gezer. And the last parts of its regions are by the great sea.

4 And Manasseh and Ephraim, the sons of Joseph, possessed it.

5 And the border of the sons of Ephraim was made by their families. And their possession toward the east was from Ataroth-addar, as far as upper Beth-horon,

6 and the confines extend to the sea. Yet truly, Michmethath looks toward the north, and it circles around the borders, toward the east, into Taanath-shiloh. And it continues on, from the east, to Janoah.

7 And it descends from Janoah to Ataroth and Naarah. and it continues to Jericho, and it extends to the Jordan.

8 From Tappuah, it passes on, opposite the sea, into the Valley of Reeds. And its exit is at the very salty sea. This is the possession of the tribe of the sons of Ephraim, by their families.

9 And there were cities, with their villages, which were set aside for the sons of Ephraim, in the midst of the possession of the sons of Manasseh.

10 And the sons of Ephraim did not put to death the Canaanite that was living at Gezer. And the Canaanite lived in the midst of Ephraim, even to this day, paying tribute.

Joshua 17

1 Now this lot fell to the tribe of Manasseh, since he is the firstborn of Joseph: to Machir, the firstborn of Manasseh, the father of Gilead, who was a fighting man, and he had as a possession Gilead and Bashan;

2 and to the rest of the sons of Manasseh, according to their families: to the sons of Abiezer, and to the sons of Helek, and to the sons of Asriel, and to the sons of Shechem, and to the sons of Hepher, and to the sons of Shemida. These are the sons of Manasseh, the son of Joseph, the males, by their families.

3 Yet truly, Zelophehad, the son of Hepher, the son of Gilead, the son of Machir, the son of Manasseh, had no sons, but only daughters, whose names are these: Mahlah and Noah and Hoglah and Milcah and Tirzah.

4 And they went before the sight of Eleazar, the priest, and Joshua, the son of Nun, and the leaders, saying: "The Lord instructed by the hand of Moses that a possession ought to be given to us, in the midst of our brothers." And so, he gave to them, in accord with the order of the Lord, a possession in the midst of the brothers of their father.

5 And by lot, there fell ten portions to Manasseh, aside from the land of Gilead and Bashan beyond the Jordan.

6 And so the daughters of Manasseh possessed an inheritance in the midst of his sons. But the land of Gilead fell by lot to the sons of Manasseh that were left.

7 And the border of Manasseh was from Asher to Michmethath, which looks out toward Shechem. And it goes out, to the right, beside the inhabitants of the Fountain of Tappuah.

8 For by lot, there also fell to Manasseh the land of Tappuah, which is beside the borders of Manasseh, and which belongs to the sons of Ephraim.

9 And the border descends to the Valley of Reeds, to the south of the torrent of the cities of Ephraim, which are in the midst of the cities of Manasseh. The border of Manasseh is to the north of the torrent, and its exit extends to the sea.

10 So it is that the possession of Ephraim is in the south, and that of Manasseh is in the north, and both are enclosed by the sea, and they are joined together by the tribe of Asher to the north, and by the tribe of Issachar to the east.

11 And the inheritance of Manasseh, in Issachar and in Asher, was Bethshean and its villages, and Ibleam with its villages, and the inhabitants of Dor, with their towns, likewise the inhabitants of Endor with their villages, and similarly the inhabitants of Taanach with their villages, and the inhabitants of Megiddo with their villages, and one third part of the city of Naphath.

12 The sons of Manasseh were not able to overthrow these cities, and so the Canaanite began to dwell in their land.

13 But after the sons of Israel had grown strong, they subdued the Canaanites, and made them their tributaries, but they did not kill them.

14 And the sons of Joseph spoke to Joshua, and they said, "Why have you given to me as a possession one lot and one portion, while I am of such a great multitude, and the Lord has blessed me?"

15 And Joshua said to them, "If you are a numerous people, go up into the forest, and cut out space for yourself in the land of the Perizzites and the Rephaim, since the possession of mount Ephraim is too narrow for you."

16 And the sons of Joseph responded to him: "We are not able to ascend to the mountains, since the Canaanites, who live in the plains, in which are situated Bethshean, with its villages, and Jezreel, possessing the middle of the valley, use chariots of iron."

17 And Joshua said to the house of Joseph, to Ephraim and Manasseh: "You are a numerous people, and you have great strength. You shall not have only one lot.

18 Instead, you shall cross to the mountain, and you shall cut down and clear out for yourselves space in which to live. And you shall be able to advance further, when you will have destroyed the Canaanite, who, as you say, has iron chariots and is very strong."

Joshua 18

1 And all the sons of Israel gathered together at Shiloh, and there they stationed the Tabernacle of the Testimony. And the land was subjected to them.

2 But there remained seven tribes of the sons of Israel which had not yet received their possessions.

3 And Joshua said to them: "For how long will you draw back in idleness, and not enter to possess the land, which the Lord, the God of your fathers, has given to you?

4 Select three men from each tribe, so that I may send them, and they may go forth and circle through the land, and may describe it according to the number of each multitude, and may bring back to me what they have written down.

5 Divide the land for yourselves into seven parts. Let Judah be its bounds on the southern side, and the house of Joseph to the north.

6 The land that is in the middle, between these, write it down in seven parts. And you shall come to me, so that I may cast lots for you about this, before the Lord your God.

7 But there is no portion among you for the Levites. Instead, the priesthood of the Lord is their inheritance. And Gad and Reuben, and the one half tribe of Manasseh, have already received their possessions beyond the Jordan in the eastern region, which Moses, the servant of the Lord, gave to them."

8 And when the men had risen up, so that they might go out to describe the land, Joshua instructed them, saying, "Circle through the land, and describe it, and return to me, so that I may cast lots for you about this, before the Lord, in Shiloh."

9 And so they went out. And surveying it, they divided it into seven parts, writing it in a book. And they returned to Joshua, to the camp at Shiloh.

10 And he cast lots before the Lord, at Shiloh, and he divided the land to the sons of Israel, in seven parts.

11 And the first lot went to the sons of Benjamin, by their families, so that they would possess the land between the sons of Judah and the sons of Joseph.

12 And their border toward the north was from the Jordan, continuing on, near the side of Jericho in the northern region, and from there, ascending toward the west to the mountains, and extending to the wilderness of Bethaven.

13 And it continues to the south beside Luz, which is Bethel. And it descends into Ataroth-addar, at the mountain which is to the south of lower Beth-horon.

14 And it turns aside, circling toward the sea, to the south of the mountain which looks out toward Beth-horon, toward the southwest. And its exits are toward Kiriath-baal, which is also called Kiriath-jearim, a city of the sons of Judah. This is their region, toward the sea, in the west.

15 But to the south, the border goes on from the part of Kiriath-jearim toward the sea, and it continues as far as the Fountain of the waters of Nephtoah.

16 And it descends to that part of the mountain which looks out toward the Valley of the sons of Hinnom. And it is opposite the northern region, in the furthest part of the Valley of the Rephaim. And it descends into Geennom, (that is, the Valley of Hinnom,) near the side of the Jebusite toward the south. And it extends to the Fountain of Rogel,

17 crossing from there to the north, and going out to En-Shemesh, that is, to the Fountain of the Sun.

18 And it passes through to the hills that are opposite the region of the Ascent of Adummim. And it descends to Abenboen, that is, so the stone of Bohan, the son of Reuben. And it continues on, at the northern side, to the plains. And it descends into the flatlands.

19 And it advances before Beth-hoglah, to the north. And its exits are to the north, opposite the bay of the very salty sea, in the southern region at the end of the Jordan,

20 which is its border to the east. This is the possession of the sons of Benjamin, with their borders all around, and by their families.

21 And their cities were: Jericho and Beth-hoglah and the Abrupt Valley,

22 Beth-arabah and Zemaraim and Bethel,

23 and Avvim and Parah and Ophrah,

24 the town of Ammoni, and Ophni, and Geba: twelve cities, and their villages;

25 Gibeon and Ramah and Beeroth,

26 and Mizpeh and Chephirah and Mozah,

27 and Rekem, Irpeel, and Taralah,

28 and Zela, Haeleph, and Jebus, which is Jerusalem, Gibeah and Kiriath: fourteen cities, and their villages. This is the possession of the sons of Benjamin, according to their families.

Joshua 19

1 And the second lot went out, for the sons of Simeon by their families. And their inheritance was,

2 in the midst of the possession of the sons of Judah: Beersheba, and Sheba, and Moladah,

3 and Hazar-shual, Balah, and Ezem,

4 and Eltolad, Bethul, and Hormah,

5 and Ziklag, and Beth-marcaboth, and Hazar-susah,

6 and Bethlebaoth, and Sharuhen: thirteen cities, and their villages;

7 Ain and Enrimmon, and Ether and Ashan: four cities, and their villages;

8 all villages around these cities, as far as Baalath-beer, the high place facing the southern region. This is the inheritance of the sons of Simeon, according to their families,

9 within the possession and lot of the sons of Judah, which was greater. And for this reason, the sons of Simeon had a possession in the midst of their inheritance.

10 And the third lot fell to the sons of Zebulun, by their families; and the limit of their possession was set as far as Sarid.

11 And it ascends from the sea and from Mareal. And it passes on to Dabbesheth, as far as the torrent, which is opposite Jokneam.

12 And it turns back from Sarid, to the east, to the end of Chisloth-tabor. And it goes out to Daberath, and it ascends opposite Japhia.

13 And from there, it continues to the eastern region of Gathhepher and Ethkazin. And goes out to Rimmon, Amthar, and Neah.

14 And it circles to the north at Hannathon. And its exits are at the Valley of Iphtahel;

15 and Kattath and Nahalal, and Shimron and Idalah, and Bethlehem: twelve cities, and their villages.

16 This is the inheritance of the tribe of the sons of Zebulun, by their families, the cities and their villages.

17 The fourth lot went out to Issachar, by their families.

18 And his inheritance was: Jezreel, and Chesulloth, and Shunem,

19 and Hapharaim, and Shion, and Anaharath,

20 and Rabbith and Kishion, Ebez

21 and Remeth, and Engannim, and Enhaddah, and Bethpazzez.

22 And its limit reaches to Tabor and Shahazumah and Beth-shemesh; and its exits shall be at the Jordan: sixteen cities, and their villages.

23 This is the possession of the sons of Issachar by their families, the cities and their villages.

24 And the fifth lot fell to the tribe of the sons of Asher, by their families.

25 And their border was: Helkath, and Hali, and Beten, and Achshaph,

26 and Allammelech, and Amad, and Mishal. And it extends even to Carmel by the sea, and Shihor, and Libnath.

27 And it turns back toward the east at Bethdagon. And it continues on as far as Zebulun and the Valley of Iphtahel, toward the north, at Beth-emek and Neiel. And it goes out to the left of Cabul,

28 and to Ebron, and Rehob, and Hammon, and Kanah, as far as the great Sidon.

29 And it turns back at Ramah, even to the very fortified city of Tyre, and even to Hosah. And its exits shall be at the sea, from the lot of Achzib;

30 and Ummah, and Aphek, and Rehob: twenty-two cities, and their villages.

31 This is the possession of the sons of Asher, by their families, and the cities and their villages.

32 The sixth lot fell to the sons of Naphtali, by their families.

33 And its border begins from Heleph and Elon, into Zaanannim, and Adami, which is Nekeb, and Jabneel, as far as Lakkum. And its exits are as far as the Jordan.

34 And the border turns back to the west at Aznoth-tabor, and it goes out from there to Hukkok. And continues on to Zebulun, in the south, and to Asher, in the west, and to Judah, at the Jordan, toward the rising of the sun.

35 And the most fortified cities are Ziddim, Zer and Hammath, and Rakkath, and Chinnereth,

36 and Adamah and Ramah, Hazor

37 and Kedesh and Edrei, Enhazor

38 and Yiron and Migdalel, Horem and Bethanath, and Beth-shemesh: nineteen cities, and their villages.

39 This is the possession of the tribe of the sons of Naphtali, by their families, the cities and their villages.

40 The seventh lot went out to the tribe of the sons of Dan, by their families.

41 And the border of their possession was Zorah, and Eshtaol, and Ir-shemesh, that is, the City of the Sun,

42 Sha-alabbin, and Aijalon, and Ithlah,

43 Elon, and Timnah, and Ekron,

44 Eltekeh, Gibbethon and Baalath,

45 and Jehud, and Bene and Berak, and Gath-Rimmon,

46 and Mejarkon and Rakkon, with a border that looks toward Joppa,

47 and there the last part is concluded. And the sons of Dan ascended and fought against Leshem, and they seized it. And they struck it with the mouth of the sword, and they possessed it, and they lived in it, calling it by the name of Leshem-Dan, according to the name of their father Dan.

48 This is the possession of the tribe of the sons of Dan, by their families, the cities and their villages.

49 And when he had completed dividing the land by lot to each one by their tribes, the sons of Israel gave a possession to Joshua, the son of Nun, in their midst,

50 in accord with the precept of the Lord, the city he requested, Timnath-Serah, on mount Ephraim. And he built up the city, and he lived in it.

51 These are the possessions which Eleazar, the priest, and Joshua, the son of Nun, and the leaders of the families and tribes of the sons of Israel divided by lot at Shiloh, before the Lord, at the door of the Tabernacle of the Testimony. And so did they divide the land.

Joshua 20

1 And the Lord spoke to Joshua, saying: "Speak to the sons of Israel, and say to them:

2 Separate the cities of refuge, about which I spoke to you by the hand of Moses,

3 so that anyone who will have struck down a life unintentionally may flee to them. And so, he may be able to escape from the wrath of a close relative, who is an avenger of blood.

4 And when he will have fled to one of these cities, he shall stand before the gate of the city, and he shall speak to the ancients of that city, the things that prove him innocent. And so shall they receive him, and give him a place in which to live.

5 And if the avenger of blood will have pursued him, they shall not deliver him into his hands. For he struck down his neighbor unknowingly, one who was not proven to have been his enemy two or three days before.

6 And he shall live in that city, until he stands before judgment in order to render the facts of his case, and until the death of the high priest, whoever it will be in that time. Then the one who killed a man may return, and he may enter his own city and house, from which he had fled."

7 And they decreed Kedesh in Galilee, at mount Naphtali, and Shechem, at mount Ephraim, and Kiriath-Arba, which is Hebron, at mount Judah.

8 And beyond the Jordan, opposite the eastern side of Jericho, they appointed Bezer, which is situated on the plain of the wilderness of the tribe of Reuben, and Ramoth in Gilead of the tribe of Gad, and Golan in Bashan of the tribe of Manasseh.

9 These cities were established for all the sons of Israel, and for the new arrivals who were living among them, so that whoever had struck down a life unintentionally might flee to these, and not die at the hand of a close relative who desires to vindicate the blood that was shed, until he should stand before the people, in order to present his case.

Joshua 21

1 And the leaders of the families of Levi approached Eleazar, the priest, and Joshua, the son of Nun, and the rulers of the extended families of each of the tribes of the sons of Israel.

2 And they spoke to them at Shiloh, in the land of Canaan, and they said, "The Lord instructed, by the hand of Moses, that cities should be given to us as habitations, with their suburbs to nourish our cattle."

3 And so the sons of Israel gave cities and their suburbs from their possessions, in accord with the order of the Lord.

4 And the lot went out for the family of Kohath, of the sons of Aaron, the priest, from the tribes of Judah and Simeon and Benjamin: thirteen cities.

5 And to the remainder of the sons of Kohath, that is, to the Levites who were left over, there went, from the tribes of Ephraim and Dan, and from the one half tribe of Manasseh, ten cities.

6 And next the lot went out to the sons of Gershon, so that they would receive, from the tribes of Issachar and Asher and Naphtali, and from the one half tribe of Manasseh at Bashan: the number of thirteen cities.

7 And to the sons of Merari, by their families, from the tribes of Reuben and Gad and Zebulun, there went twelve cities.

8 And so the sons of Israel gave cities and their suburbs to the Levites, just as the Lord instructed by the hand of Moses, distributing to each by lot.

9 From the tribes of the sons of Judah and Simeon, Joshua gave cities, whose names are these:

10 to the sons of Aaron, of the families of Kohath of the stock of Levi, (for the first lot went out for them,)

11 the city of Arba, the father of Anak, which is called Hebron, on the mountain of Judah, and its surrounding suburbs.

12 Yet truly, the fields and its villages he had given to Caleb, the son of Jephunneh, as a possession.

13 Therefore, he gave to the sons of Aaron the priest, Hebron as a city of refuge, as well as its suburbs, and Libnah, with its suburbs,

14 and Jattir, and Eshtemoa,

15 and Holon, and Debir,

16 and Ain, and Juttah, and Beth-shemesh, with their suburbs: nine cities from two tribes, just as has been said.

17 Then, from the tribe of the sons of Benjamin, he gave Gibeon, and Geba,

18 and Anathoth, and Almon, with their suburbs: four cities.

19 All the cities together of the sons of Aaron, the priest, were thirteen, with their suburbs.

20 Yet truly, the remainder of the families of the sons of Kohath, of the stock of Levi, were given this possession:

21 from the tribe of Ephraim, Shechem, one of the cities of refuge, with its suburbs, on mount Ephraim, and Gezer,

22 and Kibzaim, and Beth-horon, with their suburbs, four cities;

23 and from the tribe of Dan, Elteke and Gibbethon,

24 and Aijalon and Gath-Rimmon, with their suburbs, four cities;

25 then, from the one half tribe of Manasseh, Taanach and Gath-Rimmon, with their suburbs, two cities.

26 All the cities were ten, with their suburbs; these were given to the sons of Kohath, of the lesser degree.

27 Likewise, to the sons of Gershon, of the stock of Levi, from the one half tribe of Manasseh, went Golan in Bashan, one of the cities of refuge, and Bosra, with their suburbs, two cities;

28 also, from the tribe of Issachar, Kishion, and Daberath,

29 and Jarmuth, and Engannim, with their suburbs, four cities;

30 then, from the tribe of Asher, Mishal and Abdon,

31 and Helkath and Rehob, with their suburbs, four cities;

32 likewise, from the tribe of Naphtali, Kedesh in Galilee, one of the cities of refuge, and Hammoth-Dor, and Kartan, with their suburbs, three cities.

33 All the cities of the families of Gershon were thirteen, with their suburbs.

34 Then, to the sons of Merari, Levites of the lesser degree, by their families, were given, from the tribe of Zebulun, Jokneam and Kartah,

35 and Dimnah and Nahalal, four cities with their suburbs;

36 from the tribe of Reuben, beyond the Jordan, opposite Jericho, Bezer in the wilderness, one of the cities of refuge, Misor and Jazer, and Jethson and Mephaath, four cities with their suburbs;

37 from the tribe of Gad, Ramoth of Gilead, one of the cities of refuge, and Mahanaim and Heshbon and Jazer, four cities with their suburbs.

38 All the cities of the sons of Merari, by their families and extended families, were twelve.

39 And so all the cities of the Levites, in the midst of the possession of the sons of Israel, were forty-eight,

40 with their suburbs, each distributed by families.

41 And the Lord God gave to Israel all the land that he had sworn he would deliver to their fathers. And they possessed it, and they lived in it.

42 And he gave them peace with all the surrounding nations. And none of their enemies dared to stand against them; instead, they were brought under their sovereignty.

43 Indeed, not so much as one word that he had promised to provide for them was left empty; instead, everything was fulfilled.

Joshua 22

1 In the same time, Joshua called the Reubenites, and the Gadites, and the one half tribe of Manasseh.

2 And he said to them: "You have done all that Moses, the servant of the Lord, instructed you. You have also obeyed me in all things.

3 Neither have you forsaken your brothers during this long time, even to the present day, keeping the orders of the Lord your God.

4 Therefore, since the Lord your God has given your brothers peace and quiet, just as he promised: return, and go into your tents and into the land of your possession, which Moses, the servant of the Lord, delivered to you beyond the Jordan.

5 And may you continue to observe attentively, and to work to fulfill, the commandment and the law that Moses, the servant of the Lord, instructed to you, so that you may love the Lord your God, and walk in all his ways, and keep all his commandments, and cling to him, and serve him with all your heart and with all your soul."

6 And Joshua blessed them, and he sent them away. And they returned to their tents.

7 Now to the one half tribe of Manasseh, Moses had given a possession in Bashan. And therefore, to the one half that was left over, Joshua gave a lot among the remainder of their brothers across the Jordan, in the western region. And when he had blessed them and dismissed them to their tents,

8 he said to them: "Return to your settlements with much substance and wealth, with silver and gold, brass and iron, and a multitude of garments. Divide the spoils of your enemies with your brothers."

9 And the sons of Reuben, and the sons of Gad, and the one half tribe of Manasseh returned, and they went away from the sons of Israel at Shiloh, which is situated in Canaan, so that they might enter into Gilead, the land of their possession, which they had obtained according to the order of the Lord, by the hand of Moses.

10 And when they had arrived at the hills of the Jordan in the land of Canaan, they built an altar of immense magnitude beside the Jordan.

11 And when the sons of Israel had heard of it, and certain messengers had reported to them that the sons of Reuben, and of Gad, and of the one half tribe of Manasseh had built an altar in the land of Canaan, upon the hills of the Jordan, facing the sons of Israel,

12 they all assembled at Shiloh, so that they might go up and battle against them.

13 And in the interim, they sent to them, in the land of Gilead, Phinehas, the son of Eleazar, the priest,

14 and ten leaders with him, one from each tribe.

15 And they went to the sons of Reuben, and of Gad, and of the one half tribe of Manasseh, in the land of Gilead, and they said to them:

16 "All the people of the Lord declare this: What is this transgression? Why have you forsaken the Lord, the God of Israel, by building a sacrilegious altar, and by withdrawing from the worship of him?

17 Is it a small thing to you that you have sinned with Baal of Peor, and that the stain of that crime continues among us, even to the present day? And many of the people have fallen.

18 And yet you have forsaken the Lord today, and tomorrow his wrath will rage against all of Israel.

19 But if you consider the land of your possession to be unclean, cross over to the land in which is the tabernacle of the Lord, and live among us. But do not withdraw from the Lord, and from our fellowship, by building an altar contrary to the altar of the Lord our God.

20 Did not Achan, the son of Zerah, go against the commandment of the Lord, and so his wrath was laid over all the people of Israel? And he was only one man. If only he had perished in his wickedness alone!"

21 And the sons of Reuben, and of Gad, and of the one half tribe of Manasseh responded to the leaders of the delegation from Israel:

22 "The Lord, the almighty God, the Lord, the almighty God, he knows, and also Israel will understand: If we have constructed this altar with intent of transgression, let him not preserve us, but instead punish us immediately.

23 And if we have acted with a mind so that we might present upon it holocausts, and sacrifice, and victims of peace offerings, let him inquire and judge.

24 Instead, we have acted with this greater thought and design, that we would say: Tomorrow your sons will say to our sons: 'What is there between you and the Lord, the God of Israel?

25 The Lord has stationed the river Jordan as the border between us and you, O sons of Reuben, O sons of Gad. And therefore, you have no part in the Lord.' And by this occasion, your sons would turn away our sons from the fear of the Lord. And so we sought something better,

26 and we said: Let us build us an altar, not for holocausts, and not to offer victims,

27 but as a testimony between us and you, and between our descendents and your progeny, so that we may serve the Lord, and so that it may be our right to offer holocausts, and victims, and peace offerings, and so that tomorrow your sons may not say to our sons: 'You have no part in the Lord.'

28 And if they decide to say this, they shall respond to them: 'Behold, the altar of the Lord, which our fathers made, not for holocausts, and not for sacrifice, but instead as a testimony between us and you.'

29 May this wickedness be far from us, such that we would withdraw from the Lord, and would forsake his paths, by constructing an altar to offer holocausts, and sacrifices, and victims, contrary to the altar of the Lord our God, which was built before his tabernacle."

30 And when Phinehas, the priest, and the leaders of the delegation who were with him, had heard this, they were pleased. And they accepted very willingly the words of the sons of Reuben, and of Gad, and of the one half tribe of Manasseh.

31 And Phinehas, the priest, the son of Eleazar, said to them: "Now we know that the Lord is with us. For you are a stranger to this transgression. And so you have freed the sons of Israel from the hand of the Lord."

32 And he returned with the leaders, from the sons of Reuben and of Gad, out of the land of Gilead, into the parts of Canaan, to the sons of Israel. And he reported to them.

33 And the word pleased all who heard it. And the sons of Israel praised God, and they no longer said that they would go up against them, and fight, and destroy the land of their possession.

34 And the sons of Reuben and the sons of Gad called the altar that they had built: Our testimony that the Lord himself is God.

Joshua 23

1 Now a long time passed, after the Lord had given peace to Israel by subjecting all the surrounding nations. And Joshua was now old and very advanced in age.

2 Joshua called all of Israel, and those greater by birth, and the leaders and rulers and teachers, and he said to them: "I am elderly and advanced in age.

3 And you yourselves discern all that the Lord your God has done with all the surrounding nations, in what manner he himself has fought for you.

4 And now, since he has divided to you by lot all the land, from the eastern part of the Jordan even to the great sea, and yet many nations still remain,

5 the Lord your God will destroy them, and he will take them away before your face, and you shall possess the land, just as he has promised you.

6 Even so, be strengthened and be careful that you observe all the things that have been written in the book of the law of Moses, and that you do not turn aside from them, neither to the right, nor to the left.

7 Otherwise, after you have entered to the Gentiles, who will be among you in the future, you might swear by the name of their gods, and serve them, and adore them.

8 Instead, cling to the Lord your God, just as you have done even to this day.

9 And then the Lord God will take away, in your sight, nations that are great and very robust, and no one will be able to withstand you.

10 One of you shall pursue a thousand men of the enemies. For the Lord your God himself will fight on your behalf, just as he promised.

11 Even so, be very diligent and careful in this: that you love the Lord your God.

12 But if you choose to cling to the errors of these nations that live among you, and to mix with them by marriage, and to join with them by friendship,

13 even now, know this: that the Lord your God will not wipe them away before your face. Instead, they shall be a pit and a snare to you, and a stumbling block at your side, and stakes in your eyes, until he takes you away and scatters you from this excellent land, which he has delivered to you.

14 Lo, today I am entering the way of the entire earth, and you shall know with all your mind that, out of all the words that the Lord has promised to fulfill for you, not one will pass by unfulfilled.

15 Therefore, just as he has fulfilled in deed what he has promised, and all prosperous things have arrived, so will he bring upon you whatever evils were threatened, until he takes you away and scatters you from this excellent land, which he has delivered to you,

16 when you will have transgressed the covenant of the Lord your God, which he has formed with you, and will have served strange gods, and will have adored them. And then the fury of the Lord will rise up quickly and speedily against you, and you will be taken away from this excellent land, which he has delivered to you."

Joshua 24

1 And Joshua gathered together all the tribes of Israel at Shechem, and he called those greater by birth, and the leaders and judges and teachers. And they stood in the sight of the Lord.

2 And he spoke to the people in this way: "Thus says the Lord, the God of Israel: 'Your fathers lived, in the beginning, across the river: Terah, the father of Abraham, and Nahor. And they served strange gods.

3 Then I brought your father Abraham from the parts of Mesopotamia, and I led him into the land of Canaan. And I multiplied his offspring,

4 and I gave to him Isaac. And to him, I gave again Jacob and Esau. And I gave mount Seir to Esau as a possession. Yet truly, Jacob and his sons descended into Egypt.

5 And I sent Moses and Aaron, and I struck Egypt with many signs and portents.

6 And I led you and your fathers away from Egypt, and you arrived at the sea. And the Egyptians pursued your fathers with chariots and horsemen, as far as the Red Sea.

7 Then the sons of Israel cried out to the Lord. And he stationed a darkness between you and the Egyptians, and he led the sea over them, and he covered them. Your eyes saw all that I did in Egypt, and you lived in the wilderness for a long time.

8 And I led you into the land of the Amorite, who was living beyond the Jordan. And when they fought against you, I delivered them into your hands, and you possessed their land, and you put them to death.

9 Then Balak, the son of Zippor, the king of Moab, rose up and fought against Israel. And he sent and called for Balaam, the son of Beor, so that he might curse you.

10 And I was not willing to listen to him, but on the contrary, I blessed you through him, and I freed you from his hand.

11 And you crossed over the Jordan, and you arrived at Jericho. And the men of that city fought against you: the Amorite, and the Perizzite, and the Canaanite, and the Hittite, and the Girgashite, and the Hivite, and the Jebusite. And I delivered them into your hands.

12 And I sent wasps before you. And I drove them from their places, the two kings of the Amorites, but not by your sword, and not by your bow.

13 And I gave you a land, in which you did not labor, and cities, which you did not build, so that you might live in them, and vineyards and olive groves, which you did not plant.'

14 Now therefore, fear the Lord, and serve him with a perfect and very sincere heart. And take away the gods that your fathers served in Mesopotamia and in Egypt, and serve the Lord.

15 But if it seems evil to you that you would serve the Lord, a choice is given to you. Choose today what pleases you, and whom you ought to serve above all else, either the gods that your fathers served in Mesopotamia, or the gods of the Amorites, in whose land you live: but as for me and my house, we will serve the Lord."

16 And the people responded, and they said: "Far be it from us that we would forsake the Lord, and serve foreign gods.

17 The Lord our God himself led us and our fathers away from the land of Egypt, from the house of servitude. And he accomplished immense signs in our sight, and he preserved us along the entire way by which we journeyed, and among all the people through whom we passed.

18 And he cast out all the nations, the Amorite, the inhabitant of the land that we entered. And so, we will serve the Lord, for he is our God."

19 And Joshua said to the people: "You will not be able to serve the Lord. For he is a holy and powerful God, and he is jealous, and he will not ignore your wickedness and sins.

20 If you leave behind the Lord, and you serve foreign gods, he will turn himself, and he will afflict you, and he will overthrow you, after all the good that he has offered to you."

21 And the people said to Joshua, "By no means will it be as you are saying, but we will serve the Lord."

22 And Joshua said to the people, "You yourselves are witnesses, that you have chosen the Lord so that you may serve him." And they answered, "We are witnesses."

23 "Now therefore," he said, "take away strange gods from among yourselves, and incline your hearts to the Lord, the God of Israel."

24 And the people said to Joshua, "We will serve the Lord our God, and we will be obedient to his precepts."

25 Therefore, on that day, Joshua struck a covenant, and he set before the people at Shechem the precepts and the judgments.

26 He also wrote all these things in the volume of the law of the Lord. And he took a very great stone, and he stationed it under the oak that was in the Sanctuary of the Lord.

27 And he said to all the people, "Lo, this stone shall be to you as a testimony, which has heard all the words of the Lord that he has spoken to you, lest perhaps, afterward, you might choose to deny it, and to lie to the Lord your God."

28 And he dismissed the people, each one to their own possession.

29 And after these things, Joshua, the son of Nun, the servant of the Lord, died, being one hundred and ten years old.

30 And they buried him within the borders of his possession at Timnath-Serah, which is situated on mount Ephraim, before the northern side of mount Gaash.

31 And Israel served the Lord during all the days of Joshua, and of the elders who lived for a long time after Joshua, and who had known all the works of the Lord that he had accomplished in Israel.

32 And the bones of Joseph, which the sons of Israel had brought from Egypt, they buried at Shechem, in a portion of the field that Jacob had purchased from the sons of Hamor, the father of Shechem, for one hundred young female sheep, and so it was in the possession of the sons of Joseph.

33 Likewise, Eleazar, the son of Aaron, died. And they buried him at Gibeah, which belongs to Phinehas, his son, and which was given to him on mount Ephraim.

Judges 1

1 After the death of Joshua, the sons of Israel consulted the Lord, saying, "Who will ascend before us, against the Canaanite, and who will be the commander of the war?"

2 And the Lord said: "Judah shall ascend. Behold, I have delivered the land into his hands."

3 And Judah said to his brother Simeon, "Go up with me to my lot, and fight against the Canaanite, so that I also may go forth with you to your lot." And Simeon went with him.

4 And Judah went up, and the Lord delivered the Canaanite, as well as the Perizzite, into their hands. And they struck down ten thousand of the men at Bezek.

5 And they found Adonibezek at Bezek, and they fought against him, and they struck down the Canaanite and the Perizzite.

6 Then Adonibezek fled. And they pursued him and captured him, and they cut off the ends of his hands and feet.

7 And Adonibezek said: "Seventy kings, with the ends of their hands and feet amputated, have been gathering the remnants of food under my table. Just as I have done, so has God repaid me." And they brought him to Jerusalem, and he died there.

8 Then the sons of Judah, besieging Jerusalem, seized it. And they struck it with edge of the sword, delivering the entire city to be burned.

9 And afterward, descending, they fought against the Canaanites who were living in the mountains, and in the south, and in the plains.

10 And Judah, going forth against the Canaanites who were living at Hebron, (the name of which from antiquity was Kiriath-Arba) struck down Sheshai, and Ahiman, and Talmai.

11 And continuing on from there, he went to the inhabitants of Debir, the old name of which was Kiriath-Sepher, that is, the City of Letters.

12 And Caleb said, "Whoever will strike Kiriath-Sepher, and will lay waste to it, I will give to him my daughter Achsah as wife."

13 And when Othniel, the son of Kenaz, a younger brother of Caleb, had seized it, he gave his daughter Achsah to him in marriage.

14 And as she was traveling on a journey, her husband admonished her, so that she would request a field from her father. And since she had sighed while sitting on her donkey, Caleb said to her, "What is it?"

15 But she responded: "Give a blessing to me. For you have given me a dry land. Also give a watered land." Therefore, Caleb gave to her the upper watered land and the lower watered land.

16 Now the sons of the Kenite, the relative of Moses, ascended from the City of Palms, with the sons of Judah, into the wilderness of his lot, which is toward the south of Arad. And they lived with him.

17 Then Judah went out with his brother Simeon, and together they struck the Canaanites who were living at Zephath, and they put them to death. And the name of the city was called Hormah, that is, Anathema.

18 And Judah seized Gaza, with its parts, and Ashkelon as well as Ekron, with their borders.

19 And the Lord was with Judah, and he possessed the mountains. But he was not able to wipe out the inhabitants of the valley. For they abounded with chariots armed with scythes.

20 And just as Moses had said, they gave Hebron to Caleb, who destroyed out of it the three sons of Anak.

21 But the sons of Benjamin did not wipe out the Jebusite inhabitants of Jerusalem. And the Jebusite has lived with the sons of Benjamin in Jerusalem, even to the present day.

22 The house of Joseph also ascended against Bethel, and the Lord was with them.

23 For when they were besieging the city, which was previously called Luz,

24 they saw a man departing from the city, and they said to him, "Reveal to us the entrance to the city, and we will act with mercy toward you."

25 And when he had revealed it to them, they struck the city with the edge of the sword. But that man, and all his relatives, they released.

26 And having been sent away, he went out to the land of the Hittites, and he built a city there, and he called it Luz. And so it is called, even to the present day.

27 Likewise, Manasseh did not destroy Bethshean and Taanach, with their villages, nor the inhabitants of Dor and Ibleam and Megiddo, with their villages. And the Canaanite began to live with them.

28 Then, after Israel had grown strong, he made them tributaries, but he was not willing to destroy them.

29 And now Ephraim did not put to death the Canaanite, who was living at Gezer; instead, he lived with him.

30 Zebulun did not wipe out the inhabitants of Kitron and of Nahalal. Instead, the Canaanite lived in their midst and became their tributary.

31 Likewise, Asher did not destroy the inhabitants of Acco and Sidon, Ahlab and Achzib, and Helbah, and Aphik, and Rehob.

32 And he lived in the midst of the Canaanites, the inhabitants of that land, for he did not put them to death.

33 Naphtali also did not wipe out the inhabitants of Beth-shemesh and Bethanath. And he lived among the Canaanite inhabitants of the land. And the Beth-shemeshites and Bethanathites were tributaries to him.

34 And the Amorite hemmed in the sons of Dan on the mountain, and did not give them a place, so that they might descend to the flatlands.

35 And he lived on the mountain at Har-heres, which is translated as 'resembling brick,' and at Aijalon and Sha-alabbin. But the hand of the house of Joseph was very heavy, and he became a tributary to him.

36 Now the border of the Amorite was from the Ascent of the Scorpion, to the Rock and the higher places.

Judges 2

1 And an Angel of the Lord went up from Gilgal to the Place of Weeping, and he said: "I led you away from Egypt, and I led you into the land, about which I swore to your fathers. And I promised that I would not nullify my covenant with you, even forever:

2 but only if you would not form a pact with the inhabitants of this land. Instead, you should overturn their altars. Yet you were not willing to listen to my voice. Why have you done this?

3 For this reason, I am not willing to destroy them before your face, so that you may have enemies, and so that their gods may be your ruin."

4 And when the Angel of the Lord spoke these words to all the sons of Israel, they lifted up their voice, and they wept.

5 And the name of that place was called, the Place of Weeping, or the Place of Tears. And they immolated victims to the Lord in that place.

6 Then Joshua dismissed the people, and the sons of Israel went away, each one to his own possession, so that they might obtain it.

7 And they served the Lord, during all his days, and during all the days of the elders, who lived for a long time after him, and who knew all the works of the Lord, which he had done for Israel.

8 Then Joshua, the son of Nun, the servant of the Lord, died, being one hundred and ten years old.

9 And they buried him in the parts of his possession at Timnath-Serah, on Mount Ephraim, before the northern side of Mount Gaash.

10 And that entire generation was gathered to their fathers. And there rose up others, who had not known the Lord and the works that he had done for Israel.

11 And the sons of Israel did evil in the sight of the Lord, and they served the Baals.

12 And they abandoned the Lord, the God of their fathers, who had led them away from the land of Egypt. And they followed foreign gods and the gods of the peoples who were living around them, and they adored them. And they provoked the Lord to wrath,

13 forsaking him, and serving Baal and Ashtaroth.

14 And the Lord, having become angry against Israel, delivered them into the hands of plunderers, who seized them and sold them to the enemies that were living on all sides. Neither were they able to withstand their adversaries.

15 Instead, wherever they wanted to go, the hand of the Lord was upon them, just as he said and just as he swore to them. And they were greatly afflicted.

16 And the Lord raised up judges, who would free them from the hands of their oppressors. But they were not willing to listen to them.

17 Fornicating with foreign gods and adoring them, they quickly deserted the way along which their fathers had advanced. And having heard the commandments of the Lord, they did all things to the contrary.

18 And while the Lord was raising up the judges, in their days, he was moved to mercy, and he listened to the groaning of the afflicted, and he freed them from the slaughter of their oppressors.

19 But after a judge had died, they turned back, and they were doing much worse things than their fathers had done, following strange gods, serving them, and adoring them. They did not abandon their pursuits and their very stubborn way, by which they were accustomed to walk.

20 And the fury of the Lord was enraged against Israel, and he said: "For this people has made void my covenant, which I had formed with their fathers, and they have despised listening to my voice.

21 And so, I will not destroy the nations that Joshua left behind when he died,

22 so that, by them, I may test Israel, as to whether or not they will keep the way of the Lord, and walk in it, just as their fathers kept it."

23 Therefore, the Lord left all these nations, and he was not willing to quickly overthrow them, nor did he deliver them into the hands of Joshua.

Judges 3

1 These are the nations which the Lord left, so that by them he might instruct Israel and all who had not known the wars of the Canaanites,

2 so that afterward their sons might learn to contend with their enemies, and to have a willingness to do battle:

3 the five princes of the Philistines, and all the Canaanites, and the Sidonians, and the Hivites who were living on Mount Lebanon, from Mount Baal-Hermon as far as the entrance to Hamath.

4 And he left them, so that by them he might test Israel, as to whether or not they would listen to the commandments of the Lord, which he instructed to their fathers by the hand of Moses.

5 And so, the sons of Israel lived in the midst of the Canaanite, and the Hittite, and the Amorite, and the Perizzite, and the Hivite, and the Jebusite.

6 And they took their daughters as wives, and they gave their own daughters to their sons, and they served their gods.

7 And they did evil in the sight of the Lord, and they forgot their God, while serving the Baals and Ashtaroth.

8 And the Lord, having become angry with Israel, delivered them into the hands of Cushan-Rishathaim, the king of Mesopotamia, and they served him for eight years.

9 And they cried out to the Lord, who raised up for them a savior, and he freed them, namely, Othniel, the son of Kenaz, a younger brother of Caleb.

10 And the Spirit of the Lord was in him, and he judged Israel. And he went out to fight, and the Lord delivered Cushan-Rishathaim, the king of Syria, and he overwhelmed him.

11 And the land was quiet for forty years. And Othniel, the son of Kenaz, died.

12 Then the sons of Israel resumed doing evil in the sight of the Lord, who strengthened Eglon, the king of Moab, against them because they did evil in his sight.

13 And he joined to him the sons of Ammon and the sons of Amalek. And he went forth and struck Israel, and he possessed the City of Palms.

14 And the sons of Israel served Eglon, the king of Moab, for eighteen years.

15 And afterward, they cried out to the Lord, who raised up for them a savior, called Ehud, the son of Gera, the son of Benjamin, who used either hand as well as the right hand. And the sons of Israel sent gifts to Eglon, the king of Moab, by him.

16 And he made for himself a two-edged sword, having a handle, reaching to the middle, the length of the palm of a hand. And he was girded with it under his cloak, on the right thigh.

17 And he offered the gifts to Eglon, the king of Moab. Now Eglon was exceedingly fat.

18 And when he had presented the gifts to him, he followed out his companions, who had arrived with him.

19 And then, returning from Gilgal where the idols were, he said to the king, "I have a secret word for you, O king." And he ordered silence. And when all those who were around him had departed,

20 Ehud entered to him. Now he was sitting alone in a summer upper room. And he said, "I have a word from God to you." And immediately he rose up from his throne.

21 And Ehud extended his left hand, and he took the dagger from his right thigh. And he thrust it into his abdomen

22 so strongly that the handle followed the blade into the wound, and was enclosed by the great amount of fat. Neither did he withdraw the sword. Instead, he left it in the body just as he had struck with it. And immediately, by the private parts of nature, the filth of the bowels went out.

23 Then Ehud carefully closed the doors of the upper room. And securing the bars,

24 he departed by a back exit. And the servants of the king, entering, saw that the doors of the upper room were closed, and they said, "Perhaps he is emptying his bowels in the summer room."

25 And after waiting a long time, until they were embarrassed, and seeing that no one opened the door, they took the key, and opening it, they found their lord lying dead on the ground.

26 But Ehud, while they were in confusion, escaped and passed by the place of the idols, from which he had returned. And he arrived at Seirath.

27 And immediately he sounded the trumpet on Mount Ephraim. And the sons of Israel descended with him, he himself advancing at the front.

28 And he said to them: "Follow me. For the Lord has delivered our enemies, the Moabites, into our hands." And they descended after him, and they occupied the fords of the Jordan, which cross over to Moab. And they did not permit anyone to cross.

29 And so, they struck down the Moabites at that time, about ten thousand, all strong and robust men. None of them were able to escape.

30 And Moab was humbled in that day under the hand of Israel. And the land was quiet for eighty years.

31 After him, there was Shamgar, the son of Anath, who struck down six hundred men of the Philistines with a plowshare. And he also defended Israel.

Judges 4

1 But after the death of Ehud, the sons of Israel resumed doing evil in the sight of the Lord.

2 And the Lord delivered them into the hands of Jabin, the king of Canaan, who reigned at Hazor. And he had a commander of his army named Sisera, but this man lived at Harosheth of the Gentiles.

3 And the sons of Israel cried out to the Lord. For he had nine hundred chariots with scythes, and he vehemently oppressed them for twenty years.

4 Now there was a prophetess, Deborah, the wife of Lappidoth, who judged the people in that time.

5 And she was sitting under a palm tree, which was called by her name, between Ramah and Bethel, on Mount Ephraim. And the sons of Israel went up to her for every judgment.

6 And she sent and called Barak, the son of Abinoam, from Kedesh of Naphtali. And she said to him: "The Lord, the God of Israel, instructs you: 'Go and lead an army to Mount Tabor, and you shall take with you ten thousand fighting men from the sons of Naphtali and from the sons of Zebulun.

7 Then I will lead to you, at the place of the torrent Kishon, Sisera, the leader of the army of Jabin, with his chariots and the entire multitude. And I will deliver them into your hand.' "

8 And Barak said to her: "If you will come with me, I will go. If you are not willing to come with me, I will not go."

9 She said to him: "Indeed, I will go with you. But due to this change, the victory shall not be reputed to you. And so Sisera will be delivered into the hand of a woman." Therefore, Deborah rose up, and she traveled with Barak to Kedesh.

10 And he, summoning Zebulun and Naphtali, ascended with ten thousand fighting men, having Deborah in his company.

11 Now Heber, the Kenite, had previously withdrawn from the rest of the Kenites, his brothers, the sons of Hobab, the relative of Moses. And he had pitched his tents as far as the valley that is called Zaanannim, which was near Kedesh.

12 And it was reported to Sisera that Barak, the son of Abinoam, had ascended to Mount Tabor.

13 And he gathered together the nine hundred chariots with scythes, and the entire army, from Harosheth of the Gentiles to the torrent Kishon.

14 And Deborah said to Barak: "Rise up. For this is the day on which the Lord delivers Sisera into your hands. For he is your commander." And so, Barak descended from Mount Tabor, and the ten thousand fighting men with him.

15 And the Lord struck Sisera with great fear, and all his chariots and all his multitude with the edge of the sword, in the sight of Barak, so much so that Sisera, leaping from his chariot, fled on foot.

16 And Barak pursued the fleeing chariots, and the army, as far as Harosheth of the Gentiles. And the entire multitude of the enemy was cut down, unto utter annihilation.

17 But Sisera, while fleeing, arrived at the tent of Jael, the wife of Heber, the Kenite. For there was peace between Jabin, the king of Hazor, and the house of Heber, the Kenite.

18 Therefore, Jael went out to meet Sisera, and she said to him: "Enter to me, my lord. Enter, you should not be afraid." And he entered her tent, and having been covered by her with a cloak,

19 he said to her: "Give me, I beg you, a little water. For I am very thirsty." And she opened a bottle of milk, and she gave him to drink. And she covered him.

20 And Sisera said to her: "Stand before the door of the tent. And if anyone arrives, questioning you and saying, 'Could there be any man here?' you shall respond, 'There is no one.' "

21 And so Jael, the wife of Heber, took a spike from the tent, and also took a mallet. And entering unseen and with silence, she placed the spike over the temple of his head. And striking it with the mallet, she drove it through his brain, as far as the ground. And so, joining deep sleep to death, he fell unconscious and died.

22 And behold, Barak arrived, in pursuit of Sisera. And Jael, going out to meet him, said to him, "Come, and I will show you the man whom you are seeking." And when he had entered her tent, he saw Sisera lying dead, with the spike fixed in his temples.

23 Thus did God humble Jabin, the king of Canaan, on that day, before the sons of Israel.

24 And they increased every day. And with a strong hand they overpowered Jabin, the king of Canaan, until they wiped him out.

Judges 5

1 In that day, Deborah and Barak, the son of Abinoam, sang out, saying:

2 "All you of Israel who have willingly offered your lives to danger, bless the Lord!

3 Listen, O kings! Pay attention, O princes! It is I, it is I, who will sing to the Lord. I will sing a psalm to the Lord, the God of Israel!

4 O Lord, when you departed from Seir, and you crossed through the regions of Edom, the earth and the heavens were moved, and the clouds rained down water.

5 The mountains flowed away before the face of the Lord, and Sinai, before the face of the Lord God of Israel.

6 In the days of Shamgar, the son of Anath, in the days of Jael, the paths were quiet. And whoever entered by them, walked along rough byways.

7 The strong men ceased, and they rested in Israel, until Deborah rose up, until a mother rose up in Israel.

8 The Lord chose new wars, and he himself overturned the gates of the enemies. A shield with a spear was not seen among the forty thousand of Israel.

9 My heart loves the leaders of Israel. All you who, of your own free will, offered yourselves during a crisis, bless the Lord.

10 You who ride upon donkeys laboring, and you who sit in judgment, and you who walk along the way, speak out.

11 Where the chariots were struck together, and the army of the enemies was choked, in that place, let the justices of the Lord be described, and let his clemency be for the brave of Israel. Then did the people of the Lord descend to the gates, and obtain leadership.

12 Rise up, rise up, O Deborah! Rise up, rise up, and speak a canticle! Rise up, Barak, and seize your captives, O son of Abinoam.

13 The remnants of the people were saved. The Lord contended with the strong.

14 Out of Ephraim, he destroyed those with Amalek, and after him, out of Benjamin, those of your people, O Amalek. From Machir, there descended leaders, and from Zebulun, those who led the army to war.

15 The commanders of Issachar were with Deborah, and they followed the steps of Barak, who endangered himself, like one rushing headlong into a chasm. Reuben was divided against himself. Contention was found among great souls.

16 Why do you live between two borders, so that you hear the bleating of the flocks? Reuben was divided against himself. Contention was found among great souls.

17 Gilead rested beyond the Jordan, and Dan was occupied with ships. Asher was living on the shore of the sea, and dwelling in the ports.

18 Yet truly, Zebulun and Naphtali offered their lives to death in the region of Merom.

19 The kings came and fought; the kings of Canaan fought at Taanach, beside the waters of Megiddo. And yet they took no spoils.

20 The conflict against them was from heaven. The stars, remaining in their order and courses, fought against Sisera.

21 The torrent of Kishon dragged away their carcasses, the onrushing torrent, the torrent of Kishon. O my soul, tread upon the stalwart!

22 The hoofs of the horses were broken, while the strongest of the enemies fled away with fury, and rushed on to ruin.

23 'Cursed be the land of Meroz!' said the Angel of the Lord. 'Cursed be its inhabitants! For they did not come to the aid of the Lord, to the assistance of his most valiant men.'

24 Blessed among women is Jael, the wife of Heber the Kenite. And blessed is she in her tabernacle.

25 He begged her for water, and she gave him milk, and she offered him butter in a dish fit for princes.

26 She put her left hand to the nail, and her right hand to the workman's mallet. And she struck Sisera, seeking in his head a place for the wound, and strongly piercing his temples.

27 Between her feet, he was ruined. He fainted away and passed on. He curled up before her feet, and he lay there lifeless and miserable.

28 His mother gazed through a window and wailed. And she spoke from an upper room: 'Why does his chariot delay in returning? Why are the feet of his team of horses so slow?'

29 One who was wiser than the rest of his wives responded to her mother-in-law with this:

30 'Perhaps he is now dividing the spoils, and the most beautiful among the women is being selected for him. Garments of diverse colors are being delivered to Sisera as spoils, and various goods are being collected for the adornment of necks.'

31 O Lord, so may all your enemies perish! But may those who love you shine with splendor, as the sun shines at its rising."

32 And the land rested for forty years.

Judges 6

1 Then the sons of Israel did evil in the sight of the Lord, who delivered them into the hand of Midian for seven years.

2 And they were greatly oppressed by them. And they made for themselves hollows and caves in the mountains, and very fortified places for defense.

3 And when Israel had planted, Midian and Amalek, and the rest of the eastern nations ascended,

4 and pitching their tents among them, they laid waste to all that was planted, as far as the entrance to Gaza. And they left behind nothing at all to sustain life in Israel, neither sheep, nor oxen, nor donkeys.

5 For they and all their flocks arrived with their tents, and they filled all places like locusts, an innumerable multitude of men and camels, devastating whatever they touched.

6 And Israel was humbled greatly in the sight of Midian.

7 And he cried out to the Lord, requesting assistance against the Midianites.

8 And he sent to them a man who was a prophet, and he said: "Thus says the Lord, the God of Israel: 'I caused you to ascend from Egypt, and I led you away from the house of servitude.

9 And I freed you from the hand of the Egyptians and from all of the enemies who were afflicting you. And I cast them out at your arrival, and I delivered their land to you.

10 And I said: I am the Lord your God. You shall not fear the gods of the Amorites, in whose land you live. But you were not willing to listen to my voice.' "

11 Then an Angel of the Lord arrived, and he sat under an oak tree, which was at Ophrah, and which belonged to Joash, the father of the family of Ezri. And while his son Gideon was threshing and cleaning the grain at the winepress, so that he might flee from Midian,

12 the Angel of the Lord appeared to him, and he said: "The Lord is with you, most valiant of men."

13 And Gideon said to him: "I beg you, my lord, if the Lord is with us, why have these things happened to us? Where are his miracles, which our fathers described when they said, 'The Lord led us away from Egypt.' But now the Lord has forsaken us, and he has delivered us into the hand of Midian."

14 And the Lord looked down upon him, and he said: "Go forth with this, your strength, and you shall free Israel from the hand of Midian. Know that I have sent you."

15 And responding, he said: "I beg you, my lord, with what shall I free Israel? Behold, my family is the weakest in Manasseh, and I am the least in the house of my father."

16 And the Lord said to him: "I will be with you. And so, you shall cut down Midian as if one man."

17 And he said: "If I have found grace before you, give me a sign that it is you who is speaking to me.

18 And may you not withdraw from here, until I return to you, carrying a sacrifice and offering it to you." And he responded, "I will wait for your return."

19 And so Gideon entered, and he boiled a goat, and he made unleavened bread from a measure of flour. And setting the flesh in a basket, and putting the broth of the flesh in a pot, he took it all under the oak tree, and he offered it to him.

20 And the Angel of the Lord said to him, "Take the flesh and the unleavened bread, and place them on that rock, and pour out the broth upon it." And when he had done so,

21 the Angel of the Lord extended the end of a staff, which he was holding in his hand, and he touched the flesh and the unleavened loaves. And a fire ascended from the rock, and it consumed the flesh and the unleavened loaves. Then the Angel of the Lord vanished from his sight.

22 And Gideon, realizing that it had been the Angel of the Lord, said: "Alas, my Lord God! For I have seen the Angel of the Lord face to face."

23 And the Lord said to him: "Peace be with you. Do not be afraid; you shall not die."

24 Therefore, Gideon built an altar to the Lord there, and he called it, the Peace of the Lord, even to the present day. And while he was still at Ophrah, which is of the family of Ezri,

25 that night, the Lord said to him: "Take a bull of your father's, and another bull of seven years, and you shall destroy the altar of Baal, which is your father's. And you shall cut down the sacred grove which is around the altar.

26 And you shall build an altar to the Lord your God, at the summit of this rock, on which you placed the sacrifice before. And you shall take the second bull, and you shall offer a holocaust upon a pile of the wood, which you shall cut down from the grove."

27 Therefore, Gideon, taking ten men from his servants, did just as the Lord had instructed him. But fearing his father's household, and the men of that city, he was not willing to do it by day. Instead, he completed everything by night.

28 And when the men of that town had risen up in the morning, they saw the altar of Baal destroyed, and the sacred grove cut down, and the second bull set upon the altar, which then had been built.

29 And they said one to another, "Who has done this?" And when they inquired everywhere as to the author of the deed, it was said, "Gideon, the son of Joash, did all these things."

30 And they said to Joash: "Bring forward your son here, so that he may die. For he has destroyed the altar of Baal, and he has cut down the sacred grove."

31 But he responded to them: "Could you be the avengers of Baal, so that you fight on his behalf? Whoever is his adversary, let him die before the light arrives tomorrow; if he is a god, let him vindicate himself against him who has overturned his altar."

32 From that day, Gideon was called Jerubbaal, because Joash had said, "Let Baal avenge himself against him who has overturned his altar."

33 And so, all of Midian, and Amalek, and the eastern peoples were gathered together. And crossing the Jordan, they encamped in the valley of Jezreel.

34 But the Spirit of the Lord entered Gideon, who, sounding the trumpet, summoned the house of Abiezer so that he might follow him.

35 And he sent messengers into all of Manasseh, who also followed him, and other messengers into Asher, and Zebulun, and Naphtali, who went to meet him.

36 And Gideon said to God: "If you will save Israel by my hand, just as you have said:

37 I will set this wool fleece on the threshing floor. If there will be dew only on the fleece, and all the ground is dry, I will know that by my hand, as you have said, you will free Israel."

38 And so it was done. And rising in the night, wringing out the fleece, he filled a vessel with the dew.

39 And again he said to God: "Let not your fury be enkindled against me, if I test once more, seeking a sign in the fleece. I pray that only the fleece may be dry, and all the ground may be wet with dew."

40 And that night, God did as he had requested. And it was dry only on the fleece, and there was dew on all the ground.

Judges 7

1 And so Jerubbaal, who is also Gideon, rising in the night, and all the people with him, went to the fountain which is called Harod. Now the camp of Midian was in the valley, to the northern region of the high hill.

2 And the Lord said to Gideon: "The people with you are many, but Midian shall not be delivered into their hands, for then Israel might glory against me, and say, 'I was freed by my own power.'

3 Speak to the people, and proclaim in the hearing of all, 'Whoever has dread or fear, let him return.' And twenty-two thousand of the men from the people withdrew from Mount Gilead and returned, and only ten thousand remained.

4 And the Lord said to Gideon: "The people are still too many. Lead them to the waters, and there I will test them. And those about whom I tell you that he may go with you, let him go; he whom I shall forbid to go, let him return."

5 And when the people had descended to the waters, the Lord said to Gideon: "Whoever will lap the water with the tongue, as dogs usually lap, you shall separate them by themselves. Then those who will drink by bending their knees shall be on the other side."

6 And so the number of those who had lapped the water, by bringing it with the hand to the mouth, was three hundred men. And all the remainder of the multitude drank by bending the knee.

7 And the Lord said to Gideon: "By the three hundred men who lapped the water, I will free you, and I will deliver Midian into your hand. But let all the remainder of the multitude return to their place."

8 And so, taking food and trumpets in accord with their number, he instructed all the rest of the multitude to go back to their tents. And with the three hundred men, he gave himself to the conflict. Now the camp of Midian was below, in the valley.

9 In the same night, the Lord said to him: "Rise up, and descend into the camp. For I have delivered them into your hand.

10 But if you dread to go alone, let your servant Purah descend with you.

11 And when you will hear what they are saying, then your hands will be strengthened, and you will descend more confidently to the camp of the enemy." Therefore, he descended with his servant Purah into a portion of the camp, where there was a watch of armed men.

12 But Midian, and Amalek, and all the eastern peoples lay spread out in the valley, like a multitude of locusts. Their camels, too, were innumerable, like the sand that lies on the shore of the sea.

13 And when Gideon had arrived, someone told his neighbor a dream. And he related what he had seen, in this way: "I saw a dream, and it seemed to me as if bread, baked under ashes from rolled barley, descended into the camp of Midian. And whenever it arrived at a tent, it struck it, and overturned it, and utterly leveled it to the ground."

14 He to whom he spoke, responded: "This is nothing else but the sword of Gideon, the son of Joash, a man of Israel. For the Lord has delivered Midian into his hands, with their entire camp."

15 And when Gideon had heard the dream and its interpretation, he worshipped. And he returned to the camp of Israel, and he said: "Rise up! For the Lord has delivered the camp of Midian into our hands."

16 And he divided the three hundred men into three parts. And he gave trumpets, and empty pitchers, and lamps for the middle of the pitchers, into their hands.

17 And he said to them: "What you will see me do, do the same. I will enter a portion of the camp, and what I do, you shall follow.

18 When the trumpet in my hand blares out, you also shall sound the trumpets, on every side of the camp, and shout together to the Lord and to Gideon."

19 And Gideon, and the three hundred men who were with him, entered a portion of the camp, at the beginning of the watch in the middle of the night. And when the guards were alerted, they began to sound the trumpets and to clap the pitchers against one another.

20 And when they had sounded their trumpets in three places around the camp, and had broken their water pitchers, they held the lamps in their left hands, and sounded the trumpets in their right hands. And they cried out, "The sword of the Lord and of Gideon!"

21 And each one was standing in his place throughout the camp of the enemies. And so the entire camp was in confusion; and they fled away, wailing and crying out.

22 And the three hundred men nevertheless continued sounding the trumpets. And the Lord sent the sword into the entire camp, and they maimed and cut down one another,

23 fleeing as far as Bethshittah, and the base of Abelmeholah in Tabbath. But the men of Israel pursued Midian, shouting from Naphtali and Asher, and from all of Manasseh.

24 And Gideon sent messengers throughout all of Mount Ephraim, saying, "Descend to meet Midian, and occupy the waters ahead of them as far as Bethbarah and the Jordan." And all of Ephraim cried out, and they occupied the waters ahead of them, from the Jordan even to Bethbarah.

25 And having apprehended two men of Midian, Oreb and Zeeb, they put Oreb to death at the Rock of Oreb, and truly, Zeeb, at the Winepress of Zeeb. And they pursued Midian, carrying the heads of Oreb and Zeeb to Gideon, across the waters of the Jordan.

Judges 8

1 And the men of Ephraim said to him, "What is this, that you wanted to do, so that you would not call us when you went to fight against Midian?" And they rebuked him strongly, and came close to using violence.

2 And he responded to them: "But what could I have done that would be so great as what you have done? Is not one bunch of grapes of Ephraim better than the vintages of Abiezer?

3 The Lord has delivered into your hands the leaders of Midian, Oreb and Zeeb. What could I have done that would be so great as what you have done?" And when he had said this, their spirit, which was swelling up against him, was quieted.

4 And when Gideon had arrived at the Jordan, he crossed over it with the three hundred men who were with him. And they were so weary that they were unable to pursue those who were fleeing.

5 And he said to the men of Succoth, "I beg you, give bread to the people who are with me, for they are greatly weakened, so that we may be able to pursue Zebah and Zalmunna, the kings of Midian."

6 The leaders of Succoth answered, "Perhaps the palms of the hands of Zebah and Zalmunna are in your hand, and for this reason, you request that we give bread to your army."

7 And he said to them, "So then, when the Lord will have delivered Zebah and Zalmunna into my hands, I will thresh your flesh with the thorns and briers of the desert."

8 And going up from there, he arrived at Penuel. And he spoke to the men of that place similarly. And they also answered him, just as the men of Succoth had answered.

9 And so he said to them also, "When I will have returned as a victor in peace, I will destroy this tower."

10 Now Zebah and Zalmunna were resting with their entire army. For fifteen thousand men were left out of all the troops of the eastern people. And one hundred twenty thousand warriors that drew the sword had been cut down.

11 And Gideon ascended by the way of those who were dwelling in tents, to the eastern part of Nobah and Jogbehah. And he struck the camp of the enemies, who were confident and were suspecting nothing adverse.

12 And Zebah and Zalmunna fled. And Gideon pursued and overtook them, sending their entire army into confusion.

13 And returning from the war before sunrise,

14 he took a boy from among the men of Succoth. And he asked him the names of the leaders and elders of Succoth. And he described seventy-seven men.

15 And he went to Succoth, and he said to them: "Behold Zebah and Zalmunna, over whom you rebuked me, saying: 'Perhaps the hands of Zebah and Zalmunna are in your hands, and for this reason, you request that we give bread to men who are languishing and weakened.' "

16 Therefore, he took the elders of the city, and, using the thorns and briers of the desert, he threshed them with these, and he cut the men of Succoth to pieces.

17 He also overturned the tower of Penuel, and he killed the men of the city.

18 And he said to Zebah and Zalmunna, "What kind of men were those whom you killed at Tabor?" They responded, "They were like you, and one of them was like the son of a king."

19 He answered them: "They were my brothers, the sons of my mother. As the Lord lives, if you had preserved them, I would not kill you."

20 And he said to Jether, his firstborn son, "Rise up, and put them to death." But he did not draw his sword. For he was afraid, being still a boy.

21 And Zebah and Zalmunna said: "You should rise up and rush against us. For the strength of a man is in accord with his age." Gideon rose up, and he killed Zebah and Zalmunna. And he took the ornaments and studs, with which the necks of the royal camels are usually adorned.

22 And all the men of Israel said to Gideon: "You should rule over us, and your son, and your son's son. For you freed us from the hand of Midian."

23 And he said to them: "I will not rule over you. Neither shall my son rule over you. Instead, the Lord shall rule over you."

24 And he said to them: "I petition one request from you. Give me the earrings from your spoils." For the Ishmaelites were accustomed to wear gold earrings.

25 They responded, "We are very willing to give them." And spreading a cloak on the ground, they cast upon it the earrings from the spoils.

26 And the weight of the earrings that he requested was one thousand seven hundred shekels of gold, aside from the ornaments, and necklaces, and purple garments, which the kings of Midian were accustomed to use, and aside from the gold chains on the camels.

27 And Gideon made an ephod from these, and he kept it in his city, Ophrah. And all of Israel committed fornication with it, and it became a ruin to Gideon and to all his house.

28 But Midian was humbled before the sons of Israel. Neither were they able any longer to lift up their necks. But the land rested for forty years, while Gideon presided.

29 And so Jerubbaal, the son of Joash, went and lived in his own house.

30 And he had seventy sons, who went forth from his own thigh. For he had many wives.

31 But his concubine, whom he had in Shechem, bore him a son named Abimelech.

32 And Gideon, the son of Joash, died in a good old age, and he was buried in the sepulcher of his father, at Ophrah, of the family of Ezri.

33 But after Gideon died, the sons of Israel turned away, and they committed fornication with the Baals. And they struck a covenant with Baal, so that he would be their god.

34 And they did not remember the Lord their God, who rescued them from the hands of all their enemies on all sides.

35 Neither did they show mercy to the house of Jerubbaal Gideon, in accord with all the good that he had done for Israel.

Judges 9

1 Now Abimelech, the son of Jerubbaal, went to Shechem, to his maternal brothers, and he spoke to them, and to all the relatives of the house of his maternal grandfather, saying:

2 "Speak to all the men of Shechem: Which is better for you: that seventy men, all the sons of Jerubbaal, should rule over you, or that one man should rule over you? And consider also that I am your bone and your flesh."

3 And his maternal brothers spoke about him to all the men of Shechem, all these words, and they inclined their hearts after Abimelech, saying, "He is our brother."

4 And they gave to him the weight of seventy silver coins from the shrine of Baal-berith. With this, he hired for himself indigent and wandering men, and they followed him.

5 And he went to his father's house in Ophrah, and he killed his brothers, the sons of Jerubbaal, seventy men, upon one stone. And there remained only Joatham, the youngest son of Jerubbaal, and he was in hiding.

6 Then all the men of Shechem gathered together, and all the families of the city of Millo, and they went and appointed Abimelech as king, beside the oak that stood at Shechem.

7 When this had been reported to Jotham, he went and stood at the top of Mount Gerizim. And lifting up his voice, he cried out and said: "Listen to me, men of Shechem, so that God may listen to you.

8 The trees went to anoint a king over themselves. And they said to the olive tree, 'Reign over us.'

9 And it responded, 'How could I abandon my fatness, which both gods and men make use of, and depart to be promoted among the trees?'

10 And the trees said to the fig tree, 'Come and accept royal power over us.'

11 And it responded to them, 'How could I abandon my sweetness, and my very sweet fruits, and depart to be promoted among the other trees?'

12 And the trees said to the vine, 'Come and reign over us.'

13 And it responded to them, 'How could I abandon my wine, which gives joy to God and men, and be promoted among the other trees?'

14 And all the trees said to the bramble, 'Come and reign over us.'

15 And it responded to them: 'If truly you would appoint me as king, come and rest under my shadow. But if you are not willing, let fire go forth from the bramble, and let it devour the cedars of Lebanon.' "

16 So now, if you are upright and without sin in appointing Abimelech as a king over you, and if you have acted well with Jerubbaal, and with his house, and if you have repaid, in turn, the benefits of him who fought on your behalf,

17 and who gave his life to dangers, so that he might rescue you from the hand of Midian,

18 though you now have risen up against my father's house, and have killed his sons, seventy men, upon one stone, and have appointed Abimelech, the son of his handmaid, as a king over the inhabitants of Shechem, since he is your brother,

19 if therefore you are upright and have acted without fault with Jerubbaal and his house, then you should rejoice on this day in Abimelech, and he should rejoice in you.

20 But if you have acted perversely, may fire go forth from him and consume the inhabitants of Shechem and the town of Millo. And may fire go forth from the men of Shechem and from the town of Millo, and devour Abimelech."

21 And when he had said these things, he fled and went away to Beer. And he lived in that place, out of fear of Abimelech, his brother.

22 And so Abimelech reigned over Israel for three years.

23 And the Lord put a very grievous spirit between Abimelech and the inhabitants of Shechem, who began to detest him,

24 and to place blame for the crime of the killing of the seventy sons of Jerubbaal, and for the shedding of their blood, upon Abimelech, their brother, and upon the rest of the leaders of the Shechemites, who assisted him.

25 And they stationed an ambush against him at the summit of the mountains. And while they were waiting for his arrival, they committed robberies, taking spoils from those passing by. And this was reported to Abimelech.

26 Now Gaal, the son of Ebed, went with his brothers, and crossed over to Shechem. And the inhabitants of Shechem, uplifted by his arrival,

27 departed into the fields, laying waste to the vineyards, and trampling the grapes. And while singing and dancing, they entered into the shrine of their god. And while feasting and drinking, they cursed Abimelech.

28 And Gaal, the son of Ebed, cried out: "Who is Abimelech, and what is Shechem, that we should serve him? Is he not the son of Jerubbaal, who has appointed Zebul, his servant, as ruler over the men of Hamor, the father of Shechem? Why then should we serve him?

29 I wish that someone would set this people under my hand, so that I might take away Abimelech from their midst." And it was told to Abimelech, "Gather the multitude of an army, and approach."

30 For Zebul, the ruler of the city, upon hearing the words of Gaal, the son of Ebed, became very angry.

31 And he sent messengers secretly to Abimelech, saying: "Behold, Gaal, the son of Ebed, has arrived at Shechem with his brothers, and he has set the city against you.

32 And so, rise up in the night, with the people who are with you, and lie hidden in the field.

33 And at first light in the morning, as the sun is rising, rush upon the city. And when he goes out against you, with his people, do to him what you are able to do."

34 And so Abimelech rose up, with all his army, by night, and he set ambushes near Shechem in four places.

35 And Gaal, the son of Ebed, went out, and he stood at the entrance to the gate of the city. Then Abimelech rose up, and all the army with him, from the places of the ambushes.

36 And when Gaal had seen the people, he said to Zebul, "Behold, a multitude is descending from the mountains." And he responded to him, "You are seeing the shadows of the mountains, as if they were the heads of men, and so you are being deceived by this error."

37 Again, Gaal said, "Behold, a people is descending from the middle of the land, and one company is arriving by the way that looks towards the oak."

38 And Zebul said to him: "Where is your mouth now, with which you said, 'Who is Abimelech that we should serve him?' Is this not the people that you were despising? Go out and fight against him."

39 Therefore, Gaal went out, with the people of Shechem watching, and he fought against Abimelech,

40 who pursued him, fleeing, and drove him into the city. And many were cut down on his side, even to the gate of the city.

41 And Abimelech made camp at Arumah. But Zebul expelled Gaal and his companions from the city, and he would not permit them to remain in it.

42 Therefore, on the following day, the people departed into the field. And when this had been reported to Abimelech,

43 he took his army, and divided it into three companies, and he placed ambushes in the fields. And seeing that the people had departed from the city, he rose up and rushed upon them,

44 along with his own company, assaulting and besieging the city. But the two other companies pursued the enemies scattered in the field.

45 Now Abimelech assaulted the city all that day. And he seized it, and he killed its inhabitants, and he destroyed it, so much so that he scattered salt in it.

46 And when those living in the tower of Shechem had heard about this, they entered the temple of their god, Berith, where they had formed a covenant with him. And it was because of this, that the place had taken its name. And it was greatly fortified.

47 Abimelech, also hearing that the men of the tower of Shechem had joined together,

48 ascended to mount Zalmon, with all his people. And taking an axe, he cut down the branch of a tree. And laying it on his shoulder, and carrying it, he said to his companions, "What you see me do, you must do quickly."

49 And so, eagerly cutting down branches from the trees, they followed their leader. And surrounding the fortified place, they set it on fire. And so it happened that, by smoke and fire, one thousand persons died, men and women together, the occupants of the tower of Shechem.

50 Then Abimelech, setting out from there, arrived at the town of Thebez, which he surrounded and besieged with his army.

51 Now there was, in the midst of the city, a high tower, to which men and women were fleeing together, with all the leaders of the city. And, having very strongly sealed the gate, they were standing on the roof of the tower to defend themselves.

52 And Abimelech, drawing near the tower, fought valiantly. And approaching the gate, he strove to set it on fire.

53 And behold, one woman, throwing a fragment of a millstone from above, struck the head of Abimelech, and broke his skull.

54 And he quickly called to his armor bearer, and said to him, "Draw your sword and strike me, otherwise it may be said that I was slain by a woman." And, doing as he was ordered, he killed him.

55 And when he was dead, all those of Israel who were with him returned to their homes.

56 And so did God repay the evil that Abimelech had done against his father by killing his seventy brothers.

57 The Shechemites also were given retribution for what they had done, and the curse of Jotham, the son of Jerubbaal, fell upon them.

Judges 10

1 After Abimelech, a leader rose up in Israel, Tola, the son of Puah, the paternal uncle of Abimelech, a man of Issachar, who lived in Shamir on mount Ephraim.

2 And he judged Israel for twenty-three years, and he died and was buried at Shamir.

3 After him succeeded Jair, a Gileadite, who judged Israel for twenty-two years,

4 having thirty sons sitting upon thirty young donkeys, and who were leaders of thirty cities, which from his name were called Havvoth Jair, that is, the towns of Jair, even to the present day, in the land of Gilead.

5 And Jair died, and he was buried in the place which is called Kamon.

6 But the sons of Israel did evil in the sight of the Lord, joining new sins to old, and they served idols, the Baals and Ashtaroth, and the gods of Syria and Sidon, and of Moab and the sons of Ammon, and the Philistines. And they abandoned the Lord, and they did not worship him.

7 And the Lord, becoming angry against them, delivered them into the hands of the Philistines and the sons of Ammon.

8 And they were afflicted and vehemently oppressed for eighteen years, all who were living beyond the Jordan in the land of the Amorite, which is in Gilead,

9 to such a great extent that the sons of Ammon, crossing over the Jordan, laid waste to Judah and Benjamin and Ephraim. And Israel was exceedingly afflicted.

10 And crying out to the Lord, they said: "We have sinned against you. For we have forsaken the Lord our God, and we have served the Baals."

11 And the Lord said to them: "Did not the Egyptians, and the Amorites, and the sons of Ammon, and the Philistines,

12 and also the Sidonians, and Amalek, and Canaan, oppress you, and so you cried out to me, and I rescued you from their hand?

13 And yet you have forsaken me, and you have worshipped foreign gods. For this reason, I will not continue to free you any more.

14 Go, and call upon the gods whom you have chosen. Let them free you in the time of anguish."

15 And the sons of Israel said to the Lord: "We have sinned. You may repay us in whatever way pleases you. Yet free us now."

16 And saying these things, they cast out all the idols of the foreign gods from their regions, and they served the Lord God. And he was touched by their miseries.

17 And then the sons of Ammon, shouting out together, pitched their tents in Gilead. And the sons of Israel gathered together against them, and they made camp at Mizpah.

18 And the leaders of Gilead said to one another, "Whoever among us will be the first to begin to contend against the sons of Ammon, he shall be the leader of the people of Gilead."

Judges 11

1 At that time, there was a Gileadite, Jephthah, a very strong man and a fighter, the son of a kept woman, and he was born of Gilead.

2 Now Gilead had a wife, from whom he received sons. And they, after growing up, cast out Jephthah, saying, "You cannot inherit in the house of our father, because you were born of another mother."

3 And so, fleeing and avoiding them, he lived in the land of Tob. And men who were indigent and robbers joined with him, and they followed him as their leader.

4 In those days, the sons of Ammon fought against Israel.

5 And being steadfastly attacked, the elders of Gilead traveled so that they might obtain for their assistance Jephthah, from the land of Tob.

6 And they said to him, "Come and be our leader, and fight against the sons of Ammon."

7 But he answered them: "Are you not the ones who hated me, and who cast me out of my father's house? And yet now you come to me, compelled by necessity?"

8 And the leaders of Gilead said to Jephthah, "But it is due to this necessity that we have approached you now, so that you may set out with us, and fight against the sons of Ammon, and be commander over all who live in Gilead."

9 Jephthah also said to them: "If you have come to me so that I may fight for you against the sons of Ammon, and if the Lord will deliver them into my hands, will I truly be your leader?"

10 They answered him, "The Lord who hears these things is himself the Mediator and the Witness that we shall do what we have promised."

11 And so Jephthah went with the leaders of Gilead, and all the people made him their leader. And Jephthah spoke all his words, in the sight of the Lord, at Mizpah.

12 And he sent messengers to the king of the sons of Ammon, who said on his behalf, "What is there between you and me, that you would approach against me, so that you might lay waste to my land?"

13 And he responded to them, "It is because Israel took my land, when he ascended from Egypt, from the parts of Arnon, as far as the Jabbok and the Jordan. Now therefore, restore these to me with peace."

14 And Jephthah again commissioned them, and he ordered them to say to the king of Ammon:

15 "Jephthah says this: Israel did not take the land of Moab, nor the land of the sons of Ammon.

16 But when they ascended together from Egypt, he walked through the desert as far as the Red Sea, and he went into Kadesh.

17 And he sent messengers to the king of Edom, saying, 'Permit me to pass through your land.' But he was not willing to agree to his petition. Likewise, he sent to the king of Moab, who also refused to offer him passage. And so he delayed in Kadesh,

18 and he circled around the side of the land of Edom and the land of Moab. And he arrived opposite the eastern region of the land of Moab. And he made camp across the Arnon. But he was not willing to enter the borders of Moab. (Of course, Arnon is the border of the land of Moab.)

19 And so Israel sent messengers to Sihon, the king of the Amorites, who was living at Heshbon. And they said to him, "Permit me to cross through your land as far as the river."

20 But he, too, despising the words of Israel, would not permit him to cross through his borders. Instead, gathering an innumerable multitude, he went out against him at Jahaz, and he resisted strongly.

21 But the Lord delivered him, with his entire army, into the hands of Israel. And he struck him down, and he possessed all the land of the Amorite, the inhabitant of that region,

22 with all its parts, from the Arnon as far as the Jabbok, and from the wilderness even to the Jordan.

23 Therefore, it was the Lord, the God of Israel, who overthrew the Amorites, by means of his people Israel fighting against them. And now you wish to possess his land?

24 Are not the things that your god Chemosh possesses owed to you by right? And so, what the Lord our God has obtained by victory falls to us as a possession.

25 Or are you, perhaps, better than Balak, the son of Zippor, the king of Moab? Or are you able to explain what his argument was against Israel, and why he fought against him?

26 And though he has lived in Heshbon, and its villages, and in Aroer, and its villages, and in all the cities near the Jordan for three hundred years, why have you, for such long a time, put forward nothing about this claim?

27 Therefore, I am not sinning against you, but you are doing evil against me, by declaring an unjust war against me. May the Lord be the Judge and the Arbiter this day, between Israel and the sons of Ammon."

28 But the king of the sons of Ammon was not willing to agree to the words of Jephthah that he commissioned by the messengers.

29 Therefore, the Spirit of the Lord rested upon Jephthah, and circling around Gilead, and Manasseh, and also Mizpah of Gilead, and crossing from there to the sons of Ammon,

30 he made a vow to the Lord, saying, "If you will deliver the sons of Ammon into my hands,

31 whoever will be the first to depart from the doors of my house to meet me, when I return in peace from the sons of Ammon, the same will I offer as a holocaust to the Lord."

32 And Jephthah crossed to the sons of Ammon, so that he might fight against them. And the Lord delivered them into his hands.

33 And he struck them down from Aroer, as far as the entrance to Minnith, twenty cities, and as far as Abel, which is covered with vineyards, in an exceedingly great slaughter. And the sons of Ammon were humbled by the sons of Israel.

34 But when Jephthah returned to Mizpah, to his own house, his only daughter met him with timbrels and dances. For he had no other children.

35 And upon seeing her, he tore his garments, and he said: "Alas, my daughter! You have cheated me, and you yourself have been cheated. For I opened my mouth to the Lord, and I can do nothing else."

36 And she answered him, "My father, if you have opened your mouth to the Lord, do to me whatever you have promised, since victory has been granted to you, as well as vengeance against your enemies."

37 And she said to her father: "Grant to me this one thing, which I request. Permit me, that I may wander the hillsides for two months, and that I may mourn my virginity with my companions."

38 And he answered her, "Go." And he released her for two months. And when she had departed with her friends and companions, she wept over her virginity in the hillsides.

39 And when the two months expired, she returned to her father, and he did to her just as he had vowed, though she knew no man. From this, the custom grew up in Israel, and the practice has been preserved,

40 such that, after each year passes, the daughters of Israel convene as one, and they lament the daughter of Jephthah, the Gileadite, for four days.

Judges 12

1 And behold, a sedition rose up in Ephraim. Then, while passing by toward the north, they said to Jephthah: "When you were going to fight against the sons of Ammon, why were you unwilling to summon us, so that we might go with you? Therefore, we will burn down your house."

2 And he answered them: "I and my people were in a great conflict against the sons of Ammon. And I called you, so that you might offer assistance to me. And you were not willing to do so.

3 And discerning this, I put my life in my own hands, and I crossed to the sons of Ammon, and the Lord delivered them into my hands. What am I guilty of, that you would rise up in battle against me?"

4 And so, calling to himself all the men of Gilead, he fought against Ephraim. And the men of Gilead struck down Ephraim, because he had said, "Gilead is a fugitive from Ephraim, and he lives in the midst of Ephraim and Manasseh."

5 And the Gileadites occupied the fords of the Jordan, along which Ephraim was to return. And when anyone from the number of Ephraim had arrived, fleeing, and had said, "I beg that you permit me to pass," the Gileadites would say to him, "Could you be an Ephraimite?" And if he said, "I am not,"

6 they would ask him, then say 'Shibboleth,' which is translated as 'ear of grain.' But he would answer 'Sibboleth,' not being able to express the word for an ear of grain in the same letters. And immediately apprehending him, they would cut his throat, at the same crossing point of the Jordan. And in that time of Ephraim, forty-two thousand fell.

7 And so Jephthah, the Gileadite, judged Israel for six years. And he died, and he was buried in his city in Gilead.

8 After him, Ibzan of Bethlehem judged Israel.

9 He had thirty sons, and the same number of daughters, whom he sent away to be given to husbands. And he accepted wives for his sons of the same number, bringing them into his house. And he judged Israel for seven years.

10 And he died, and he was buried in Bethlehem.

11 After him succeeded Elon, a Zebulunite. And he judged Israel for ten years.

12 And he died, and he was buried in Zebulun.

13 After him, Abdon, the son of Hillel, a Pirathonite, judged Israel.

14 And he had forty sons, and from them thirty grandsons, all riding upon seventy young donkeys. And he judged Israel for eight years.

15 And he died, and he was buried at Pirathon, in the land of Ephraim, on the mountain of Amalek.

Judges 13

1 And again, the sons of Israel did evil in the sight of the Lord. And he delivered them into the hands of the Philistines for forty years.

2 Now there was a certain man from Zorah, and of the stock of Dan, whose name was Manoah, having a barren wife.

3 And an Angel of the Lord appeared to her, and he said: "You are barren and without children. But you shall conceive and bear a son.

4 Therefore, take care that you do not drink wine or strong drink. Neither shall you eat anything unclean.

5 For you shall conceive and bear a son, whose head no razor shall touch. For he shall be a Nazirite of God, from his infancy and from his mother's womb. And he shall begin to free Israel from the hand of the Philistines."

6 And when she had gone to her husband, she said to him: "A man of God came to me, having the countenance of an Angel, exceedingly terrible. And when I had inquired of him, who he was, and where he was from, and what name he was called, he was not willing to tell me.

7 But he responded: 'Behold, you shall conceive and bear a son. Take care that you do not drink wine or strong drink. And you shall not consume anything unclean. For the boy shall be a Nazirite of God from his infancy, from his mother's womb, even until the day of his death.' "

8 And so Manoah prayed to the Lord, and he said, "I beg you Lord, that the man of God, whom you sent, may come again, and may teach us what we ought to do about the boy who is to be born."

9 And the Lord heeded the prayer of Manoah, and the Angel of the Lord appeared again to his wife, sitting in a field. But her husband Manoah was not with her. And when she had seen the Angel,

10 she hurried and ran to her husband. And she reported to him, saying, "Behold, the man appeared to me, whom I had seen before."

11 And he rose up and followed his wife. And going to the man, he said to him, "Are you the one who spoke to my wife?" And he responded, "I am."

12 And Manoah said to him: "When will your word be fulfilled. What do you want the boy to do? Or from what should he keep himself?"

13 And the Angel of the Lord said to Manoah: "Concerning all the things about which I have spoken to your wife, she herself should abstain.

14 And let her eat nothing from the vine. She may not drink wine or strong drink. She may consume nothing unclean. And let her observe and keep what I have instructed to her."

15 And Manoah said to the Angel of the Lord, "I beg you to agree to my petition, and to let us prepare a kid from the goats."

16 And the Angel answered him: "Even if you compel me, I will not eat from your bread. But if you are willing to offer a holocaust, offer it to the Lord." And Manoah did not know that he was an Angel of the Lord.

17 And he said to him, "What is your name, so that, if your word is fulfilled, we may honor you?"

18 And he answered him, "Why do you ask my name, which is a wonder?"

19 And so, Manoah took a kid from the goats, and libations, and he placed them upon a rock, as an offering to the Lord, who accomplishes wonders. Then he and his wife watched.

20 And when the flame of the altar ascended to heaven, the Angel of the Lord ascended in the flame. And when Manoah and his wife had seen this, they fell prone on the ground.

21 And the Angel of the Lord no longer appeared to them. And immediately, Manoah understood him to be an Angel of the Lord.

22 And he said to his wife, "We shall certainly die, since we have seen God."

23 And his wife answered him, "If the Lord wished to kill us, he would not have accepted the holocaust and the libations from our hands. He would not have revealed all these things to us, nor would he have told us the things that are in the future."

24 And so she bore a son, and she called his name Samson. And the boy grew up, and the Lord blessed him.

25 And the Spirit of the Lord began to be with him in the camp of Dan, between Zorah and Eshtaol.

Judges 14

1 Then Samson descended to Timnah. And seeing there a woman from the daughters of the Philistines,

2 he went up, and he told his father and his mother, saying: "I saw a woman in Timnah from the daughters of the Philistines. I ask that you take her to me as wife."

3 And his father and mother said to him, "Is there not a woman among the daughters of your brothers, or among all my people, so that you would be willing to take a wife from the Philistines, who are uncircumcised?" And Samson said to his father: "Take this woman to me. For she has pleased my eyes."

4 Now his parents did not know that the matter was done by the Lord, and that he sought an occasion against the Philistines. For at that time, the Philistines had dominion over Israel.

5 And so, Samson descended with his father and mother to Timnah. And when they had arrived at the vineyards of the town, he saw a young lion, savage and roaring, and it met him.

6 Then the Spirit of the Lord rushed upon Samson, and he tore apart the lion, like a young goat being torn into pieces, having nothing at all in his hand. And he was not willing to reveal this to his father and mother.

7 And he went down and spoke to the woman who had pleased his eyes.

8 And after some days, returning to marry her, he turned aside so that he might see the carcass of the lion. And behold, there was a swarm of bees in the mouth of the lion, with a honeycomb.

9 And when he had taken it in his hands, he ate it along the way. And arriving to his father and mother, he gave them a portion, and they also ate it. Yet he was not willing to reveal to them that he had taken the honey from the body of the lion.

10 And so his father went down to the woman, and he made a feast for his son Samson. For so the young men were accustomed to do.

11 And when the citizens of that place had seen him, they presented to him thirty companions to be with him.

12 And Samson said to them: "I will propose to you a problem, which, if you can solve it for me within the seven days of the feast, I will give you thirty shirts and the same number of tunics.

13 But if you are not able to solve it, you shall give me thirty shirts and the same number of tunics." And they answered him, "Propose the problem, so that we may hear it."

14 And he said to them, "Food went forth from that which eats, and sweetness went forth from that which is strong." And they were unable to solve the proposition for three days.

15 And when the seventh day had arrived, they said to the wife of Samson: "Coax your husband, and persuade him to reveal to you what the proposition means. But if you are not willing to do so, we will burn you and your father's house. Or have you called us to the wedding in order to despoil us?"

16 And she shed tears before Samson, and she complained, saying: "You hate me, and you do not love me. That is why you do not want to explain to me the problem, which you have proposed to the sons of my people." But he responded: "I was not willing to reveal it to my father and mother. And so, how can I reveal it to you?"

17 Therefore, she wept before him during the seven days of the feast. And at length, on the seventh day, since she had been troubling him, he explained it. And immediately she revealed it to her countrymen.

18 And they, on the seventh day, before the sun declined, said to him: "What is sweeter than honey? And what is stronger than a lion?" And he said to them, "If you had not plowed with my heifer, you would not have uncovered my proposition."

19 And so the Spirit of the Lord rushed upon him, and he descended to Ashkelon, and in that place he struck down thirty men. And taking away their garments, he gave them to those who had solved the problem. And being exceedingly angry, he went up to his father's house.

20 Then his wife took as a husband one of his friends and wedding companions.

Judges 15

1 Then, after some time, when the days of the wheat harvest were near, Samson arrived, intending to visit his wife, and he brought her a kid from the goats. And when he wanted to enter her bedroom, as usual, her father prohibited him, saying:

2 "I thought that you would hate her, and therefore I gave her to your friend. But she has a sister, who is younger and more beautiful than she is. And she may be a wife for you, instead of her."

3 And Samson answered him: "From this day, there shall be no guilt for me against the Philistines. For I will do harm to you all."

4 And he went out and caught three hundred foxes. And he joined them tail to tail. And he tied torches between the tails.

5 And setting these on fire, he released them, so that they might rush from place to place. And immediately they went into the grain fields of the Philistines, setting these on fire, both the grain that was already bound for carrying, and what was still standing on the stalk. These were completely burned up, so much so that the flame also consumed even the vineyards and the olive groves.

6 And the Philistines said, "Who has done this thing?" And it was said: "Samson, the son-in-law of the Timnite, because he took away his wife, and gave her to another. He has done these things." And the Philistines went up and burned the woman as well as her father.

7 And Samson said to them, "Even though you have done this, I will still fulfill vengeance against you, and then I will be quieted."

8 And he struck them with a tremendous slaughter, so much so that, out of astonishment, they laid the calf of the leg upon the thigh. And descending, he lived in a cave of the rock at Etam.

9 And so the Philistines, ascending into the land of Judah, made camp at the place which was later called Lehi, that is, the Jawbone, where their army spread out.

10 And some from the tribe of Judah said to them, "Why have you ascended against us?" And they responded, "We have come to bind Samson, and to repay him for what he has done to us."

11 Then three thousand men of Judah descended to the cave of the rock at Etam. And they said to Samson: "Do you not know that the Philistines rule over us? Why would you want to do this?" And he said to them, "As they have done to me, so I have done to them."

12 And they said to him, "We have come to bind you, and to deliver you into the hands of the Philistines." And Samson said to them, "Swear and promise to me that you will not kill me."

13 They said: "We will not kill you. But we will deliver you tied." And they bound him with two new cords. And they took him from the rock at Etam.

14 And when he had arrived at the place of the Jawbone, and the Philistines, shouting aloud, had met him, the Spirit of the Lord rushed upon him. And just as flax is usually consumed by a hint of fire, so were the ties with which he was bound broken and released.

15 And finding a jawbone which was laying there, that is, the jawbone of a donkey, snatching it up, he put to death a thousand men with it.

16 And he said, "With the jawbone of a donkey, with the jaw of the colt of a donkey, I have destroyed them, and I have struck down a thousand men."

17 And when he had completed these words, singing, he threw the jawbone from his hand. And called the name of that place Ramath-Lehi, which is translated as 'the elevation of the jawbone.'

18 And being very thirsty, he cried out to the Lord, and he said: "You have given, to the hand of your servant, this very great salvation and victory. But see that I am dying of thirst, and so I will fall into the hands of the uncircumcised."

19 And so the Lord opened a large tooth in the jawbone of the donkey, and water went out from it. And having drank it, his spirit was revived, and he recovered his strength. For this reason, the name of that place was called 'the Spring called forth from the jawbone,' even to the present day.

20 And he judged Israel, in the days of the Philistines, for twenty years.

Judges 16

1 He also went into Gaza. And there he saw a harlot woman, and he entered to her.

2 And when the Philistines had heard of this, and it had become well known among them, that Samson had entered the city, they surrounded him, placing guards at the gate of the city. And there they were keeping watch all night in silence, so that, in the morning, they might kill him as he was going out.

3 But Samson slept until the middle of the night, and rising up from there, he took both doors from the gate, with their posts and bars. And laying them upon his shoulders, he carried them to the top of the hill that looks toward Hebron.

4 After these things, he loved a woman who was living in the valley of Sorek. And she was called Delilah.

5 And the leaders of the Philistines went to her, and they said: "Deceive him, and learn from him wherein lies his great strength, and how we may be able to overcome him and to impose restraints on him. And if you will do this, each one of us will give you one thousand one hundred silver coins."

6 Therefore, Delilah said to Samson, "Tell me, I beg you, wherein lies your very great strength, and with what might you be bound, so that you could not break free?"

7 And Samson answered her, "If I will be bound with seven cords, made of sinews not yet dry, but still damp, I will be weak like other men."

8 And the princes of the Philistines brought to her seven cords, such as he had described. And she bound him with these.

9 And so, those hiding in ambush with her, in the bedroom, were expecting the end of the matter. And she cried out to him, "The Philistines are upon you, Samson!" And he broke the cords, as one would break a thread of flax, twisted for cutting and singed by fire. And so it was not known wherein lay his strength.

10 And Delilah said to him: "Behold, you have mocked me, and you have spoken a falsehood. But at least now, tell me with what you may be bound."

11 And he answered her, "If I will be bound with new cords, which have never been used, I will be weak and like other men."

12 Again, Delilah tied him with these, and she cried out, "The Philistines are upon you, Samson!" For an ambush had been prepared in the bedroom. But he broke the bindings like the filaments of a web.

13 And Delilah spoke to him again: "How long will you deceive me and tell me falsehoods? Reveal with what you ought to be bound." And Samson responded to her, "If you weave the seven locks of my head with a loom, and if you tie these around a spike and fix it to the ground, I will be weak."

14 And when Delilah had done this, she said to him, "The Philistines are upon you, Samson." And arising from sleep, he withdrew the spike with the hairs and the weaving.

15 And Delilah said to him: "How can you say that you love me, when your soul is not with me? You have lied to me on three occasions, and you are not willing to reveal wherein lies your very great strength."

16 And when she had been very troublesome to him, and over many days had continually stayed nearby, giving him no time to rest, his soul was faint, and he was weary, even unto death.

17 Then disclosing the truth of the matter, he said to her: "Iron has never been drawn across my head, for I am a Nazirite, that is, I have been consecrated to God from my mother's womb. If my head will be shaven, my strength will depart from me, and I will be faint and will be like other men."

18 Then, seeing that he had confessed to her his whole soul, she sent to the leaders of the Philistines and ordered: "Come up just once more. For now he has opened his heart to me." And they went up, taking with them the money that they had promised.

19 But she made him sleep upon her knees, and recline his head upon her bosom. And she called a barber, and he shaved his seven locks of hair. And she began to push him away, and to repel him from herself. For immediately his strength departed from him.

20 And she said, "The Philistines are upon you, Samson!" And awaking from sleep, he said in his mind, "I will break away and shake myself free, just as I did before." For he did not know that the Lord had withdrawn from him.

21 And when the Philistines had seized him, they immediately plucked out his eyes. And they led him, bound in chains, to Gaza. And enclosing him in a prison, they made him work a millstone.

22 And now his hair began to grow back.

23 And the leaders of the Philistines convened as one, so that they might offer great sacrifices to Dagon, their god. And they feasted, saying, "Our god has delivered our enemy, Samson, into our hands."

24 Then, too, the people, seeing this, praised their god, and they said the same, "Our god has delivered our adversary into our hands: the one who destroyed our land and who killed very many."

25 And rejoicing in their celebration, having now taken food, they instructed that Samson be called, and that he be mocked before them. And having been brought from prison, he was mocked before them. And they caused him to stand between two pillars.

26 And he said to the boy who was guiding his steps, "Permit me to touch the pillars, which support the entire house, and to lean against them, so that I may rest a little."

27 Now the house was full of men and women. And all the leaders of the Philistines were there, as well as about three thousand persons, of both sexes, on the roof and in the upper level of the house, who were watching Samson being mocked.

28 Then, calling upon the Lord, he said, "O Lord God remember me, and restore to me now my former strength, O my God, so that I may avenge myself against my enemies, and so that I may receive one vengeance for the deprivation of my two eyes."

29 And taking hold of both the pillars, on which the house rested, and holding one with his right hand and the other with his left,

30 he said, "May my life die with the Philistines." And when he had shaken the pillars strongly, the house fell upon all the leaders, and the rest of the multitude who were there. And he killed many more in his death than he had killed before in his life.

31 Then his brothers and all his relatives, going down, took his body, and they buried it between Zorah and Eshtaol, in the burying place of his father, Manoah. And he judged Israel for twenty years.